All right, welcome back.
In this lesson, we're going
to discuss a new feature that
prevents passwords for
being exposed in the MongoDB
configuration file.
MongoDB configuration
files often
contain all the information
necessary to start up
a MongoDB process.
In some ways, it's a good
thing that all this information
can be contained in one place.
We know which file to edit when
we want to change something,
and we know where to look
when something changes.
If we decide to
change the tls mode,
for example, we'd see
that reflected here.
However, there's some
trade to this approach.
In particular,
including an entry
for password secrets in
the configuration file
leaves sensitive data
exposed in plain text
if not properly secured.
Exposing these passwords
as strings in the YAML
can complicate auditing within
an organization in addition
to deepening the fallout in the
event of a system compromise.
So instead of pointing
MongoD to a config file
and storing security
parameters in this file,
we can reference some
environmental variable
on the local system.
In this case, the
environmental variable
has to be a
function, which means
that we can do something simple
like just returning a string.
This is probably
not the most secure.
So like any other bash function,
we can make a web request here
if we want.
This web request can
retrieve something
from an external service, for
example, a password vault.
So just to see how
this works, we're
going to take a look at
the old configuration file
format, where we had to pass
the password as a string.
So in this example,
the tls certificate
we're using to start up MongoD
is protected with a password.
And in our configuration
file, the certificate key
file password is passed as
a string just m042password.
This variable is
pretty sensitive.
So let's pass it as an
environmental variable instead.
So in this example, we
passed this exec parameter
and asked it to execute
the environmental variable
get_certificate_password.
So get_certificate_password
is just
a function on the local system
that returns our certificate's
password.
Here the -n removes the
new line and white space
around the string m042password.
This way, the configuration
file can use this string
without manipulating it further.
So we can use this
configuration to start up
MongoD with this command.
Note that we need to pass
this additional parameter
configExpand and
then specify that we
want to use the exec
option in our config file.
We can see a log message
noting that it did process
the exec config
expansion, and the process
started successfully.
So we can also do
instead of passing
an environmental variable is ask
MongoDB to make a web request.
As we showed earlier, we
can make a web request
through the
environmental variable,
but MongoDB provides a
way to do it directly
from the configuration file.
This option will use
the local web request
library on whatever
platform you're running on.
So that'll be WinHTTP
on Windows or libcurl
on any other platform.
So in this example, the
password for our tls certificate
we're using to start up MongoD
is passed from a web request
with __rest.
We don't have as much
control over the rest call
as we did on the local
environment variable.
So while we could just
trim out the whitespace
from the environmental variable,
this file is on another server.
So we're going to specify
that we want a string output
and then trim the
whitespace around it.
And when we launched MongoD
with this config file,
we need to specify that
we're going to make a rest
call in the config.
And that took a
minute, because it
needed to make a request
to a different server,
but it eventually did
start successfully.
So just to recap
in this lesson, we
discussed the new
alternatives to storing
passwords in config files.
As a reminder, those
two alternatives
are environmental
variables and web requests.