Welcome back.
In 4.2, we've introduced
clientside field level
encryption.
What this means as
the name suggests
is that you can now encrypt
data in MongoDB at field level.
First, let's discuss
why we want to do that.
A lot of MongoDB we use
cases require the storage
of sensitive data such as
medical records or payment
details.
This data is encrypted
at client layer
prior to being
inserted into MongoDB
and is never
decrypted in MongoDB.
Additionally, field
level encryption
allows you to make
data permanently
unavailable by revoking the
keys which can decrypt the data.
Whatever the key, the
data is unintelligible,
hence complying with
any regulations which
require the data to be
permanently deleted.
Clientside encryption guarantees
that sensitive data can only
be encrypted and decrypted
with both access to MongoDB
and a separate key
management provider.
Once enabled, data can
be seamlessly encrypted
and decrypted with minimal
application code changes.
This enables an
encryption key to be
revoked at any stage,
which permanently
makes the data inaccessible.
Let's have a look at
how we implemented
this feature in MongoDB 4.2.
The driver interacts
with multiple components
to implement clientside
field level encryption.
So it interacts with
the MongoDB closer
to get remote JSON schemas,
the MongoDB key vaults
to get encrypted data keys
and create new data keys,
and AWS KMS server to encrypt
and decrypt fetch data keys
and encrypt new data keys.
And then there's the
mongocryptd to ask
which values in BSON
commands must be encrypted.
So we talked about
the MongoDB key
vault. The key vault is a
special MongoDB collection
containing key documents.
You can either choose
to co-locate this
on your MongoDB cluster
or on a separate cluster
depending on your use case.
The key material
in the key vault
is encrypted with a
separate KMS service.
Therefore, encryption
and decryption
requires access to both the
MongoDB cluster and the KMS
servers.
There's a key stored in
the key vault per document
in the collection.
Each of these keys can
be individually revoked
to prevent access to that data.
So we also mentioned
the mongocryptd.
The mongocryptd
is a local process
which is needed for
collection auto encryption.
It speaks to the
MongoDB wire protocol,
and the driver uses mongocryptd
by connecting with a Mongo
client.
By default, the driver will
attempt to automatically spawn
a mongocryptd process.
The mongocryptd
process is shipped
as part of the MongoDB
4.2 enterprise binary
and is available for all Atlas
and Enterprise customers.
There are two options
available when
using field level encryption.
You can choose to
provide a schema
to the mongocryptd process
in your application code.
This allows mongocryptd to
automatically encrypt fields
based on a specific schema.
You can also choose to manually
encrypt individual fields using
your application code.
It's important to note that
if you have a client which
does not use the encrypted
connection options,
it will still be able to
read from the collection.
You can see in this
example we have
a driver which isn't configured
to use an encrypted connection.
It's still able to
read everything apart
from this field which has been
encrypted using field level
encryption.
So let's recap.
Field level
encryption allows you
to encrypt data at field level.
Keys are stored in a
MongoDB collection called
the key vault. This can
either be co-located
on the same cluster
as your data,
or it can be on a
separate cluster.
These keys are encrypted
with a master key which
is stored in an
external KMS server,
and your client
must be configured
to use an encrypted collection
through a process called
the mongocryptd, which is
shipped as part of the MongoDB
enterprise binary.
If your client is not
configured to use encryption,
it will not be able to
read unencrypted values
from the collection in MongoDB.
Any unencrypted
fields can be read.