Here's the scenario,
you've got an application.
And as your user base grows,
your user activity grows
and your server
speed is dropping.
You've got a dev environment
that's set up just like prod,
and your goal is to figure
out what's going on.
Let's check it out.
First, let's go into our
VM and start a replica set.
Great.
Next, let's generate our
data set with this script.
This might take a few minutes.
OK, so the next script is
going to simulate a home
page for a user at an
e-commerce web site.
I just wrote something to print
everything out in the shell,
but it should give
you an idea of what
the web site would look like
and what data it would display.
OK so at this point
when I hit Enter,
I'm going to do a simulated
user log in on my site's landing
page.
This is an e-commerce site.
That's what it's
going to display.
Again, we're assuming we're
doing this in a development
environment.
Let's turn on the
profiler first.
I'll do this in a new tab.
OK now that my
profiler is on, I'm
going to go back, hit
Enter, and see what happens.
So I want you to imagine that
a log-in page is displayed--
something like this.
It's saying hello.
This is your name.
Here's your username.
I know it was
generated randomly,
so the user name doesn't
look much like the name.
Tells us when our
last log-in was.
Looks like we have a
cart ready for checkout.
We're buying some
forks, pillow, etc.
We've got some
contact information
to review, some phone
numbers, an address.
OK, well let's go back,
shut off our profiler,
and let's see how
many documents we got.
15.
OK, so this is my first sign
that something went wrong.
Here, I just went
to a landing page.
I did one thing and
I've got 15 queries that
seem to have hit my database.
That doesn't look good.
Let's just look at these
planned summaries real quick.
Index scan, index
scan, ID hack, which
is basically an index scan
using the underscore ID field.
OK everything is using
an index, so that's good.
My queries are
efficient, it's just
that I've got so many of them.
Let's look a little deeper.
OK, query on phone numbers.
Query on phone numbers.
That's a good piece
of information.
When a collection is being
queried multiple times,
that's a sign that the
application is just
finding one document
at a time when it might
be able to find multiple ones.
Right now the database is
asking for these phone numbers
by their underscore ID
three times in a row
all for a single user.
And I know it was a
single user because I
generated this set of queries
by logging in as just that user.
Now, the underscore IDs
that we're looking for
are actually all different.
Note that this
one ends with a 9.
This one ends with a b.
This one ends with a d.
So they're not quite asking
the exact same question,
but it's asking very similar
questions all in a group.
This is an anti-pattern in
any database, by the way--
and that includes MongoDB,
relational databases,
whatever you're looking at.
The problem is with how the
application was written.
Instead of doing a query for
just one record at a time,
a smart application would
group together the phone number
queries and then query the
database for an underscore ID
that matches any from that
set of three underscore IDs.
That's really not a
schema design issue
and it wouldn't require a
change of schema to fix.
But it is an anti-pattern
and it's worth noticing.
OK let's move on, I'm going
to use a little aggregation
to eliminate the redundant
queries on each namespace.