Let's talk about schema design.
Obviously this isn't a
schema design course,
but you do want to be
able to identify some
of the most obvious
signs of a bad schema
and what they might mean.
The thing to keep in mind is
that the structure of your data
affects performance.
This can't be emphasized enough.
If you're at least
aware of this fact
you can be mindful when
creating an application.
Now, in your application
evidence of schema
design problems can show
themselves in a few ways.
First, you might have
a situation where
every time a user lands on
a page or clicks a button
or otherwise does just one
thing the application fires off
a whole bunch of queries.
A separate problem can arise
if the application is packing
lots of rarely used data
into it's frequently accessed
documents.
MongoDB needs to hold at minimum
an entire document in RAM
in order to read
from it, and it often
needs to pull multiple
documents into the cache
at the same time.
If your application is
packing rarely use data
into a document that needs
to be touched frequently,
that means it's
more likely to evict
other important
data from the cache
when that document gets read.
Multiply this across a
collection and the net result
is that the server could
be paging a lot more data
than necessary in order to
service the application.
In this chapter we'll
investigate some examples
of these issues, find
their root causes,
and discuss how to fix them.
Let's get started.