OK, so I can see that this
logins collection appears
twice.
Once when I query it,
once when I insert on it.
So that's fine.
It's everything else
that's the problem.
I'm counting eight
collections that we're
hitting just to get the
information for a standard user
login.
That's totally unacceptable.
One of the patterns
of schema design
is that data that
is queried together
should be in the same
document whenever possible.
It's obvious already that
that's not the case here.
Looking at these, I can see
that I'm looking first at one
and then another collection for
the information that I need.
Let's look at our schema
for user phone numbers.
Yikes.
OK, I'm seeing
nothing but what was
obviously once a joined table
in a relational database.
I've got a user ID
and a phone number ID
and then this label field
seems to have some metadata
about the phone number.
OK, let's look at phone numbers.
OK.
So my phone number document
has just a phone number
and an extension.
Now here's the problem.
I'm not just hating
on relational schemas.
They're great for
relational databases.
My problem is that
someone tried to take
that, that relational schema
and move it into MongoDB.
And here's where
the problem arises.
Instead of just
querying the data once,
they're querying users
to get a user ID then
querying user phone numbers
to get the phone number IDs
and then querying
the phone numbers
collection to get
the phone number that
really should have been in
the user document itself.
This is so not
worth the overhead
of the additional queries.
This phone number should
be in my user document
not in a phone numbers document
much less a phone numbers
document with a user
phone numbers document
we have to query just to join
these two in the application.
OK let's back up and look
at our user document.
OK, I've got a full name,
username, password, birthday,
but my log in itself shows
well, let's move over.
Address, phone number,
shopping cart, last log in.
Yeah, that all should be
packed into the user document.
By now I've got a
great deal of evidence
that over normalization
is the anti-pattern that
caused most of these problems.
By the way I also
want to point out
that when I look through
these collections,
I don't see a raise
in any of them.
And it looks like
user phone numbers
is being queried just to avoid
an array of phone numbers.
Again, this is the
sort of thing that
happens in a relational
database, which makes sense.
Because in a
relational world, you
don't just get to pack an
arbitrary number of items
into a record.
You don't have arrays.
But you can in MongoDB,
and you should.
Let's see our list
of collections.
OK, so I just built the
system dot profile collection
but everything else is
used by this schema.
How do we fix this?
Ultimately, this is a
schema that the developers
are going to have to fix.
And it's probably going to be
an uncomfortable conversation
telling them that
that's the situation.
If all this data is going to
be needed every time the user
lands on a page,
it should all get
thrown into the user document.
And those other collections
should be eliminated.
This is going to be true for
phone numbers, addresses,
and the shopping cart.
OK.
But you might ask, well, what
if two people share an address?
Doesn't that mean that you have
to store the address twice?
And the answer to that is, yes.
You do have to store
it twice, three times,
maybe even 10 times if
friends are shipping
other friends they're gifts.
It's worth an occasional copy
of an address or phone number
because you're going to need it.
And you don't want to
perform unnecessary joins
in your application.
That extra space that
you have to take up
is going to mean that you
get a lot of extra speed
in your database.
By the way, I wouldn't
advocate for eliminating
all of these other collections.
For example, I'd recommend
putting just the last log
in into the application and
also into the logins collection.
But probably not eliminating
the logins collection entirely.
Same for the purchase history.
Why?
Because while any
given person is only
going to have so many
addresses or phone numbers,
their number of
logins and purchases
will just continue
to grow over time.
Eventually, you're going to
end up with documents packed
with things you don't want.
What I'd recommend is just
storing that last log in time
plus the shopping cart
and the user document
since that's all we need
for the landing page.
You can use a find
an update query
to reset the last log to the
present, performing a read
and write in a single query,
and then separately insert
its document into logins.
Which is a cheap operation.
If the user wants to see
their purchase history,
put that on a separate web
page that they can click on.
And perform the purchase
history query at that point.
They shouldn't need to see their
full log in history every time
they log in.
But maybe I want to store
that for analytics purposes.
So we'll keep it away
from the user document
because that should
just hold the data we
need when they log in.
OK.
What did we learn?
First, avoid round
trips to the database.
User events should only generate
a small number of queries.
Second, use arrays where
needed and of course
where they won't
grow indefinitely.
Third, a little
de-normalization is OK
as long as it's in the
interests of speed.
And forth, please don't just
migrate relational schemas.
There are a lot
of things that are
patterns for
relational schemas that
are anti patterns for MongoDB.
And that's how we
investigate a schema.