Now it's time we learned about
lookup, a powerful stage that
lets you combine information
from two collections.
For those with some
knowledge of SQL,
lookup is effectively
a left outer join.
If that didn't make
any sense, don't worry.
Let's break it down.
In database terms,
a left outer join
combines all documents
or entries on the left
with matching documents
or entries from the right.
So A left outer joined with
B would look like this.
The lookup stage has this form.
The from field here is
the collection from which
we want to look up documents.
Keep in mind, the collection
you specify in the from field
cannot be sharded and must
exist within the same database.
LocalField here is a field in
the working collection where
we express the aggregation
command that we
want to compare to.
ForeignField here,
is the field we
want to compare from in the
collection we specified in
from.
Lookup will form a strict
equality comparison.
And the as field here,
is the new field name
we specify that will show
up in our documents that
contains any matches between
localField and foreignField.
All matches will be put
in an array in this field.
If there were no
matches, the field
will contain an empty array.
Let's visualize
this in an example.
Suppose we're aggregating
over an airline's collection
and we want to fetch
which alliance the airline
belongs to.
As the argument from would
specify air alliances.
Next, we would specify
name as the argument
to localField, the value
we want to compare to.
The argument to a localField
can resolve to either an array
or a single value.
Then we specify airlines as
the argument to a foreignField
the value we want
to compare from.
The argument to
foreignField can also
resolve to either an
array or a single value.
We can see that based
on the argument so far,
Penguin Air won't
match anything.
Delta Airlines
will match SkyTeam.
And Lufthansa will
match Star Alliance.
Those matches were brought
into the current document
as alliance.
We could have given
any string value
we wanted, but keep in mind,
that if we specify a name that
already exists in
the working document,
that field will be overwritten.
Notice here that because the
document was named Penguin Air
and did not have any results,
there is an empty array.
Oftentimes after
a lookup, we want
to follow it with a match
stage to filter documents out.
Another thing to know, lookup
retrieves the entire document
that matched, not just the field
we specified, the foreignField.
All right, let's look
at lookup in actual use.
Let's combine information from
the air airlines collection
with the air
alliances collection,
putting all the
airline information
within the alliance document.
First, let's look at the
schema in our airlines
alliances collection.
OK, the data we
need for localField
is in the airline's field.
Let's look at the
airline's schema,
so we know what value to
use as the foreignField.
All right, easy enough.
It looks like the information
we need for foreignField
is in the name field.
That should be all the
information we need.
Let's build the pipeline.
All right, we specify air
airlines to the from field,
airlines as the localField
name as the foreignField.
And here we chose to
overwrite the airlines field
with the information
we get back.
It makes sense.
We'll be replacing the
names with entire documents.
Let's see the output.
Pretty cool.
We can see that lookup did
just what we expected it to do.
We could follow this with
some projections or even
another lookup stage to
perform some powerful reshaping
and analysis.
But for now, that's enough.
We've covered a lot of
information in this lesson.
Lookup is a powerful
stage that can
help help reduce
network requests
and combine information
from different collections
together for powerful
and deep analysis.
Here are a few things
to keep in mind.
The from field
cannot be sharded.
The from collection must
be in the same database.
The values in localField
and foreignField
are matched on equality.
And as can be any
name, but if it
exists in the working document,
that field will be overwritten.