The next stage we'll learn
about is the $group stage.
Key to our comprehension of
group is to understand the one
required argument-- the
_id field of this stage.
The expression or expressions
we specify to _id becomes
the criteria the group stage
uses to categorize and bundle
documents together.
In this picture, we're
grouping coins based
on their denomination, so the
expression specified to _id
would be the
denomination field path.
Let's see this in
action using real data.
All right, let's group documents
in our movies collection
based on the value they
have in their year field.
By grouping, we can see
we have fundamentally
changed the structure of
the resulting documents.
Group matched them based on
the value of the year field.
Documents with identical
values got bundled together,
and each unique value
produced an output document
that shows us the values
or value we grouped on.
By itself, this may
or may not be useful
depending on the use case, and
just grouping on one expression
is functionally equivalent to
using the distinct command.
Let's explore the other powerful
feature of the group stage--
the ability to use aggregation
accumulator expressions.
We can specify
additional fields we
want to calculate
in the group stage,
and as many as we're required
to accomplish our goal.
Here we are going to group on
the value of year, as before.
We also calculate a new field
called num_films_in_year
using the $sum
accumulator expression.
Each time group categorizes
a document for us,
the sum expression gets called.
Since we specified a value
of 1, each matching document
is going to sum 1 to the
value of num_films_in_year.
Let's see it in action.
The same results as
before, with the addition
of the num_films_in_year field.
We can see that there was only
one document with a value 1874
in the year field,
while there were 2,058
documents with the value 2014.
Quite a busy year.
Let's perform the
same aggregation
with the source stage
appended to the end
to order our results.
Great.
We can start to
get an indication
that as a year
value increases, we
have more documents
in our collection.
This brings up an important
point about the expression we
specified _id.
Document values used
in the expression
must resolve to the same
value or combination
of values in order for
documents to match.
Let's look at an example.
Here we're using
the size expression
to get the value of
the directors array.
I'm wrapping it in this
$cond conditional expression
because if the value
we specified as size
doesn't evaluate to an array
or is missing, size will error.
So if directors is an array,
return the size of directors.
Otherwise, 0.
As documents flow in,
this will be evaluated,
and documents with the
same number of directors
will be grouped together.
All documents without
director information
or with an empty
array for directors
will be grouped as well.
We call the field numDirectors,
but could have given it
any name we wanted.
When documents are
grouped together,
we'll calculate a
field called numFilms
and just count how
many documents match.
We'll also average the
metacritic information,
and assign that to a field
called averageMetacritic
for all the matching
documents in a group.
Again, we could have specified
any name for numFilms
or averageMetacritic.
Lastly, we'll just sort the
documents in descending order.
Let's see it in action.
Wow, a film with 44 directors,
but the average metacritic
is null.
Let's explore this by
looking at the document.
All right, scanning
the document,
we can see that the metacritic
field is missing entirely.
This illustrates an
important concept.
It is crucial to understand
the type of data coming in
to properly interpret
the results we calculate,
and we may be required to
sanitize our input in some way
to calculate a result at all.
Accumulator expressions will
ignore documents with a value
at the specified field
that isn't of the type
the expression expects, or
if the value is missing.
If all documents encountered
have an incorrect data
type or a missing value
for the desired field,
the expression will
result in null.
OK, we're gaining a good
understanding of how both
the expressions applied to
the _id groups documents,
and how expressions specified
to our accumulators work.
But what if we wanted
to group all documents,
rather than just a subset?
By convention, we specify null--
or an empty string--
as the argument to _id.
Before we run this pipeline,
let's set an expectation.
I expect the value
of count to be
equal to the number of documents
in the movies collection.
Let's test.
All right, 44,497.
And the total
number of documents?
Again 44,497.
An exact match.
Rather than duplicating
functionality
in a very unoptimized way,
let's do something that
is useful for all documents.
Let's calculate the
average metacritic rating.
Here, we use a match stage
to filter documents out
with a metacritic that isn't
greater than or equal to 0.
Documents missing
metacritic information,
or with a non-numeric
value at that field
won't make it through.
And we can assume the
average metacritic rating
among all documents that
had metacritic information
is around 56.93.
And that covers the group stage.
Let's summarize.
_id is where we specify what
incoming documents should be
grouped on.
We can use all accumulator
expressions within group.
Group can be used multiple
times within a pipeline,
and it may be necessary
to sanitize incoming data.