In some situations, we might not
be interested on the full list.
Let's say, for
example, that we only
want Dave's direct reports
and their direct reports.
So let's say two levels down.
Now a single lookup
is depth zero,
meaning that if
we match for Dave
and we are only
interested on knowing
the documents of
its direct reports,
we just need to set the
depth of our lookup to zero.
But if we want to
do two levels down,
we would need to
have a depth of one.
And therefore, we'll find
a full data structures
of Andrew, Elyse, and Ron.
Graph lookup allows
us to do that.
Using the previous
dataset, child reference,
where we have a direct
reports reference
inside of each document.
If you want to go
two levels down,
till_2_level down reports, you
just specify a maxDepth field,
value equals 1, on
our graphLookup.
After we run this, we have
our matching documents.
And then the list of
results of direct reports
to Dave up to two levels down.
So we can see here that,
for example, Andrew
will be listed, as
well as Ron and Elyse,
and obviously, all of
Dave's direct reports.
So basically, maxDepth will
restrict how many times
we want to recursively
find documents
that match or they
are connected using
the FromField and
the connecToField.
But let's say that, apart from
defining a maxDepth field of I
only want to go two
levels down, I also
want to know how far
away are those elements
to the first element
that I find in my lookup.
Basically, I want to know how
many recursive lookups did
I need to do to find the
particular documents.
For that, I have
depthField, which
I can specify a field name
which will tell me exactly that,
how many recursive
lookups were needed
to get this particular point.
When I run this I can see
that Eliot is on number zero,
meaning that I only needed
one single lookup to find it.
Then again, it's the
first base lookup.
Same thing for Meagan,
same thing for Richard,
same thing for Carlos.
But for Andrew, I need to go
one recursive or, in this case,
two recursive lookups down.
Same thing for Ron and
same thing for Elyse.
By specifying
depth field level I
can get the information of how
many recursive lookups were
needed to find that
particular element
on the descendants field here.