While modeling tree structures,
there are different patterns
that we can follow
depending on how we
want to juggle with our data.
So let's have a look, for
example, to an org chart.
We're going to have the
different individuals
in the company, like
for example, we're
going to have our CEO.
And to our CEO,
he's going to have
a bunch of different reports,
like the CMO, CRO, CTO,
services, and CFO.
All of them
reporting, obviously,
to this particular individual.
Then we're going to have
a sublayer between this
where are we going to have
the different individuals that
report directly to the CTO.
In this case, we're going to be
having the SVP of Engineering
reporting directly to that
CTO and also the VP of Product
also to the CTO.
And further down the
line, we're going
to have the different reports
of the different core areas,
like for example, in education,
cloud, or even VP of Core.
So modeling such a
tree in a document
or a structure of documents
we might have a couple
of different alternatives.
So for example, in this
particular structure,
we're going to have
a parent reference.
Now a parent reference means
that for each single document
we're going to have a particular
attribute of field that
will indicate us
who do we report to,
who is our parent in the tree
structure, or in this case,
the org chart that
we are defining.
So for example, here we can
see that Carlos, our CRO,
reports to 1.
And 1 referring to the _id,
the primary key, of Dave,
which is our CEO.
So we're going to have
a 1 to n relationship,
where each document will
point to its reports_to,
which in turn will be
then the _id field value
of the designated parent.
With this schema it's
quite easy to navigate
between different documents.
So if I want to go from
Carlos to his reports_to,
or to whom he reports to, I
just follow this and go directly
to Dave, which is
value _id equals 1.
So there's always a link
between reports_to and _id.
Now what happens if we want
to know the full reporting
structure of, for example, Dave.
I want to know all
of his direct reports
but also his direct
reports' reports.
We can go and fetch,
for example, Dave's.
And we know that he doesn't
report to anyone but we have
his _id.
So if we want to know exactly
who reports directly to Dave,
we can use the reference and the
value of his _id and find all
of his direct reports.
If we want to know the full
structure of reporting, well,
we would just need to go back
and forth to do the database
to understand exactly, for each
element or for each document
that we find, check who
reports-to and do the query
again, based on his _id.
Now this continuous
pinging of the database
is quite inefficient.
For each request
that we get, we need
to ping the database again.
The alternative
to this operation
will be to use our new
operator graphLookup.
So in this particular
example here,
I want to know the full
reporting structure that
reports to our CTO, Eliot.
So to do this with
graphLookup we need
to run a query similar to this.
We start by matching
the document
that we want to start to analyze
from with the match operator.
So in this case, I want to
find the reporting structure
to Eliot, therefore, I'm going
to match for all documents that
contain this particular name.
And then we have the
graphLookup operator
that will retrieve all
subsequent descendant documents
from the parent reference.
So this will be a self lookup.
Starting with the _id value of
the previous first encountered
document, connecting
from the field _id,
this is the field I'm going to
search on for the subsequent
graphLookups, but we are going
to be using the reports_to
value to match, and use that to
use for the subsequent queries.
And then I'll be
storing all documents
that I encounter from the
lockup up as all_reports.
After I run this query,
I'll find the document
that I wanted, the one that
matches name equals Eliot.
I can see his title.
And then I can find,
thanks to the graphLookup,
all his descendant reports.
In this case, it's going to
be Cailin, then Andrew, Ron,
Shannon, and Elyse.
Now this just tells me all of
the descendants beneath Eliot.
So in this case,
graphLookup will
allow me to find all
different nodes that
are beneath a particular
node that I'm finding.
We can also ask the
reverse question,
which is, given an
element on the org chart,
what is the hierarchy to
upper levels of reporting?
So for example, if I
give the VP of Education
I want to know
the full structure
till I get to the top parent
of our tree, root level.
To do that, what we need to do
is, again, match on the element
that we are interested
on, in this case Shannon,
and then invert the connectFrom
and connectTo fields,
but also starting with the
different startWith value.
In this case, we're going to
be starting with reports_to.
connectFrom will be also
reports_to but the connect
field, the value that we're
going to pick up to match
against reports_to will be _id.
And we're going to be storing
that information, that chain,
into a field called bosses.
Once I run this, I can see that
Shannon has the set of bosses.
He has Dave.
Eliot, and, obviously,
his direct boss, Andrew.