Let's take a moment to learn
about using accumulator
expressions with
the $project stage.
Knowledge of how to
use these expressions
can greatly simplify our work.
One important thing
to keep in mind
is that accumulator
expressions within $project
work over an array within
the given document.
They do not carry values forward
to each document encountered.
Let's suppose we have a
collection named example
with this schema.
If we perform this
aggregation, this
will be the result. An output
document for every input
document, with the average of
that document's data field.
For this lesson, we're going
to explore this data set.
It's the average monthly low and
high temperature for the United
States as well as monthly ice
cream consumer price index
and sales information.
And here's what the data
looks like in our collection.
We can see we have
a trends array
with documents that contain
all the information we'll need.
Easy enough to work with.
Let's go ahead and find the
maximum and minimum values
for the average
high temperature.
We'll explore two different
methods to find the maximum.
First, we'll use the
$reduce expression
to manually find the maximum.
Before I run this,
let's break it down.
Here, I'm specifying the
$reduce expression. $reduce
takes an array as its
input argument here.
For the argument to initial
value, the value or accumulator
we'll begin with, we're
specifying negative infinity.
I hope we'll never have
a monthly average high
temperature of
negative infinity,
but in all seriousness,
we're using negative infinity
because any reasonable value
we encounter should be greater.
Lastly, we'll specify the
logic to the end field here.
This is using the $cond
conditional operator and saying
if $$this.avg_high_tmp is
greater than the value which is
held in our accumulator, then
return this.avg_high_tmp.
Otherwise, just
return the value back.
So compare the current value
against the accumulator value,
and if it's greater,
we'll replace it
with the value we
just encountered.
Otherwise, we'll just keep
using our current max value.
Notice the double dollar signs.
These are temporary
variables defined for use
only within the
$reduce expression,
as we mentioned in the
aggregation structure
and syntax lesson.
$this refers to the current
element in the array.
$value refers to the
accumulator value.
It will do this for every
element in the array.
OK, let's run this.
And we see the max high was 87.
Wow, that was
pretty complicated.
Let's look at an easier
way to accomplish this.
I think we can all agree
that this is much simpler.
We use the $max group
accumulator expression
to get the information we want.
And again, we get
max high of 87.
OK, let's get the minimum
average temperature.
Here, we use the $min
accumulator expression
and we can see our
max low was 27.
All right.
We now know how to
use max and min.
We can also calculate averages
and standard deviations.
Let's calculate the
average consumer price
index for ice cream, as well
as the standard deviation.
Here, we're calculating
both in one pass.
For the average_cpi field,
we specified the $avg
average expression,
telling it to average
of the values in the
icecream_cpi field
in the trends array.
And here, the cpi_deviation is
calculated almost identically,
except we're using the
population standard deviation.
We're using standard
deviation pop
because we're looking at
the entire set of data.
However, if this was only
a sample of our data,
we'd use the sample standard
deviation expression.
Great.
We can see that the
average consumer price
index was 221.275 and
the standard deviation
was around 6.63.
We could use this
information to find
data that is outside norms
to point to areas that
might need special analysis.
The last accumulator expression
I'd like to show is $sum.
As the name implies, $sum sums
up the values of an array.
We can see that the yearly
sales were 1,601 million.
And that covers
accumulator expressions
available within $project.
Here are a few things
to keep in mind.
The available accumulator
expressions in $project
are sum, average, max, min,
standard deviation population,
and standard deviation sample.
Within $project, these
expressions will not carry
their value forward and operate
across multiple documents.
For this, we'd need to use
the unwind stage and group
accumulator expressions.
For more complex
calculations, it's
handy to know how to
use $reduce and $map.