By now, you probably
already realize
that MongoDB offers a
flexible data model.
Documents can be of
different shapes and forms,
and organized in such
a way that it reflects
both applications
dynamic data structures
and scalability requirements.
We can have very flat,
root level only fields
in our documents, are quite
complex and deeply nested
schemas that reflect obligation
needs for fast operations
and business logic.
A common set of
data structures that
require both complex nesting
levels and flexible storage
layer tends to be graph, or
tree hierarchy use cases.
Data sets can be as simple
as a reporting chain
HR datastore, or complex
data structures that
map airport traveling routes
or even social networks.
Telco switch, disease
taxonomy, and fraud
detection are among several
different use cases where graph
queryability and flexible data
representation go hand in hand.
Unlike graph specific
databases, MongoDB
is designed to be a
general purpose database,
meaning that we want to provide
a very good infrastructure
to support operational
and analytical use cases.
With MongoDB 3.4, we are
extending furthermore
the query capabilities
of MongoDB
by offering dollar graph lookup.
Graph lookup allows developers
to combine their flexible data
sets with graph or
graph-like operations.
This enables all of
those complex data
sets to be processed,
analyzed, and transformed
using a single data source.
When designing and implementing
graph relationships
and designing its
queries, we generally
need to think about
transitive relationships.
If a reports to b,
and b reports to c,
then a indirectly reports to c.
In standard SQL, such
hierarchical queries
are implemented by way
of recursive common table
expressions.
In relational algebra, this
is called transitive closure.
Graph lookup allows looking
up recursively a set
of documents with a
defined relationship
to a starting document.
Graph lookup is very similar
to our dollar lookup operator.
It's another lookup with a
few important variations.
We will have from field
that specifies a collection
that this stage
retrieves results from,
a startWith field that specifies
the connectToField value
or values that we should start
our recursive search with.
We have a connectFromField
that determines
a field in each document
in the from collection
that is used to perform
the next recursive query.
And we have the
connect to field that
sets the field in each
document in the from collection
that is queried against
each recursive query.
As specifies a field
in the output document
that will be assigned the
array of results of that graph
lookup.
maxDepth-- this is
an optional field
that specifies the maximum
number of recursive depth
for the graph lookup.
depthField, also optional,
specifies the field name
in which the result
document will
be set to the recursive depth
at which the document was
retrieved.
This will be 0 for
the first lookup.
And we also have
restrictSearchWithMatch,
another optional field
that specifies a filter
to apply when doing the
lookup in the from collection.
Looks right, doesn't it?
In the following lesson, we
are going to get ourselves busy
and start experimenting
with this new feature,
looking to a new set
of different examples.