So now don't forget about
the underlying restrictions
of running
aggregation pipelines.
The first thing I want to
raise your attention to
is the memory allocation.
The dollar graph lookup,
due to its recursive nature,
and the fact that it might bring
back several thousand megabytes
of memory just on a single query
may require significant amount
of memory to operate
properly, not
only due to the
recursiveness, but also given
the complexity of the
documents and how broad
your queries might be.
So allowDiskUse
will be your friend.
Another important thing to keep
in mind is the use of indexes.
Now in MongoDB, as in
any other database,
indexes will accelerate or
might accelerate our queries.
In the case of graph lookup,
having our connectToField,
which is the field in
the front collection
that we're going to be using
on the recursive query.
Having this particular
field indexed
will be a good, good thing.
Another important aspect to take
into consideration is the fact
that they our from
collection cannot be sharded.
So if you are using
graph lookup stage,
we cannot use a shard collection
in our from collection.
Also, unrelated
match stages do not
get pushed before graph
lookup in the pipeline.
Therefore, they will
not be optimized
if they are not related with the
dollar graph lookup operator.
So keep that in mind when
building your pipeline.
Now, and last important thing,
is giving its recursive lookup
nature, dollar graph lookup
makes it allow memory usage
without spilling to disk.
Take that into consideration.
Even though that you are
using allow disk use,
this may still exceed
the 100 megabytes
of maximum memory allowed
per aggregation pipeline