So far we've been analyzing
graph lookup on self lookups,
meaning that we find a
document then we implement
the graph lookup and then we
find also subsequent documents
that match what I intended.
And then I do another one on
the self-join, and so forth,
which is nice and fun but we
can do a lot more than that.
As in any other
ordinary lookup, we
can start from one
initial collection
and lookup another collections,
and doing the recursive
lookups as we see fit.
Obviously, we don't
need to restrict
to just one original document.
We have multiple that
will follow always
the same behavior.
For this particular
demonstration,
I'm going to use this air
database that I have here.
So in this air database, what
I have is two collections,
one of them is airlines
and another one is routes.
In a particular
airline document,
it's a pretty flat
document, where
I have all the information I
need for a particular airline.
Its alias, its iata code, the
country, and where the airline
itself is based, basically
saying which airport is
base to this home airline.
On collection routes,
what I can find
is information on the airline,
where does the flight depart
from, the source airport,
where does it reach,
the destination airport,
and some other information,
like if it's codeshare, its
stops, and the type of airplane
or the airplane that
actually is operating
this particular route.
So in this scenario, I'm going
to have information on airlines
and information on routes.
So if you imagine this very
sketchy map of the world, where
we have the blue
points and identifying
the airports, and the routes
connecting these dots,
giving an airline that
operates certain routes,
we can try to identify that
from a given airport, where
the airline is based
out, where can I
go with a maximum, for
example, of one layover?
Say that I want to go from
this particular place here,
where can I go through?
I have at least three different
routes departing here.
But from those routes I
can go multiple other ways,
depending on the number of
layovers that I want to do.
If I want a list
of all connections,
and by restricting,
for example, the number
layovers, or
something like that,
we can do that
using graph lookup.
So again, if I want to
start with TAP Portugal,
finding its own base
airport and knowing
every single destination,
regardless of the airline,
that I can go from
its base airport,
in this case, Portugal-- my
home town, very lovely city--
where can I go with a
maximum of one connection?
The full list of
connected the airports
will be given by this query.
I can see here that I
am going all the way
to Athens passing through
Gatwick Airport in London.
Now comparing
maxDepth here, we're
using one instead of
zero, is because we
are starting from airlines
and searching on routes.
And maxDepth only will restrict
the number of recursive lookups
on the front collection.
So I started my collecting
the matching document
that I want and then I'm
going to only lookup,
or in this case, graph
lookup twice, the first one
and another one, on
the route's collection.
Previously, we used the same
value for the two levels
down since we were doing
a self-recursive lookup.
But let's say that, starting
from a particular airport
and connecting to
all other airport,
regardless of the
airlines, is not really
what I was intending.
Not only I want to start from
the base airport of a given
airline, I also
want to make sure
that all flights that
I'm connecting with
are using the
exactly same airline.
So I don't want to
connect from, for example,
Porto to New York
and then the next hop
to be on a different airline.
No, not at all.
I want to make sure I'm always
using the same carrier all
the way through its network.
To do that we can also restrict
the search with a match.
And in this case,
I want to make sure
that the only lookups that
I'd retrieve match the airline
name with the same one that
I'm originally intending,
in this case, TAP Portugal.
So what are we doing?
Are matching on airlines,
finding the airline document
that matches name
equals TAP Portugal,
We're going to
graphLookup from routes,
setting up the values
in chain, using
as initial value
of the base airport
of this original documents.
Connecting the
destination airport
with the source airport, So the
value of destination airport
will be using this recursive
query over the field source
airport with a
maximum of one hop.
So I only want one layover.
But always using
the same airline.
Once I do this, I can have the
full list of all connections
that I intended,
always traveling
within the same airline.