Another pattern
that we can apply
will be to have the
reverse referencing.
Let's say that in
this case, we're
going to have the
definition of our CEO,
but inside of that
document we're
going to have the reference
to all his direct reports,
its children nodes.
Same thing for CTO,
we can be referencing
all of its immediate
reports, and the same thing
down the line.
To do this, we just need
to transform our documents.
Instead of having a reference
back to its parents, what we're
going to have is each
single document referencing
is direct reports.
In this example here,
we can see that Dave,
with his title of CEO, has this
list of direct reports, Eliot,
Meagan, Carlos,
Richard, and Kristen.
With this structure,
getting immediate children
can be achieved by
a single operation.
If I find documents
where name equals Dave
I immediately get its full
list of direct reports.
So a level down from Dave.
But getting the full
tree to its last element
requires something
more elaborate.
And again, $graphLookup
is here for the rescue
with one single operation.
In this scenario, we
changed the document schema
starring the immediate
child references,
again, on direct_reports.
And therefore, if we want to
get the full list of descendants
we will need to
do the following.
We will go through
again the same
matching, finding the node
where we want to begin with,
expressing where are we going
to fetch the information from.
In this case, again, a self
graphLookup, self lookup.
We're going to start
with the direct reports,
so this is the
first set of values
that we're going to be
using to iterate from.
We're going to connectFromField
direct_reports,
going to be using that for
the subsequent graph queries
but we are going to
connectToField name.
So every time we match a element
of direct reports with a name
we'll do this recursively.
And we'll start
this in all_reports.
Once we run this, we'll have
the following structure.
We'll find that Dave has
a set of direct_reports
but all_reports are going
to be matched and found
on this field.
We're going to have Dan,
Shannon, Elyse, Ron,
Andrew, and so on.
So at the very end, what
we have is basically,
for all different
direct reports,
we match, or are trying to find,
a document in the name field.
And for his
direct reports,
we do this recursively,