Let's learn about another
useful aggregation
stage, the $unwind stage.
$unwind lists unwind
in an RA field,
creating a new document for
every entry where the field
value is now each entry.
Let's visualize this
with an example.
If I had the following schema
on the left, title and genres,
and $unwind on the
genres field, I'll
get back documents on the right.
What?
Am I saying that I'm generating
a document for each array
entry, when it was all
tighten and well-embedded?
Why might this be useful?
One example is when we'd like
to group on individual entries.
In the group lesson, we grouped
movies based on their year.
And we tried to group
on year and genres,
we would have gotten back
many distinct entries
because, within
group, arrays are
mashed on pure equality,
not equivalents.
So this array of
Adventure Action
would not match this
array of Action Adventure.
Let's use $unwind
for something real.
Let's find the most
popular genres by year
from 2010 to 2015 within
the movie's collection.
I'm going to go ahead and limit
this, and say that I'm only
considering entries
with a runtime of 90
minutes or greater.
And for popularity, I'll use
a value in the imdb.rating.
Let's break this down.
Here, we begin with the
$match stage, ensuring
we have an imdb.rating
value by specifying
that it must be greater than
0, and filtering documents
based on year and runtime.
Then we unwind the genres
array, creating a new document
for each entry in
the original array.
Then we'll group on the year,
and the now single genre values
field, and use the
average expression
to calculate the average_rating
from imdb.rating.
Finally, we sort, first
on the year descending,
and then the
average_rating descending.
Let's test it out.
It's close, but not
quite there yet.
We can see we're getting the
most popular genre by year,
but we're getting
all results back.
We just want a single
document per year,
with the highest-rated genre.
There are many ways
to accomplish this.
We'll just look at one
of the most simple.
Let's examine this new pipeline.
It's identical to
the previous one,
with the addition
of these two stages.
The previous pipeline
was returning
in the format we wanted.
There were just too many
documents being returned.
Here, in this
additional group stage,
we group documents together
based on their year.
And since they are already
sorted in the order we need,
we just take the first
value we encounter
for the genre and
the average rating.
Then we finish with a $sort
to make sure that they're
return and the order we want.
Let's see if it works.
Excellent.
One document per year, with
the highest-rated genre
in that year.
We've seen how $unwind works.
Now there's a few
less things to cover.
We've been using the
short form for $unwind.
Here's the long
form for contrast.
In the long form,
we specify the array
we want to unwind by providing
a field path expression
to the path argument.
We can provide a string
to includeArrayIndex.
This will create another
field in the document
with whatever name we
specify, with the value
to the index of the element
in the original array.
Lastly, we can provide
a true or false value
to preserveNullAndEmptyArrays.
True will create an entry
with an empty array,
with the value
specified in the path
as either null, missing,
or an empty array.
One more thing of note.
If the documents in our
collection are very large,
and we need to use
$unwind, we may
exceed the default memory limit
of the aggregation framework.
As always, match early,
retain only the information
needed with project,
and remember that we
can specify to allow disk use.
And that covers $unwind
We've learned a lot.
Let's recap on a few things.
$unwind only works on
an array of values.
There are two forms for unwind,
the short form and long form.
Using unwind on large
collections with big documents
may lead to performance issues.