So the labs in this
course will be completed
inside a virtual machine.
And this lesson is about how
to set up the virtual machine
on your host machine.
But first, why are we using one?
The first is that it's to
sandbox the environment.
We want to give you an
environment that you
can use without messing
with the existing
settings on your local machine.
This also allows us to
avoid dependency and system
troubleshooting.
So all the dependencies
are downloaded for you.
And you can focus
on the learning.
Third, it also allows us to
provide more consistent support
for our students
throughout the course.
If we know that everyone's
running the same operating
system, we can more quickly
diagnose and solve problems
that you have.
So how does it work?
You boot up a Vagrant virtual
machine on your computer.
And it uses your
computer's memory, storage,
and CPU in order to function
just like a real computer.
And by using a process
called SSH, or Secure Shell,
you can connect to
the virtual machine.
Once you're connected,
you can treat it just
like a regular computer.
And you can connect it with
your terminal or command prompt.
In this course, you'll launch
mongod processes and replica
sets all inside your
virtual machine.
But in order to do
that, we're going
to ask that you install
two dependencies.
The first is VirtualBox.
VirtualBox as an open
source hypervisor
that allows us to run virtual
machines on your host machine.
The second is Vagrant, which
is an open source tool that
allows us to build and
maintain these virtual software
environments very quickly.
More specifically, Vagrant
makes it really easy
to copy files and share
files from your host machine
to your virtual machine.
For example, if you had an
exercise handout or some code
that you wrote on
your local machine,
you can take those files
and copy them directly
into the virtual machine.
We'll see more about
this in a minute.
As part of the
lecture notes, you'll
find the instructions to
install these two software
tools for Windows.
So I won't be
spending too much time
in this video regarding that.
But once you have
those installed,
we'll start setting up the
virtual class environment.
So first, we're going
to create a directory
for this course called
m103 and a parent directory
called university.
This -p here creates the parent
directory university in case
it doesn't exist.
So here we have
a recursive copy,
which is notated
by the -r, which
is used to copy
entire directories
into another location.
In this case, we're copying
the m103-vagrant-env directory
into the m103 folder.
So now that we're inside
the m103 vagrant environment
folder inside the
m103 course folder,
we can start looking
around the actual handout
to see what we just downloaded.
As we can see, we have a Vagrant
file and a provisioning file.
The Vagrant file
specifies some baseline
operating system image details.
As you can see, we have
the operating system
that we're running, Ubuntu.
And I just want to quickly draw
your attention to this folder
that we created called Shared.
This folder is going to connect
our virtual machine to our host
machine.
So at any point, if you want
to copy a file from your host
machine into the
virtual machine,
be it a handout for
a lab or some code
that you wrote on your host
machine, all you'd have to do
is copy it in the shared folder
inside the virtual environment
and it would copy it
into the virtual machine.
There are some other
details in here,
such as the name of
the box, mongod-m103,
and the amount of memory, which
is just over two gigabytes.
There's also an
external IP address
for the Vagrant box,
192.168.103.100,
which you'll actually have
to use in some later labs.
So now we can take a look
at the provisioning file
and see what's inside.
This file is quite a bit
longer than the Vagrant file.
And it's written in
Shell script because it
needs to download some things
in order for you to complete
the course materials.
The provisioning file overall
specifies the dependencies
and all the necessary
software that
will be required to
complete the labs.
And it will also download
the validation scripts
you'll run in order
to check your work.
We have some commands
here defining
which version of
MongoDB to install
and where to place some
files and configurations
and any third-party software.
You don't really need to
know any of this stuff.
But just in case
something does go
wrong with the virtual
environment during the course,
we might ask you to change some
of the settings and variables
inside these files.
The chances of that
are very small, though.
So in general, try not to
mess around with these files.
The reason we're
using Vagrant is
so that you can focus on
the course material and not
dependencies or any
of that other stuff.
So now that we've
taken a look at some
of the files you
got in the handout,
we actually bring
Vagrant up and go over
some of the commands you can
use to configure the Vagrant
box once it's running.
The first that we're going to
learn is called vagrant up.
This is going to actually
bring our box up as specified
in the Vagrant file and
the provisioning file.
This may take a while to
run, especially if it's
your first time running it.
So just wait a few minutes
and it should complete.
So once this box
is running, we can
check the health and status
of the box using the command
vagrant status.
This tells us that our
mongod-m103 box is running.
And it also gives
us some commands
that we can use to shut
it down with vagrant halt,
suspend it with vagrant
suspend, and start it
back up with vagrant up.
Without further ado,
let's SSH into the box.
So here we can connect
to the box using the SSH
with the command vagrant ssh.
This will recognize the Vagrant
file and provisioning file
and use it to connect
to the right VirtualBox.
So once we've
SSHed, you can tell
that the Shell
prompt has changed
to say vagrant and m103.
And this is a good thing.
It means that we're no longer
connected to our host machine
and we're actually
connected directly
to the virtual machine.
And we can run commands
to actually explore
our virtual machine.
We'll just take a look
at the mongod version
that's installed on our box.
And we can see it's version
3.6, which is the latest.
This is because the provisioning
file went and got the latest
version of MongoDB for us.
So we didn't have to
figure out how to do it.
It also installed on
the right location
so that you can jump
right in and start
running Mongo commands.
If we want to exit the box,
all we have to do is type exit
and we're connected back
to our host machine.
If we want to stop the box,
we can run vagrant halt.
And this will gracefully shut
down our virtual machine so
that the state stays the same.
And if we run vagrant up
again, it'll bring it back up.
We can verify this by
running vagrant status again.
And as we can see,
the box is running.
So just to recap, here's
what will be expected of you.
Download the handout
that contains the Vagrant
environment.
Unzip the handout and place
it in your new m103 folder
for this course.
You can bring the virtual
environment up with vagrant up,
and they connect with SSH.
In order to verify the
provisioning script ran
the correct way, you can
check the version of MongoDB
that's installed inside
the virtual machine.
If you want, you can exit the
box and put our system to rest,
and then bring it back up
again so that you can use it.
All right.
Thanks for listening.
Good luck setting up your
own virtual environment.