Hi there, and welcome to M103,
basic cluster administration.
My name's Matt,
and I'm going to be
one of your instructors
for this course.
Together, we'll learn
about deploying MongoDB
in various
architectures, and how
to use the basic administrative
tools at your disposal.
In the first chapter,
we'll discuss
Mongod, which is
the core database
process that handles
data requests
and manages data access.
We'll also cover
important aspects
of deploying a single Mongod
process, such as enabling
authentication and
exploring the database logs.
In the second
chapter, we'll discuss
how MongoDB supports
high availability
by replicating our data.
With multiple copies of data
on different database servers,
replication provides a
level of fault tolerance
against the loss of a
single database server.
In this course, we'll go
through the general architecture
and behavior of a replica set,
and the different deployment
strategies you can use to
better suit your application.
In the final chapter,
we'll discuss
scalability and
how MongoDB scales
horizontally through sharding.
In this course, we're
going to cover topics
like the architecture
of a sharded cluster,
how queries are handled, and how
to choose the way your data is
distributed.
This course is
three chapters long.
And with each chapter, there'll
be a new set of lesson videos.
After each lesson,
there will be a quiz
to assess your learning
of the material.
Lab exercises are dispersed
throughout each chapter
so that you can apply what
you've learned throughout.
So let's go over a few logistics
of the course very quickly.
Who's the target audience?
This is a basic course.
So it's suitable for
people on both development
and administration teams.
It's expected that you already
have some basic knowledge
or understanding of databases
or a basic familiarity
with MongoDB.
For example, if you took
M001 on MongoDB University,
and you feel comfortable with
what you learned in that class,
then you're in the right place.
How does the grading work?
There are quizzes,
labs, and a final exam
as deliverables on your
part during the course.
1/2 of your grade
in the class will
be determined by how
you do in the labs,
and the other half will be
determined by your performance
on the final exam.
The quizzes are ungraded
and they exist mainly
to help you track your own
understanding of the material.
Students with a grade
of 65% or greater
will receive a passing
grade and a certificate
of course completion.
Throughout the course,
we highly encourage
you to participate in
the discussion forum.
We provide knowledgeable
teaching assistants
who are there to help
answer your questions.
But you also have
your fellow classmates
who are often very
helpful resources, as they
take the course alongside you.
By the end of this
course, you should
be familiar with the different
tools and techniques used
to administer basic
MongoDB deployments.
You'll be able to identify
different MongoDB architectures
and use the MongoDB
shell to configure them.
So without further
ado, thank you
for deciding to learn with us.
And we wish you
the best of luck.