So what if we
wanted to only index
the subparts within the
waveMeasurement field?
We can use the wildcard
projection option
when creating the index.
You may be familiar
with projections
from the MongoDB query language.
The concept is
exactly the same here,
except we're specifying
which fields we wish
to index in the collection.
The wildcard projection can be
used to specify a set of fields
to include in the
index, or it can
be used to specify
a set of fields
to exclude from the index.
To index all subparts in
the waveMeasurement field,
we would do the following.
OK, great.
So our index is created.
Let's see how our
queries perform
when querying a field
in a nested document
in the waveMeasurement field.
We're going to query
on waveMeasurement.
seastate.quality.
And have a look at
the Explain plan.
OK, great.
So our query used the index.
All good so far.
But let's say we don't
want to index all subparts
of the waveMeasurement field.
We see that we're only accessing
the waveMeasurement.wave
subpart.
So the fields outside this
double nested document
are not needed.
We can index on
waveMeasurement.waves,
and also parts using
wildcard indexes also.
Let's go back to the shell
and see how we can do this.
This command is creating an
index on waveMeasurement.waves
and all subparts.
You may notice that we're
using the familiar MongoDB
query language dot notation
and the $** operator
that we used earlier on.
So our index has been created.
Let's query to see
how to index works.
So here, we're querying on
waveMeasurement.waves.height.
Great.
We can see that our
query used the index.
One note about covered
queries, that is,
queries which can retrieve
all the requested data
from the index itself without
needing to actually go
to the collection.
As we've seen above, queries
which use multiple fields
can benefit from
wildcard indexes.
But it's also important to note
that wildcard indexes can only
cover queries if the query
is on a single field.
In other words, if the user
is querying on a single field
and uses a projection which
returns only that field,
then the wildcard index
can cover the query.
Something similar to this.
For queries with
multiple fields,
we will need to manually create
compound indexes if we wish
to have these queries covered.
Let's review the syntax
for wildcard indexes.
We can use the standard
createindex command
to create a wildcard index.
But we need to use
the $** operator
if we want to index
everything in the collection.
We can use standard dot
notation to specify a subpart
to index in each document.
And we can also use
wildcard projections
to specify which fields and
subpatterns we wish to index.
Let's recap.
Wildcard indexes are useful
for unpredictable workloads.
They are not a replacement for
traditional standard indexes.
You can index on all
fields in a document
or on a subset of fields,
using either dot notation
or wildcard projections.
And that's a brief introduction
to our new wildcard index
feature in MongoDB 4.2.