Hi there.
In this lesson, we're going to
talk about wildcard indexes.
Wildcard indexes are a
new index type in MongoDB.
Which, as their name suggests,
allow you to dynamically create
indexes on all
fields, or a selected
subset of fields for each
document in a collection.
Let's take a step back
and talk about why we
would want to use this feature.
Here at MongoDB, we
always say that you
should only index fields that
your queries frequently access.
And that still applies.
Wildcard indexes
aren't a replacement
for traditional indexes.
So remember, indexes are
great for query performance,
but come at a cost.
Each index needs
to be maintained.
And every document that's
written to the database
needs to update all the
relevant indexes as well.
Then why would we index
everything, I hear you say.
And I can definitely
understand your trepidation.
There is a method to
our madness, however.
Some workloads have
unpredictable access patterns.
For instance,
sensor data for IoT
use cases, or weather stations.
In such cases, each
query may include
a combination of an
arbitrarily large number
of different fields.
This can make it very difficult
to plan an effective indexing
strategy.
For these workloads,
we needed a way
to be able to index
on multiple fields
without the overhead of
maintaining multiple indexes.
MongoDB indexes any
scalar values associated
with a specified path or paths.
For fields that are
documents, MongoDB
descends into the document
and creates index keys
for each field
value paired finds.
For fields that
are arrays, MongoDB
creates an index key for
each value in the array.
This is similar to how multi
key indexes handle arrays
at the moment.
If the array contains
sub-documents,
MongoDB again will descend
through those documents,
and index all field value pairs.
Let's have a look at how
we can use these indexes.
Let's say we have a
collection, and decide
that we want every field in
the collection to be indexed.
Without wildcard
indexes, we would
have to create and
maintain a lot of indexes
based on whatever new access
pattern our application uses.
If we instead use
a wildcard index,
we can assume that certain
indexes exist without the need
to manually create them.
So let's have a look at
our weather collection
here, which we've loaded into
Atlas Cluster using the sample
data feature.
We've created a new
application, and during testing
have noticed that
the access pattern is
completely unpredictable.
And are really struggling
to see a pattern
where a set of
indexes would serve
all our queries efficiently.
Wildcard indexes give
us the ability to index
all fields in all
documents in a collection.
We want to index all fields in
the sample_weather collection.
Let's jump into a Mongo
Shell and do that.
This command uses $**
as a wildcard operator,
which tells MongoDB to index
everything in the collection.
OK, so our index is created.
Let's check it out.
We're going to query on a nested
document in our collection.
Let's say that we need to
view all data points where
a wave height is 0.5.
Let's write a query to get
that data from our database.
OK, so here we're
querying on a sub-document
of wave measurement
that waves are height.
So great, our query
used the index.
But what if we wanted to query
on two fields in the document?
So here, we're
querying on two fields.
Let's say I execute the query
and look at our Explain Plan
again.
We have a winning plan,
which uses an index.
And we also have our
rejected plans down below.
So what you may have noticed
is that each of these plans
is on a single field index.
And this is because
the wildcard index
will generate one virtual single
field index at query execution
time.
And then the planner
will assess them using
the standard query plan score.
This is because
the wildcard index
will generate one virtual
single field at execution time
for each field in the query.
And the planner will assess them
using standard plan scoring.