All right, welcome back.
In this lesson, we're
going to discuss
some ways we can use this new
wildcard index in MongoDB.
We're going to
cover two examples.
The first involves
any collection
with an unpredictable query
shape and the other affects
the way that we would
implement the attribute pattern
in our data model.
Collections with an
arbitrary query shape
are good candidates
for the wildcard index.
Arbitrary query patterns
become more common
as data becomes richer
and more abundant,
especially in a
database like MongoDB
that encourages very
large documents.
And because we can use data in
every facet of our business,
we don't always
know how a data set
will be used when we create it.
In this example, we have
a collection of loan data
where we store
information about the loan
with a sub-document describing
information about the borrower.
Let's say that our
department wants
to learn more about the
types of borrowers we have.
We know that our queries will
be run against the borrower
sub-document, but we
don't know exactly
which fields will be
most important to us
because we just started
exploring the data.
So to enable this sort of
open-ended data exploration,
we can create a wildcard index
on every field in the borrower
sub-document.
We create the index with
the createIndex command,
but instead of a
regular field here,
we use this notation to
denote all the sub pads
of the borrower sub-document.
Then when we query on
age or any other field
in the borrower
sub-document, we know
that this query will be
supported by at least a single
field index.
This wildcard index
can also be used
to simplify our implementation
of the attribute pattern.
For those who are not
familiar, the attribute pattern
is a data modeling strategy that
we can use to index and query
across an arbitrary
number of attributes.
In this example, the
attributes are the number
of streams that a song
received on different streaming
platforms.
We've taken all the
top-level fields
describing these
different counts
and put them all
in sub-documents
in the same array.
This way, we don't need to query
across these different fields.
We can just query on
streams.k or streams.v.
Similarly, we could
create a compound index
on streams.k and streams.v,
and all new sub-documents
in the streams array that
contain a "k" or a "v"
will result in a new
index key being created.
But if we use a wildcard
index on the streams field,
which looks like streams.$**,
then we can use an object here
instead of an array
of sub-documents.
And we can assume that every
field in this sub-document
will be index.
In this example, we
didn't need to use
an array of sub-documents
for these key value pairs
and give them all a
particular name like k
and v. We just create an
index and all the sub-pads
in the stream
sub-document, and then we
can query on any
of those sub-fields
knowing that they'll be
supported by an index.
So in this lesson, we discussed
two important use cases
for the wildcard index.
The first was a
collection where we
don't know the
exact queries which
the wildcard index
mitigates by creating
a single-field index on
every field in a document
or sub-document.
The second was simplifying our
implementation of the attribute
pattern in our data by
using a wildcard index
on a sub-document
containing our attributes.