Hi there.
In this section, we're going to
talk about the new hybrid index
build feature in MongoDB 4.2
on how this feature removes
database locks.
In our quest to continually
improve MongoDB,
we've redesigned
index builds to remove
the trade-offs and limitations
of the previous index
build types.
First let's have a look at
why we've made these changes.
In previous versions
of MongoDB, we
had two different methods
of building indexes.
The first was a
foreground index build,
which was the most performant
but had the unfortunate side
effect of locking the entire
database for the duration
of the index build.
This meant that
you could neither
read from or write
to the database
for the duration
of the index build.
Let's try this in the
mongo shell in 4.0
to see how this
locking can affect
operations on a database
during an index build.
As you can see, we cannot find
or insert any documents while
the index build is in flight.
You can see how this
could be problematic
if triggered on a production
database in error.
Let's try this in MongoDB 4.2.
First we're going
to create an index.
And while the index
build is in flight,
we're going to open a new
shell and try and insert
some documents.
As you can see,
there's no locking.
Great.
So in previous releases, we also
had background index builds,
which don't hold a
lock on a database
but aren't as performant as
a foreground index build.
The background index build uses
an incremental approach that
is slower than the
foreground index build.
That is to say that the
background index build
will periodically
lock the database
but will yield to incoming
read and write operations,
releasing resources to
attend to incoming requests.
If the index is larger
than the available RAM,
the incremental approach
can take much longer
than a foreground index build.
The other downside
of background indexes
is that the index
structure resulting
from this type of index build is
less efficient than foreground
indexes, resulting in less
optimal index traversal
operations.
In this latest release,
we have addressed
these trade-offs with our new
hybrid index build feature.
From 4.2 onwards, there will
be no need for a background
or a foreground index build--
only one hybrid mechanism that
takes the best of both worlds.
The new hybrid index build
has both the performance
of a foreground index build
and the nonlocking properties
of a background index build,
meaning that all database
operations can
proceed uninhibited
for the duration of the build.
This is now the only way to
build an index on MongoDB.
It's the only option available.
It's important to note that
the index structure remains
unchanged.
However, the method we use to
build the indexes has changed
to allow database operations
to continue as normal
for the duration of the build.
So let's recap.
MongoDB has one index
build type, which
is lockless and performant.
Our motivation for this was
to address the trade-offs
of building indexes using
foreground and indexes using
the background methods.
We can now build indexes
quickly and without the need
to lock the entire database.