Currently MongoDB enforces
and 1,024 byte index key size
limit on all indexes created.
That is to say that if any
value for a key in the index
exceeds this limit the
index build would fail.
In other words,
you could not index
on fields whose values
exceeded this size limit.
This limit also applies
to a combination
of fields in a compound index.
That is to say that
if the combined
values of the fields
in a compound index
exceed 1,024 bytes the
index build will fail.
You may be happy to hear that
this limitation is going away
in version 4.2.
Our motivation for
this change are
that there are certain use cases
where having fields exceeding
this limit are a requirement.
Up until now it has not been
possible to create indexes
on any field that
contain the value that
exceeded 1,024 bytes.
This could be problematic
for data sets which
have long string values.
Another reason
for this change is
to facilitate a new index type.
This index type,
named Wild Card,
allows you to easily index
all fields in a document.
To use this new index
we needed to be sure
that users would not have
to worry about a field
hitting this limit and making
their index build fail.
So in summary, MongoDB 4.2
removes the index key size
limit.
You can now index on any
key, regardless of the size
of the values it contains.