Let's discuss the
content that is going
to be covered in this course.
Other than the
overview chapter, there
are four main chapters
on performance, Indexes,
Index Operations,
CRUD Optimizations,
and Performance on Clusters.
In the first
chapter, Indexes, you
learn how indexes
are a critical part
of providing efficient
access to the data that
lives in your database.
Here, you'll learn
about what indexes
are, how both indexes
and other data
are stored on disk, the most
common types of indexes, how we
can optimize sorting
through the use of indexes,
and the different types
of secondary indexes
and their properties.
After we've covered what indexes
are, in the second chapter,
we'll then discuss
how we practically
work with these indexes.
Here, we'll discuss how to
build, discover, delete,
and rebalance indexes, query
plans, the explain method, how
to use hint and index filters,
how indexes impact our servers
resources, and
finally, we'll examine
some basic benchmarking.
We'll then dig into chapter
3, CRUD Optimizations,
where we'll talk about what
other factors can affect
performance, as
well as how indexes
can interact with your queries.
Here, we're going to
examine optimizing
your CRUD optimizations, covered
queries, regular expressions,
insert performance, index fields
with a mixture of data types,
and last we'll take a look
at how indexes interact
with the aggregation pipeline.
In the last chapter, we'll
talk about distributed systems.
Here, you're going to
learn about performance
considerations in a
distributed system,
increasing write performance
with sharding, reading
from secondaries in
your replica sets,
replica sets with
specialized indexes,
and finally, we'll discuss how
to optimize your aggregation
pipeline.
That's a great overview of
the content in this course.
Now that you know what
we're going to discuss,
let's get started.