Hi I'm Kirby.
Welcome to M 2 0 1
MongoDB performance.
Highly performant
database architectures
are a key condition of
mission critical software
infrastructure.
Throughout this course we're
going to discuss performance
in the context of MongoDB.
This course is
five chapters long,
with each chapter there will
be a new set of lesson videos.
After most of these
videos there'll
be a quiz to assess your
learning of the material.
At the end of each
chapter, there
will also be a set of
related lab exercises.
Let's go over a few
logistics of this course.
Target audience.
This is an intermediate
course suitable for people
on both the development
and operations teams.
It is expected that you have
some basic understanding
of databases.
How does grading work?
Well, there are quizzes,
labs, and a final exam
as deliverables on your
part of the course.
Quizzes are ungraded and
exist to make sure you're
understanding the content.
Your grade in the
class, however,
will be based on how
well you do on the labs
and on the final exam.
Each of these being worth
about 50% of your final grade.
Students who receive
a 65% or greater
will receive a passing grade
and will receive a certificate
of course completion.
Finally I'd highly
encourage you to participate
in our discussion forum.
We have knowledgeable teaching
assistants who are there
to help answer your questions.
And you also have
your fellow classmates
who can aid in
answering your questions
and are often very knowledgeable
and helpful resources.
Based on our
experience, we've seen
that students who perform
best in the course
are often those who are very
active in the discussion forum.
This course will be divided
into five main chapters.
There's the Overview chapter,
Indexes Index Operations,
CRUD Optimization, and
Distributed Systems.
Each of these topics
will take a deep dive
into one or more
performance related
aspects concerning MongoDB.
By the end of this
course, you should
be familiar with the
different techniques used
to increase the performance
of your MongoDB servers.
And you should be capable of
analyzing the different trade
offs that are
commonly encountered
in different
performance scenarios.
With all that being
said, we're super
excited to have
you in this course
and wish you the best of luck.