But do not forget that not
all writes and read operations
are non-locking operations.
Writing constantly
to the same document,
for example, and in
similar place updates
will require each write
to block all other writes
on that same document to comply.
In situations such as
this, multiple CPU's do not
help performance.
Because the threads can not
do their work in parallel.
Since always the
same document will
be affected by the same write.
As you probably already
noticed, MongoDB is a database.
And one of the things
expected from databases
is their ability to persist
information written.
Genius we may say.
For persisting data,
MongoDB will use disks.
The IOPS, which stands for input
output operations per second,
that your server DISK
provides, the faster
we can write and read data.
And the faster your
persistency layer
will respond to database
and application requests.
The types of disks will greatly
affect the overall performance
of your MongoDB deployment.
If we compare the
different types of disks.
HDDs, SSDs, EBS, volumes, in
terms of random access latency
and IOPS, we can
immediately tell
that there is going to be a big
difference between what one can
expect, in terms of
performance, given
the different types of disks
that we might be using.
This can be used in
different architectures.
More specifically, we can
use RAID architectures
in our servers for redundancy
of read and write operations.
MongoDB will benefit from some
but not all RAID architectures.
The recommended
RAID architecture
for MongoDB deployments
is RAID 10, or RAID 1- 0.
This architecture
is the one that
offers more redundancy
and safeguards
guarantees with a good
performance combination.
On the other hand, we highly
discourage deployments
that use RAID 5, or even RAID 6.
Since these do not typically
provide sufficient performance
to MongoDB deployments.
We also recommend
avoiding RAID 0.
Because while providing
good write performance,
it provides very
limited availability.
It can lead to reduced
performance on read operations.
Britain is a disk
architecture that
provides both
redundancy of segments
across physical drives.
But also allows
extended performance,
since it last
penalization of multiple
writes, reads, and
reads and writes.
In the same disk
allocated segments.
Which is quite awesome for
a database like MongoDB.
A particularly important
aspect of MongoDB
is the ability to use
several different disks.
That might be available
in your servers.
This will allow to distributing
IO load of different databases,
indexes, journaling, and
other files like lock files.
Which allow you to optimize your
MongoDB overall performance.
MongoDB deployments also
rely on network hardware.
Applications will
reach the database
by establishing connections
to the hosts, where
MongoDB instance is running.
The faster and the
larger the bandwidth
is for your network,
the better performance
you will experience.
But this is not the end of
the story regarding network
utilization with MongoDB.
MongoDB is a distributed
database for high availability.
Rapid [INAUDIBLE] clusters do
the high availability part.
But also for horizontal scaling,
where the shard and cluster in
all its different
components, allows
you to get a horizontal
distribution of your data.
The way that your
different hosts
that hold the different nodes
of your cluster are connected,
can affect the overall
performance of your system.
Also, the types of network
switches, load balancers,
firewalls, and how far apart
the cluster nodes are--
either by being distributed
across different data centers
or regions.
The type of connections
between data centers,
especially latency--
we haven't cracked going faster
than the speed of light yet--
will play a great deal in
the performance experienced
by your application.
This aligned with
the write concern,
read concern, and
read preference
that your application can
set while emitting commands
or doing requests
to the server, needs
to be taken into
consideration when
analyzing the performance
of your application.