When talking about performance,
we cannot forget about
the actual hardware
configuration that will support
our database and
application deployments.
A full disclosure of how to tune
and size your hardware needs,
for a given deployment, are
out of scope for this course.
We have other specific
courses on this subject.
That we recommend
you guys to take.
But let's just do a quick
pass on the hardware
and configuration of
our system, and why
it becomes an
essential consideration
for the overall performance
of your deployments.
MongoDB is a high
performance database.
But to operate correctly, while
supporting your applications,
requires adequate
hardware provisioning.
Let's review which hardware
resources and configurations we
have available.
And how MongoDB uses those
computational resources.
A computer or server can be
represented in its essence
by the Von Neumann architecture.
Where we are going to
have a CPU for processing
and calculations.
Memory for execution.
Disk and IO-- although
you may consider Disk
as another type of IO.
For persistency
and communications
between servers, or even
within our host processes.
These are the main resources
that MongoDB relies on
to operate adequately.
In MongoDB deployments, as in
many other modern databases,
memory is a
quintessential resource.
Over the past few years,
the availability of RAM
and the fall of its
production costs
contributed for the development
of databases' architectures.
That privileged the users
of this fast and performant
resource.
The fact that RAM or
memory is 25 times faster
than common SSDs also makes
this transition of Disk
oriented into RAM oriented a
nice, strong appealing factor
for databases to be designed
around usage of memory.
As a result of this,
MongoDB has storage engines
that are either very
dependent on RAM,
or even completely in
memory [? execution ?] modes
for its data
management operations.
A significant number of
operations rely heavily in RAM.
Like the aggregation
pipeline operations,
the index traversing.
Writes are first performed
in RAM allocated pages.
The query engine requires RAM
to retrieve the quarter results.
And finally, connections
are handling memory.
Roughly, one megabyte per
established connection.
And therefore they
require memory space.
It is safe to say that the
more RAM you have available,
the more performance your
department of MongoDB
will tend to be.
CPU is used by all applications
for computational processing.
Databases are just another
category of applications.
MongoDB is no different.
But the utilization
of this resource
is generally more attached
with two main factors.
Storage engines
that we are using,
and the concurrency
level that your MongoDB
instance will be subjected to.
By default, MongoDB will
try to use all available CPU
cores to respond to
incoming requests.
Our non-locking concurrency
control mechanism,
using wired tag
or storage engine,
rely heavily in the CPU
to process these requests.
This means that if we have
non-blocking operations,
like writing different documents
concurrently or responding
to an incoming query
requests like Reads,
MongoDB will perform
better the more CPU
resources we have available.
Also, there are certain
operations, like page
compression, data
calculation operations,
aggregation
framework operations,
and map reduce, amongst
others that will require
the availability of CPU cycles.