In this lesson, we're
going to discuss
the options available to
us when reading and parsing
through a document
using the Java driver.
We will contrast these
varying approaches to find
the one that suits us best.
For the purposes
of this lesson, we
will create an actors
collection that
contains documents
corresponding to each actor.
In our first example, we
want to create a basic case
where the structure
of the actor class
mimics a document from
the actors collection.
So we will call this
class actor basic.
Notice how each property data
type matches the document field
data type.
That is because this
method implies a strict one
to one correspondence between
document field data types
and the class
properties data types.
This method uses pojo code.
The first thing that we need
here is a pojo codec registry.
You can think of a registry as a
factory of codecs, where codecs
are an abstraction that
determines how Bson data is
converted and into what type.
There are default
and custom codecs.
So let's start
with a default one
and see what it can do for us.
The mechanism for
pojo support is
via the pojo codec
provider which
provides a builder
for configuring how
and what pojo to support.
The builder allows registering
of classes and packages
where the helpful setting
that directs the provider
to automatically try and
handle any pojo it sees.
Here, where instantiating
a codec registry
and telling you to use
the pojo codec provider,
building it with an
automatic setting which
uses type introspection
to determine
the properties of the
given pojo and accurately
apply the default codec.
Let us test this.
The first time we run this
test, it shouldn't work.
Why is that?
Well, our actor basic object
is the only point of reference
our codec registry has.
And it seems to me
that it is missing
some crucial information.
Let us add Bson annotations
in the actor basic class.
These add the field
name references
as part of our
actor basic class.
And the codec registry
is now able to see
the corresponding structure
between the actor basic object
and the document fields.
Let's run the test again.
Wonderful!
This basic case of
reading from the database
is not always close to reality.
As you have learned in earlier
lessons, a field in a database
can have different
data types, which
needs to be taken care of.
Additionally,
sometimes your app uses
data types that are
different from what
is stored in the database.
To demonstrate a
case like that, we
will use actor with
string ID object, which,
as you may have guessed,
is an actor class where
the ID field is not an object
ID, but a string instead.
In this case, we have
several different ways
to reach the desired
result. The first option
is to write a method that will
manually map each document
field to the actors string ID
properties by using set ID, set
name, and et cetera.
Our from document method
does exactly that,
and returns actor
with string ID object
that is filled
with the new data.
Let us test if our from
document mapper works,
and whether we were
able to successfully map
values in each field to
the values in the actor
with string ID class.
Reading seems to work.
But if we want to
write to the database,
we will have to
create a method that
does the reverse
of from document,
and manages data insertion
from actor class to document.
This process doesn't
seem too terrible
because of our simple use case.
But as the complexity and
size of our documents grows,
this can get more
tedious than needed.
There are easier approaches
to going from Bson
to a Java object.
So let's take advantage of
the simplicity of our case
and see what other options
are available to us,
namely, let's look
at a custom codec.