As you may have noticed from
the first example of using POJO
and a default
Codec, using a Codec
allows us to write cleaner code.
Theoretically, we could
use a default codec again.
But that would deprive
us of the opportunity
to have a value
assigned to the ID field
due to a type mismatch.
Because now, our ID field is
a string and not an object ID.
As you know, ID is the
document primary key,
which therefore uniquely
identifies a MongoDB document.
So it sounds like
something we want
to have in our actor with
string ID object, as well.
As of today, the default
Codec doesn't automatically
set the underscore ID value at
insert time using POJO Codec.
So there is a little
more work that
needs doing to have a
complete transfer of data.
To accommodate for the
missing underscore ID
value or any cross
type conversions,
we will use a custom Codec
that will help handle our POJO.
We've provided you with this
Codec for our specific use
case.
Feel free to take a look
and see how it works.
Now, with our custom
Codec in place,
we can encode a bson
object ID straight
into the object with string
ID value, among other things.
We first establish the use
of our new custom Codec.
Then we create a Codec registry
with this custom Codec.
Finally, we can access
the actors collection
with the use of our custom Codec
that is specifically tailored
for the actor documents.
We can then retrieve our actor
from the collection as an actor
with string ID object.
Let's test if this works.
Fabulous.
The question now
is, why use POJO
over manually mapping field
values into the object
attributes?
Well, the first reason
for me is that it is
a more elegant implementation.
The second is writing.
When you use POJO
with a custom Codec,
not only do you get
to read directly
from bson into your
object in a cleaner way,
but you also get to write
straight from an object
into a bson collection.
While you can do
this with POJO code,
you will have to sacrifice
any type of mismatching
between your class objects
and the supported bson types,
like in our ID field case.
So let's look at the
custom Codec example
to demonstrate the write.
Just like before, we create
a new actor Codec object,
which is our custom Codec.
We now create a Codec registry
using that custom Codec,
and we can then access our
collection using our custom
Codec registry.
Create a new actor
with string ID
and write it directly
to that collection.
Check that the idea value is
not known and see if it works.
And it does.
Finally, the last method
that we wanted to show you
is the one that allows us to
use a default Codec registry
while customizing the
fields that we know
need special treatment.
For example, if you
have a field that
would need type conversion,
like our ID field,
or has various different
data types in it.
This needs to be addressed
when the documents are
read into our JAVA application.
So here's another
approach to handling it.
In this case, we will use
the default Codec registry
while applying a custom approach
to the field in question,
which, in our case,
is the ID field.
We create a custom
Codec for that field
specifically instead of creating
it for the whole object.
So first, we select
a class that will
be used as our POJO,
which, in our case,
is the actor with
string ID class.
We then get the property that
needs type conversion, which,
in our case, is the
ID property, and then
apply type conversion to
the property of interest.
String object ID Codec
describes specifically
how to encode and decode
the object ID into a string,
and vise versa.
We use the default
Codec registry
with the changes implemented
above to registering a class
model builder with the
POJO Codec provider.
And we're done.
Let's test if this worked.
Looks like it did.
Let us now run all the test
cases we talked about today
and see if we can
summarize what we learned.
Excellent.
Everything checks out.
Let's recap the advantages
and disadvantages
of the methods discussed
in today's lesson.
First, the POJO implementation
is much cleaner.
It outsources
translation between BSON
and object to a
custom Codec, which
makes it easier to manage
and maintain the code.
In either approach,
the field names
don't have to match the
object attribute name.
In case of the
custom codec, this
is easy to accommodate in
the code by the BSON property
annotation only
for the fields that
don't correspond to the
attribute name one-to-one.
To map the document
to an object manually,
you have to make use of getters
and setters, while using a POJO
allows for automatic
introspection.
Also, handling of
generics and sub-documents
is cleaner and easier
to maintain with POJO,
utilizing the custom Codec
or the field customization
approach instead of
writing separate methods
to traverse sub-documents
with getters and setters.
Finally, when writing a
document object to the database,
the document ID is
automatically generated
and can be accessed
in the document
object for the subsequent
use of the mapping method.