In this lesson, we're going
to perform our first read
operation in MongoDB
using the Java driver.
We've taken care of setting
up our database handle
in the abstract lesson class.
So let's get started.
If you've used other
drivers in the past
you may be familiar with a
find one collection method.
The Java driver for MongoDB
includes no such method.
To find a single document,
we'll use the limit() method,
which you'll learn
about in a later lesson.
This will find
the first document
that matches a query
predicate in natural sort
order, most likely as they
were entered into the database.
We do not expect the
document returned to be null,
so we name this, unexpected.
Find() returns a find iterable.
We use the iterator()
method to convert this
into a MongoCursor.
Because you're passing in a new
document with no information,
we'd expect it to find the
first document encountered
in the collection.
In the MongoDB shell
this would look like,
movies.find().limit(1).
We use the next method to get
the next item in the iterator.
Running this test, we should
expect some random document,
and after we've consumed
the iterator with next(),
we expect the iterator
to have nothing left.
Excellent.
Let's go ahead and
find a document
that matches a predicate.
For this example,
we will find a movie
where Salma Hayek is
listed in the cast field.
Let's define our query.
We want a document where
the value, Salma Hayek,
is at the cast key.
Because cast is
an array, MongoDB
will look at all elements
of the array to match this.
This is because MongoDB treats
arrays as first class objects.
And here we're using a
shorthand for find one,
like used in the previous test.
What might happen if we were to
call next on an iterator, that
didn't have anything in it?
It will throw a
NoSuchElementException.
Let's issue a query that
won't match anything.
This, will throw a
NoSuchElementException.
To be safe, we should
use the tryNext() method.
This will return null if
nothing exists in the iterator.
Finding one document is
useful, but it's only
one particular use case.
What if we want to
find all documents that
match a predicate?
One method to do
so is following.
Our query is the same as our
previous query, where Salma
Hayek, is in the cast field.
We will create an ArrayList()
to hold our results,
then we issue a query,
and send them directly
into our container.
From previously exploring the
data set, we expect 29 results.
Let's look at one of
the documents now.
We'll look at the output
on the test results.
Here the title is,
Roadracers, year 1994,
and so on, and so on,
and in the cast field
there she is, Salma Hayek.
Looking at the document,
we can see that there
is a lot of information.
What if we only wanted
the title and year?
You may be familiar with
projection mechanics
in the Mongo shell, where
we might do something like,
db.movies.find cast Salma
Hayek title 1, year 1.
The collection object also
has projection functionality,
but the usage is different
than that in the Mongo shell.
Because we specified that
we want to keep two keys,
and didn't explicitly
remove the ID key,
we expect to get a document
back with three keys
title, year, and ID.
And let's make sure that
they are what we expected.
So as we just saw, unless we
explicitly remove the ID key,
it will remain in the
result. To remove the ID,
we can pass zero in the
projection() argument.
Remember, one means
retain, and 0 means remove.
For this example, let's
also search for movies
where Johnny Depp, is
a cast member as well.
We'll build a query so that only
movies with both Salma Hayek,
and Johnny Depp, are returned.
For that, we'll use the
$all operator, in the shell,
this would be
something like this.
So there should only be
one result in our data set,
and now we should only have
two keys, title and year.
Querying MongoDB through the
driver may feel odd at first,
but eventually it will
feel like second nature.
We saw how to limit the
results to one document,
or get all documents that
match a query filter.
We also saw how to
include, only the fields
we wanted in the result set,
and how to remove the ID field.
A few things to keep in
mind, finding one document
typically involves querying on
a unique index, such as the ID
field.
When projecting, by specifying
inclusion for example,
title 1, all fields
we don't include,
will be excluded,
except for the ID field.
If we don't want the ID
field returned to us,
we must explicitly exclude it.
Lastly, the specific query
patterns you saw here
are much easier to build,
again more in a future lesson.