In this lesson, we
are going to connect
your newly created Atlas
cluster to MongoDB Compass
and explore some of the
functionality of Compass.
If you don't have
Compass on your machine,
please download it by
following the link below.
First, let's connect
to our Atlas cluster.
After following the
read me, your cluster
should look something like this.
In Atlas, hit Connect
under the cluster name.
And then connect
with MongoDB Compass.
If you have Compass open
when you're doing this,
you'll notice a message
pop-up saying that a MongoDB
connection string is detected.
If you click on Yes,
most of the information
required for the connection
will be filled in for you.
The only thing that you
will have to specify
is the password.
Otherwise, make sure that
the filled in information
corresponds to what is provided
for you below the video.
And hit Connect.
Once connected, you
should be able to see
the databases available to you.
Admin and local are
default databases
and are already in place
when you create a cluster.
Let's take a look at mflix,
which we recently imported.
You can select the database
that you're interested in
either from the left
menu, where you can also
get the list of the
collections in the database,
or by clicking on the
database in the right section
of the screen.
Today, we will explore
the movies collection.
This is the Documents
tab that gives you
a preview of the documents
in the collection.
Here, you can see that there is
a document with a film titled
Carmencita with a
cast of one person,
Carmencita, a poster located
at the given URL, and so on.
Not all documents have all
the same fields as this one.
And various fields contain
various data types in them.
You can explore this tab
later on your own time.
To get a better overview of
the various data types that
are involved in the
movies collection,
we will check out the
Schema tab in Compass.
But, first, let's clarify
what schema means.
Schema is structure.
And in case of MongoDB,
it is document structure.
MongoDB is a flexible
schema database,
which simply means that
the structure isn't
enforced unless you tell it so.
For example, you can see that
in this document some fields are
present in all documents
and some aren't.
Let's move on to the Schema tab.
Hit Analyze Schema.
Analyze Schema gives us
a summary of the document
structure based on a
sample of 1,000 documents
in the collection.
This allows us to
explore another aspect
of a schema flexible
database, which
is that you can create
collections with fields that
have varying value types
across different documents
without getting an error.
The left column represents the
field names and data types.
The right column gives
us a general summary
about the values
these fields hold.
For example, if we look
at the awards field,
we can see that
some of the values
are strings, while
some are undefined.
And if you look at
the graph on the right
and you hover over some
of the values there,
you see that 10% of the
films have one nomination, 6%
have two wins, and so on.
The cast field is
a bit different
and seems to be
mostly array values
with a small fraction
of the values having
an undefined type.
An array does not
give us quite enough
information about
the field, which
is why underneath that label
you can see string label, which
tells us that the
values in these arrays
are of type string.
Clicking from one to another
gives us a different kind
of summary on the right.
With array, we get the
summary about arrays.
With string, we get the
sample of string values.
Other interesting data types
that we can observe here
are date, integer, and
document, which you
can explore in a similar way.
You can use the
Schema tab to get
an idea of the
documents and data types
that you will be dealing with.
Another useful Compass feature
is located in the Aggregations
tab.
If you don't have the
latest version of Compass,
but you want to have
access to this feature,
feel free to pause
this video and update
your version of Compass
to any version above 1.14.
Throughout this course,
you will be exposed to
and will work with different
types of MongoDB queries.
The Aggregations
tab in Compass helps
to organize, construct,
save, and more
when working with
aggregation queries.
You will cover the
details of how exactly
an aggregation query works
later in this course.
For the purposes
of this lecture,
I'm going to create a
simple query looking
for all documents whose
director field value matches
Sam Raimi, the great director
of the Army of Darkness
and other masterpieces.
What if I wanted to use this
query in my code somewhere?
We can do that, too.
Hit the Menu icon on the
right of SAVE PIPELINE,
and select Export To Language.
Feel free to look at the
other options in that drop
down menu in your spare time.
They are all addressed in
our documentation in the link
below.
To use this query
in your application,
you selected Export To Language.
And, now, you can select the
language of your choice, which
in our case is Java.
Success.
You can now copy a
line of Java code
into your Java-based
application.
And if you haven't yet
import to the libraries
necessary for MongoDB
and Java to communicate,
you can select Include
Import Statements
to see which tools are needed
for this particular query
to run successfully.
You can then copy, paste this
in the appropriate section
of your application and get
along with your development.
You can check out the
documentation for this feature
by following the linked below.
Feel free to experiment
with these features
and try them out on your
own before moving on
to the next lecture.
This is the end of our
Compass Basics lesson.
Enjoy what follows.