Let's start by
instantiating MongoClient
object since this is the
pillar of our client--
your code-- and server--
the atlas cluster--
communication.
To do this, we'll be using
the MongoClients builder.
For this example, we'll
be using MongoDB uri
that defines to which cluster
how we should be connecting.
Once I have my
connection string,
I can go ahead and
call MongoClients
and create a MongoClient
instance by providing the user
uri string.
The MongoClients object will
create a MongoClient instance
by extracting the client
connection settings
from the connection string.
However, we can extend
the configuration
by setting configuration
options that may not
be present in the
connection string uri
by sending the MongoDB
client's object.
This class contains
a builder method,
a static class
method called builder
that allows you to compose
the different types of client
settings upon each other.
So in this case, we are
applying the connection string
that we created
via the uri string,
we are applying an application
name to the client connection
settings, and
we're also creating
an applyToConnectionPoolSettings
by calling a lambda that
calls a builder that allows
you to define, for example,
connection pool settings
like maxWaitTime.
Once we call build, we can
pass that client's settings
and create our mongoClient with
the create MongoClients method.
Once we run this test, we
can see that everything,
it's properly
asserted as NotNull.
Now that we have a
MongoClient instance,
we can go ahead and
connect to our cluster
and list all available databases
by calling listDatabaseNames.
This will be very similar
to do the following command
in the shell--
db.getMongo( ).getDatabaseNames.
This command returns a
MongoIterable instance,
an iterable object that
we can use to iterate over
results of a given command.
We will use MongoIterable
quite a lot in this course.
Important to note that
iterable instances get
exhausted, like a
cursor, so you may
want to consider using the
iterable instance to fill
arrays and lists if you need
to go over the contents more
than once.
Then we have our
MongoDatabase object.
We will use this
object to the access,
create, and drop
our collections,
run commands, and define
database-level preferences,
read concerns, and a lot of
other different configuration
options.
To get the database,
we just need
to do mongoClient.getDatabase
and provide
the name of the database that
we are interested on accessing.
Here, because we did not
specify a Read Preference,
the driver will use the default
configuration which is primary.
If we run the tests, you can
see that everything gets green,
and all of our
databases get listed.
A MongoCollection
instance is what
is used to read and write to
the documents which is usually
the entity the application
processes to manipulate
the data it needs.
To instantiate a
collection, we need
to provide a collection name to
the MongoDB database instance.
In this example, we are
using the basic form
of interacting
with data defining
the MongoCollection
where we return Document
instances from any given query.
However, MongoCollection
allows us to specify Codec
so that we can return
business objects,
application-defined classes,
as return of the queries.
More about this on our
POJO support lessons.
All of our Data
Manipulation language--
DML-- will be expressed via
a MongoCollection instance.
Once we run the tests,
again, everything gets green.
The basic data structures
in MongoDB are documents.
The document model
is what we consider
to be the best way
to represent data.
Using documents makes your
application definition
as close as possible to
your OOP object models.
Since we are dealing with an
Object-Oriented Programming
language like Java,
having a class
that represents the document's
structure becomes imperative.
So in this case, I'm
going to instantiate here
a new document which will
have a particular structure.
This document defines
a MongoDB document
that looks like this
in its JSON format
where we have a name
which has two fields--
first and last.
And obviously, we can
use those documents to be
inserted into the collection.
We use documents for
everything in MongoDB
to define data objects,
define queries,
define update operations,
define configuration settings.
At the Java layer, we
have the document class,
but we also have the BSON class.
The Document class
implements the BSON interface
because Documents, well,
they are essentially
BSON data structures.
We will use instances of
BSON, throughout the course,
to define fine-tuned
aspects of our queries
like query operators
and aggregation stages.
More on that in the
next following lectures.
So let's recap.
Application needs to use a
client-side library, a driver,
to interact with MongoDB.
There are two types of
drivers, async and sync,
which we will be
using in this course.
And there are a few basic
MongoDB Java driver classes
that define the
MongoDB server data
structures like MongoClients,
MongoDatabase, MongoCollection,
Document, and BSON.