Hello and welcome to
Chapter One of the course.
We've already covered all of
the bookkeeping information
for the course and explored
the application structure.
So now it's time to dive in.
In this chapter we're going to
discuss and explore basic read
operations, adding
fuel protections,
and how to handle
different query predicates
to allow searching our
data set from the UI.
Our goal is that by
the end of this chapter
you are comfortable
with basic query
semantics and basic shaping
operations the decline
application might
typically require.
Remember to read those
user stories closely
and run the unit tests.
And I hope you enjoy
this chapter of M220.