In this lesson, we are going
to start using our MongoDB Java
driver by creating a
database connection,
and walk you through
the different objects
that this library
exposes in order
for us to build
applications and manipulate
data stored in MongoDB.
So let's first define what
we are going to be using.
To communicate with the
MongoDB database server, that
in this course is hosted
by our MongoDB Atlas,
we need to establish a
connection between the client
and the server.
To do that, we need to use
a client-side library that
enables our application code to
establish such communication.
These client-side
libraries are called
drivers in MongoDB lingo.
There are numerous
types of drivers
from MongoDB covering all
the most common programming
languages.
In this course, we'll be using
the official Java MongoDB
driver.
For Java, we publish
two different drivers--
mongodb-driver-sync,
for synchronous,
which we'll be using in this
course, mongodb-driver-async,
for asynchronous.
That uses callbacks to
interact with the application.
We are not going to cover
the asynchronous driver
in this course.
However, feel free to go ahead
and experiment on your own.
There is a third driver, our
uber mongodb-driver-legacy,
which we have since
deprecated, which
is used to combine both
the sync and async models.
You should not be using
that going forward.
Within our [? mflex ?]
application,
we have already set up
the dependencies for you,
so no need to take any action.
But it is always good to
know what is out there,
so you can make the appropriate
decision for your own projects.
Within the driver, there
are a set of object classes
that we need you to know of--
the MongoDB client, the
base connection class
that handles
configuration options
and establishes
the communication
between the cluster and
the application, your app.
The MongoDB database, the
MongoCollection class, and then
we have Bson objects.
Well, that is also defined
in the Java driver classes,
since Document implements
the Bson interface.
We will be using
Document quite a lot,
especially to define
corporate tickets
and return back documents
from the collections.
But we are also
going to be using
quite a lot of Bson objects
to define components
of our query predicates,
update objects, aggregation
stages, and some other
types of operations.
In MongoDB nearly every
piece of information
from the database data
communication inquiries
are documents.
So it's a very important
class to keep in mind.
In essence, these are the main
basic objects that our MongoDB
Java driver exposes.
But enough talk.
Let's see these
objects in action.