In this lesson, we're going
to use the builders that
are included in the
MongoDB Java Driver
to greatly ease the composition
and structure of our queries.
There are several builder
classes to help us.
They are filters, projections,
sorts, aggregation, updates,
and indexes.
In this lesson, we'll go
over filters and projections.
Let's get started.
Let's find the movie
with Salma Hayek
in it composing a query
directly with the document
and an identical query
with filters builders.
In the shell, this
would be db.movies.find
cast: Salma Hayek, limit 1.
First, we'll look at what the
raw document looks like where
we create a new document and
specify that the cast should
equal Salma Hayek.
given what we know
from the data set,
the title should be Roadracers,
and the expected year is 1994.
And now with the
filters API, notice
that we've made the
switch from document Bson.
Here, we're using
the equal filter,
specifying that the field name
cast should equal Salma Hayek.
We issue our query the same way.
And the result here and the
result here should match.
Great, we got the same results.
Now, I don't know about
you, but this feels
like a much better API to me.
Let's look at a
query where we want
to find movies with both
Salma Hayek and Johnny Depp
as cast members.
So in the shell, this
would be db.movie.find cast
$all: Salma Hayek Johnny Depp.
And here's how we do
it with a raw document.
Cast, and then a
new document $all.
And specifying a list,
Salma Hayek and Johnny Depp.
We'll issue our query
and store our results.
There should be only one result.
Now let's look how to
do this with filters.
Again, we used the Bson class.
And this time, we
specify all, cast, values
Salma Hayek, Johnny Depp.
We issue our query and
assert that the results here
will equal the results here.
And they do.
Now, I'd argue that this
query is much cleaner.
Filters contains all of the
operators you may be used to.
Now, let's issue a query
that's slightly more complex.
We'll find all movies where Tom
Hanks is a cast member released
after 1990 but before 2005 with
a minimum metacritic of 80.
So here, we specify
equal cast Tom Hanks.
Greater than where the year
is 1990, less than year 2005.
And gte, or greater than
or equal to, metacritic
with a value of 80.
Here, we issue our
query and store them
into our results array list.
And we should get four results
back with the titles Forrest
Gump, Toy Story, Toy Story
2, and Saving Private Ryan.
Perfect.
Filters are powerful and
easier to work with compared
to assembling a document.
We highly recommend
you use them.
Let's move onto projections.
Projections are very
succinct and expressive,
allowing us to say what we mean.
Let's look at an example.
In this projection, we'll
specify that we only
want the title and year fields.
And we'll forget to
project away the _id field.
In the shell, this will look
like db.movies.find cast: Salma
Hayek.
and we project title 1, year 1.
Here, we assemble
our query using
a raw document and a projection
using a raw document.
title 1, and we append year 1.
We should have three keys--
title, year, and _ID.
Now, with projections, it takes
on a slightly different form.
Here, we're using
a filter builder
saying where the cast
should equal Salma Hayek.
We issue our query.
And this time in the projection,
we just specify the fields
that we'd like to include--
title and year.
And this result should
equal the previous result.
Now, let's say we want
to exclude the _ID field.
Well, we issue the same query.
And this time in the projections
we specified fields to
include as well as exclude.
Perfect.
The results from the old
style the new style matched.
If we only wanted to
exclude the _ID field,
there is a convenience
method to do so--
excludeId.
Here, we specify our find.
And in projection, the fields
we include are title and year.
And we've specified that
we'd like to exclude the _ID.
And this result should match
our previous result where we
manually specified
to remove the _ID.
Great.
This concludes our
lesson on builders.
Let's summarize.
Builders allow us to be
extremely expressive.
They include all of the query
operators and projection
operators to allow us to
fine-tune our queries.
Here are a few things
to keep in mind.
Filters can be composed
together for robust queries.
Projections offers methods
such as include, exclude,
and exclude _ID.
Projections also
includes methods
for every other projection
operation supported by MongoDB.
And that's our
lesson on builders.