Hello.
In this lesson, we're going
to review our application
architecture and
functionality, as well
as some tools that we'll use to
build and test the application.
You will be working on
MFlix, a service that
allows users to browse
for their favorite movies,
see the movie reviews, and
leave their own impressions
about a given motion
picture for others to see.
To get access to the
app and the tickets
that you will be working
on, please download
the handout available
for this lesson.
In it, you will find
all the material
that will be used
throughout this course.
At the top level of
the MFlix Java handout,
you will find a
README file, which
helps you setup all the
necessary components
and dependencies that you
need for MFlix to function.
When you set everything up,
please follow the README
carefully.
And if you hit any roadblocks,
remember to check out
the class online forum.
Before we talk about the
front and back-end components,
it is important
to mention that we
will be using Maven to aid
in compiling and managing
our code, and Spring Boot as the
framework for our application.
The files pertaining
to Maven are
located at the top of
the MFlix directory.
They should not be
modified for Maven
to serve its purpose
successfully.
Feel free to take a
look at these files.
However, you will not
need to change anything.
We will not be covering
Spring Boot or Maven in-depth
in this course feel free to
explore those tools on your own
by following the
documentation links that
are attached to this lesson.
Maven allows you to run commands
and most of the necessary tests
from the command line.
Simply type mvn test to
run all the test files,
or type mvn spring-boot:run
to run the application.
However, you do not need to
run tests or launch MFlix
from the command line.
You can use your ID for
those tasks just as well.
Keep this functionality in
mind as an alternative way
to quickly check your
progress as you're
moving along the
tickets in this course.
As you just saw, the Maven files
are already complete for you
and have full
functionality, which
is why they are marked
in red in this diagram.
That is to signify that they
won't require any changes
throughout this course.
The entire app infrastructure
is built for you
under the source within
the main directory.
Before we get to
look at that, it
is important to address
the testing of the app
functionality that
you will be building.
The unit tests are
created for you,
and are placed in
the test folder.
When working on
the tickets, first
read the ticket description.
Then to verify
your understanding,
check out the respective unit
test in the test java mflix api
daos directory.
For every ticket
that you complete,
there is always a
corresponding test file.
You may notice that there is
an additional folder called
lessons under the
test directory.
This folder contains
example code
that will be used throughout
the course during lectures.
You may use the files in this
directory to follow along.
Now, we can finally address the
front and back-end components
of our application.
Follow me along this
journey up and back
down the directory tree.
We need to get back to source,
then get on our merry way
to main.
Since your assignments
for this course
will be tickets that
focus on the API
implementation and the app
to database communication,
there will be no need to modify
the front-end files, which
are all located
under the resources
in the build directory.
However, you will,
at some point,
have to make changes to the
application properties file,
as you hopefully
saw in the README.
So where are the tickets?
The files you will be working
on to complete the tickets
are located under the java
mflix api daos directory.
You will see other files
and folders along the way.
Pay no attention to them,
as they are set in stone,
and do not need to be
modified for the app to work.
In daos, you will find
the Movies.Dao, UsersDao,
and other files.
These are the
files that you will
need to edit to complete
your tickets, adding
awesome functionality
to MFlix, to the delight
of its users and yourself.
Once a ticket is
complete, remember
to extend beyond the unit
test and observe the added
functionality by using
the MFlix user interface.
Given that we're
working in Java,
it is important to mention
how the strongly-typed nature
of Java will affect some
aspects of our development.
If you're not familiar of
the term strongly-typed,
feel free to pause this video
and follow the linked below
to get a brief
overview of the term.
As you know, when
working with Java,
you have to declare a
data type for every object
that you create, and
that object is then
bound to the declared data type.
From the previous
lesson, you also
know that MongDB's
almost the exact opposite
of that, and almost
any field can have
different data types as values.
While the difference between
types like int and long
shouldn't be an issue
when parsing data in Java,
we might run into issues
with other data types.
This is important
to keep in mind,
and we will certainly
be addressing
this in a separate
lesson down the line.
This is the end of our
brief overview of the MFlix
architecture.