Hi MongoDB Java developer,
welcome to M220J.
I'm Varsha and it's my pleasure
to be one of your instructors.
This course is one of
our language variant
courses for MongoDB developers.
It's intended for people who
have taken our introduction
to MongoDB course or have two
to three months of experience
working with MongoDB.
You should have
basic familiarity
with Java before
starting this course.
Here, you will learn how to
use MongoDB's Java driver
to build performant, resilient,
and robust applications.
You'll be put in the
role of a new developer
on a team implementing the
database layer of an API.
Each lab in this course
is called a ticket
and each ticket has a
user story and unit tests.
For a given ticket, you
will read the user story,
make all the tests pass,
and use the pre-packaged UI
to run integration tests
and get your validation code
for the corresponding ticket.
Throughout this
course, you will learn
to create and share a
database connection,
perform the basic Create, Read,
Update, and Delete operations
through the driver, handle
errors, utilize the MongoDB
best practices and more.
The technology stack
is pretty simple.
We're using Spring Boot,
MongoDB, and React.
The React application is
pre-built and bundled for you
and the API layer is
also fully implemented.
You'll only be
implementing the functions
which directly call to MongoDB.
So welcome again to this course.
We hope you enjoy the material
that we've prepared for you
and wish you the best of luck.