In the previous
lesson, we talked
about what a shard key is.
Now, we're going to talk about
what makes a good shard key.
First, let's recap.
You enable sharding
at the database level.
You shard collections.
Enabling sharding on a
database does not automatically
shard the collections
in that database.
And, you can have both sharded
and unsharded collections
in the same database.
Not all collections
need to be equal.
First, let's talk about using
a shard key that provides
good right distribution.
These are the three
basic properties, here.
The cardinality of
the shard key values,
the frequency of the shard key
values, and whether or not the
shard key increases or
decreases monotonically.
We're going to go over
each of these one by one.
The first, is that
the chosen shard key
should have high cardinality.
Cardinality is the measure
of the number of elements
within a set of values.
In context of the
shard key, it is
the number of unique
possible shard key values.
This is important
for two reasons.
The first is that if
your shard key supports
a small number of unique
possible values, then
that constrains the
number of shards
you can have in your cluster.
Remember, chunks
define boundaries
based on shard key
values, and a unique value
can only exist on one chunk.
Let's say we shard
on a field whose
values are the number of
states in the United States
of America.
That's 50 states, so
50 possible values
and an upper limit of 50 chunks.
And, therefore, 50 shards.
That's quite good, but imagine
if we, instead, sharded
on the days of the week.
Now we're down to 7 shards.
What if we happen to pick a
shard key that was a boolean?
Now we're down to two shards.
Having a higher cardinality
gives you more chunks,
and with more chunks the
number of shards can also grow,
not restraining your
ability to grow the cluster.
I mentioned two reasons earlier.
The second reason is actually
related to our next property.
The frequency of a
shard key represents
how often a unique value
occurs in the data.
Going back to our
states example,
imagine if we have a workload
where 90% of the time
we're inserting documents
where the state is New York.
That means 90% of
our data is going
to end up in the chunk whose
range include New York.
That's not good.
Remember that a chunk
lives in a single shard.
So now 90% of our writes
are going to this one
shard that has that one chunk.
That's pretty
severe hot spotting,
and that's not what we want.
Remember the
cardinality property?
Even though the values
for possible states
had high cardinality,
our workload
has high frequency,
leading to bad performance.
If our workload
has a low frequency
of the possible
shard key values,
then the overall distribution
is going to be more even.
Now, if I have a very
low frequency shard key
combined with very
low cardinality,
like days of the week, I'm
still potentially going
to have problems.
So the two of these properties
work very closely together.
Finally, we have to
consider whether or not
the shard is
monotonically changing.
Monotonically
changing here means
that the possible shard key
values for a new document
changes at a steady
and predictable rate.
Think of a field that
has numeric progression.
Time stamps or
dates, for example,
are monotonically increasing.
Similarly, a stopwatch timer
is a monotonically decreasing
value.
Why is this a problem?
Remember that MongoDB splits
your documents into chunks
of data, each chunk having
an inclusive lower bound,
and then exclusive upper
bound to shard key values.
All documents that fall
into the range of a chunk
are stored in that chunk.
If all of your new documents
have a higher shard key value
than the previous
one, then they're
all going to end up
in that one chunk that
contains the upper boundary of
your possible shard key values.
So, even though timestamps
are technically very high
cardinality, lots
of unique values,
and very low frequency,
nearly no repetition
of those unique
values, it ends up
being a pretty bad shard key.
Fun fact, the
object ID data type
is actually
monotonically increasing.
That's why sharding on the
ID field isn't a good idea.
There are some tricks for
achieving even distribution
of monotonically changing
shard key's, and we're
going to talk about
that in a later lesson.
The ideal shard key
provides good distribution
of its possible values,
have high cardinality,
low frequency, and
change non monotonically.
A shard key that can
fulfill those properties
is more likely to result in an
even distribution of written
data.
Having a shard key
that doesn't quite
fulfill one of these
property doesn't
guarantee bad
distribution of data,
but it's not going to help.
So far, we've talked
about properties
that allow for good
right distribution,
but there is one other thing
to consider-- read isolation.
MongoDB can route queries
that include the shard key
to specific chunks,
whose range contains
the specified shard key values.
Going back to the
states example,
if my query includes
state New York,
MongoDB can direct
my read to the shard
that contains my data.
These targeted queries are
very fast because MongoDB only
needs to check in with a single
shard before returning results.
When choosing a
shard key, you should
consider whether
your choice supports
the queries you run most often.
Now, it's possible that
the fields you query on
make for pretty bad shard keys.
In that case, consider
specifying a compound index
as the underlying index
for the shard key, where
the extra field
or fields provide
high cardinality, low
frequency, or are themselves
non monotonically changing.
So, without the shard
key to guide it,
MongoDB has to ask
every single shard
to check if it has the data
that we're looking for.
These broadcast operations
are scatter gather operations
and can be pretty slow.
Let's go over some
considerations
of choosing a shard key.
We've already
talked about these,
but I want to emphasize them.
You cannot unshard a
collection once sharded.
You cannot update a shard
key once you have sharded
a collection.
You cannot update the values for
that shard key for any document
in the collection.
What that basically means is
that your choice of shard key
is final.
Whenever possible, try to test
your shard keys in a staging
environment first,
before sharding
in production environments.
If you use the Mongo dump
and Mongo restore utilities,
you can dump, drop, and
restore the collection.
But that's non-trivial.
So again, whenever
possible, you really
want to test in a
staging environment
where you can safely
drop and restore
the collection without
impacting production workloads.
Let's recap.
Good shard keys provide
even right distribution
and, where possible,
read isolation
by supporting targeted queries.
You want to consider the
cardinality and frequency
of the shard keys, and
avoid monotonically changing
shard keys.
Finally, really
remember, unsharding
a collection is hard.
You really want to avoid it.