In a prior lesson, we
talked about how the Mongos
routes queries at a high level.
We're going to dig into
more detail here on targeted
versus scatter
gather query routing.
Remember that each
shard contains
chunks of sharded data,
where each chunk represents
an inclusive lower bound
and exclusive upper bound.
The context of a replica
set keeps a table
of the shard chunk The Mongos
s keeps a cached local copy
of this metadata table.
That means that each Mongos has
a map of which shard contains
any given shard key value.
Briefly, minKey represents
the lowest possible shard
key value.
Think of this like
minus infinity,
while maxKey represents the
highest possible shard key
value, maximum infinity for
you math purists out there.
These chunks handle capturing
the lower and upper boundaries
of your shard key
values, so that you
don't have to worry
about redefining what
the lowest or highest
possible shard key value
is for the collection.
So when the Mongos receives a
query whose predicate includes
the shard key, the Mongos
can look at the table
and know exactly which
shards to direct at query to.
The Mongos opens a cursor
against only those shards
that can satisfy
the query predicate.
Because the Mongos is
targeting the query
to a subset of shards
in the cluster,
these targeted queries
are generally faster
than having to check in with
every shard in the cluster.
If, for example, the Mongos
can satisfy the entire query
by targeting a single
shard, then the Mongos
can even bypass the merge stage
and just return the results.
This is particularly fast.
When the query predicate does
not include the shard key,
than the Mongos cannot derive
exactly which shards satisfy
the query.
These scatter gather queries
must necessarily ping and wait
for the reply of every
shard in the cluster,
regardless if they
have something
to contribute towards the
execution of the query or not.
Depending on the number
of shards in your cluster,
the amount of network latency
between shards and Mongos
and a number of other factors,
these queries can be slow.
That's why we advised
in the Shard key lessons
to choose a shard
key that satisfies
the majority of your
queries, or at least the most
common and important ones.
Now, on a similar note, ranged
queries on a hashed shard key
are almost always
scatter gather,
because two adjacent
shard key values are
likely to be on two
completely different chunks.
There's a pretty low
probability that the Mongos
will be able to satisfy
the ranged query
with a subset of shards
within the hash based
ranged query predicate.
Single document queries
on a hashed shard key
can still be targeted though.
One thing to emphasize, if
you're using a compound index
as your shard key, then you
can specify each prefix up
to the entire shard key and
still get a targeted query.
So let's say we have a shard
key on sku, type, and name.
I can use any of the
shard key prefix fields,
up to the full shard key,
to perform a targeted query.
But I can't use any arbitrary
field in the shard key.
So even though type and name are
part of the shard key itself,
I haven't included the full
prefix leading up to either
of these fields, so we cannot
get our targeted query.