OK, so MongoDB can scale.
Awesome.
Let's do it then.
Let's go ahead and build
the scalable cluster right
off the bat.
OK.
Not so fast young Padawan.
Let's look into when you should
definitely consider to shard.
First let's understand
what indicators we
should check for to see if
we really got to the moment
for sharding.
One of the first things
to do is to check out
if it is still economically
viable to vertical scale.
When we need to address
a throughput performance
or volume bottleneck,
which are generally
the technical drivers for adding
more resources to your system,
the first step would be to
check if we can still add
more resources and scale up.
Great, but we need to
validate that adding
more of those vertical
resources, such as adding more
CPU, network, memory, or disk
to your existing servers,
is economically
viable and possible.
So in case we have a
small set of servers,
checking that, increasing that
server's unit resources, in any
of the identified
resource bottlenecks,
gives you an
increased performance
with very little downtime
in an economical scale way.
Adding 10 times more RAM to
solve a memory allocation
bottleneck does not cost you 100
times more, if that's the case,
great.
That should be your reasoning
for continuing to scale up.
You are still able to do so
in economical viable manner,
but you will eventually
reach a point
where vertical scaling is no
longer economically viable
or it's very difficult to
say impossible to accomplish.
Let's say that your current
architecture relies on servers
that cost $100 per hour.
You have three
member rep cassettes,
so you're sitting on
top of $300 per hour.
The next available type of
server costs $1,000 per hour,
but where your overall impact
in performance is only of 2x,
that is probably not going
to be a very wise decision.
10 times the cost per server for
only two times the performance
overall.
You will probably
be way better off
with a horizontal scale
where you increase in cost
will be, let's say, three times.
Three more servers for
another rep cassette,
plus three more for your
configuration servers,
with a potential increase
of performance of 2x.
$900 per hour is more
acceptable than $3,000
for the same
performance improvement.
The economics here will
play a considerable weight
in your decision.
Another aspect to
consider is the impact
on your operational tasks.
Let's say that you are
currently considering
increasing the
size of your disks
to allow moving from
one terabyte disk
space to 20 terabyte disks.
The purpose of that
is to scale vertically
your storage capabilities,
which is totally fine.
But if we are expecting to
run these at 75% capacity,
this will mean loading up
to 15 terabytes of data.
Which means 15 times
more data to backup.
Like a quite significant
amount of other aspects,
this will probably mean that
you will take 15 times more
time to back up those servers,
probably an even bigger penalty
while restoring
such large servers,
as well as doing initial
syncs between replica sets.
And we have to account now
for impact on the network
when backing up those
15 terabytes of data.
In such a scenario,
having horizontal scale
and distributing that amount of
data across different shards,
will allow getting
horizontal performance gains
like parallelization
of the backup, restore,
and initial sync processes.
Remember, that even though these
may be infrequent operations,
they can become serious
scalability issues to handle
from the operational side.
This same scenario
will also impact
your operational workload.
15 times bigger
dataset per MongoDB
will most likely translate to at
least 15 times bigger indexes.
As we know, indexes are
essential for the performance
of our queries in a database.
If they take 15 times more space
per processing unit or server,
they will require more
RAM so that indexes
can be kept in memory.
A very important part
of your working dataset.
Increasing the size of
your disks most likely
will imply eventual increasing
the size of your RAM, which
Brings added costs or other
bottlenecks to your system.
In such a scenario sharding,
the parallelization
of your workload
across shards, might
be way more beneficial for
your application and budget
than the waterfall of
potential expensive upgrades.
A general rule of
thumb indicates
that individual
servers should contain
two to 5 terabytes of data.
More than that just becomes too
time consuming to operate with.
Finally, there are
workloads that intrinsically
play nicer in distributed
deployments that
sharing offers, like single
threaded operations that
can be parallelized and
geographically distributed
data.
Data that needs to be stored
in specific regional locations
or will benefit from
being co-located
with the clients that
consume such data.
As an example of a
single thread operations
will be aggregation
framework commands.
If your application
relies heavily
on aggregation
framework commands
and if the response
time of those commands
becomes slower over
time, you should
consider sharding your cluster.
That said, not all stages
of the aggregation pipeline
are parallelizable.
So a deeper understanding
of your pipeline
is required before
making that decision.
You can learn all about it in
our M121 MongoDB Aggregation
Course.
So stay tuned for that.
Finally, geodistributed
data is significantly simple
to manage using zone sharding.
Zone sharding allows us
to easily distribute data
that needs to be co-located.
Zone sharding is out of
scope for this course,
but bear in mind that
this is an efficient way
to manage geographically
distributed data sets.