So far, we've only talked
about the default shard key.
However, there's an
additional type of shard key
that is useful for
certain scenarios.
That is the hashed shard key.
That is a shard key where the
underlying index is hashed.
Previously, if we had a document
where, let's say x was 3
and the shard key
was on x, MongoDB
would place it into
the following chunk
where the value of 3 falls
into the trunk range.
With a hashed shard key, MongoDB
first hashes the value 3, then
uses that hash value
to decide which
chunk to place the document in.
The hash shard key does
not mean that MongoDB
stores your shard key
values with hashes.
The actual data
remains untouched.
Instead, the underlying index
backing the shard key itself
is hashed.
And MongoDB uses
the hashed index
for partitioning your
data, so you end up
with a more even
distribution of your data
across the sharded cluster.
So when would you want to
use a hashed shard key?
In the previous
lesson, we talked
about monotonically increasing
or decreasing shard key fields,
like dates or time stamps.
Because these values
are constantly
increasing or decreasing
in numeric progression,
you get hot spotting.
But the output from
the hash function
can change drastically
between values
that are, themselves, similar.
For example, if I have
two documents where
the shard key values
are two and 3,
the hashing function might
output the shard key values
as 609,000.
Apply that same logic to a time
stamp, two numerically adjacent
timestamps would be hashed
to very different values
and are therefore
more likely to end up
on different chunks
and different shards.
Now there are a few drawbacks
to using a hashed shard key.
Since everything is
hashed now, documents
within a range of
shard key values
are likely to be
completely distributed
across the sharded cluster.
So ranged queries on
the shard key field
will now have to hit
multiple shards, instead of
a single shard.
Comparatively, a
non-hash shard key
is more likely to
produce documents
that are on a single
chunk in a single shard,
meaning ranged queries are
more likely to be targeted
with a non-hashed shard key.
You're going to lose the
ability to use features
like zone sharding for the
purpose of geographically
isolated reads and writes.
Again, if everything
is randomly distributed
across every shard
in the cluster,
there's no real
way to isolate data
into groupings like geography.
You can't create hashed
compound indexes.
You can only hash a
single field shard key.
That plays into
why these are best
used for monotonically changing
single fields, like timestamps.
Also, the value in the hashed
index must not be an array.
Finally, because the index
is using hashed values,
you're going to
lose the performance
an index can provide for sorting
documents on the shard key.
To create a hashed
shard, you're going
to start by enabling sharding
on the database using
sh.enablesharding.
Remember, this does
not automatically
shard your collections.
You're still going
to create an index,
but now you're going
to specify that it
is a hashed index
instead of specifying
negative 1 or 1 as the
value of the indexed field.
Finally, you're going to
use sh.shardcollection,
still specifying the
database and collection,
but you're going to specify
hashed for the shard key value.
To recap, hashed shard
keys provide more even
distribution of data of
a monotonically changing
shard key field.
Hashed shard key's do not
support fast sorts, targeted
queries on ranges
of shard key values,
or geographically
isolated workloads.
Finally, hashed indexes
are single fields
and do not support arrays.