So until this
point, we've learned
about MongoDB deployments
of small and average sizes.
So it's feasible to store an
entire data set on one server.
In a replica set, we
have more than one server
in our database.
But each server still has to
contain the entire dataset.
As our dataset
grows to the point
where our machines
can't properly
service client applications,
one of our options
is just to make the
machines better.
We could increase the capacity
of individual machines
so they have more
RAM, or disk space,
or maybe a more powerful CPU.
This is referred to
as vertical scaling.
But this could potentially
become very expensive.
And besides,
cloud-based providers
aren't going to let us
scale vertically forever.
They'll eventually put a
limit on the possible hardware
configurations, which
would effectively
limit our storage layer.
In MongoDB, scaling
is done horizontally,
which means instead of making
the individual machines better,
we just add more machines and
then distribute the dataset
among those machines.
The way we distribute data in
MongoDB is called Sharding.
And Sharding allows
us to grow our dataset
without worrying about
being able to store it
all on one server.
Instead, we divide the
dataset into pieces
and then distribute the
pieces across as many shards
as we want.
Together, the shards make
up a Sharded Cluster.
In order to guarantee
high availability
in our Sharded
Cluster, we deploy
each shard as a replica set.
This way, we can ensure a
level of fault tolerance
against each piece of data
regardless of which shard
actually contains that data.
So with our data distributed
across several servers,
queries may become
a little tricky.
We query our database looking
for a specific document.
It's not obvious at first
where to look for it.
So in between a Sharded
Cluster and its clients,
we set up a kind
of router process
that accepts queries from
clients and then figures
out which shard should
receive that query.
That router process
is called the Mongos.
And clients connect to Mongos
us instead of connecting
to each shard individually.
And we have any number
of Mongos processes
so we can service many different
applications or requests
to the same Sharded Cluster.
So Mongos must be
pretty small, right,
to know where each piece of data
is at any given point in time
in a massive Sharded Cluster?
But actually, Mongos
doesn't know anything.
It uses the metadata
about which data
is contained on each shard.
And that metadata is stored
on the Config Servers.
But the data on
the Config Servers
is used very often by Mongos.
So we need to make sure that
data stays highly available.
And you can probably guess how
we guarantee high availability
here.
Yes, we use replication.
We replicate the data
on the Config Servers.
So instead of a
single Config Server,
we deploy a Config
Server Replica Set.
So that's a high level overview
of Sharding in MongoDB--
the Sharded Cluster contains
the shards where the data lives;
the Config Servers,
which contain
the metadata of each
shard; and the Mongos,
which routes the queries
to the correct shards.