In this lesson, we're going
to talk about the shard key.
This is the indexed
field or fields
that MongoDB uses to partition
data in a sharded collection,
and distribute it across
the shards in your cluster.
Let's start with
how the shard key is
used to distribute your data.
Consider a collection with some
number of documents in them.
MongoDB uses the shard key
to divide up these documents
into logical groupings that
MongoDB then distributes
across our sharded cluster.
MongoDB he refers to
these groupings as chunks.
The value of the field or fields
we choose as our shard key
help to define the
inclusive lower bound,
and the exclusive upper
bound of each chunk.
Because the shard key is used
to define chunk boundaries,
it also defines
which chunk a given
document is going to belong to.
Every time you
write a new document
to the collection, the Mongo
S router checks which shard
contains the appropriate chunk
for that documents key value,
and routes the document
to that shard only.
That's how sharded
clusters handle
distributed write operations.
Depending on what shard
is holding a given chunk,
a new document is routed to
that shared and only that shard.
This also means that
your shard key must
be present in every
document in the collection,
and every new document inserted.
So I could shard
on as sku or type,
but not imdb since
that field isn't
included in every document
within this collection.
Shard keys also support
distributed read operations.
If you specify the shard
key as part of your queries,
MongoDB can redirect the
query to only those chunks,
and therefore, shards that
contain the related data.
Ideally, your shard key should
support the majority of queries
you run on the collection.
That way, the majority
of your read operations
can be targeted
to a single shard.
Without the shard
key in the query,
the Mongo S router would need to
check each shard in the cluster
to find the documents
that match the query.
We'll go into the specifics
of targeted versus broadcast
operations in a later lesson.
Let's go over a few important
aspects of your shard key.
First, I mentioned
earlier that the shard key
are an index field or
fields in your collection.
This is a hard requirement.
You cannot select a field
or fields for your shard key
if you do not have an existing
index for the field or fields.
You'll need to create the index
first before you can shard.
Sharding is a
permanent operation.
Once you have selected
your shard key, that's it.
Furthermore, the shard
key is immutable.
Not only can you
not change it later,
you cannot update the shard key
values of the shard key fields
for any document
in the collection.
So choose carefully.
The next lesson
has some guidance
on choosing a good shard
key, so stay tuned for that.
Finally, you cannot
unshard a collection.
This kind of builds off of
shard keys being immutable.
Once you have
sharded a collection,
you cannot unshard it later.
The steps for
sharding are actually
pretty straightforward.
First, you need to use
sh.enablesharding, specifying
the name of the database,
to enable sharding
for the specified database.
This does not automatically
shard your collections.
It just means that
the collections
in this particular database
are eligible for sharding.
This won't affect
other databases
in your MongoDB cluster.
Next, you have to
create the index
to back your shard key for the
collection you want to shard,
using db.collection.createindex.
Remember, we're going to
substitute collection here
with the name of the collection
we want to create the index on.
Finally, we're going to
use sh.shardCollection,
specifying the full
path to the collection,
and the shard key to shard
the specified Collection
let's actually try this
in action real quick.
So here, you can see I'm
using sh.status status
to show that I have a two
shard sharded cluster.
I'm currently connected
to the Mongo S.
I'm going to switch
to the m103 database,
because I want to
shard the products
collection in that database.
I'm going to enable sharding
on the m103 database first.
Now before we
shard a collection,
we need to decide what
key we will be using.
I'm using db.products.find0ne
to show you those one document
from the products collection.
I'm going to use the sku
field for my shard key.
Before sharding,
I need to ensure
that the selected key or keys
that compose my shard key
are supported by an index.
So let's create an
index on sku using
db.collection.createindex.
So here, I'm creating
the index on sku,
and I have specified
ascending here.
It's not super important.
And you can see
here that I now have
this additional index on sku.
Remember that all collections
have an index on ID by default.
Finally, I'm going to
shard the collection using
the next I just specified.
Here, I have the full path
to the products collection,
m103.products, and
then the shard key
that I want to use for
this collection, sky.
If I run sh.status,
I can now see
that the m103.primary
collection has a shard key,
and has actually
already been broken up
into three separate chunks.
So if I run sh.status
again, we can see now
that the collection
is marked as sharded
because it has a shard key.
My documents have actually been
already broken up into chunks,
and distributed across the
two shards in my cluster--
two chunks in shard 1,
one chunk in shard 2.
And we can even see the ranges
of values for each chunk.
To recap, your shard determines
the partitioning and data
distribution of data across
your sharted cluster.
Shard keys are immutable.
You cannot change
them after sharding.
Shard key values
are also immutable.
You cannot update a
document shard key.
And you need to create
the underlying index first
before sharding on the
indexed field or fields.