So far, we've been briefly
discussing the term
chunks in a quite loose way.
So let's take a few minutes
to review what chunks are
and what can we do with them.
In a prior lecture,
we've mentioned
that the config servers
hold the cluster metadata.
Things like how
many shards we have,
which databases are sharded,
and the configuration
settings of our shard cluster.
But one of the most
important pieces
of information that the
config servers hold,
is the mapping of
the chunks to shards.
Right, let's jump into our
terminal to see this in action.
If I jump into the
config database
and show the collections,
you'll see a long list
of different collections
that hold information
about this shard cluster.
Within the chunks collection,
if we find one document,
we will see the
definition of a chunk.
In this case, we can see
what's the name space
that this chunk belongs to?
When was this chunk
last modified?
Which shard holds this chunk?
But more importantly,
we can see the chunk
bounce the Min and max
fields indicate exactly that.
But let's step
back a little bit.
Once we add documents
in our collections,
these documents contain fields
that we can use as shard keys.
For example, if we decide to
use field x as our shard key,
the minute we shard
our collection,
we immediately define
one initial chunk.
This initial chunk goes
from minKey to maxKey.
An important thing to note
is that chunks lower bound
is inclusive, while chunks
upper bound is exclusive.
The different values that
our shard key may hold
will define the keyspace
of our sharding collection.
As time progresses, the
cluster will split up
that initial chunk
into several others
to allow data to be evenly
distributed between shards.
All documents of the same
chunk live in the same shard.
If we would have only
one magnanimous chunk,
we could only have one
single shard in our cluster.
The number of chunks
that our shard key allows
may define the max number
of shards of our system.
This is why cardinality
of the shard key
is an important
aspect to consider.
There are other aspects that
will determine the number
of chunks within your shard.
The first one is our chunk size.
By default, MongoDB takes 64
megabytes as the default chunk
size.
That means that if a chunk
is about 64 megabytes,
or within 64 megatons
range, it will be split.
We can define a chunk size
between the values of one
megabyte and 1024
and one gigabyte.
The chunk size is
configurable during runtime.
So if we decide to
change a chunk size,
we can easily do so.
But before we go in
changing our chunk size,
let's have a look to how many
chunks we currently hold.
As you can see here,
from our sh.status,
the chunks mark
tells me that shard--
m103 shard 1 has two chunks.
While m103 shard
2 has one chunk.
But I want to lower my chunk
size to see what happens.
To do that, what
I need to do is,
basically, go to my
settings collection
and save a document
with ID chunk size,
with the determined value that
I intend the chunk size to be,
in megabytes.
Once I've done so, if
I run again, sh.status,
I can see that nothing changed.
Well, why?
Well, the component responsible
for the thing is the mongos,
and since we have not given any
indication or signal to mongos
that it needs to
split anything--
because no new data came in--
it will basically do
absolutely nothing.
If something is working, why
Porter bother trying to fix it?
So, for us to see some action
going on, what we need to do
is tell the mongos to
actually do something.
So I'm going to go
ahead and import
this other file, products part
2 that I just recently changed,
so I can see some
splitting going on.
Once I import this
data, we'll connect back
to see if there is
any more chunks.
Right, sweet.
So we're done with our
imports, so let's connect back.
And again, let's do our
sh.status for a second.
Sweet.
Now I have a lot more
chunks, all kind of still
not very well balanced,
but that's fine.
It will take them some
time to actually balance
everything between all shards.
But, the good thing
is that, I no longer
have just one and
two chunks spread
across two different shards.
I have around 51
chunks right now.
And if I run it again, I'll see
that, eventually, the system
will be balanced.
Another aspect that will
be important for the number
of chunks that we can generate
will be the shard key values
frequency.
Now, let's consider that
the chosen shard key
wasn't that good after all.
Although the cardinality
initially was very good,
we have an abnormal
high frequency
of some keys over time.
So let's say, for example,
if 90% of our new documents
have the same shard
key value, this
might generate an
abnormal situation.
What do we call jumbo chunks?
Jumbo chunks can be
damaging because they
are chunks which are way
larger than the default
or defined chunk size.
The minute a chunk
becomes larger
than the defined
chunk size, they
will be marked as jumbo chunks.
Jumbo chunks cannot be moved.
If the balancer sees a chunk
which is marked as jumbo,
you will not even
try to balance it.
You will just leave
it in its place,
because it's basically marked
as too big to be moved.
In very extreme
cases, there will
be no split point
on those chunks,
and therefore, they will
not be able to be moved
at all, or even
split, and that can be
very, very damaging situation.
So, keep an eye for that.
Please do consider the
frequency of our shard key,
to avoid situations like jumbo
chunks as much as possible.
So, let's recap.
Chunks are logical
groups of documents
that are based out of
the shard key key space,
and have bounds
associated to it.
Min bound, inclusive.
Max bound, exclusive.
A chunk can only live at one
designated shard at the time.
And all documents within the
bound defined by the chunk
live in the same shard.
Shard key cardinality frequency
and configured chunk size
will determine the
number of chunks
in your sharded collection.