In this lesson, we're going
to talk about how the mongos
router does the job
of routing queries
across your sharded cluster.
So the mongos is the
principal interface point
for your client applications.
All queries must be
redirected to the mongos.
So here we have a find
operation against the products
collection, looking
for this document
where the name is how to mongos.
The first thing
that the mongos does
is determine the list of shards
that must receive the query.
Depending on the
query predicate,
the mongos as either targets
every shard in the cluster
or a subset of shards
in the cluster.
If the query predicate
includes the shard key,
then the mongos can
specifically target
only those shards that
contain the shard key value
or values specified in
the query predicate.
These targeted queries
are very efficient.
If the query predicate does
not include the shard key,
or has generally very wide
in scope, such as a range
to query that spans multiple
or all shards, than the mongos
has to target every
shard in the cluster.
These scatter gather
operations can be slow,
depending on factors such
as the number of shards
and your cluster.
We're going to go into more
detail on targeted versus
scatter gather queries, as well
as how the mongos knows who
to target, in the next lesson.
Whether we're doing targeted
or scatter gather queries,
the mongos opens a
cursor against each
of the targeted shards.
Each cursor executes
the query predicate,
and returns any data returned
by the query for that shard.
The mongos now has the results
from each targeted shard.
The mongos merges all
of the results together
to form the total
set of documents
that fulfills this
query, and then returns
that set of documents to
the client application.
The mongos also has specific
behavior when it comes
to cursor operators, such
as sore, , limit and skip.
For queries where
you specify a sort,
the mongos pushes the sort down
to each shard in the cluster
and then performs a merge
sort of the results.
With limit, the mongos
pushes the limit down
to each shard in the cluster,
and then reapplies that limit
after merging the
returned results.
With skip, the mongos
performs the skipping
on the merged set of results,
and doesn't push anything down
to the shard level.
If you're using
aggregation, there's
more specific behavior depending
on the pipeline you've created.
Now, that is out of
scope for this lesson.
So, please take a look
at the documentation
linked below for a more
complete discussion
of how mongos handles
routing aggregation queries.
To recap, the mongos handles all
queries in a sharded cluster.
For any given query, it
builds a list of shards
to target the query to,
and merger's the results.
It can also handle query
modifiers such as sort,
limit, and skip.