All right, so in
this lesson, we're
going to talk about a
very important database
in the sharded cluster,
the config database.
First thing you need to
know about the config DB
is that you should generally
never write any data to it.
It's maintained
internally by MongoDB,
and it's used internally.
So, generally, you will
never need to actually write
any data to it.
However, it's got some
useful information in it,
so we are going to read from it.
So, I'm just connected to mongos
and I'm running a quick s.h.
status on it just
to see the typology
of the sharded cluster.
So this is going to give us
a lot of output about some
of the shards, about
the active mongos's.
It's going to give us some
information about the database
in our sharded cluster.
But all of this data is actually
stored in the config DB.
Here, and just switching
over to the config database.
I'm going to take a look
at the collections we
have in there already.
So these are all the
collections that we have access
to in the config database.
The first one we're
going to look at
is the databases collection.
So here, I'm just
printing the results
from our databases querie.
So this is going to return
each database in our cluster
as one document.
It's going to give
us the primary shard
for each database,
and the partition here
is just telling
us whether or not
sharding has been
enabled on this database.
In this case, the m103
database has sharding enabled.
Now, take a look
at the collections.
So this is only going to give
us information on collections
that have been sharded.
But for those collections,
it will tell us the shard key
that we used.
In this case, the m103
products collection
was sharded on sale price.
And it also tell us whether
or not that key was unique.
This one's going to
tell us about the shards
in our cluster.
And here, you can see
the hostname contains
the replica set name
because these shards are
deployed as replica sets.
The chunks collection
is possibly
the most interesting collection
in this whole database.
So each chunk for every
collection in this database
is returned to us
as one document.
The inclusive minimum
and the exclusive maximum
define the chunk range
of the shard key values.
That means that any document in
the associated collection who's
shard key value falls
into this chunks range
will end up in this chunk,
and this chunk only.
So this collection is
sharded on sale price.
And we see that this
chunk has documents
with values of sale price for
a minKey key to about $15.
MinKey, here, means the
lowest possible value
of sale price or
negative infinity,
if you want to think
about it that way.
This chunk has documents
with sale prices
of at least $14.99,
but lower than $33.99.
For example, if I were to insert
a document into this collection
that had a sale price of $20,
it would end up in this chunk.
The config database
also some information
on the mongos process currently
connected to this cluster,
because we can have
any number of them.
As we can see right
now, we only have one.
But it'll give us a lot
of information on it,
including the mongos version
that's running on the mongos.
So, just to recap,
in this lesson
we've covered the
collections that we
have in the configure
database, including
but not limited to, shards,
chunks, and the mongos.
But remember, never
write to this database
unless instructed to
by MongoDB support
or our official documentation.
It has some useful
information, but it's generally
meant for internal
MongoDB usage only.