So we've been talking sharded
charted clusters for a bit now.
And you've heard at
least a few times
about this concept of
even distribution of data.
We know that a good shard
key should contribute
to how evenly MongoDB
can distribute
your data across the
shards in your cluster.
But how exactly does MongoDB
perform that data distribution?
Recall that with
sharding, MongoDB
splits your sharded collections
into chunks of data.
As you insert data
into the collection,
the number of chunks on
any given shard will grow.
The MongoDB balancer
identifies which
shards have too many
chunks and automatically
move chunks across shards in the
sharded cluster in an attempt
to achieve even
data distribution.
Currently, the
balancer process runs
on the primary member of the
config server replica set.
In prior versions
the Mongo ES was
responsible for running
the balancer process.
The balancer process checks the
chunked distribution of data
across the sharded cluster and
looks for certain migration
thresholds.
If it detects that
there is an imbalance,
it starts a balancer round.
The balancer can migrate
chunks in parallel.
A given shard cannot participate
in more than one migration
at a time.
So take the floor of
n divided by 2, where
n is the number
of shards, and you
have the number of chunks that
can be migrated in a balancer
round.
With this cluster,
I've got three shards,
so I can migrate-- at
most-- one chunk at a time.
If we had four
shards, the balancer
could migrate up to
two chunks at a time.
So we're going to need a second
round to completely balance
this cluster.
These rounds happen
consecutively
until the balancer process
detects that the cluster is as
evenly distributed as possible.
Typically, the Mongo ES handles
initiating a chunk split.
But the balancer is fully
capable of performing splits.
It will do so if it detects
chunks that need to be split
or as a part of defining chunk
ranges for zone sharding.
Now, zones are out of
scope for this lesson.
So just remember that the
balancer can split chunks
if needed.
Now, there is a performance
impact of migrating chunks.
The balancer already
has behavior built in
to minimize workload
disruption, such as the one
chunk per shard limitation.
To that end, MongoDB
surfaces a number
of methods for controlling
the behavior of the balancer.
You can start or stop
the balancer at any time.
If you stop the balancer
in the middle of a round,
then the balancer stops only
after that balancing round
completes.
sh.startBalancer
and stopBalancer
allow you to set a
time limit timeout
value for how long to wait to
stop or start the balancer.
The interval defines
how long the client
should wait before checking
the balancer status again.
Set balancer state
just takes a boolean
and is either on or off.
There is also a
process for scheduling
a time window for when
this sharded cluster
balancer can run.
It does require modifying
the config database, which is
out of scope for this course.
But we'll link to the
tutorial below if you'd like
to read up on it for yourself.
To summarize, the
sharded cluster balancer
is responsible for evenly
distributing chunks of data
across your sharded cluster.
Starting with MongoDB
3.4, the balancer
runs on the Primary member of
the config server replica set.
And the balancer process
is completely automated
and requires minimal
user input or guidance.
There are methods for
controlling it, however.