So in this lesson, we're going
to walk to the architecture
of a sharded cluster.
The most important aspect
of a sharded cluster
is that we can add
any number of shards.
And because that
could potentially
be a lot of different
shards, client applications
aren't going to communicate
directly with the shards.
Instead, we set up a kind of
router process called mongos.
Then the client
connects to mongos,
and mongos routes queries
to the correct shards.
So how does mongos figure out
exactly where everything is?
Well it has to
understand exactly how
the data is distributed.
So, let's say this data
is on soccer players.
Some of you may know
them as football players.
We split our data set on the
last name of each player.
So players with last
names between A and J
are stored in the first
shard, between K and Q
on the second shard, and between
R and Z on the third shard.
Mongos is going to
need this information
to route queries the client.
For example, if the
client sends a query
to mongos about
Luis Suarez, mongos
can use the last name
Suarez to figure out exactly
which shard contains
that player's document,
and then route that query
to the correct shard.
We can also have
multiple mongos processes
from high availability
with mongos,
or to service multiple
applications at once.
The mongos processes are
going to use the metadata
around the collections that
have been sharded to figure out
exactly where to route queries.
The metadata for this
collection will look like this.
But the data is not
stored on mongos.
Instead, the collection
metadata gets
stored in config
servers, which constantly
keep track of where each piece
of data lives in the cluster.
This is especially important
because the information
contained on each shard
might change with time.
So mongos queries the config
servers often, in case
a piece of data is moved.
But why might a piece
of data have to move?
Well, the config servers
have to make sure
that there's an even
distribution of data
across each part.
For example, if there
are a lot of people
in our database with
the last name Smith,
the third shard is
going to contain
a disproportionately
large amount of data.
When this happens,
the config servers
have to decide what data
has to be moved around
so the shards have a
more even distribution.
In this example, all the
names beginning with R
hadn't moved to the second
shard from the third shard,
to make room and third shard for
all those people named Smith.
The config servers will then
update the data they contain,
and then send the data
to the correct shards.
There's also a chance
that a chunk gets too big
and needs to be split.
In that case, mongos
would split the chunk.
We'll talk more about this
in the lesson about chunks.
In the sharded
cluster, we also have
this notion of a primary shard.
Each database will be
assigned a primary shard,
and all the non-sharded
collections on that database
will remain on that shard.
Remember, not all
the collections
in a sharded cluster
need to be distributed.
The config servers will assign
a primary shard to each database
once they get created.
But we can also change the
primary shard of a database.
We're just not going to
cover that in this course.
The primary shard also has a
few other responsibilities,
specifically around
merge operations
for aggregation commands.
So while we're talking
about merging results,
I just to point
something out here.
In our example, the data
is organized across shards
by the name of each player.
So if the client
receives a query
about the age of a
player, it doesn't
know exactly where to look.
So it's just going
to check every shard.
It's going to send this
query to every single shard
in the cluster.
And it might find a
few documents here,
a few documents here.
And each individual
shard is going
to send their results
back to mongos.
The mongos will gather results,
and then maybe sort the results
if the query mandated it.
This stage is called
the shard merge,
and it takes place
on the mongos.
Once the shard
merge is complete,
the mongos will return the
results back to the client,
but the client won't be
aware of any of this.
It will query this process
like a regular mongoD.
So just to recap,
in this lesson we
covered the basic
responsibilities
of mongos, the metadata
contained on the contact
servers, and we defined the
concept of a primary shard.