So let's take a look at how you
can actually see whether or not
a query is targeted, and how
many shards were targeted.
I'm using the m103
database here,
and I'm going to show that we
have our products collection
within the m103 database.
I'm running sh.status to
show that we have two shards.
As you can see, m103.products
is sharded on sku,
and is distributed in
three chunks total.
I have to on shard
1 and 1 on shard 2.
Now, I'm going to issue a
find against the products
collection specifying
this document where
sku is this value.
I'm also going to add the
explain query modifier
so that we can dig
a little bit deeper
into how we get our results.
So, let's take a look here.
First of all, notice for
stage we have single shard.
That means for this
specific query,
not only was Mongos able to
target a subset of shards,
it was able to retrieve
the entire results set
from a single shard without
needing to merge the results.
This shards array displays
each shard queried,
and provides the specific
plan executed on that
shard for executing the query.
As you can see here,
under the winning plan,
there is actually a
index scan underneath,
because the shard
MongoD could use the sku
index to satisfy the query.
So let's try to do this
again, except now, we're
going to look up the name
against this particular video
game.
So a few clear
differences, for our stage,
we now have shard merge.
Furthermore, if you look
under the shards array,
we have both shard
1 and shard 2.
So this is a scatter gather
query, and required a merge.
Remember that name
isn't in our shard key,
so this is necessarily
a scatter gather query.
So, actually, these two
queries, both sku on this value
and the name on this value, were
returning the same document.
But by specifying sku
instead of the name,
I can get a result more quickly.
Now if I know that my workload
would be querying against name
90% of the time,
then it would have
been better for me to have
chosen name instead of as sku
as the shard key.
So, let's recap.
Targeted queries
require the shard key
as part of the query predicate.
For compound shard
keys, it can be
a prefix of the shard key
up to the entire shard key.
Ranged queries on the
shard key may end up
with similar
performance to a scatter
gather query, depending
on how wide your range is.
But that's only if you're
using a very wide shard range,
or if you have a
hashed shard key.
Without the shard
key, the Mongols
must perform a
scatter gather query.
This means that the
Mongo must check
in with every single
shard in the cluster.
The scatter gather
queries are going
to be the slowest, compared
to a targeted query.