So now that we've gone
over the architecture
of a basic sharded
cluster MongoDB,
we're actually going to
build one in our course
virtual environment.
So, right now, all we have
is a replica set M103 repel.
This is just a
normal replica set,
but eventually it will become
the first shard in our cluster.
This diagram is the
bare minimum required
to start a sharded cluster--
essentially, just the mongos,
a config server replica set,
and at least one shard.
The main things we have to build
are the CSRS and the mongos.
The rest of the work will
just be connecting everything
together.
The first thing we're going to
build is our config servers.
So this is the
configuration file for one
of our config servers.
It's going to be one of the
nodes in the CSR's, but it's
just a regular
MongoD, so it's still
going to have a port, a
DB path, and a log path.
Now the config servers
that a very important role
in the shard cluster.
So we have to specify,
in the configuration,
that this is in fact
a config server.
So, here, I'm just
going to use that file
to start up a mongoD process.
And, here, I'm going to do the
same thing for the other two
nodes in the CSRS.
And you can find those config
files in the lecture notes.
They look very similar
to the first one.
So we enable this replica
set to use authentication,
and the key file authentication
is fine because we already
created our key file.
We're going to share the
same key file in this setup
since all mongoD
instances are running
on the same virtual machine.
But in a real
production environment,
X509 certificates
would be the way to go.
Having a shared password
like the key file,
when shared across
multiple machines,
increases the risk of that
file being compromised.
So just keep that in mind.
Here, I'm just initiating the
config server replica set.
And here, I just use
the localhost exception
to create our super user.
So now, I'm just going to
authenticate as the super user.
One means that it worked.
And now we can start
adding those to the set.
Here's our second
node, and our third,
and now we have a complete
config server replica set.
I'm just going to verify
that with rs.ismaster.
And it looks like the set
has three nodes in it.
So now we have our CSRS up and
running, we can start up mongos
and then point mongos in the
direction of our config server
replica set.
So this is the configuration
file for mongos,
and the first thing
you're going to notice
is that there is no DB path.
That's because mongos doesn't
need to store any data.
All of the data
used by mongos is
stored on the config servers.
So in the sharding section,
we've specified those.
And note that we specified
the entire replica set instead
of the individual members.
We also enabled key
file authentication,
so we're going to need to
authenticate to mongos.
But it will inherit the same
users as their config servers,
and we'll see that in a minute.
So this is the command
we use to start mongos.
We passed the config
file, like we did before.
But, note that this is
not a mongoD process.
Mongos is a different process
with different properties.
So just bear that in mind.
So, as we saw before,
mongos has auth enabled,
and it's also going to
inherit any users that we
created on the config servers.
So this user is
actually ready to go.
And it looks like we're in.
Just going to check
the status here.
So, sh.status is
the most basic way
to get sharding
data from mongos.
And if we take a
look at the output,
we can see that we have the
number of mongos's currently
connected, and we also
have the number of shards.
Right now, this is empty because
we don't have any shards.
But, you can probably
see where this is going.
Right now, we have
a mongos running
with the config servers.
And actually we also have a
replica set that we can use.
We just need to tweak
the configuration so we
can use it as a shard node.
So this is the
configuration file
for the first node
in our replica set,
and I've changed it slightly.
I've added this restriction on
the cache size and gigabytes,
because Vagrant
only has permission
to use two gigabytes of memory.
So I wanted to reduce the stress
on the overall environment.
This is generally not good
practice in production,
but it's going to be necessary
once we start sharding
collections in this cluster.
So this is the one
line that we have
to add if we want to enable
sharding on this node.
This line is going
to tell mongos, hey,
you know you can use me as a
shard node in your cluster.
We have to add this line
to every single node
in the replica is set.
So I just changed the config
files for all three nodes
in our set, but the
nodes still need
to be restarted in order to
account for those changes.
We're going to do a rolling
upgrade in order to do this.
Which means, we're going to
upgrade the secondaries first,
then bring them back up, step
down the current primary,
and then upgrade that last node.
Here, I'm just connecting to
one of the secondary nodes.
Just going to switch
to the admin--
database, and
shutdown, this node.
And here, I'm just
starting a backup
with the new configuration.
Do the same thing
for our third node.
And here, I'm starting
up the third node
with a new configuration.
So now that both
secondaries have
been upgraded for the
new configuration,
I'm going to connect
to the primary,
and then step it down so I
can upgrade that one, too.
I'm just going to force an
election so this node becomes
a secondary, and it worked.
Now I'm going to shut
this node down as well.
So now I'm just starting
up our last node
with the new configuration,
and it worked.
So now we've
successfully enabled
sharding on this replica set.
Now I'm going to
connect back to mongos.
So once I'm connected
back to mongos,
I can add the shard that
we just enable sharding on.
And we specified the
entire replica set,
so we only need to
specify one node in order
for mongos to discover the
current primary of this replica
set.
And, it looks like it worked.
I'm just going to
check sh.status,
and our list of shards
now has one shard in it.
And as we can see, we
only specified one node,
but mongo was able to discover
all the nodes in the set.
So just to recap
here-- we covered
how to launch mongos and a
config server replica set.
We learned how to enable
sharding on a replica set,
and we did so by way
of a rolling upgrade.
And we added shards
to our cluster.