Now the last example
I have would show you
how you might want
to create a rollup
table with some
kind of a summary
from an existing collection
that has detailed information.
And in this case, we're
going to say that an existing
collection has all
of the registration
for all of the events
that we're doing,
and I want to create a
registration summary where
I show the number of people
who registered by day, where
the day represents the date
that the registration came in.
And in this case, I might
create the registration summary
collection first by analyzing
all of the existing data,
and then incrementally update
by doing periodic rollups
into the summary.
So here, rather
than merging on _ID,
we're going to merge
on the event and date,
that's the unique identifier
for each record in the summary
table.
And we're going to create a
unique index on event date
so that things will get
matched up correctly.
And now for the very
first run, we're
going to say I would like to--
and by the way, I'm let's say
doing analysis for MongoDB
World 19 registrations.
I'm going to match where
event_id is MDBW19.
I'm going to group
by data string here.
We'll create a string of a
particular normalized format.
So that's what I'm
going to group on here,
and I'm going to count up
how many in total there are.
And then I'm going to
project the new document
where event is MDBW19.
Date is you this grouping showed
me, and total is the count.
And then I'm going to output
that or merge into regsummary,
merging on event
and date fields.
So this is what's
coming out here,
and it's going to get
inserted into the collection.
If the collection already
existed with data,
it will overwrite for every
day with the new total.
And there we have
maybe a whole bunch
of days in this collection.
Now another day or
two goes by and I say,
hey, I last ran
this on the 22nd.
It's now the 24th, I'd like
to run this for the 22nd.
I'd like to run
this for the 23rd.
For a single day, I might
run something like this.
I'll still match
the event_id MDBW19,
but I'm going to
now limit things
where the date is,
basically, during May 22nd.
Right?
It's greater than
midnight 22nd, but less
than midnight of the 23rd.
I'm going to count up the total.
Now I'm going to create this
record where this is the event.
This is the date.
Right?
That's the then I'm
querying by so that's
the date I'm having field on.
I'm now merging into
regsummary on event and date,
and the record is going
to look like this.
And if that date
was already there
because maybe we got a
partial result for the 22nd
when we ran it before, now
that it's after the 22nd,
it's going to give me the entire
total and overwrite whatever
the previous total was.
So because I'm doing
a total sum here,
I don't want to merge it or
add it to an existing value.
I just want to write that that's
the total of registrations
we got on that day.