Now let's look at a
completely different use case
where you want to append
from a temporary collection
into some permanent collection.
This might be a use case where
you have a data collection,
and periodically
you get a new load
of a subset of
data, which you load
into this collection
called temp.
You will now do some kind
of cleansing and analyzing
the records to make sure they're
valid before appending them
to the existing data collection.
So your pipeline
would be whatever
it is that you do to validate
that this data in temp
collection is of the right
format, and the right type,
and the right whatever
else you need to verify,
which you will now
append into data.
Now, append here means
that when there's no match,
it will insert.
And I've specified that
when there is match,
I want it to fail, because
I don't expect ever
to find a match here.
The reason is that I would only
find a match if I'd already
loaded this data.
And I don't really expect
to ever run a job twice.
So this is an example of
having the pipeline raise
an error if an
unexpected event happens,
such as finding that there's
already a record that newly
arriving data would
match up to, which
means something has gone
wrong or not according
my expectation.
This is similar, if you're
familiar with SQL, to SQL's
INSERT INTO table 1
SELECT * from table 2.
And it just says insert
into this existing table.
Now, if the table
doesn't exist, it'll
just insert into a new table.