Let's look at a few examples
now using this new stage.
Single view example
would be where
you may be maintaining
in a particular database
a collection of users
and, among other things,
you want to track
whatever arbitrary fields
you know about the
users from some--
maybe a third party
API that you're
pulling in for mflix service.
And the same thing for
mfriendbook service.
So you have multiple collections
that represent that user
information.
You want to merge
it in periodically
into your single view.
So imagine your single
view is the user.
The _id would be the unique
merging key here that would be
used, maybe a date of birth
and some other fields.
Now you'd construct a pipeline
from mflix.users collection
and merge it into single
view users collection.
So you might have a project
that creates this _id field,
which is $username.
So maybe the same user name is
stored in username field there.
And now you merge into.
You specify a different
database and collection name.
You see whenNotMatched, discard.
This makes sense because you
don't want this merging service
to create a new record for
a user that doesn't exist,
because it would be missing
a lot of required fields,
for example.
But when it does
match, then it's
going to do a
default merge, which
means that the fields here--
which _id of course matches.
And then mflix has the full
document from this mflix
collection, so it
will just get merged
into an existing document.
If there was an earlier
mflix field here,
it will get overwritten
by the new document.
Now you can run the
exact same thing
on your mfriendbook.users
collection.
You have the same pipeline
again transforming the username
into the _id field.
And now here the mfriendbook
field, which will get
added, or set, or overwritten,
if there was one there already,
with whatever this
new information is.
Again, if a user doesn't
match an existing _id value,
it will just get discarded
rather than inserted if that
option was not there.