Now that we know how new
incoming documents will
be matched to
existing documents,
it's good to understand
what happens in each case
by default, and what other
options are available to you.
When documents coming from
the source to the target,
either each incoming document
doesn't match anything
in the target, or it matches.
If nothing is
matched, usually, you
will want to insert
the new document.
If something is matched,
you will probably
want to somehow
overwrite this document.
Right?
Maybe update it with
new information,
or completely replace it.
We give you two fields
in $merge to specify
what action should be taken
when there isn't a match
or when there is a match.
Both of them are optional.
By default, when there is no
match, we will do an insert.
When there is a match, we will
merge the new incoming document
with the existing document.
Now, a merge here means we
will add all the top level
fields of the new document
to existing document,
but that will preserve all
the fields in the existing
document that don't exist in
the new incoming document.
I'll show you an
example of this later.
But you can think of
this as sort of an update
with an upsert
option set to true.
Right?
It says that update set these
new fields into an existing
document.
If there isn't an existing
document, then insert it.
So the default action
is like an upsert
into the target collection.
That's the easiest
way to remember it.
Now, the other options
when there isn't a match
are discard and fail.
Both of these would probably
be useful in a scenario
where you always expect to
find a matching document.
And if a match is not found,
then something is wrong.
Imagine doing some kind
of partial processing
where you're calculating
some additional information
to be merged with
an existing record,
and if the existing record
isn't found, that's an error.
In that case, you would
want to raise an exception.
That would be fail.
In other cases, it's OK
if you don't find a record
to update with the
new information,
but you also don't
want to create
that record, in which case
that option would be discard.
Now, when there is a
matching document found,
you can specify four
options to whenMatched,
in addition to the
default merge action.
They are replace, keep
existing, fail, and then
one more special option here.
Replace and keep existing
is straightforward.
Replace means the incoming
document will completely
overwrite or replace the
matching document in the target
collection.
Keep existing will discard
the incoming document
and leave the existing document
in the target collection
as it is.
And fail would be useful
when you absolutely
do not expect to find a match.
I'll show you an
example of that later.
The last option you have when
a document that's incoming
matches an existing
document is useful
when you want to merge their
values of fields somehow,
but a simple merge
option is not sufficient.
The.
Brackets here represent that
you can specify your own custom
pipeline that will
be used to compute
a new document to be written
to the target collection.
You can compute it
from fields of, both,
the incoming and existing
versions of the document.
Now, the pipeline is limited to
stages that do single document
transformations, like
project or $addFields,
and it will be applied to
existing matched document
in the target collection.
Any field names,
like $a or $total,
are referring to fields
in the existing document.
But you can refer to fields
in the incoming document with
a special variable, $$new.
Now, this may look
to you, very much,
like the new
aggregation pipeline
in update, which is new in 4.2.
And it is.
It's the exact same
implementation,
and we even give
you the same alias
for ad fields, known as $set.
And what this pipeline is
doing is, for matched document,
it's going to set a field total
to a sum of already existing
dollar total, right here.
And $$newtotal, that's the
total from the document
that's flowing
through the pipeline.
Here's an example.
If you're incoming document
has underscore ID 37 total 64,
and then there's
some other field F1.
And our target has the
same idea, obviously.
That's how they merge.
And it has an already existing
total in some other F1.
This pipeline will only
modify the total field.
It will set total to
be the sum of the two.
The other two fields
will be left alone.
Compare this with example
two where, on match, we're
going to use replace with,
which creates a new object.
And that new object is merging
the entire new incoming
document-- that would be
the one on the left here--
just with a single
field object where
total is computed as a sum of
new total and existing total.
And here, you can see that the
F1 field is actually inherited
from incoming because
it's in $$new.
And the only field from
$$new that's being changed is
the total.
Now, there's one other option
that merge syntax allows.
And that option is only
allowed and only makes
sense when you're
using a custom pipeline
for the whenMatched
field, and that's let.
Let allows you to define
variables from your incoming
or $$new document.
And if you don't specify left,
it's exactly as if you did
specify left, but defining
variable new to be $$ dollar
route, which is the
entire incoming document.
So a different way to rewrite
this particular pipeline
might be to add a let, which
preserves just the total
from the new incoming document.
And on a match, it sets total in
the existing document to a sum
of $total and $$itotal, which
is this variable over here.