Hi.
This is Asiya, and I'm going to
talk about the new merge stage
in the aggregation pipeline.
The only way of saving
the aggregation pipeline
prior to MongoDB 4.2,
was by writing it
to a new, unsharded
collection, via the $out stage.
If the collection you wanted
to write already existed, $out
would replace it
with the new version,
and it couldn't be sharded.
This only supported
a subset of what
people want to do with the
output from an aggregation,
and so MongoDB 4.2
introduces a new stage,
which allows flexible
ways of saving results
of the aggregation into an
already existing collection,
whether or not it's
sharded or unsharded.
We called it $merge.
Now, you'll have a pipeline
like you normally do,
and then as the last stage,
you would specify $merge
with some options,
which we will review.
Now unlike $out
stage, this new stage
can output to any existing
collection, whether it's
sharded or unsharded
You're allowed
to output to a collection
in a different database,
and you can specify exactly
how you want the new documents
from this aggregation to
be merged into the existing
collection.
That's why we call it $merge.
Now, when documents
from an aggregation
are to be added to an
existing collection,
the question is, how
should we merge them
with the documents that
already exist in this output
collection?
Since there are multiple ways
you might want to handle this,
merge provides you with
options to describe
exactly what you want.
Let's look at $merge syntax now.
The only required argument
to $merge is target.
You specify into and then
the name of the collection
that you want to merge
your output with.
The simplest syntax
of that is just
to give it a string, which
represents a collection
name in the same database that
you're running the aggregation
in, but you can also
specify a full object
with the name of the database
in the name of the collection,
if the output is supposed to
go to a different database
than the one that
you are running
the aggregate pipeline in.
Now, I said you might
want to specify how
to handle matching documents.
But before we decide
what to do on match,
we have to understand how
documents are matched.
You can specify the fields on
which to match the documents.
When deciding how to match
them, the documents that
are incoming to the
target collection,
if the user doesn't specify
the optional on argument,
the server will use the
field as the merging field
for all unsharded
target collections.
And the combination of
_id and your shard key
if the collection is sharded.
If that's how you want
to merge documents,
then you don't have to
specify the field at all.
But if you want to specify
a different unique key
to match documents
on then you would
specify either a
single field name
or if there's multiple fields,
an array of them in the
on argument.
We do require that if you
specify your own merging key,
there must be a unique
index present on it.
This is of course
so we can uniquely
identify the document
in the target collection
to match with an incoming
document from the aggregation.
So to recap, $merge allows
you to output results
of an aggregation pipeline right
into another collection, giving
you options to specify whether
you want to merge or insert
or how you want to merge the
results with the existing
documents, allowing
you to output
to an existing sharded
or unsharded collection,
as well as to a collection
in a different database
than the one that you're
running the aggregation.