One of the more powerful
query operators for a raise
is $elemMatch.
To consider an
example of $elemMatch,
we'll need to do just a
little bit of head scratching.
For this I'd like you to imagine
that we've added one more field
to our movie details data set.
Now we haven't really done
this, but suppose we did.
This field, called boxOffice,
reflects the box office revenue
for all countries in which
a movie was released.
Imagine that every document in
our movie details collection
contained such a
key, and suppose
that the value for
this key is an array
with embedded
documents as entries.
Each array element
for boxOffice,
lists the country and
revenue in millions
for each of those countries.
Now suppose that we'd like
to match all documents where
the revenue for
the country Germany
is greater than 17 million.
Note that a movie details
document with the box office
revenues listed here
would not match this query
because the revenue listed for
Germany here is 16.2 million,
which is obviously
less than 17 million.
We might think a query that
satisfies this objective would
be something like this.
Where we simply specify
boxOffice.country as Germany
and boxOffice.revenue
as greater than 17.
Again, given the way
we've set boxOffice,
this is actually 17 million.
Now this filter will
retrieve documents that
match both of these selectors.
However, the selectors do not
need to match in the same array
element.
So a document having this array
as its value for boxOffice
would match because there is an
element for which the country
is Germany here, and another
element for which revenue
is greater than 17.
And in fact, every other
element in this array
has a value that's
greater than 17.
Let's look at an example.
I'm going to create a single
document in our movie details
collection with a
boxOffice field.
Going to our mongo
shell, and here I'm
connected to my Atlas
sandbox cluster.
I'm going to use
the video database.
Then again, remember
that the shell
is a JavaScript interpreter.
I'm going to use findOne to
locate the movie, The Martian,
and I'm going to
assign that document
to this variable, martian.
So my query was successful.
And if I simply type
martian, the interpreter
will display the value
for this variable,
which is in fact this movie.
So now in the shell in
memory, I have an object
that reflects the movie, The
Martian, from our movie details
collection, and a
reference to that object
in my variable martian.
Now this document
contains an _id.
What I'm going to
do eventually is
insert a version of
this document that
contains the boxOffice field.
And I don't want to get
a duplicate _id error,
so I'm going to delete that
field from my martian object.
Now if I look at
this document again,
I can see that the _id field
has in fact been removed.
Now what I'd like to do
is add a boxOffice field
to the subject by simply setting
boxOffice equal to this array,
and note that this array is
the same one we've been looking
at throughout this example.
Now if I look at my
martian document again,
I can see that it
does in fact have
a boxOffice field with
each of the elements
we've been looking at.
So now we've updated
this object in memory
to contain the boxOffice field.
Let's insert this into our
movie details collection.
For this we're going to
use the insertOne method,
and we can see from the response
that our insert was successful.
And here's the ObjectId of
the newly inserted document.
We can double check this,
and doing a quick search
for the movie, The Martian.
Here we can see that we've
got two documents returned,
and that the second
of these does
contain our boxOffice array.
Now if we try our query
that doesn't use $elemMatch,
we can see that it does match
our newly created document.
In fact, it will
even match this query
because there is one entry
in the boxOffice array,
the one for USA, that
is greater than 228.
This demonstrates
that we do need
to use $elemMatch in order to
perform this type of filter
correctly.
Here's how we do that.
So note that when I issue this
query, no results are returned.
Let's talk about
it a little bit.
This query doesn't
return any results
because it's doing
the right thing.
It is filtering
for documents that
have a single element in
the boxOffice array that
lists the value
Germany for country,
and a value for revenue
that is greater than 17.
And again, that's 17 million.
So the syntax here
is specify the field
you want to filter on.
$elemMatch expects a
document as its value,
and within that document
you specify selectors
that will then be used
to identify at least
one element in this array that
matches all of these criteria.
Now we'll find the martian
if we change our query
to look for German box office
revenue greater than 16 million
because there is one element
in the boxOffice array where
country is Germany, and
revenue is greater than 16.
So that is the
$elemMatch operator.