In this lesson, we're going
to consider logical operators.
In particular, we're going
to focus on $or and $and.
Now I also want
to make you aware
that there is a $not
operator and a $nor operator.
But in this lesson, we're going
to look just at "or" and "and".
Let's take a look at an
example using the $or operator.
What we're going
to do here is look
for documents based
on their rating
using both the
tomato meter, which
is produced by the reviews
of the general public who
care to comment, and
the metacritic, which
is a score generated based on
the reviews of movie critics.
Now the assumption
baked into this query
is that the general
public are easier
graders than movie critics.
We're looking for documents
in our movie details
collection that have
a tomato dot meter
rating greater than 95 or a
metacritic rating of greater
than 88.
Let's look at the syntax here.
$or takes as a value an array
in which we specify selectors.
In this case, we're
using greater than 95
for tomato meter and greater
than 88 for metacritic.
Now let's run this query and
take a look at the results.
We can see that "Toy Story 3"
actually matched both criteria.
It has a tomato meter
rating of greater than 95
and a metacritic score
of greater than 92.
And then here's one where the
general public and the critics
we're pretty far apart
in rating this movie--
this being the document
for "Groundhog Day".
So again, $or takes an
array as an argument.
The elements of the
array are selectors.
Any one of which
can be true in order
to match a document that will
be returned by this query.
Now let's look at
the $and operator.
Something that I want
to point out about $and
is that it's necessary
only in certain situations.
For example, we could use
$and here and restrict results
to those movies where both the
metacritic score and the tomato
meter score were high.
Let's look at an
example of that.
So now only movies
where both tomato
meter and metacritic scores are
high are being returned to us.
But the thing to note is
that the $and operator
in this particular
query is superfluous.
The reason being that the
query we just did here
is equivalent to this one.
Selectors in a
filter are implicitly
anded together already.
And we can see that
if we apply this query
without the use of $and that
we get exactly the same search
results.
So why is there a $and operator?
The reason is
because sometimes we
need to specify the same field
more than once in a filter.
If I were to try to do this,
using just a simple filter,
I would not get the
intended results
because the keys in a JSON
document must be unique.
For example, if our
query were this instead,
the last use of the metacritic
key would be the one used.
The $and operator allows me to
specify multiple constraints
on the same field in
situations such as this
where I need to do so.
In this case, we need all
documents for which metacritic
is not equal to
null, but does exist.
Remember that null will
match keys that actually
have the value
null and those that
do not contain the key at all.
This type of query might be
useful for an application
in which we know we've got
a little bit of dirty data
where possibly there
are fields that
have a metacritic value
that is equal to null.
But what we really want
is for all our metacritic
values to actually have a
numerical value of some kind.
And so if I execute this,
then I do get documents
where the metacritic
field exists
and where I do have a value
other than null for that field.
And we can always flip this
to see only documents where
metacritic is null and
the field actually exists.
Let's run this query instead.
Now, there aren't actually
any such documents
in this collection.
And what I mean by that
is they're not in fact
any documents where
the metacritic field
has a value of null.
So let's create one.
For this, I'm going
to go to Compass.
And despite the fact that the
document we're looking for
is already right
here, I would like
to limit the result
set that we're looking
at to just this document.
Applying that filter, we
see one document returned
and that it is in fact "Once
Upon a Time in the West".
Now, in order to
create a document that
has a null value for metacritic,
what I'm going to do here
is use the copy
document button that I
see to the right of my document
here in the Compass Interface.
That pulls up a modal with
a copy of that document
and gives me an
opportunity to insert it.
But before I insert
it, what I want to do
is go to the
metacritic field change
its value to null and
make sure that I change
its type to null, as well.
Then what I'll do is insert it.
But first, note that
there is no underscore ID
for this copy of the document.
When I insert it,
another score ID value
will be created for me.
And now I have two documents
that have this title.
The first is the
original document.
And the second is my copy
with metacritic set to null.
Now if I run that
same query in a shell,
we can see that we match the
document we just inserted.
Before we close this lesson,
I'll just go back to Compass
and delete that
document I inserted
to clean up after myself.
So again, remember
that $and is used
in situations where we need
to specify multiple criteria
on the same field.