Now let's take a
look at dollar size.
We use dollar size to
match documents based
on the length of an array.
The countries field in the
movie details collection
stipulates the country in
which the movie was filmed.
In cases where the
movie was filmed
in more than one country,
you'll see multiple countries
listed in the countries array.
This query will
identify movies that
were filmed in just one country,
because for the country's array
field we're specifying a filter
such that we see in our search
results that have a size or
length of one for the countries
array.
And if we scroll
through our results,
we can see that in
fact just one country
is listed for each one
of these documents.
Contrasting these with
a number of other films
we've seen, if instead of
displaying the results we take
account, we can see that 1,915
documents in our movie details
collection have just
one country listed,
compared to the 2,295 documents
in the collection as a whole.
And that is dollar size.