MongoDB supports
a query operator
that allows us to use regular
expressions to match fields
with string values.
If you're looking for more
comprehensive text search,
I encourage you to look at the
text operator and full text
indexes.
Full text search is outside
the scope of this course,
but I mention it here because
it's related to $regex
and may be of interest to you.
Now to use the
$regex operator you
need to have a fairly
good understanding
of regular expressions,
but it's important you
know this operator
exists for the situations
in which regular expressions
make sense for an application.
Now in our movie
details collection,
the documents have an awards
field that has as its value
an embedded document
with a field called text.
This text describes the
awards that a given movie
has received.
And for this particular
data set given
the way it was generated, if a
movie has one or was nominated
for an Oscar, you'll see that
reflected in the first word
of this text field.
This field has a certain
pattern it follows
in reporting on the
awards for movies,
and we can see that reflected if
we just do a bit of projection
on the entire collection.
So what I'm going to
do is run a find query,
and all were running
this fine query
for is in order to
do this projection.
The way we do that is by simply
specifying an empty document
as our filter.
This empty document will
match every document
in the collection.
So for Oscar winning movies, we
tend to see the word one first
and nominated first for
Oscar nominated movies.
Now there are some other words
that follow the same pattern,
but for purposes
of this example,
let's go ahead and use the
fact that Oscar awards are
stipulated in this way.
Here we have an example of the
use of the $regex operator.
If you're not familiar
with regular expressions,
this syntax is probably
a little bit confusing,
but we'll clear that up.
A full explanation of
regular expressions
is outside the scope of
this particular lesson,
but essentially these slashes
delimit the regular expression.
The caret here means start at
the beginning of whatever field
we;re matching on, in this
case, the awards.text field.
At the very beginning of
the value of that field,
we want to match exactly a
capital W, a lowercase O,
a lowercase N. Then this dot
is a wild card character.
It stipulates that we
should match any character,
and then with the
asterisk here we're
matching any character
any number of times.
So in summary, what this
regular expression is matching
is the word won at the
beginning of the text field
for the awards
embedded document.
And we don't care what
comes after the word won.
It can be anything.
And what I really
need to do here
is make this just a
little bit more precise,
and put a space here to
indicate that there must
be a space after the word won.
I want to ignore for
example any documents where
the field begins with the word
wonder or some other word that
has these three letters
at the beginning.
So let's take a look at that.
And in fact, let's
do this version
of it projecting out the title
and the awards.text field.
And you can see that
we're getting back
the kinds of documents that
we want, all Oscar winners.
So that's a very simple example
of using the $regex operator.
If you have a use case where
regular expressions are
important, that is where
you have a string field,
and you want to
match documents that
have a particular pattern
of text in that field,
the $regex operator is
the one you should use.
And if you have such
a use case, I strongly
encourage you to dive deeper
into the use of this operator.
There's a great deal
of flexibility there.