In this lesson, we will discuss
comparison query operators.
These are operators
that allow us
to match based on a fields value
relative to some other value.
In our movie details
collection, most documents
have a field called run time.
This makes a good starting point
for considering some comparison
operators.
Here I have mongo shell
connected to my sandbox Atlas
cluster.
We're going to
filter for all movies
that have a run time
greater than 90.
Now runtime is
specified in minutes,
so this is all movies longer
than an hour and a half.
If we like we can
actually project out
just the title and the
runtime to give us a quicker
summary of this results set.
You can see that every
document in our result set
does in fact have a runtime
greater than 90 minutes.
Now let's revisit the
syntax for a minute.
Why is it structured this way?
The idea here is to
maintain consistency
with equality filters.
And to be clear by
equality filter,
I simply mean a filter
for an exact value.
For equality filters, we
define a specific value
a key should have in
matching documents.
In the case of
this query, instead
of specifying a value we
need runtime to be equal to,
we are instead expressing
the type of relationship
we want all documents in the
result set to have with respect
to the runtime field.
This syntax also makes it very
convenient to express ranges.
For example, I can
stipulate that I'd
like to see movies
greater than 90 minutes
long and less than 120 minutes.
To do that, we can
use this query.
And for the sake
of completeness,
I'll mention that $lt is
the less than operator.
Now what I really
want is for all movies
that match my filter to be
greater than or equal to 90
minutes and less than
a equal to 120 minutes.
So I can modify
my filter slightly
to use the greater than
or equal to, or $gte
operator, and the $lte operator.
Let's run this.
Here we can see we've lost a
few results from the last time
because now we're
specifying that we
want movies in a range
up to only two hours.
So with this query, we
had quite a few movies
that were in fact
longer than two hours.
And with this one,
only those that
are between 90
minutes and two hours.
Of course, with
comparison operators
were not limited to working
with a single field.
We can easily work
with as many fields
as we need to using
combinations of comparison
operators, other operators,
and equality matches.
Suppose we're interested in
movies that are highly rated
and also have long run times.
Let's mix things up
a little bit more
by using an embedded document
field, the tomato meter.
Now for tomato meter,
the max is 100.
So what I'll do is
combine a selector
for tomato meter
looking for values
that are greater
than or equal to 95
with runtime looking
for values that are
greater than or equal to 180.
So in this case, movies that
are three hours or longer.
Here we can see that we
have two results that
meet these criteria.
The Godfather:
Part II, of course,
being very long, and in my
opinion, the best of the three
godfather movies.
So let's take a look at
what other comparison
operators there are.
$eq, has exactly the same
semantics as the equality
matches you're
already familiar with.
We've looked at greater than,
greater than or equal to,
less than, and less
than or equal to.
Now let's take a look at not
equal to, or $ne and $in.
First, we'll look at $ne.
Now in a lot of
applications, particularly
if we're doing something
like data cleaning,
we might be interested
in partitioning our data
because we know we
have some fields that
are not as expected.
A lot of movies
in this collection
have four rated a
value of unrated.
So maybe we just want to
look at all documents that
have an actual rating, such
as PG, PG-13, R, et cetera.
We can use $ne to do this, and
the semantics of this filter
are that we'll
match all documents
that for the rated key
will have a value that
is anything other than or
that is not equal to unrated.
Now there's one thing I
should mention about $ne.
In addition to matching
all documents containing
a rated field whose value is
something other then unrated,
$ne will also return
documents that don't
have a rated field at all.
MongoDB supports a
flexible data model.
There are many use
cases for documents
in the same collection
to have fields
that other documents do not.
In MongoDB data models,
rather than store
a null value for field,
we will often simply not
store at field at all.
In another lesson, we look at
how to distinguish documents
that do not have a given field.
OK, so the last comparison
operator I want to look at
is the $in.
$in, allows us to specify
one or more values.
Any one of which should cause
a document to be returned.
This filter we'll select
all documents where
the value of rated is G or PG.
Documents with either of those
two values for the rated key
will match this filter.
And here we can see that
in fact, all results
have a value of either PG
or G for the rated key.
If we wanted to
extend this, we simply
add another element to the
array value of our $in operator.
Please note that the value
of $in must be an array.
In this case, documents
that have a value for rated
that is any one of these
three values will be returned.
If we make this up a
little bit, and change this
to just movies that
are R rated and PG-13,
you see that now our results
are matching those criteria.
There is also an
operator that allows
us to do the reverse
of what the $in does.
I'll leave it as
an exercise to you
to experiment with
that operator.
And with that, we've covered
the comparison operators
for doing queries
within MongoDB.
These significantly expand
the types of queries
that we can do against
a MongoDB collection.