In another lesson
I mention that,
because of its
flexible data model,
MongoDB supports operators that
allow us to detect the presence
or absence of a given field.
Also, as you know, although
not usually a good idea,
it is possible to have the
same field in the collection
have a different value type
from one document to another.
The MongoDB query
language provides
operators that
enable us to handle
both of these situations.
They're called
$exists and $type.
So let's take a look at an
example of $exists first.
For this we'll look again
at the M001 class Atlas
cluster and the
video.movies collection.
Within the movies collection,
we have quite a few old movies.
Many of these movies predate
the MPAA movie rating system.
What we might want to
do with an application
is test for the
existence of a rating.
Here in compass, I've connected
to the class Atlas cluster.
Let's filter for documents that
contain an MPAA rating field.
So the syntax of
$exists is that we
specify the key were
interested in testing
for the existence of.
And as the value for
that key in our filter,
we supply a document that
has $exists as the key
and a value of
either true or false.
If the value we
specify here is true,
then we will match documents
that contain this key.
And if it's false,
we'll match documents
that do not contain the key.
Note that the documents
containing the MPAA rating key
are substantially less than
the total number of documents
in this collection.
Let's do the reverse now
and set $exists to false.
Now we can see that movies
retrieved in response
to this query do not contain
an MPAA rating field at all.
If we scroll through
the schema view,
we see that right here where
MPAA rating should appear,
it does not.
That's because with
this filter applied,
compass is only
looking at documents
that do not have this field.
I should note here something
you might run into with respect
missing fields.
No is a value that is commonly
used in relational databases
for rows that do not have any
data for a particular column.
And for this
example, we're going
to switch quickly to our
Atlas sandbox cluster
and take a look at the
movie details collection.
Some MongoDB users
prefer to include a key
and simply set its value
to null for documents that
have no value for that field.
In order to support
queries for nullish values,
if you filter for
something like this,
tomato.consensus
null, this filter
will match both documents that
explicitly have the value set
to null, like we see
in this document,
and those that do not contain
the key tomato.consensus
at all, as we see in
this document, which
not only doesn't
have tomato.consensus
but doesn't have the
tomato field period.
For collections
containing documents
with null values
for some fields,
you will inevitably
run into this.
So be on the lookout.
Now let's take a look
at the $type operator.
We'll continue to work with
our video.movies collection
for our example.
Take a look at the
viewer rating field.
What we see here in the
schema view for video.movies
is that the value
type for viewer rating
really depends on which
document we look at.
Some have a value
type for double,
some have a value
type of Int32, others
have a value type of undefined.
We can filter for documents
that have a particular value
type for a field using
the $type operator.
Let's look at an example.
And for this, I'd like to
return to the Mongo shell.
Here I have a shell connected
to the M001 class Atlas cluster.
With this command, our filter
will match only documents
in the video.movies
collection that
have a value for viewerRating
that is a 32-bit integer.
And we can see that in
each of these documents,
the viewerRating is
in fact an integer.
I can flip this and look
for just doubles instead.
And here we can see that these
are floating point values.
If you'd like to review how
to filter for other types,
please see the documentation.
It includes
comprehensive coverage
for all of the value types
that you can filter for,
along with additional detail
about the $type operator.
$exists and $type allow us to
ask meta questions of sorts
about documents in a
collection, and thereby
give us some important tools
in working with MongoDB support
for flexible data models.