Now let's look at operators
for array-valued fields.
First, we'll look at $all.
$all matches array fields
against an array of elements.
In order for a document to
match a filter using $all,
all the elements
we're looking for
must be included in
that array field.
Now they don't necessarily
need to be in this order,
but each one of these must
occur in the genre's field
in this example.
So here, we're
filtering for documents
that have been classified as
falling into the comedy, crime,
and drama genres.
Considering the
syntax for $all, note
that it's specified as
the value of the field
were searching on in our
filter, and that $all
has, as its value, an array.
And if we try this query
in the mongo Shell,
we see that, in fact, each
one of the search results
does contain these three
genres in it genres field.
Note also that if we loosen
up our query a little bit,
and instead search for movies
that fall into the genres
comedy and drama, then we see
a mix of movies, all of which
have comedy and drama
listed among their genres,
but which also
list other genres,
whether it be romance,
adventure, thriller,
or something else.
So that's $all.