In this chapter, we're
going to talk about
some more advanced MongoDB
query language concepts.
The MongoDB query language
provides extensive support
for filtering documents
of all shapes and sizes,
even those with
complex schemas
We'll look at the variety
of query operators available
and how to use them.
Note that because all four types
of CRUD operations-- create,
read, update, and delete--
require a filter,
our query operators
may be used in your filters
for any of the query language
methods we have discussed.
You can find a complete
list, with links
to reference material
for all query operators,
in the MongoDB documentation.
We're going to do an overview
of each type of operator
with some very
concrete examples.
The best way to learn is
to get your hands dirty.
as part of this
chapter, we'll have
you do a number of
quizzes and labs
to give you quite
a bit of experience
with these operators.
Let's get started.