Cross shard distributed
transactions will always
need to coordinate a commit
across shards, incurring
more performance costs than if a
transaction targeted one shard.
For the most
performant workloads,
try to optimize
your transactions
to target one shard.
You can do this by
targeting queries
with your shard
key value included.
If you do not send your
shard key value in the query,
all shards must be targeted.
Secondly, you can
try and co-locate
chunks that may be access
together within a transaction.
A chunk is a set of documents
within a defined range
of shard key values.
If you logically
have data that is
likely to be accessed
together, you
can leverage zones
to co-locate chunks
so that it's more likely
a transaction will
target only one shard.
If your application
use case does not
allow for co-locating
data, try, if possible,
to write to only one shard.
Writing to only one
shard regardless
of the number of
shards you read from
can save on some of the
commit protocols steps.
While writing to one
shard within transaction
is more performant than
writing to several shards,
this approach is still
not as optimized as only
targeting one shard for
all reads and writes
within the transaction.