Hello.
I'm Ali Cabral, a product
manager on the core server.
You may remember me from
the MongoDB 4.0 university
course where I introduced multi
document acid transactions
and replica sets.
MongoDB transactions are
conversational, familiar,
preserve atomicity
across operations,
and have snapshot isolation.
They are multi-document,
multi-statement,
and can span any namespace
across your MongoDB instance.
But let's remember,
even before transactions
were launched prior
to 4.0, MongoDB
atomicity at the
single document level.
For instance, if you
updated multiple fields
in a single update
statement, you'd
have the all or nothing
execution guarantee.
Now in MongoDB
4.2, we've extended
multi-document transactions
to sharded clusters,
making application development
even easier with MongoDB.
However, just as we
discussed with replica sets,
this should not
fundamentally change
how you use the database.
Let's review our seven
transactions guidelines
that still apply.
First, all data modeling
rules still apply.
Just because you
have transactions
now does not mean
you should start
normalizing your
data across tables
just like you did in
relational systems.
To fully leverage
the document model,
use the rich
structure of documents
to store related data together.
Second, transactions should not
be the most common operation
in your application.
Really, this is a sanity
check for the first guideline.
When transactions are the
most common operation where
you always read or modify
multiple documents,
this often points to legacy
data modeling practices that
just don't apply to MongoDB.
Third, pass in the
session to all statements.
It's very important to remember
to pass in the session object
to any CRUD operation
you want to execute
within the transaction context.
Fourth, implement retry logic.
Transactions can always abort.
In MongoDB 4.0, we
introduced error labels
to listen for and respond
to you by retrying
the transaction or the commit.
Now in MongoDB 4.2, we've
introduced a new callback API
for transactions that
retries automatically
for up to 120 seconds.
You don't need to explicitly
listen to error labels
any longer.
Fifth, don't unnecessarily
leave snapshots open.
When we keep transactions
open, MongoDB
has to keep all of the
history since the snapshot
time of that transaction.
Once the transaction
completes, the system
can clean up that history.
As a guardrail, we have a
configurable transaction
lifetime limit seconds
which defaults to 60 seconds
and proactively cleans up
long-running transactions.
You can change
this value, but you
must test with your
expected workload
and keep an eye on
cache pressure buildup.
You should also make
sure to commit or abort
even read-only
transactions, as this
relieves the system from needing
to unnecessarily store history.
Next we have our sixth and
second to last guideline.
To trigger write conflicts,
make sure you're doing writes.
Reads do not trigger
write conflicts.
And no-op writes do not
trigger write conflicts.
No-op writes are writes that
don't modify the document.
For instance, if I
changed a color to red,
and the color was already red
in the document, this is a no-op
and doesn't make it
to the storage engine
and won't trigger
write conflicts.
Our final and seventh guideline
is plan for DDL operations.
DDL operations, like create
index and drop database,
compete with active
running transactions.
When a DDL operation is waiting
on a transaction to finish,
no operations that
need to access
that namespace
for the first time
will be able to until the
DDL operation completes.
MongoDB 4.2 introduces
distributed transactions,
making transactions
even more powerful
as they extend to cross shards.
This chapter will lay
out the foundation
for working with
distributed transactions
and your environment.