Hi there, and welcome back.
We've made some improvements
to the backup architecture
in Ops Manager 4.2 for
backing up MongoDB 4.2.
Before we get into what
these improvements are,
let's have a look at what we
had in previous versions of Ops
Manager, and talk about our
motivation for these changes.
So with previous
versions of Ops Manager,
we maintained a copy of
the data for the replica
set in the form of the head db.
The head db standalone
MongoD which
has started to apply
oplogs that were
sent from the backup agent.
So this meant that
during the initial sync
phase of the backup process, we
couldn't generate any snapshots
until the head db had caught up
with the node from which oplog
was being sent from.
So the steps in the
process were as follows.
So the backup
agent would open up
a tailable cursor on
the replica set member
which it was syncing from.
And then it would
begin to stream
oplog entries and documents,
referred to as oplog slices
and sync slices to the oplog
store and the sync store.
Once there was enough oplog
and sync slices transferred,
the head db would
start and begin
to replay oplog operations
to get the snapshot
consistent to a point in time.
So the head db is then stopped.
And a snapshot is persisted to
the blockstore or file system
store.
This process meant that if
your backups required a resync,
you would have to wait for
the initial sync process
to complete before you could
start taking snapshots again.
So in Ops Manager 4.2, we've
changed the backup architecture
to make use of
WiredTiger checkpoints
and remove the need for a
head db and its associated
initial sync process.
This only works for
MongoDB 4.2 being backed up
with Ops Manager 4.2.
All older versions
of MongoDB still
use the old architecture
for backups.
While outside the
scope of this lesson,
it's important to note that we
enhanced the checkpoint ability
in the WiredTiger storage
engine to implement
this new backup flow.
The new feature is
called the Backup Cursor.
WiredTiger uses multi-version
concurrency control, or MVCC,
as it's referred to.
At the start of an
operation, WiredTiger
provides a point in time
checkpoint of the data
to that operation.
A checkpoint presents
a consistent view
of the database at
a point in time.
When writing to disk,
WiredTiger writes all the data
in a checkpoint to disk in a
consistent way across all data
files.
The now durable data acts as a
checkpoint in the data files.
The checkpoint ensures that the
data files are consistent up to
and including the
last checkpoint,
i.e. checkpoints can
act as recovery points.
Let's have a look at
the changes in how
Ops Manager does backups.
So now, when a backup
job is initiated,
the backup agent will pick a
node to take a snapshot from.
And this is based on numerous
factors, such as the priority
of the node, as
we'd ideally like
to take a snapshot from a node
that won't become primary.
We need to know if a node
is primary or secondary.
We always prefer to take a
snapshot from a secondary node,
so as not to put additional
load on the primary.
And then we need to know
where the previous snapshot
location was, so which node did
we take the last snapshot from?
A node is then selected
in order of preference.
And the preference
is as follows.
Hidden secondary, a
secondary we have previously
taken a snapshot from,
any secondary, and then,
as a last resort, we'll take
a snapshot from the primary.
So once we've
decided which node we
want to take a snapshot
from, the backup agent
will open up a Backup
Cursor on that note.
This is a new
aggregation pipeline
command that's used by the agent
for the backup process only.
The Backup Cursor command
will return a cursor
to a list of files
that need to be copied.
It's important to note
that this functionality is
only available for
MongoDB 4.2 Enterprise.
So the Backup Cursor will
preserve the state of the data
at that point in time
in the data directory
using WiredTiger checkpoint.
This operation does not block
read or write operations
on the database.
So the agent will then
collect all of those files
and transfer them to
the daemon machine,
and then to the snapshot
store you choose.
A checkpoint can be written out
either as blocks to a MongoDB
blockstore or as blocks
to an S3 Bucket in AWS,
or any other S3
compatible storage device.
The metadata for those blocks is
written to the MongoDB database
on the Ops Manager server.
There are some restrictions
for this first iteration
of the new backup
flow functionality.
The first being that we can't
back up sharded clusters.
This is coming in
a future release.
But at the moment, we can
only backup replica sets.
There is also no point in
time restore functionality.
Again, this will be coming
in a future release.
And queryable restores do not
work with the new backup flow
at this time.
And finally, we can
only backup MongoDB 4.2
with the new backup flow.
Any other releases
of MongoDB can still
be backed up using a standard
backup flow in Ops Manager 4.2.
Remember, these
limitations are only
for the initial GA release.
We'll be incrementally
rolling layout improvements
to new backup flow
on a monthly basis.
So let's recap.
We've updated the backup
flow and Ops Manager 4.2
remove the need for the head db.
The agent now uses
WiredTiger snapshots
and pushes those snapshots
directly to the daemon machine,
eliminating the
need for you to wait
for the traditional
initial sync process.