In MongoDB 4.2, when
a tree node replica
set is in a state where
two nodes are performing
an initial sync, the replica set
will no longer have a primary,
and therefore won't
accept writes.
That is, where we used to have
primary Startup 2 and Startup
2, we now have secondary
Startup 2 and Startup 2.
Startup 2 lets you continue
to write your replica set.
When the replica set
is in this state,
you can now
reconfigure the replica
set to have a single voting
node using automation.
So now when a replica
set is in this state,
you can perform a
reconfiguration, if needed,
so that the number of
voting nodes is equal to 1,
and the replica set will
continue to accept writes.
It's important to note
that your client may not
acknowledge writes if you're
using a custom write concern
value.
That is to say,
that if specifying
a write concern where
more than one node needs
to acknowledge the write--
w:2, for instance-- a replica
set with one voting member will
not acknowledge any writes
until that write concern can be
satisfied.
W majority and W1 writes
will be successful
if the replica set has
a single voting node.
For more information
on write concerns,
please refer to
our documentation.
Another new feature in Ops
Manager 4.2 Account Manager
are service users.
Remember, Cloud Manager and
Ops Manager organizations
can contain multiple projects.
And projects can contain
multiple clusters.
Previously, you could
only generate API keys
at a project level.
Also, there was no granularity
with regard to access control
with these API keys.
This meant that if a user was
given an API key associated
with a project, they had access
to a full range of features,
including closer administration.
Also, previously,
personal API keys
were not visible to
the Ops Manager admins.
This meant that if a
person left the company
and you had revoked
their LDAP access,
they could still
use their API key.
Given the principle
of least privilege,
we only want to
grant authorization
to a user as needed.
Sometimes we need to
programmatically retrieve data,
but have no need to make changes
to the cluster or to the users,
for instance.
So what are service users?
They are a way for you to assign
API keys at organization level
and grant permissions
to the API key.
You can do this directly
from the Cloud Manager or Ops
Manager UI.
There are five different
organization permissions
we can grant to an API key, the
first being Organization Owner.
The Organization Owner has root
access to the organization,
including the project
owner role to all projects
in the organization.
This service user
also has access
to administrator organization
settings, users and teams,
and access to delete the
organization permissions
granted to the roles below.
The organization Project Creator
provides project creation
access, as well as
permissions being
granted to the
organization member role.
The Organization
Billing Admin role
provides access to administrator
billing information
for the organization, as well
as all permissions granted
to the organization member role.
The Organization Read
Only role provides access
to everything in
the organization,
including all projects
in that organization.
And finally, the
Organization Member role
provides read only access to
the organization, including
settings, users, and billing.
Remember, API keys are only used
for accessing this information
programmatically.
You can still get all
of this information
and perform all
of the tasks we've
listed through Declare
Manager and Ops Manager UI.
So let's recap.
Ops Manager 4.2
and Cloud Manager
provide two new features.
Automation Now allows you
to reconfigure a tree node
replica set where two nodes
are performing initial sync so
that you have one voting member.
This ensures that
your replica set
can take writes while
it's in this state.
We've also added
service users, which
are a way for you to
assign roles to API keys
at organization level to
allow finer-grained access
control for your applications.