Welcome back.
In Ops Manager 4.2, the
Enterprise Kubernetes Operator
is no longer in beta.
With the new 4.2
release cycle, we
are also releasing the general
availability of the Kubernetes
Operator.
Before we go into the new
Operator and what it can do,
let's review what
Kubernetes is and why
we'd want to use it what
Ops Manager and MongoDB.
Kubernetes is an open-source
container orchestration system
for automating application
deployment, scaling,
and management.
It was originally
designed by Google,
and is now maintained by
the Cloud Native Computing
Foundation.
Looking into its
formal definition,
we can identify that
Kubernetes manages deployments
of containerized
applications, meaning
that applications and systems
running on top of containers
can be managed by a
Kubernetes cluster.
There are many different
terms and concepts
related with a containerized
system and Kubernetes,
and the main ones that
we're going to be looking at
are containers, pods,
replicasets, nodes,
and clusters.
On a high level, Kubernetes
can be represented by something
similar to this diagram.
Each Kubernetes closer
has a master node,
which talks to
older notes in order
to maintain your
cluster's health.
It holds an important set of
processes that are out of scope
with this lesson,
but we are going
to provide links to the
Kubernetes documentation
so that you can read up on
these processes a bit more.
Kubernetes nodes can have
several different specs.
We can compose a
Kubernetes cluster
with physical, virtual,
cloud server nodes.
Each node is composed with the
necessary process to run pods.
Each node has a
container runtime,
which generally Docker, to allow
the nodes to deploy and run
containers.
A pod is the smallest
deployable unit
of computing in Kubernetes.
A pod can be composed of one or
several different containers,
and it also allows the
definition of shared network
and storage resources.
Kubernetes also allows
pods to be fault-tolerant
and highly available.
They're meant to provide
the same operational high
availability as
MongoDB replicasets.
However, this is implemented
quite differently.
In the new version of Ops
Manager, it's easier for you
to effectively manage your
containerized environment using
automation.
To see why we introduced the
Operator in Ops Manager 4.2,
first, let's have a look
at how automation works
without Kubernetes in the mix.
There's a single agent
installed per host,
and that agent pings back to
the Ops Manager web server.
The web server stores
a JSON representation
of the gold state of the
cluster, called the automation
config.
When this config is
changed either in the UI
or via the API, the
agents on each host
will start to go
through transformations
to get the deployment
to its gold state,
whether that be adding
a node, adding a shard,
or updating a user.
This works great when
we're talking about
hosts in the normal
sense of the word,
but what about containers?
The concept of a host
is somewhat conflated,
as a container is an isolated
environment in which process
is run.
We should really install
one agent per container.
And the problem here is that
this can become quite complex
quite quickly, having
to route internal IPs
and ports within the container
to external IPs and ports
on the host.
The Kubernetes Operator is
a lightweight process that
lives inside a Kubernetes pod.
The Operator handles
the deployment
of containers with an image
which contains the MongoDB
agent, and this agent
can managed, back up,
and monitor your
deployment as normal.
The Operator also acts
as an intermediary
between the agent and
the Ops Manager server,
removing the
complexities of managing
your internal or external IP
routing between the containers
and Ops Manager so
that you can use
all of the standard
monitoring, automation,
and backup functionality
in Ops Manager as before
with the added
functionality of being
able to deploy and
manage containers
directly from Ops Manager.
So let's recap.
The Kubernetes Operator is
now an official release.
It's no longer in beta.
You can deploy and
manage containers
directly from Ops
Manager by having
Ops Manager deploy an image.
Each image installed
using the Operator
has the MongoDB agent
pre-installed and ready
to use to monitor,
manage, and back up
your MongoDB deployment.