Welcome back.
In this lesson, we're going
to talk about the MongoDB
Agent, which is a new agent
coming to office manager 402
and clear manager.
We currently have
three separate agents
to monitor, manage and
backup your deployment
in cloud and Ops Manager.
We have the monitoring
agent, which
is responsible for
gathering metrics
from your MongoDB deployment.
We have the automation
agent, which
is responsible for deploying,
administering and managing
your MongoDB processes.
And the backup agent, which
is responsible for streaming
oplog from your
MongoDB replica set
and keeping your
backups in sync.
Up until now, to use each
individual functionality,
you needed to install and
manage each of these agents.
Each agent was a
separate binary.
We've now combined
the functionality
into a brand new agent
called the MongoDB Agent.
This separate agent
will handle all
of the functionality
of the three agents,
without the need to install
three separate packages.
You simply install
among the MongoDB Agents
and activate which
function you wish to use.
It's important to
note that as before,
if you do not have any process
imported for automation,
the MongoDB Agent will not
automate the processes.
Automation is not mandatory,
but definitely recommended.
Let's install the new agent
and deploy a replica set.
OK, so up to this point, the
entire installation process
has been exactly the same as
it was with previous agents.
Let's start the agent
process and jump into the UI
to see if our agent is pinging
back the Cloud Manager.
OK, great.
We can see that our agent is
pinging by the Cloud Manager.
Now we need to activate which
functions we're going to use.
As we're using a
single server here,
we're going to activate all
functions on this server.
As you can see, moderating and
backup are displayed in the UI.
And that's because
automation will not
be used unless you explicitly
manage your deployment.
If we were using
multiple servers,
we could activate
one or more functions
on each agent
based on the needs,
and how we have our
deployment configured.
Let's activate backup a
monitoring on this agent.
OK, so our changes are deployed
and our agent is ready to go.
OK, so let's add a new replica
set from the Deployment page.
When you come to the replica
set configuration page,
you can either manually
enter all the values,
or you can use the
autofill option, which is
what we're going to use here.
And then we just click
Create Replica Set.
Review and Deploy
and Confirm Deploy.
OK, we can see now that
our change is successfully
deployed.
We have a replica set.
And that's it.
You can now manage,
monitor and backup MongoDB
with a single agent.
So what happens if you already
have the standard agents
installed and running?
No problem.
If you're using managed agents,
i.e., your agents are currently
managed by the automation
agent, when the MongoDB Agent is
available, you will see the
usual banner notification
that your agents
are out of date.
You'll then be guided
through a process in the UI,
and the agents will be
updated to the MongoDB Agent
and assigned the
correct functions.
So at a high level, the
steps are as follows.
The automation agent stops any
monitoring of backup agents.
Then enables
monitoring and backup
on the servers where
monitoring or backup were
running as an agent.
It removes the stopped
monitoring and backup agent
binaries.
And unlocks the MMS monitoring
agent or MMS backup agent users
in the MongoDB instance, so that
you can delete them if desired.
The MongoDB Agent uses the
MMS automation agent user
to connect to your instances.
OK, so if you're using
self managed agents
and manage your agents
yourself, the process
is slightly more involved.
The steps are as follows.
When the automation
agent is available,
you'll see the
banner notification
that your monitoring and
backup agent are out of date.
When you're ready to update,
click Update in the banner.
A workflow that guides you
through the update process
starts.
Once the MongoDB Agent is
installed on the server,
it enables the
monitoring and backup
where they existed as a
standalone agent before.
The MongoDB Agent puts the old
monitoring and backup agents
into standby mode, and no
longer shows them in the UI.
We've created a detailed FAQ
in our docs, which we've linked
in the notes for this lesson.
Rest assured, you will be
supported with the new agent
and the upgrade process.
So let's recap.
We now have one agent which
is responsible for monitoring,
backup and automation.
You no longer need to install
three separate agents to manage
your MongoDB deployment.