Let's talk about
pipeline optimization.
We've already learned
about using match and sort
stages early, and to use
indexes using limit and sort
stages to produce top
K results, and how
to allow the use of more
than 100 megabytes of memory.
Let's dive further and look
at pipelines themselves
and how they might be optimized.
Let's consider the
following aggregation
that gives the length
of movie titles
that begin with vowels and
sorts them by the frequency.
So we begin with
our match stage,
looking for titles that
begin with a vowel,
ignoring the case.
We then project our title
size, composing size and split
together, and splitting
the title on spaces.
In our group stage, we're
grouping like documents
together based on that title
size we just calculated
and getting a count.
Finally, we're going to sort
in descending direction.
So the highest frequency
should be coming back first.
Let's run this to get
an idea of the results.
We can see that the most
common length for a movie title
appears to be three words and
there were 1,450 documents that
fell into this group.
We can also see that the most
uncommon length for a movie
title is 17 words, with only
one document in this group.
Let's now examine the
explain information
for this aggregation.
So we have the same
pipeline as before.
But this time we're
appending explain
true to get the explain output.
Let's take a look
at the results.
There is a lot of
interesting information here.
We can see what our query was,
the fields that were kept which
happened to be title and _id,
and then the query planner.
A little further down, we
can also the winning plan
that used a fetch stage
followed by an index scan.
We can probably do a
little better than this,
because we know that
we have an index that
should support this query.
We can also see the
stages that were executed.
Here's our converted project
stage where we see _id true--
this is implicit, remember--
the title size
where we calculated
the size of our
title, and then we
can see our group and our
sort along with the sort key;
pretty interesting information.
So let's see if
we can do better.
Our goal is to try and get this
to be a covered query, meaning
there is no fetch stage.
So this aggregation pipeline is
nearly identical to the first
one we had, except I'm
explicitly getting rid
of the _id field.
Remember, the project
stage implicitly
keeps it unless
we tell it not to.
Let's see if we get
the same results.
And we do indeed get the
same results as before,
where it looks like movies
with a length of three words
have the most occurrence
with 1,450 documents.
OK.
We verified the same results.
Let's check the explain output
to see if we've improved
our query performance at all.
Again, the same pipeline we just
used also projecting out _id,
just adding the explain true
option to the aggregation
function.
And looking at the
explain plan, we
see again we have the
same query on the cursor.
This time the fields
are different.
We're keeping the title
and projecting away _id.
Let's go ahead and go
down to the winning plan
to see if we avoided
that fetch stage.
All right, so looking
at our winning plan,
we can see it's much better.
I can see there's
no fetch stage.
So our match stage
was indeed covered.
When we see a fetch
stage, it means
MongoDB had to go to the
document for more information,
rather than just using
information from the index
alone.
Of some interest here, we
can also see that _id was now
projected as false.
This is because we explicitly
provided that information.
So let's see if we
can do even better.
So here's our new
modified pipeline, where
we have the same match stage.
However, this time we
have no project stage.
Instead, we perform the
logic we need within group
and then sort on those results.
Let's see it in action.
All right, pretty cool.
We got the same
results, three words,
count of 1,450 documents.
Let's check the
explain output to see
the difference
between this pipeline
and our previous pipeline.
All right, let's look
at the explain output.
We can see that the
query is the same.
We can see that the fields are
the same as well-- title 1,
_id is 0.
How did the
aggregation framework
know to do this when we didn't
specify a project stage?
Let's cover that in a moment.
Down in our winning
plan, we can see
there was no fetch
stage, which meant
that this is a covered query.
If we scroll all the
way down to the bottom
to look at the rest of
our pipeline stages,
we can see the next stage
after our query is group, then
our sort, and we're done.
A key takeaway here is to
avoid needless projects.
As we saw, the
aggregation framework
assumed we knew what we were
doing with each project.
However, if the
aggregation framework
can determine the shape of
the final document based only
on initial input, internally
it will project away
unnecessary fields.
That was a mouthful.
So let me explain that
in a little more detail.
In the first match stage,
the only field we cared about
was the title.
In the group stage, again,
the only field we care about
is the title.
We use this composition
of expressions
to get the number of
words in the title.
But we can do that
in line by evaluating
first splitting the title
on spaces into an array,
and then getting in
the size of the array.
There's no need for an
intermediary project stage,
because we can just calculate
that value in line here.
This is a very powerful feature.
We should always strive to
let the optimizer work for us.
Additionally, this removes a
stage that ultimately adds time
to the pipeline.
Let's think about that.
Say we have 100,000 documents
in our movies collection.
In the match, we
filter down to 10,000.
Now in group, we have 10,000
documents come through.
And in sort, we have maybe 15.
Well, with that intermediary
project stage that we really
didn't need, we had 100,000
come in, then we have 10,000,
and we'd send all 10,000 through
that intermediary project
before they got to
the group stage.
That's 10,000
additional iterations
that we just avoided.
So as a general
rule, don't project
unless you are doing some
real work in this stage.
And remember that add
fields is available.
OK, one last note
before we move on,
we could replace group
and sort by sort by count.
It really is the
same under the hood.
It just saves us on typing.
Keep that in mind.