All right, let's now discuss
another common operation
that developers encounter when
using a one-to-end pattern,
like the attribute or
the subset patterns,
such as stocks traded in a given
moment or the top 20 customer
reviews for a product.
How do we efficiently
work with that data
if we'd like to perform some
aggregation framework analysis?
Let's imagine we're working with
documents of this schema, that
is tracking all buy
and sell transactions
on our trading platform.
We'd like to analyze how many
total transactions we have,
as well as how
many buys and sells
were performed per time stamp,
and then use this data later
in our pipeline.
In other words, we want to
group data in the document,
not across documents.
Let's take a look
at the collection
and think about how we
might accomplish this.
OK, so we have our
time stamp, and then we
have our trades array
with many, many documents.
OK, this might be
our first approach,
where we unwind the
trades array, and then
group on the time and the
action, [INAUDIBLE] account.
And then group again,
just on the time,
and pushing the action and
account for that type of action
into an array, and then getting
the total number of actions we
performed per that time stamp.
So we should get total
actions per document
with the individual numbers
of buy and sell actions.
Let's test it up.
OK, we can see that it's
the same pipeline as that
from the previous slide.
We unwind the trades array,
group on the time stamp
and the action, and then group
again just on the time stamp.
We've added this
sort stage here, just
to ensure we get consistent
ordering for comparison later
on.
All right, it gives us
the results we expected--
total actions and the
number of buy and sell
actions per document.
This is a visual representation
of the previous pipeline.
The black squares
are our documents.
If we start with four
documents and unwind a field
with just three
entries per document,
we now have 12 documents.
We then group our
documents twice
to produce the desired
results, ending up
with the same number of
documents we started with.
This should start to feel
horribly inefficient.
Sadly, it gets worse.
Let's examine how this
inefficiency impacts operations
in Shard D environment.
Each shard performs the unwind.
Initial processing for
the first group stage
will be done on the shards.
But the final grouping has to
happen in a single location.
Every other stage, including the
entirety of the second group,
would then take place
on that location.
Imagine if three or four
other stages followed.
When not grouping
across documents,
this causes needless overhead
in network traffic and causes
[INAUDIBLE],, after
the group, to be
run in the location
of the merge,
rather than remain distributed.
Here, we're shown that
the grouping is happening
on Shard A. In reality, it
could happen anywhere at random
in our cluster.
So we really need a way
to iterate over the array
and perform our desired
logic within the document.
Thankfully, we have
map, reduce, filter,
and the accumulator expressions
available in the project
stage to remedy this problem.
Let's examine this pipeline.
We'll get the size of
the resultant arrays
by filtering to
remove the action we
don't want for that field.
In this case, we
only allow documents
through that had
the buy action--
here, the sell action.
Lastly, we'll just get the
size of the trades array
to get how many
total trades we had.
Now, this seems
almost too simple,
so let's look at it in action.
Again, this is the same pipeline
as on the previous slide.
The sort stage is
added just to ensure
we get consistent results,
so that we can do comparisons
later.
Awesome--
functionally-identical results.
And I'd argue that this format
is easier to reason about.
Let's look at the previous
output to compare.
And here are the results
from that previous pipeline
where we used the double group.
We can see the
information we still
want is embedded within
this actions array.
This is a visualization
of our new pipeline.
Our new pipeline produced
functionally-identical results,
but visually-- we can
see in the execution--
is much different.
Rather than performing
unnecessary work
and possibly moving and
collapsing our pipeline
to a single location, causing
a slowdown in extra network
usage, we retain the
same number of documents
performing the work in a
targeted manner and in place.
And in the shard
environment, the benefits
are tangible as well.
We've kept all work
distributed among the shards.
All right, but wait-- but wait.
That's all fine for
essentially binary input,
when we want to count the
occurrence of something.
But what if we want to do
something more meaningful?
What if we'd like to find how
many times a specific stock was
bought, sold, and what the
total price was for each?
Let's find that information
out for MongoDB stock.
Again, map, reduce, filter,
and the accumulator expressions
available on the project
stage are amazing tools.
So this is one example
pipeline that would
produce those results for us.
First, we specify the
reduced expression.
As the input array, we'll go
ahead and filter the trades
array, filtering out
any stock ticker that
isn't equal to MongoDB.
The initial value and the
value that will be used
as the accumulator value,
dollar-dollar value--
we're going to specify this
document, with two keys--
buy and sell-- that
are each documents,
with keys of total
count and total value.
Here, an in is our logic.
We start with this
conditional expression,
where we check if this dot
action is equal to buy.
Remember, dollar-dollar
this refers
to the current element
of the input array.
Remember, we
filtered that, so we
know we're only going
to get documents that
had MDB as the ticker symbol.
So if it is a buy action,
we modify the total count
by adding one to
dollar-dollar value,
dot buy, dot total count.
Remember, dollar-dollar
value refers
to the accumulator,
which we set initially
to be this value right here.
We also modify total value
by adding this dot price
to dollar-dollar value,
dot buy, dot total value.
And if this was a buy action,
we don't modify sell in any way.
We just reassign
it back to itself.
If it is a sell action, we
essentially do the same thing,
adding one to sell-total-count
and adding this stock price
to sell-total-value, and then
finally re-assigning buy back
to itself, because
this was a sell.
We can see that,
based on MongoDB only,
the buy total count was 10,
and the sell total count
was five for this
specific document.
We can also see the
dollar value associated
with all the transactions.
Again, we see 22 and 19
and the value associated.
All right, we've covered a lot
of information in this lesson.
Let's go ahead and summarize
what we talked about.
First, avoid unnecessary stages.
The aggregation framework can
project fields automatically
if the final shape of
the output document
can be determined
from initial input.
Second, use accumulator
expressions--
as well as dollar-map,
dollar-reduce,
and dollar-filter expressions--
in project stages before
an unwind, if possible.
Again, this only
applies if you need
to group within a document,
not among your documents.
Lastly, every high-order
array function
can be implemented
with dollar-reduce
if the provided expressions
do not meet your needs.