In this lesson, we're going talk
about aggregation performance.
And specifically,
we're going to discuss
how we can utilize indexes when
we run aggregation queries.
And we're also going to discuss
some of the memory constraints
that apply to
aggregation in MongoDB.
Before we get into
these different topics,
I first want to
point out that there
are two high-level categories
of aggregation queries.
First of all, there are
real time processing queries
and then there are
batch processed queries.
"real time" is in quotes here
because you can never have
truly real time processing.
There will always be
some kind of delay
between when a query is executed
and when that query responds.
Real time processing is so
that we can provide data
to applications.
This means that performance
is more important.
A user is going to perform
some kind of action,
the action is going to
trigger an aggregation query,
and then the results
of that query
need to be provided
back to the user
in a reasonable amount of time.
With batch processing,
on the other hand,
we're generally talking
about doing aggregation
to provide analytics.
And since we're
providing analytics,
that means that these
jobs are typically run
on some kind of periodic basis.
And the results
are not inspected
until minutes, hours, or
even days later from when
that query was actually ran.
This means that
query performance
is less important than
with real time processing.
Throughout this
lesson, we're going
to focus on the first
type, real time processing.
Now some of these
principles will also
apply to the batch
processing category.
But for the most part we'll
be discussing strategies
to optimize aggregation
performance for real time
processing.
Now with that out
of the way, let's
go ahead and discuss the
meat of this lesson, index
usage for aggregation queries.
Now as you come to
learn in this course,
indexes are a vital part
of good query performance.
And this same idea applies
to aggregation queries.
Basically, we want to
ensure that our aggregation
queries are able to use
indexes as much as possible.
Now naturally,
since aggregation is
a bit different than
your typical find query,
determining index usage is
a bit different as well.
With an aggregation
query, we form a pipeline
of different
aggregation operators,
which transform our data into
the format that we desire.
Now some of these
aggregation operators
are able to use indexes,
and some of them are not.
But more importantly,
since data moves
through our pipeline from the
first operator to the last,
once the server encounters
a stage that is not
able to use indexes, all
of the following stages
will no longer be able
to use indexes either.
Fortunately for us,
the query optimizer
tries its best to
detect when a stage can
be moved forward so that
indexes can be utilized.
But if you understand the
underlying principles of how
this works, you can
be more confident
in your query
performance, and you'll
have to rely less on
the query optimizer.
In order for us to determine
how aggregation queries is
are executed and whether or
not indexes are being utilized,
we can pass the
explain true document
as an option to the
aggregation method.
This will produce
an explain output
similar to what we are
used to seeing with find.
Now for the rest
of these examples,
we're going to be dealing
with this hypothetical orders
collection.
And we're going to go
ahead and assume that we
have an index on customer ID.
Unsurprisingly,
the $match operator
is able to utilize indexes.
This is especially true if it's
at the beginning of a pipeline.
You'll see a natural
theme here of that
we want to see operators
that use indexes
at the front of our pipelines.
Similarly, we're
always going to want
to put sort stages as close
to the front as possible.
We saw with find queries how
serious our performance can
be degraded when sorting
isn't able to use an index.
For this reason, we
want to make sure
that our sort stages come before
any kind of transformations
so that we can make sure that
we utilize indexes for sorting.
If you're doing a
limit and doing a sort,
you want to make sure that
they're near each other
and at the front
of the pipeline.
When this happens, the server
is able to do a top-k sort.
This is when the server
is able to only allocate
memory for the final number of
documents, in this case, 10.
This can happen even
without indexes.
This is one of the most highly
performant non-index situations
that you can be in.
Optimizations like
this are performed
by the query optimizer
whenever possible.
But if there is a chance that
this optimization can change
the output it results,
then the query engine
will not perform this
kind of optimization.
That's why understanding
these underlying principles
is important.
Now those are the
basic aggregation
optimizations that you can do.
Now let's discuss some
of the memory constraints
that you should be aware
of when doing aggregation.
First of all, your
results are all
subject to the 16
megabyte document
limit that exist in MongoDB.
Aggregation generally
outputs a single document,
and that single document will
be susceptible to this limit.
Now this limit does
not apply to documents
as they flow through
the pipeline.
As you transform documents,
they can actually
exceed the 16 megabyte
limit, but whatever
is actually returned will still
fall under the 16 megabyte
limit.
The best way to
mitigate this issue
is by using $limit and $project
to reduce your resulting
document size.
Another limitation that you're
going to want to be aware of
is that for each
stage in our pipeline,
there's a 100 megabyte
limit of RAM usage.
Now the absolute best
way to mitigate this
is to ensure that your
largest stages are
able to utilize indexes.
This will reduce your
memory requirements,
since indexes are generally much
smaller than the documents they
reference.
Moreover, with sorting,
they dramatically
reduce memory
requirements, because you
don't need to allocate extra
memory for that sorting.
Now if you're still running
into this 100 megabyte limit
even if you're using
indexes, then there's
an additional way
to get around it.
And that is by
specifying allowDiskUse
true on your aggregation query.
This will allow you to
spill to disk, rather
than doing everything in memory.
Now this is important to
understand that this is
a absolute last resort measure.
Hard drives are thousands
of times slower to access
than memory, so by
splitting to disk,
you're going to see serious
performance degration.
In some situations,
this is necessary,
but you need to be aware
that this will seriously
decrease performance.
Since allowDiskUse true will
seriously impact performance,
you'll see this more often
on the batch processing
kind of jobs, rather than
real time processing.
And the last thing I want to
point out here is that allow
disk usage does not
work with $ graphLookup,
and that's because $graphLookup
doesn't currently support
splitting to disk.
Let's recap what we've learned.
So in this lesson,
we discussed some
of the different
optimization strategies
for utilizing indexes with
your queries for aggregation,
and we also discussed some
of the member constraints
that apply to aggregation, and
how you can mitigate and get
around those issues.