in this video I like to discuss a list
of security best practices that you
should follow to harden your MongoDB
deployment this list the best practices
should act as a checklist before giving
the green light to any production
MongoDB system many of the items on this
list we've already covered in depth in
this course in general I'm going to
spend less time talking about the topics
that we've already covered in depth in
previous videos and I'll spend more time
discussing topics that we haven't
explicitly covered in this course the
first item our list of best practices is
enable access control and enforced
authentication now that we're near the
end of this course this should be pretty
easy for you to do we've already talked
a lot about specific authentication
mechanisms and methods that mam going to
be supports like scram sha-1 and x.509
certificates I would however like to
point out the following sub items first
authentication should be a requirement
for all clients of your database and
this leads nicely into the next item
which is enable authentication on each
MongoDB server you want to ensure that
each MongoDB server has authentication
enabled don't forget about that
read-only secondary that your data
science team uses security is only as
strong as the weakest link in your chain
the next item is configure role based
access control again by now you should
be very familiar with MongoDB this role
based access control model and how it
works the following sub items will be
important for you to check off as you
sip access control in your deployment
when you first set up your deployment
you want to create a single
administrative user that will be able to
configure the rest of your users when
creating new users you want to ensure
that there's a unique user freeze person
or application accessing the database
with each of these new users you want to
follow a principle of least privilege
only give a user the absolute minimum
access that they need it's better to be
safe than sorry it's also important to
take advantage of MongoDB as built-in
roles and when necessary group roles
together the next bullet point is
encrypted communication I don't want to
spend too much time on this one because
we've already covered this one
extensively already but that does not
mean it's not important generating and
managing SSL certificates across an
number of machines and clients can be
cumbersome at times but ensuring that
your mom would be servers only accept
secure connections brings a lot of peace
of mind plain and simple you should
ensure that are using TLS connections
across your deployment we've already
talked about encrypting communications
the next logical item to talk about is
encrypting and protecting data now we've
talked a lot about the encryption at
rest that is provided by MongoDB
Enterprise but I'd also like to talk
about some other important security
points first of all if you're using
wired tiger' then you should make sure
that using encryption at rest but
moreover it's important that when you're
using encryption at rest that you have a
k-map solution so that you're able to
easily rotate your keys on a regular
basis and if you don't have access to
encryption at rest because you don't
have access to MongoDB Enterprise then
you should fall back on using some type
of file system device or physical
encryption something that we didn't
explicitly talk about that it's
important is to use file system
permissions to protect your MongoDB data
files make sure that the only users
running mangu D service have access to
the files and that other users cannot
read or write from them the easiest way
to do this is to run to mod it's 700 on
the data DB directory
this gives read write execute
permissions to the owner your dedicated
user and gives no permissions to the
owners group and no permissions to
anyone else in the system we haven't
talked much about this next bullet point
which is limit network exposure this is
a more traditional non MongoDB specific
security best practice you can
significantly reduce the risk that
affects your deployment by instituting a
strong network exposure security posture
this can be done a number of ways but
it's most traditionally achieved about
the use of either firewalls or VPNs or v
pcs if you're in the cloud firewalls
allow administrators to filter and
control access to a system by providing
granular control over network
communications the main idea here is to
limit incoming network traffic on a
specific port to specific systems
thereby limiting incoming traffic from
untrusted hosts for best results and to
minimize overall exposure ensure that
only traffic from trusted sources can
reach your Mongo D or Mongo s instances
and that the mangu D and Mongo es
instances can only connect to trusted
outputs virtual private networks and
virtual private clouds on the other hand
link to networks by providing a
encrypted and limited access trusted
network typically MongoDB users who use
the PN's use TLS rather than IPSec VPNs
for performance issues it's not a bad
idea to continue using a firewall even
inside of a VPN MongoDB supports its own
firewall of sorts there's a
configuration parameter called bind IP
where at the database level you
configure connections from a specific IP
address or subnet using all three of
these security best practices ensured
the most secure network setup we've
already spent time talking about
auditing with MongoDB we know that it's
important to always audit any kind of
database configuration changes and for
some users that make sense to audit
changes to the data within our database
but those users should understand that
there are performance implications in
doing this we alluded to this next item
in a previous checklist it's important
that on the machines that you have
MongoDB instances running that you have
a dedicated user for running those
services that user should exist for the
sole purpose of running MongoDB and it's
related monitoring Damons
it's very important that this user is
not the root user we spent a lot of time
in this course discussing the different
configuration options within MongoDB
there are some configuration options
that are important for you to ensure are
disabled in production this includes
disabling the web interface that can be
connected over HTTP as well as the REST
API that request can be made to both of
these features are deprecated and
disabled by default
both only support the MongoDB CR
mechanism and therefore should be used
absolutely only for backwards
compatibility reasons and then there's
disabling server-side scripting MongoDB
supports the execution of JavaScript
code for certain servers had operations
like MapReduce group and where if you
not use these methods and operators then
you should disable server-side scripting
with the no scripting option via the
command line this
feature MongoDB as you can imagine could
potentially expose your server to the
injection of malicious JavaScript if
you're a part of a government
organization that requires security
technical implementation guides commonly
referred to as Stig's then you can
request one by going to MongoDB calm /
IP / contact / dig requests and finally
it's important to consider security
standards compliance if you're a part of
an organization that has security
compliance standards like PCI HIPAA or
NIST 80 53 then I suggest that you look
our MongoDB security reference
architecture white paper which is linked
below now this list is by no means an
exhaustive list of every possible
security best practice that you and her
team should be implementing that being
said in general this list should provide
you with a very good place to improve
your overall security posture with
regards to MongoDB