Now let's go ahead and
use our last example
and actually go ahead
and try out this filter.
In this video, we're going
to go ahead and build off
of the example we
saw in the last video
and actually try and
test out this filter.
If you remember from last time,
we created an audit filter
where we monitored creating
or dropping collections.
Let's go ahead and start the
MongoDB for this audit filter.
I still have my configuration
file from a previous video,
so let's go ahead and just
add the audit filter directly
into this file.
So here is our
configuration file.
We just need to add a line
that looks like this where
we specify a filter, and then
we define the audit filter
that we've made.
And now, like before,
we can go ahead and just
run with --config, our
configuration file, and --fork.
Now, I do want to point out, if
we didn't use a configuration
file, we could use the
--auditFilter option,
like so, and then just pass
a string to this option.
But since we've
already specified that,
we can just hit enter.
Now we'll go ahead
and tail our log.
And you can see that, so
far, there's nothing in here.
And now, in our last example,
we tried to authenticate,
and that showed
in the audit log.
So let's first
authenticate and make sure
that that doesn't show up.
And when I hit Enter, we see
that the authentication failed.
And when I go back to
log, we shouldn't see it.
And, awesome, we don't see it.
However, if I try to
create a collection now,
and I run db.createCollection
with a test collection,
it says, OK.
And, right here, we
can see our audit log.
We have an atype of
createCollection.
We have our time stamp,
our local, our remote.
And then, of course,
we actually see
the params that are passed in.
So the namespace,
or the collection
that we're trying to create,
was on the test.t database,
and it was a collection
called "testcoll."
Of course, we
don't actually have
to run the
createCollection command.
MongoDB has a flexible schema.
So you'll create a
collection on the fly.
You can see here, I can
show the collections.
You see our test collection.
And I can also just run
db.insert on a collection that
doesn't exist yet.
And MongoDB will dynamically run
createCollection on our behalf.
And so we should
see that in the log.
And we do.
There's our other
createCollection.