Now that you have a good,
high-level understanding
of what we can use
auditing for, we
can take a moment to look at
what auditing logs actually
look like.
Of course, auditing
logs are outputted
in either JSON or BSON.
And here's an example of what
an audit log will look like.
All audit logs will have the
same eight top-level fields--
atype, ts, local, remote,
users, roles, param, and result.
Let's take a moment and break
each one of these fields
down so we know what
we're dealing with.
First we have atype.
It's a string.
It's short for "action type."
We'll talk more about action
types in a later video,
but an example would be
something like authenticate,
create index, create
user, or add [? shard. ?]
These should sound
familiar, because they're
very similar, if not the
same, as a lot of the commands
we run on a regular basis.
Next we have ts, which is
short for "time stamp."
It's a document.
And, inside of this document,
it will contain the date and UTC
time of the event.
Then we have local.
Local is another
embedded document.
And inside this document
will have the local IP
address and the port number of
the running mongod instance.
Similar to local,
we have remote.
It's also a document,
just like local.
And it will contain the
remote IP address and port
number of the incoming
connection associated
with this event.
Next we have users,
which is an array.
This is an array of user
identification documents.
Because MongoDB allows
a session to log
in with a different
user per database,
this array can have
more than one user.
Each document contains a
user field for the user name
and a db field for
the authentication
database of that user.
We also have a roles array.
This is an array of
documents that specifies
the roles granted to the user.
Each document contains a role
field for the name of the role
and a db field for the database
associated with that role.
Then we have param.
This is also a document.
This is where the meat of
our audit log will live.
Any specific details
for the event live here.
This is tightly
associated with the atype.
For example, if we have
an atype of authenticate,
then we can expect a param that
is a document with the fields
user, db, and mechanism.
And finally, we have a
result, which is an integer.
This is our error code.
If our result is non-zero,
meaning an error,
then that error is going
to be directly related
to the atype associated with
the event that we're logging.