In this video, we're going
to talk about auditing
with MongoDB.
Auditing is an enterprise
feature of MongoDB.
And for certain organizations
and administrators,
auditing is a very
important part
of security infrastructure.
Auditing can be used
for a myriad of things.
But from a security
perspective, it
is most often used for the
following three things.
First, it's often used
for accountability
of the users of our database.
Auditing is also commonly
used to investigate
suspicious activity.
And finally, it is used
to monitor and gather
data about specific
database activities.
Once enabled, the
auditing system
can record four different
categories of operations.
First, we can monitor
schema modification, or DDL.
We can also audit the
management and configuration
operations used to configure
our replica sets and sharded
clusters.
Of course, we can also audit the
access to our database as well
as the authorization
[? within ?] [? side ?]
of our database.
And finally, we can even
audit CRUD operations
on our database.