Organizations are
increasingly storing
sensitive personally
identifiable information, PII,
on MongoDB and are
facing the challenge
of complying with
security policies
and external regulations
such as HIPA, PCI and FERPA.
These policies usually
require encryption on disk
when storing sensitive
or private data in order
to protect it from being
accessed by unauthorized users.
In order to address these
regulated use cases,
MongoDB offers database
file encryption
as part of its
enterprise offering.
MongoDB 3.4 is further
strengthening its data
protection offering
by adding an option
to redact client data
from the system log files.
Additionally, log
assertions will contain
no content in this mode.
Rather the source
file and line number
will be provided instead.
This option will prevent
potentially sensitive data
from being written
to system logs, which
are stored and encrypted.
This will greatly simplify
the best practices
for deploying MongoDB
in regular environments
and helps to ensure PII data
is protected where possible.
There are important
supportability trade-offs,
though, to redacting client
data from the system logs.
The new option will redact
all values from documents.
Therefore, the
logs will only show
the set of keys queried against
without the actual values used
to filter.
While still helpful,
this will weaken
the power of our
system logs from
a diagnosability standpoint.
Now, let's have a look
to some examples where
we can see the configuration
options and trade-offs
while enabling log redaction.