So let's go ahead and set
up our MongoD instance.
But let's start by setting
it up in the-- let's say--
normal mode without
any log redaction.
And then we're going to be
activating the redaction
to see the differences
in the logs.
The first thing
that we need to do
is pretty much go
to our data folder.
And there's a
redaction folder there.
So as you can see here,
it's completely empty.
So I'm going to use
this as my DB path
on this particular shell.
Now I'm going to
specify the DB path,
and just point there
to this folder MongoD.
There's no other flag.
There's no other thing then
just putting it up on 27017,
and this DB path right here.
So as you can see from
the logs everything
is boot up correctly.
So I'm going to keep
this window here.
And I'm just going to
jump to another one
that I have here already set up.
So I can establish
here my connections.
Then the next thing
that I'm going to do
is basically connect
to my instance.
Here we are.
Connected on my
local instance, I
can now set up a
couple different things
to get a more
comprehensive look.
First thing I'm going
to do is to show you
how to set up a
profiling level that
allows us to capture
every single [INAUDIBLE]
instruction into our logs.
And to do that, I just need
to set my profiling level.
Keep it at 0.
This is a default set up.
But setting up the slow
ms value to minus 1.
This is a simple
trick to just collect
every single instruction
they had my MongoD
instance is going to process.
It will be captured on its log.
And so I do this.
I can see how it was before.
Our slow ms was set
to 100 milliseconds,
as you should all know.
And it's all good.
It's all OK equals 1.
Now that I have that, I'm
going to use a redact database.
So once I move there, I'm
going to create a collection.
Right now there's no
collections whatsoever.
So I'm just going to
create a new collection
that I'm going to call
sensitive, for sensitive data.
And I'm going to
insert a document which
I'm going to say that going
to have a field called secret.
And I'm going to say
that this should not
be found in the logs.
It's a single string,
all very clear
that I do not want to find
this message in my logs.
So once I do this and once
I insert, if I move back
to my output of my
logs, we can see clearly
here in clear text the message
that I've just inserted.
In this case, as
you can see, I'm
writing to the sensitive
namespace, or collection
this case, and I'm
writing this document.
It has the message secret.
This should not be found in the
logs which unfortunately, this
is the case right now.
Because we haven't
enabled redaction yet.
Now to enable redaction, we
have three different options.
The first option is to pass
to the MongoD at boot up time.
The client log data flag.
With this set up, we will
immediately initiate MongoD
with the capability of
redacting the client's
data into the logs.
So any logged operation,
any of slow ms operation
that MongoD has to process,
it will be logged in the logs,
but redacted.
The other option
would be to set it up
on the MongoDB config files.
Like for example, if I
have this sample here,
called MongoD underscore
redaction dot com,
can see that I'm setting up
the db path, a log system where
I'm going to throw
the log into the file.
And importantly, under
Security, there's
a new flag called redact
client log equals true.
Now the other option,
the third option,
would be to just
connect to MongoDB.
And again, you know that we
are not using any redaction
at the moment.
Now what I need
to do is basically
run the admin command.
Setting up a perimeter,
which in this case
it will be redact client
log data to true or 1,
in this case.
And once I do this, now I've
enabled this MongoD to redact
all operations that are
going to be taking more
time than slow ms. To do that,
let's go to our redact database
and just run sensitive
collection again
with a new insert statement
saying that our secret now
is going to be really, do
not show this in the logs.
And hopefully we will not see
such a message in our logs.
So once we insert it, we
go back to our message.
And here we see a lot of hashes.
All of these operations
were in fact commands
that MongoDB completely
redacted so they would not
show its content on the logs.
From all the three
different options
that we have to set up
this file correctly,
we should take in
consideration a few things.
If we do it in the run time,
we can definitely do that.
But once the server reboots,
we need to make sure
that we set it up again.
So that is a risk that
we forget about it.
So pay attention to that.
If we set it up on the
config file, or even
on the MongoD runtime-- so
when we specify a service
or something like that,
the best way to do
it is to use the
config file obviously.
But this will guarantee us
that from the initial point
in our execution of
this MongoD instances,
we will have log
redaction enabled.
And in case that
our server reboots,
you always pick up the
configuration options
from its file.
So we will be safe
that all the log
information will be redacted.
Now also take note that the
flag can be set on MongoS,
or should be set on
MongoS and MongoD.
In the shard
environment you need
to go to all individual MongoS's
and all individual MongoD's
to make sure you do not forget
to redact the log messages
on all of these machines.
So for Hyperloop purposes,
you might add new nodes
to a replica set.
If you are redacting
everything, you
intend everything to be
redacted on both your primary
and secondaries, you need to
make sure that all of them
have this flag active.
Otherwise, might
get a leak there
from one of the
MongoD's which have not
enabled the redaction flag.
Another interesting thing
is that we've seen an insert
command, but for find
commands or update
commands we will not see the
actual data of our queries.
We only be seeing the query
shape of the queries that
will be logged in our logs.
And this is how you set up your
log redaction on MongoD 3.4.