In this video, we're going
to talk about audit filters.
And so by now, you might be
asking yourself the question,
what is logged by default
when we have auditing enabled?
And we already know that
there are four categories
of events that can be logged
through MongoDB's auditing
system.
There are Schema,
or DDL, Operations.
There are Replica Set and
Sharded Cluster Operations.
There are Authentication and
Authorization Operations.
And finally, there are CRUD,
also known as DML, Operations.
But by default, we only
audit these three categories.
And the reason this
is is the same reason
we have audit filters
in the first place.
And that's because when
we audit everything,
we have too many logs.
And we also have
performance loss.
We have performance loss
because we're constantly writing
to disk for every operation.
That's why CRUD is not
audited by default,
even when auditing is enabled.
If CRUD was enabled by default,
then virtually every operation
on your database would
have an additional write.
And those additional
writes are going
to make you lose performance
on your database.
And moreover, we just
have too many logs.
We were just logging
so much stuff,
it's hard to even
know what's going on.
And that's why
audit filters exist.
Audit filters, like the
logs that they describe,
are defined in JSON.
We specify an audit filter
using a filter document.
As you can see,
this filter document
is pretty straightforward.
Here, we're creating
a filter document
where we want to log any time
that there's a createCollection
or dropCollection, atype.
Essentially, all we're doing
is writing a query document
with the MongoDB
query language as
if we are querying these logs.