Let's go ahead and
modify our config file
so we can pass the appropriate
parameters to our MongoDB.
The first thing we do is go
ahead and delete our filter
from last time.
And now, in order to enable
the auditing of DML operations,
actually all we want to
do is enable the auditing
of authorization success.
We can enable this auditing
via server parameter.
And this is how we do that.
We just use a server
parameter and say
"auditAuthorizationSuccess"
and set it to true.
And now, any kind of operation
that passes successfully,
in this case DML
or CRUD operations,
should now be audited.
Let's go in and try it out
by starting our server.
Now that our server's
up and running
with CRUD operations
being audited,
we can now go ahead and
test our CRUD operation.
Le'ts go ahead and switch to
the my-application database.
And, from here, we can go ahead
and try to insert something
into the products collection.
And here, I'm going to insert
a product called "candy bar"
into the products collection.
And it was inserted.
And now let's go ahead
and see our audit
logs and see if this CRUD
operation was logged.
And, right here, you can see
that we have an "authCheck."
We actually though, we
have a bunch of authChecks,
but this is the authCheck
that pertains to us.
We can see that there is
an insert into products,
and then we have the following
document, productName "candy
bar."
But it's important
to point out here
that there are
lots of authChecks.
There's an authCheck
to make sure
that we're Master,
another authCheck
to make sure that we're
Master, another authCheck
to make sure that we're Master.
There's a lot of noise in here.
So it's highly recommended
that you don't actually
turn on CRUD operations to
be audited unless you really,
really need that functionality
from a security perspective,
because we are significantly
increasing the write load
that the server has.
So if this server was under
a high amount of write load
from clients, then
the server is going
to be having a
bunch of additional
writes just for
auditing purposes.
That would take away
from its ability
to handle the writes that
are coming in from clients.
And that's how you
enable auditing
for CRUD operations
with MongoDB.