In this video, we're going
to talk about auditing DDL.
With traditional SQL
databases, SQL statements
generally fall under
one of two categories.
A statement is either a DDL--
a Data Definition Language
statement or DML--
Data Manipulation
Language statement.
As you can imagine,
DDL statements
are statements
that make a change
to the schema of a database.
Whereas, DML statements
manipulate the actual data
within them.
While MongoDB has a flexible
schema, which could potentially
imply that there is no DDL,
the MongoDB query language
actually supports
several DDL operations.
Here's a short list
of a few action types
that the auditing system uses
that would fall under DDL.
We have things like
createIndex, createDatabase,
renameCollection,
dropDatabase, et cetera.
If you actually look
at all the action types
that the MongoDB
auditing system supports,
you'll notice most
of them are actually
related to DDL rather
than DML operations.
This is because, for the most
part, auditing within MongoDB
is designed to
monitor changes made
to the actual configuration
of our databases.