In this video, I'm going to
cover how to actually enable
auditing from the command line.
Here's a very typical
command to start a mongod.
In order to enable auditing,
we add the auditDestination
option.
This option will
take an argument
which will determine
where the logs go.
In this case, I
specified syslog,
meaning that the logs will
go to the system's logs.
Virtually all operating
systems have a system log.
Your system logs are
very OS dependent,
so depending on your
operating system,
you just need to look up where
your system logs are stored.
And that's where
these logs would go.
We can also output our
auditing logs to standard out.
If we want to do that, we
use the console keyword.
Now of course, we can
also output our audit logs
to a file of our choosing
by using the file argument.
When we choose to output
our logs to a file,
we'll need to add
two more options.
And here are the two
additional options,
auditFormat and auditPath.
auditFormat takes an
argument which can either
be JSON or BSON, and auditPath
takes an additional argument,
which, of course,
is the path of where
we want to store the audit log.
One reason you'd output your
logs in BSON instead of JSON
is because BSON serializes
to disk a lot faster.
There's no serialization
process between BSON and JSON
when you just output
directly to BSON.
Of course, you're going to
lose some ease of readability,
because with a JSON
the file you can just
pop right into the file and
read your logs immediately.
But if you are worried
about write performance,
then you can always use BSON
to have high write throughput
on your audits.
For now, let's stick
with JSON so you can see
what our logs look like easily.
And we can see that our server
has successfully started.
And I'm going to go to
another shell and go ahead
and tail those logs.
And here I'm using the tail
command with the -f option
so we can see our auditLog.json
update in real time.
We'll go back to another
shell, and we'll connect.
And now if I try to
authenticate with a user
that we know is phony, we
should see that in the log.
And here, we can see that
the authentication failed.
And if we go to our other shell,
and we see the log right here.
And just like we showed
in our last video,
there's an atype, a time stamp,
a local and remote IP address,
as well as a list
of the users who
executed the command, which,
of course, is nothing,
since we weren't logged
in to anyone yet.
And then you can
actually see that it was
an authentication action type.
And here were the
parameters that were passed.
It was a user, "baduser."
The password is redacted.
And we can see that is
executed on the test databse
using SCRAM-SHA-1.
Of course, we can
also make our lives
a lot easier by specifying
this configuration
in a configuration file, which
is what I've done so already.
Here I have this
config.yaml file.
And if we take a look, and
this configuration file
makes a lot of sense.
We have our mongo.log
going to its regular place.
We have dbPath going
to its regular place.
And then, just like we
saw in the last command,
I'm saying that out auditLog
will be to a file for JSON.
And here is the name
and path of the file.