Let's go ahead and create
a DDL audit filter.
Let's create a filter
audit anytime a user
tries to create an index
on a specific database.
A great way to figure out what
your filter document is going
to look like is to just
turn auditing on, and then
run the type of query that
you want to audit for,
and then just look
at the logs, and see
what those kind of
audit logs look like.
Let's go and do this now.
I still have my
config.yaml file.
Let's go ahead and go in
here and remove the filter
that we currently have so
that we can audit all events.
Now, we can go ahead
and restart the server.
Now that our server's
up and running,
let's go to and connect
to it and create an index
on a specific database.
So we need to figure out
what specific database
we want to use.
We could use a test database,
but let's do something
a little bit more interesting.
Here, I'm going to switch
the myApplication database.
And I said that we wanted to
audit the creation of indexes.
So let's go ahead
and create an index.
Our index has been created.
Let's go ahead and
look at the audit
logs to see what kind of audit
documents were generated.
We have a bunch
of output in here.
Let's go through it.
Now, this is for
another collection,
so that's from our last test.
That means that all of these
are actually what we care about.
The first one here
is createDatabase.
That's because the myApplication
database didn't exist yet.
Makes sense.
Next, we have
createCollection, and that's
because the products
collection did not exist
on the myApplication database.
And then, here we go, here's
what we really care about,
createIndex.
And we have this
big param object.
Let's go out and copy
this and reformat it
so it's a little
bit easier to read.
I have copied it
into my clipboard.
Now, I'm going to open up
the text editor of my choice
and just paste it in here.
Let's go ahead and
reformat this so it's
a little bit easier to read.
Now our document's a
lot easier to read.
So what do we want
to look for here?
We want to look for
the creation of indexes
and, also, the specific
database, in this case,
myApplication.
Well, right off the bat,
we can see createIndex,
so atype is probably
a field we're
going to want to keep track of.
I don't see anything
important, nothing important.
Scroll down, nothing important.
Oh, here we go.
I see myApplication.
Probably going to want to
pay attention to this one.
Don't care about it, don't care
about it, don't care about it.
We could care about
this, but we're
getting the same information
for right here, so I
guess it doesn't really matter.
Let's go ahead and
remove everything
except for the things
that I mentioned
that we want to care about.
Now, we can see a document that
describes the kind of thing
that we're looking for.
But it isn't quite right.
This would only
audit the creation
of indexes on the
products collection
on the myApplication database.
We just want to audit
the creation of indexes
on the myApplication database.
Well, if you're familiar with
the MongoDB query language,
you know that it
supports regexes.
We can probably just
use a regex to define
namespaces that include only
the myApplication database.
Now, we have a
regex that will look
at the very beginning
of this field
and will look for
my-application, the database
that we care about.
And then it will
immediately look
for a period
signifying that we're
switching to now some
kind of other namespace,
whether it be a collection or
some other nested database.
We can simplify this
query a little bit
by embedding ns inside a
param with dot notation.
Fantastic, I think we have
our query ready way to go.
Let's try it out.
Let's go and update config.yaml
with our new filter.
We just say "filter" and
specify our filter document.
You'll notice I'm
using single quotes,
because I use double quotes
within the actual document
itself.
Go ahead and save, and
restart the server.
We can now connect to the
server and test our filter.
First let's try
creating and index
on a database that
isn't my-application.
I'm currently on
the test database.
Let's do a collection different
than products, just to be fun.
Now, since we're not talking
to the myApplication database,
we shouldn't see this
in the audit logs.
Index was successfully created.
And now let's switch the
my-application database.
And from here,
let's create indexes
on two different collections.
Both of them should be logged.
Success, great.
Let's do it on a
different collection.
And here's another index.
So we'd expect to see both
of these in the audit log.
I'll just tail the audit log.
And then, here, we can
see all of our new logs.
The first one is shutdown.
That was from when I
restarted the server.
Create index,
my-application on products.
Key was test.
Cool, that was there.
And create index, "bazz"
on my application.
Awesome.
I didn't see anything in
here about the test database.
I just saw stuff pertaining
to myApplication.
It looks like our filter
works successfully.