In this video, I'd like to talk
about vulnerability reports
with MongoDB.
At MongoDB, we take the security
of our database very seriously.
A part of our mission
to keep MongoDB secure
includes vulnerability
reporting from our users.
If you believe you
have discovered
a vulnerability in MongoDB,
or have experienced a security
incident related to MongoDB,
please report the issue
to aid in its resolution.
We've tried to make
reporting of vulnerability
as easy as possible.
There are two ways to
report a potential MongoDB
vulnerability.
The first way, which is the
recommended notification
method, is to submit a
ticket to the SECURITY
Project on our JIRA.
The second way is to
simply just send an email
to security@mongodb.com.
If you would like to
encrypt your message,
you can use our PGP public
key encryption, which
will be linked below the video.
All vulnerability
reports will be
responded to within 48 hours.
In order to best serve
MongoDB's security
team and our developers,
all vulnerability reports
should contain as much
information as possible.
And in particular,
these following items
are highly recommended.
Of course, you're going
to want to include
the name of the product
that you've identified
a potential issue with.
And then next, you can include
any common vulnerability
information.
If there's a CVSS score, which,
if you're not familiar with,
is a score from one to
10, 10 being the worst,
that rates the severity
of a vulnerability.
If the vulnerability is a
publicly- or commonly-known
type of vulnerability, then
please also include the CVE,
the Common Vulnerabilities
and Exposures identifier.
And of course, if you're open
to be contacted by MongoDB
security staff, please
include any necessary contact
information.
If needed, MongoDB
representatives
will serve a conference call to
exchange information regarding
the vulnerability.
I would like to point
out that MongoDB
takes all of our vulnerability
reports very seriously.
We validate all submitted
vulnerabilities and will
use JIRA to track all
communications regarding
a vulnerability, including
requests for clarification
or additional information.
Finally, we ask that if you
find a potential security
vulnerability, that
you do not publicly
disclose any information
regarding the vulnerability
or exploit the issue.
This will give us
the opportunity
to analyze the vulnerability,
to respond to the notification,
and to notify key users,
customers, and partners.
The amount of time required
to validate a reported
vulnerability depends
on the complexity
and the severity of the issue.
We take all vulnerabilities
very seriously.
And we will always
ensure that there
is a clear and open
channel of communication
with the reporter.
After validating
an issue, MongoDB
will coordinate a public
disclosure of the issue
with the reporter in
a mutually-agreed time
frame and format.
If required or requested, the
reporter of a vulnerability
will receive credit in the
published security bulletin.