Now that we've looked at
how to audit DDL operations,
let's take a moment and look
at how to audit DML operations.
The other common
statement category in SQL
is DML, or Data
Manipulation Language.
As the name implies, DML
refers to the manipulation
of data within your database.
With MongoDB, we generally
refer to DML operations
as CRUD-- the ability to
create, read, update, and delete
our data.
With regards to auditing
DML, virtually all
of the operations that we
would consider DML operations
fall underneath the
authCheck action type.
This is because CRUD operations
are passed as parameters
to the authCheck event.
Every time that you try to
create, read, update or destroy
data within your
database, authCheck
is going to be the action
type that's actually firing
from an auditing perspective.