Do you still have
alter table nightmares?
Memories of modifying the schema
of your relational database?
Performing complex
tasks under pressure,
so you could limit the amount
of downtime for your users?
If so, welcome to
your new world.
If you did not have
any nightmares or never
updated relational
databases, welcome too
to this bright world.
You will love the pattern we
will cover in this lesson.
It makes modifying the schema
used by your application
a much smoother process.
The question when
user database is not,
if you will update your schema,
but when would you update it?
Nearly all applications
in their lifetime
will require updates to
their database schema.
Unfortunately, those updates
take time and require downtime
for relational databases.
If anything goes wrong when
you reopen the service,
it may be difficult
to revert back to what
you had prior to the migration.
The schema versioning pattern is
based on the [INAUDIBLE] aspect
of documents in MongoDB.
Because documents can
have different shapes.
By that, I refer to
having different fields
or different types
for a given field.
We construct our applications
to deal with those variants.
Let's say we have Bob White
as a person in our people
collection.
Bob was born a
while ago, and can
be reached at home or at work
through these phone numbers.
Then we have Junior,
Bob White's son.
Bob is from a generation
that got used to cell phones.
And we need to add this
information to his profile,
and have our
application deal with
this additional information.
I suspect making this
change was not too painful.
It would even be pretty smooth
with a relational database,
as adding a column
is not a big deal.
Now, as the next
generation of White--
Bob III-- does not
have a phone at home.
However, has account with
Skype, Google Hangouts,
Viber, and who knows
what next week.
Well, this is becoming difficult
to handle in the application.
But because the developers
took the wonderful class
Entry 20 on Data
Modeling, they realized
that the attribute pattern
would be a good fit here.
So instead of
growing the documents
with unpredictable
contact methods,
the attribute
pattern is applied.
The application could easily
handle the differences
in the Bob White documents.
It just has to know
the different shapes
with different [INAUDIBLE].
Here, instead of dealing
with an additional field,
you get to see an array
of contacts method
when you process it accordingly.
To help the application
identify the shape,
we will have a version
field and set it
to 2, the non-presence
of this field
being the implicit version 1.
Note that this field is
present in each document.
This is in contrast to
a relational database,
where you only have one
global number to track
the version of the schema.
Here we have each
document telling us
which version of the
schema to adhere to.
The first thing
you will need to do
is to change the
application so it
can read all the different
version of the documents.
You can use separate
handlers or function
to handle the
different versions.
The field schema
version makes it
easy to decide where
to send the document.
Alternatively,
reshape the document
when you see an old version,
and then process it.
Testing that functionality
is relatively easy.
As you start adding
documents with the upcoming
shape to your test
environment, and then
observe how the application
deals with those changes.
Update your application
server so they
use the modified application.
Once the migration of all
documents is completed,
it's up to you to
decide to remove or not
the obsolete code.
New documents get written in
the latest schema version.
For existing documents, you
can piggyback on the fact
that you're going to make an
update to change the shape
and write it in the new schema.
As a matter of fact,
I remember a customer
that had billions of documents,
a lot being inactive.
And that was their only
migration strategy.
That means that the old obsolete
documents remained unchanged,
because they did not
want to pay the price
to update them with a job
running for a few weeks.
Alternatively to this
selective update strategy,
the most common one is
to have a background
task to do the updates.
You can have both
processes doing
the migration of documents,
and that will still be fine.
The thing to understand
is that while you're
updating your application
server, assuming
you have more than one, you
won't [INAUDIBLE] any downtime.
Once done, you can
take the time you
need to update the documents
by running an updater.
And that can be done
in a few passes.
While the documents
are getting updated,
your application servers can
handle both schema version work
well with all documents,
old and new shapes.
At the end, if and once
all documents are updated,
you can remove the code
to handle the old version
in your application.
Some users keep it
there for protection
or for keeping the ability
to reimport documents
in the old shape.
Anyway, there's a lot
of possible variations
of migration.
Just ensure you get a plan.
Time to formalize our
schema versioning pattern.
The problem in schema
versioning pattern addresses
is avoiding downtime when
using a schema update.
If you have a small system with
the ability to bring it down
for an acceptable
period of time,
you may just want to do
that and do your updates
the old fashioned way.
Updating all documents can
take a long time-- hours, day,
or even weeks when
dealing with big data.
And there is the situation
where you have so many legacy
documents, or any other
reason for which you don't
want to update everything.
As illustrated in
our previous screens,
the solution is to use a
field present in each document
to keep the version number.
Schema version is suggested,
but not mandatory.
As a matter of fact,
the field can also
be omitted, and have
the application detect
the shape or the version
based on the list of fields
present or missing.
However, I prefer
explicitly using a field
to identify the version.
Secondly, the
application should be
able to handle the different
shapes of the documents.
And finally, layout the strategy
to migrate your documents.
You are in charge.
You have all the time you need
to do the things correctly.
As I said earlier,
most application--
especially the successful ones
that live for a long time--
will require schema changes.
Unless you can afford
downtime, this pattern
is likely going to be
very useful to you.
On the benefits side,
they are pretty evident.
You can avoid downtime.
You feel in control
of the migration
the whole time, done
when you want to do it.
On the trade-off
side, if you have
an index in the field
that's not located
at the same level
in the document,
you may need to index while
you're doing the migration.
And finally, unlike the fiscal
debt, the technical debt,
and environmental
debt we are usually
leaving to the next
generation, at least
here we can build system
that should be easier
to maintain and migrate
by your future colleagues.
In summary, the schema
versioning pattern
is a great pattern if you
want to avoid downtime
while performing schema
upgrade and want to stay
in control of those upgrades.