Some computations are
very expensive to do.
If you store your information
as base units in your database,
you may find yourself redoing
the same computations,
manipulations, or
transformations over and over.
In big data systems, these
kinds of repeated computations
can lead to very
poor performance.
What kind of transformations
are usually applied to data?
The list is long.
However, they usually fall into
one of those three categories--
mathematical operations,
fan out operations,
and roll-up operations.
We will group those under
a new pattern, which we
will call the computed pattern.
The mathematical operations
are easy to identify.
These are the ones where we
compute a sum or an average,
find a median, et cetera.
These are often associated with
calling a built-in function
in the server.
Why does it matter that we
want to apply a pattern here?
Let's say we have a write
operation that comes in.
This piece of data is added as a
document to a given collection.
Another part of the application
reads this collection and does,
let's say, a sum on the numbers.
If we are doing 1,000 times
more reads than writes,
the sum operation we
do with those reads
is identical and very often
does the exact same calculation
for each of those
read operations.
We can save ourselves from
all those identical operations
by calculating the results when
we get a new piece of data.
Once we have a
new piece of data,
we read the other
element for the sum
and store the result in another
collection with documents
more appropriate to keep
the sum for that element.
This results in much fewer
computation in the system,
and we also reduce the
amount of data being read.
See here, each sum reads
all those documents.
Since we don't have to do the
computation that at read time,
we also save on those
read operations, too.
In this example, that will
be 1,000 fewer computation
and 1,000 fewer reads.
A good example of this will be
keeping track of ticket sales
and then reporting
the sale numbers--
let's say for a specific movie--
on a movie website.
There are likely fewer
screening happening
per hour, which will
be all right, than page
views for the given movie where
we want to display the sums.
So instead of summing
those screenings document
to display the total
viewer and sales every time
access the movie,
we are better off
keeping the information
in the document
and updating it every time we
get a new screening document.
We don't have to
keep the screenings
once the calculation is done.
However, the idea was to
regenerate the sums if needed,
or give us the ability
to do more analytics.
Fan out operations.
First, what does fan out means?
It means to do many tasks to
represent one logical task.
There are two basic schemes.
Either you fan out on
reads, which means in order
to return the appropriate
data, the query must fetch data
from different locations,
or you found out
on writes, which means
every logical write
operation translate into several
writes to different documents.
In doing so, the read does
not have to fan out anymore,
as the data is
pre-organized at write time.
If you don't pay
attention to this pattern,
you are likely doing
fan out on reads.
Why would you use
fan out on writes?
If the system has plenty of time
when the information arrives
compared to the acceptable
latency of returning data
on read operation,
then preparing
the data at write time
makes a lot of sense.
Note that if you are
doing more writes
then reads so the system
becomes bound by writes,
this may not be a
good pattern to apply.
A good example for this pattern
will be a social networking
system for sharing photos.
The system may copy the new
photo on each follower's home
page as it gets the new photo.
This way, when a user
load its own page,
the system does not have to
spend resources assembling
all the information from all
the people this user follows.
Everything needed for
the user's home page
would be available via
single document, which
lead to a much better
experience with the site.
Roll-up operations.
We use this terminology
in a position
to drill-down operation.
In the roll-up operation,
we merge data together.
For example, grouping categories
together in a parent category
will be a roll-up.
Grouping time-based data from
small intervals to large ones
will be another good
example of a roll-up.
This type of roll-up
is often seen
in reporting for hourly, daily,
monthly, or yearly summaries.
Any operation that wants
to see data at a high level
is basically looking
at rolling up data.
Mathematical computations
are roll-ups.
However, roll-ups
are more generic.
You can often think
of roll-up data
as running a group operation.
So similarly to
mathematical computation,
doing those roll-ups
at right time
may make more sense
than having our read
operation pay the costs of
processing the transformations.
Let's look at a
concrete example.
An inventory has
different wine types.
The inventory change once in a
while, however, not frequently.
What is more frequent is
looking at the wine organized
by various categories.
For example, I may
want to see the count
of wine types per country
of origin or per type
so I can buy what is
missing in my inventory
to cover all my customer needs.
If I'm looking more often at
the information on the right,
the non-aggregated data
than the changes that
are happening on my
collection on the left,
it makes more sense
to generate this data
and cache it in the
appropriate documents.
When should you apply
the computed pattern?
If you see you are
using a lot of CPU,
this may be a sign
that you're doing
much more than transferring
data from and to the disk.
Keep in mind that some
tasks like compressing
and decompressing data
between the disk and the cache
requires a lot of CPU, too.
Secondly, if you have
long read operation
that depends on complex
aggregation queries,
you might want to
make them run faster.
Time to formalize
a computed pattern.
The problem the computer
pattern addresses
is avoiding doing the same
computation over and over,
especially if they're expensive.
The solution is to
perform the computation
and store the result in
the appropriate document
and collection.
If you need to redo
the computation
or want to be able
to redo them, just
keep the source of
your computations,
meaning keep the smaller
documents or piece
of information.
Common use cases where you
may want to use the pattern
are the Internet of Things,
event sourcing, time series
data, and any scenario where you
do repeated similar aggregation
queries.
The benefits you get
from the computed pattern
are faster read and less
utilization of resources,
mostly CPU and disk.
However, it may be
difficult to diagnose
that you may benefit from such
patterns on a large existing
cluster.
It is easy to abuse
the computed pattern.
Use it when you need it, as
the required computation may
add complexity to
the application code.
So here it is.
This is our computed pattern.
In summary, the computed
pattern is a useful pattern
if you want to avoid performing
similar operations many times.