In this lesson,
we will summarize
some additional
patterns that may also
be beneficial in your design.
The following patterns
are less often
applied in designs than the
one we have covered so far.
However, it is a beneficial
to be aware of them
so that you can recognize them
when you may need to use them.
The approximation
pattern is used
to reduce the number of
resources needed to perform
some write operations.
This pattern uses an
approximation function
to produce a
result. For example,
if an application wants
to track page views,
it could write to the database
every time a page is viewed,
but this could quickly
overload your database
with hundreds of thousands
of extra writes per day.
In this case, instead,
an approximation function
can be used to increment the
counter only once in a while,
instead of doing a write for
each individual page view
add from the server.
The approximation
pattern is used
whenever there is a significant
tolerance to data imprecision,
or when an operation
is expensive to compute
with very little value
added by precision.
Its implementation is
to do fewer writes,
but with a higher payload.
The application can
do the operation
every 10 operations,
100 operations,
or whatever factor makes sense.
Typical use cases for
the approximation pattern
are web page counters, any
counters with tolerance
to imprecision,
metric statistics.
The typical benefits
of this pattern
are a reduction in
the number of writes,
less write contention while
updating the same documents,
statistically
valid numbers, even
if not exact per unit of time.
The implementation
of this pattern
must reside in the
client side application.
This pattern is not
specific to MongoDB.
It can be used with
any other databases.
However, the need for
this sort of optimization
surfaces more often with
big data applications.
Our next pattern is used to
handle potential outliers
in your data.
An outlier is something
that stands out
from the rest of the crowd.
In the world of big
data, standing out
means you may have a
characteristic that
is few orders of magnitude
higher than the norm.
For example, a famous singer
may have 100 million followers
on the social media app,
while the majority of users
have less than 1,000 followers.
The danger with outliers is
that they could drive developers
to implement a solution that
is suboptimal for 99.99%
percent of use cases just
to accommodate the outlier.
Implementing a
solution like this
will honestly harm the
majority of queries.
Do not be afraid of implementing
a design that works well
for the vast
majority of use cases
and then identifies these
outliers as exceptions.
The application can
then be instructed
to handle just these
outliers differently.
Here's an example
of implementation
where a document
representing a movie
has a field to store a list
of extras, up to 1,000.
This will work for
almost every movie.
If a movie happens to have
more than 1,000 extras,
it refers to additional
documents that
contain the rest of the extras.
Typical use cases for
the outlier pattern
are social networks
and other applications
related to popularity, apps
containing famous people
or objects.
The main benefit of this pattern
is that the application remains
optimized for most use cases.
The drawback is that
the application must
handle the outliers separately.
And it makes it harder
to write queries
that can process
the whole data set
in the one uniform operation.
As with other
patterns, this one also
has a handle on the client
side, meaning that it
can be used with any database.
However, it also surfaces more
often in modern and big data
applications.
To recap this lesson, we
listed some additional patterns
that may be seen
less frequently,
but they are still
worth knowing.
The first is the
approximation pattern,
which allows us to reduce
the number of resources used
by an operation that
may not be crucial
and can be approximated.
The outlier pattern
allows your apps
to optimize for the
most frequent use
cases, while still successfully
handling important outliers.