When we want to
organize objects,
we can either group
them by what they
have in common or by
their differences.
This will result in either
keeping the documents
in the same collection or
in different collections.
For example, if we have
a product from Canada,
a product from Mexico,
a customer from Canada,
and a customer from
Mexico, it is likely
that we will group the
two customers together
and the two food items together.
We usually group
objects based on
queries we want to
perform on the system.
A major restriction with
most other base systems
is that it is difficult
to query objects
across different
tables or a collection.
If there is one collection
for the customers
and the one collection
for the products
it becomes more difficult to
find all things Canadians,
for example.
If the main query
of this system is
that they're mining objects
and people by country,
then we will
probably put together
everything in one collection.
So we should group things
together because we
want to query them together.
When grouping
objects together that
may have substantial
differences, for example,
using a vehicle collection to
store cars, trucks, and boats,
and other types of
vehicle would lead
us to query the vehicle
for registration,
ownership, vehicle taxes.
A specific vehicle type
may have specific aspects
that are not shared with
the other types of vehicles.
A car typically has four
wheels, which we can omit.
Other trucks have a variable
number of wheels and axles.
While the boat usually has none.
These differences make a
car, or truck, and a boat
polymorphic entities
for a vehicle object.
The usual implementation that
represents polymorphic objects
as a field that describes
the name of this shape
for a given document
or sub-document.
In our current
example, a vehicle type
identifies the document type
and lets the application and all
the expected field
for a particular type
or shape of the document.
The document of
type car will imply
that the vehicle has four
wheels, while the truck should
have a field to identify
the number of wheels
in the field to identify
the number of axles.
Due to the nature of
the document model,
there is usually
polymorphous in our database.
We refer to the polymorphic
pattern in our schema designs
when we can clearly name
the different entities that
are represented in
the same collection.
Another common situation when
this pattern can be applied
is when dealing with a
product catalog application.
Some products may have
a color, like a shirt,
for example, while describing
a book by this color
rarely makes sense.
In this situation, we're
also using polymorphism.
However, in a more casual
way, as there are tons
of different product types.
In this case, it's up
to you to spell out
that they are using
the polymorphic pattern
in your schema design.
So far, we discussed a
polymorphic document type
in the context of a
shape of a document.
However, we can also
apply this model
to subentities, such
as sub-documents.
For example, if we take
a person, let's say,
Norberto, Norberto is Portuguese
and lives in New York.
So he has an address in the USA.
It is a typical urban
address in the US,
with a building number, street
name, city name, and zip code.
Norberto has also an
address in Portugal.
This structure is similar
to the address in the USA.
However, a well-known
building in Portugal
may not have a building number.
Portugal does not use zip code.
However, they have a
critical post style, which
translate to a postal code.
The critical post
style is 7 digits long.
So if we want to have a
valid data on the postal code
or a zip code, they will
have to be a little bit
different, as they have
to handle 7 and 5 digits,
respectively.
Because our addresses
are the documents
that we want to apply the
polymorphic pattern to,
each of these documents need
a field to specify its shape.
We could use an additional
field, however, in this case,
the country name should do it.
Based on the country
for a given address,
we can determine the shape
of that sub-document.
The polymorphic
pattern is commonly
used when implementing
a single view solution.
A single view solution
allow for the aggregation
of data from different sources
into one central location.
It is common that
the different sources
exist because systems tend
to be designed to deal
with one single problem.
An integrated view is key to
gaining meaningful insight
across all this
data, but it's often
difficult to merge these
data sets together.
A typical tabular or
relational database approach
to solving this problem tends
to be very complex, resource
intensive, and incomplete.
We've seen several organizations
over the years failing
to create a relational schema
that could accommodate data
from different sources,
different relational database
schema, or different data sets.
The complexity of this problem
becomes greatly reduced
when users decide to
use MongoDB to create
this unified view of the data.
Imagine an insurance
company that
has acquired many
other insurance
companies over the years.
Each acquired organization
represents their insurance
policies in a different way,
using a different schema
in their tabular or
relational database.
When a customer calls
the insurance company,
they need to specify which
system the specific insurance
policy is stored in and
access the given system.
It is possible
that some customers
had policy with several of
these insurance companies, which
means that they would
have multiple policies
across the different systems.
For example, some home
policy may be in System A,
while his car policy may
be in System B. Imagine
the mess it creates
and the impact it has
on the customer, who
is not able to receive
a single unified policy.
By creating a single view that
merges all sources of data
into one MongoDB
database, the organization
is able to see all the
policies and information
about the given customer
on their one single system.
In this example, we are bringing
data from different sources
into one common collection.
First, we select
the field that we
want to use to identify
the customer ID.
Let's say we want to use
the Social Security number.
Second, maybe some
fields are easy to merge.
Let's say that the first and
the last name of the person
can be easily identified
in the different sources,
and they carry the same values.
That will result in keeping
only this shape for this field.
Pick the field name you
want, however, the values
are the same.
Finally, some fields may be more
messy and difficult to merge.
For example, let's
say that addresses
have proven to be difficult to
clean and represent uniquely.
For that, we can keep a
list of variants found
in the different databases.
We can confirm the right
value with the customer later
or write a separate intelligent
process a few months down
the road to unify these
three sub-documents.
This approach help us be
operational very quickly,
and then we can improve
the information we extract
in an incremental fashion.
Before we wrap up this
lesson, let's quickly
mention that this schema
versioning pattern is
using the polymorphic pattern.
Its implementation
can be described
as a version field that dictates
the shape of the document.
And let's organize
what we've been
describing and illustrating.
The problem that the
polymorphic pattern addresses
is allowing us to
keep documents that
have more common things
in the same collection.
The solution is to
have a field that
keep tracks of the shape of
the document or sub-document.
Then have the application
use different code paths
to handle the differences in
the documents using that field
value.
If the differences
are substantial,
we often have subclasses
allowing the different concerns
in the base class to
handle the similarities.
This is classic
object-oriented programming.
The most common use
cases for this pattern
are single view implementations,
product catalogs, and content
management applications.
This is a pattern that is
relatively easy to implement.
It reflects very well one
of the main advantages
that the flexible
document model offers us.
So this is the overview
for polymorphic pattern.
In summary, the polymorphic
pattern is a basic pattern.
A lot of other
patterns are, in fact,
a specialization
of this pattern.
We can also use the polymorphic
pattern in a more generic way
to store different
shapes of documents
within the same collection.