In the early days
of programming,
you would feed the giant
computers with punch cards,
like this one on the left.
Each instruction would
store on a separate card.
And yes, it was
preferable to not
draw the ordered stack of
cards, especially if you did not
use some kind of
label to reorder them.
Just a little later,
the advent of terminals
permitted the developers to
put all these instruction
in a file, like the one
we have on the right.
This was better.
However, as programs got
bigger, the files got larger,
and it was not a viable
solution anymore.
The solution at that
time was to group
a set of instructions together.
Call it files, classes,
libraries-- this
is still the system
in use today.
The point I want to make
is that sometimes you need
a middle-of-the-road solution,
because both extreme are not
working well and far
from being optimal.
The punch card is too
granular, while the single file
solution is too broad and does
not provide enough granularity.
Translating that to MongoDB
and the document model,
let's look at an
example of Internet
of things devices, which
I will refer as IoT
for the rest of the lesson.
Let's say we have 10
million temperature sensors,
and each sensor is sending us
a piece of data every minute,
the temperature it's measuring.
This is 36 billion pieces
of information per hour.
Trying to store each
piece in a document
may not work as we get too
many documents to manage.
On the other end, if we keep
one document per device,
each document is likely
to reach the maximum size
of 16 megabytes after a while.
Even if it does not
reach that size,
it may still be
unmanageable and not
very efficient to handle
these large documents.
So what should we do?
Here, we'll make
some suggestions.
However, if you recall
their methodology,
the suggestions make
more sense if we
know the workload of the
problem and the main queries
of our system.
One suggestion is to have one
document per device, per day.
Each document would
only carry information
for a single device
on a single day.
Then the next day, we will
create a new document.
I decided to create
one array per hour.
This translates in
an easy to understand
document for a human.
However, it makes it a
little bit more complicated
for a program.
If the application
wants to average
a temperature for
a given period,
it needs to retrieve
the array or the section
of the array for each
hour of that period
and do the calculation.
If this is a common
query, then maybe
a single array for the
whole day makes more sense.
Another option is to have one
document per device, per hour.
Here, our time stamps includes
the date and the hour.
We have one document for 1:00
PM and one document for 2:00 PM.
There are more documents, 24
times more than this example.
However, the
documents are smaller.
Note that I'm also using
a different way to store
the temperature values.
Here, instead of
using a single array,
we use a document where
the keys are the minutes.
In the first set of documents,
I must fill the empty positions.
For example, if I don't get
the data for the fifth minute,
I must put something-- zero
or null, but something.
As for these documents, I simply
insert the values I receive.
In the event I did
not get a piece
of data for the fifth
minute, the field temp
dot five will not exist.
Again, there are a ton of
possible configurations.
So unless you know
the workload, it
is difficult to tell
which one is the best.
This concept of
grouping information
together is called bucketing.
And as you guessed,
the bucket pattern
is often used in
the IoT scenarios.
Here's another example.
We will build a
collaboration platform.
The platform will
have chat windows
that we'll call channels.
One solution is to keep
one document per message.
However, this may become messy
and may require more processing
to organize the
messages together.
An alternative is to keep
all the messages for a given
chat in a single document.
That may work, but over
time, each document
may become bigger
than what we want,
as we care more for a recent
message than the old one.
Again, the middle
solution will be
to arrange the messages
in the bucket--
All messages for a
channel for a given day.
One nice thing
about this design is
that it's very easy to delete
documents older than x days,
or then archive them.
I can use zone charting
and move my old messages
to a chart that resides
on cheaper hardware.
One final note on this example.
When you think
about bucketing, you
refer to two
independent variables.
One will be the big
container, the main document,
here identified by
your underscore ID.
And the other part of the
one-to-many relationship
will be your bucket.
This is where you will
put N piece of data
from the one many
relationship in the bucket.
That brings us to the last
use case I want to describe.
The NoSQL database
family is composed
of document databases
like MongoDB,
but also for the members like
key value databases, graph
databases, and
column-based databases.
What if our solution requires a
document databases for most use
scenario?
But one use case
scenario is better
served by a
column-based database.
A column-based database
stores information per column
instead of per row or document.
So when you want to process
only one column across all
the documents, like it is
frequently done in analytics,
it's very efficient,
as it brings in memory
only the data it needs.
As you know, MongoDB brings
in memory full documents.
If we have a use case
that will benefit
a lot from a
column-based approach,
we could install a separate
database next to MongoDB
to handle this use case.
However, in order to
make our deployment model
as streamlined as possible,
adding different technology for
this alone will come with
an unnecessary technical
complexity.
Let's use MongoDB to model data
that is column-based oriented.
Going back to our earlier
example of IoT device,
let's assume these
device are [INAUDIBLE]
station that returns
a bunch of information
like temperature,
pressure, and lightning.
If we were to store all
the info for a given
device in each document, we
could query across variables.
However, this ability
is not needed.
But what is really needed is
to process all data regarding
one field at the time, meaning
one column, for example,
the intensity of light.
We may want to break up the
measurement in many documents
so processing one type
of data does not require
bringing everything in memory.
When processing light, we bring
these documents in memory.
When processing pressure,
we bring these documents
in memory.
Note that both sides are
using the bucket pattern.
It is just that the
one on the right
has a structure more
similar to columns.
Also, know that
information for the device,
like the location and anything
else about the device,
has been left out of the
documents on the right side
and put somewhere else.
If you need to search
or aggregate results
on these fields, you should
keep them in the documents.
Again, this is
not going to be as
optimal as a column-based
database system.
However, it's a good
work-around if you
don't want to install
two database systems.
Let's look at some
restriction or gotchas
when using the bucket pattern.
If you need to frequently
access elements in the buckets
to do updates,
deletions, or want
to insert in specific
locations, this may not
be the best pattern to use.
If you need to get the
data sorted in any way,
it is preferable
to have it sorted
in the buckets themselves.
In this example, all the
temperature in the buckets
were already sorted
by date and time.
Ad hoc queries may
be difficult to do,
as you need to understand
the underlying structure.
So this pattern works better
when the storage representation
is hidden [INAUDIBLE]
by the application.
Time to formalize
our bucket pattern.
The problems the bucket
pattern address are helping us
size our documents to satisfy
the combination of read
and write operations
of our workload.
This helps embed a
one-to-many relationship,
where the many side is too
big or grows beyond bounds.
The solution is to find
the optimal amount of info,
then store it in arrays
or arrays of arrays
in our main objects.
The one-to-many relationship
is transformed so the one
side becomes N documents.
What are the common use cases?
Obviously IoT systems,
then data warehouse
is a good candidate, as you
can analyze larger chunks
of time-based data at once.
In short, any one object
that has ton of information
associated to it.
The right size of
your documents will
translate into the right
number of disk accesses
and the right amount of data
transfer by these accesses.
It makes the data
more manageable.
For example, it is easy to
delete section of your data
by simply deleting the documents
corresponding to that period.
On the trade-offs,
ensure you know
all you want to query the data.
If every query translate to
an aggregation query, that
will first [INAUDIBLE] the
data, the schema you choose
may not be the right one.
Also, it may not be
friendly to all BI Tools,
as your users need to understand
the schema to do the queries.
What may have been a
simple MongoDB or SQL
query may become much
more difficult to express.
So this is our bucket pattern.
In summary, the bucket
pattern is a great pattern
if you want a middle
ground solution
between fully embedding
and fully linking data.
However, this is
an advanced pattern
that should be used
only when you have
a good grasp of your workload.