Hi there.
In this lesson, we
are going to learn
about how to model hierarchical
information using tree patterns
and examine common
situations where
tree patterns can be used.
There are several
types of use cases that
find hierarchies
between objects or nodes
and the relationship
between them,
use cases like company
organization charts,
subject areas structures in
a given domain like books
in a bookstore, or even
a more typical example,
the categories of products for
a given e-commerce site or shop.
All of these examples are
hierarchical in nature
where there is a direct
relationship between the parent
nodes and the child nodes.
Each hierarchical
node relationship
comes associated with
common operations that
will be useful to us
in many situations
regardless of the actual
content of the database, things
like who are the
ancestors of node X
or reports to Y. Find all
nodes that are under Z,
or change all categories
of N to under P.
These are common operations
applicable to any information
that is hierarchical in nature.
Documents, in themselves,
are hierarchical structures.
They contain
multidimensional information
within a given node, such as the
relationships between a product
and the stores that
the product's sold at
or the reviews of
the same product.
However, when representing
the dependency and hierarchy
between nodes of
the same entity,
like categories, it is
better to use tree patterns.
The document model
offers a few patterns
for modeling tree structures.
We have the parent
references, child references,
arrays of ancestors,
and materialized baths.
In the case of
parent preferences,
the document holds a
reference to the parent node
in the tree hierarchy.
We can collect all ancestors by
running an aggregation pipeline
with a graph lookup
stage to retrieve
all subsequent parents of the
immediate parents traversing
the full tree.
To find all reports
of a given parent,
we can run a find command
matching for the parent
and then retrieving
all children nodes.
In order to change
all nodes that
report, or are children of
one parent, in other words,
change all categories under N
to [INAUDIBLE] children of P,
we can use an update operation.
For parent references,
we can perform operations
like who reports to Y and
change all categories under N to
under P using very
little code and changing
only one single document.
To find all nodes
that are under Z,
that is also pretty
straightforward.
However, we have to iterate
over a set of documents.
We can also respond
to questions,
Who are the ancestors of node X,
by resorting to a lookup, which
is essentially as joined, which
may not be ideal to accomplish
this operation.
This is where the child
reference model comes in.
In the child reference
model, the parent node
contains a single array of all
the immediate node children.
In this example, the office
node has three children-- books,
electronics, and stickers.
So to perform the operation
finding all nodes that
are under Z, in this
case, under office
becomes a less
computational demanding
operation for the database.
A single request retrieves
all of that information.
However, other
questions like, who
are the ancestors of node X,
become a bit more complicated.
Finding all nodes
that report to Y
or even changing all
categories under N to under P
are not ideal for this pattern.
Another model to represent
the hierarchy of a tree
is the array of ancestors model.
This model uses an
ordered array to store
a list of all of a node's
ancestors on that node.
This model is very efficient
for finding what are
the ancestors of a given node.
They are all stored
in the ancestor array.
We can also find out which
is the immediate reporting
or parent node
using array position
operators if we know the
level that the node occupies
in the tree.
The next operation, which is
still possible, a bit more
tricky to do, is to change
all categories under N
to under P, since this
operation requires a few more
trips to the database to apply
all the necessary changes.
A variation of the
array ancestors
is the materialized
paths pattern.
In this approach, we
use a string value
to describe the node's ancestors
with some value separator.
In this example, we have a
string ancestors with a value
.Swag.Office.
That describes the direct branch
of the books node in the tree.
Using the materialized
path's approach
comes with a great benefit.
We can use a single
regular expression
over a single index field
value for all queries prepended
on the root tree
node, which means
that we can use a
simple index in order
to find a particular path of
a branch in our hierarchy.
In this approach, we can
access our ancestor's fields
to quickly answer the question,
who are the ancestors of X?
For the question,
who reports to Y,
this is a simple query but
potentially not very efficient,
even relaying on a single field.
The index will not
be used if we do not
ask for the full branch
matching path from root.
Finding all nodes
that are under Z
suffers from the same
problem as reports to Y.
And finally, moving nodes around
might be quite challenging
depending on the node
that we are moving
and the reports that subsequent
node in the hierarchy chain.
For any given
application that relies
on hierarchical
information, there
is nothing stopping
us from using
any combination of different
patterns in our model.
As an example, here is
the categories collection
which represent the
categories of products
in our e-commerce application.
In this example, we are using
both the array of ancestors
and the parent reference model.
And why did we decide to use
this combination of patterns?
We want to be able to do a
couple specific operations very
quickly and without lots
of unnecessary logic.
These operations
include navigating
to the immediate
parent node and finding
all categories of products
that descend from a given node.
Tree parents are used to model
hierarchical data structures.
There is a good variety
of tree patterns
that we can apply as a solution
for those same hierarchical
data structures modeling.
These are generally used in
org charts, product categories,
and others.
The different patterns
offer different benefits.
Child references are ideal
to navigate the descending
the hierarchical of nodes of
our tree, where on each node,
we can find the immediate
child references.
Parent reference is
ideal to navigate upwards
in the tree in institutions
where the tree is constantly
being updated or moved.
Array of ancestors
is ideal to get
a full view of a branch
of the tree structure
up to the node itself,
where materialized
path is an alternative to use a
single field index on a string
value that enables the
user to regular expressions
to find documents in
a branch of the tree.
Tree patterns are
an effective way
of representing these use cases.
But let's recap.
Documents are very good data
structures to represent nodes
in a tree.
The fact that documents can hold
parts or branches of the tree
within themselves
allows us to represent
in a very efficient
way models that do not
rely on suboptimal
drawings to retrieve
the hierarchical information
we require for each node.
There are several different
ways to represent nodes
of a tree using documents,
and you can even
use a combination of different
patterns in your model.
The choice of which
patterns you use
should be based on which are
the most common operations
that your application
will be performing
and optimized for those
choosing the best pattern that
allows you to do the
most efficient queries
on that particular application.