What a week.
Don't worry if it looks
like a lot of information.
You can always go back
to a specific pattern
later, if you forgot
about it and suspect
it may be a good match for
the schema you're working on.
Let's have a quick
overview of the affinity
[? for ?] patterns with
the common use cases.
I want to stress the point
that the patterns we identified
under a given use case
are not necessarily
all applicable to your problem.
Neither the ones not
selected should be discarded.
The tables simply highlights the
most likely and most important
ones that may appear
for a given use case.
For example, while
working on the Internet
of Things projects,
the project often
uses the bucket patterning.
However, even if
not highlighted,
it may benefit from
the tree pattern,
If the devices organize in
a hierarchy of some sort.
This matrix is
there to guide you
toward the most
likely patterns first.
A special note
about the computed
and the schema versioning
patterns-- the computed pattern
is generic and applicable
to most use cases.
As for the schema
versioning one,
it is applicable
to all use cases.
So ensure you get
a good grasp of it.
Then you'll be ready
to use it, when needed.
In summary, in this chapter,
we learned a few schema design
patterns.
Those act as powerful
transformation,
when designing schema.
If you most likely care
about ease of development
and there's not any difficult
performance requirements
to meet, you may not need
many of those patterns.
The pattern and also provide a
common language for the team.
And finally, using
the patterns lets
you have a more
predictable methodology.