In this lesson,
we're going to cover
connection pooling in MongoDB.
So connection pooling is
all about reusing database
connections.
The connection
pool itself is just
the cache of
database connections
maintains that
they can be reused
when future requests to
the database are required.
When issuing several different
requests of the database,
we could take the lazy
approach and just create
a new connection whenever
we needed to make a request.
And then when the
request is done,
we just destroy the connection.
The issue with this approach
is that establishing a database
connection requires
time and computing
resources to complete the
handshake with the server
and everything else.
We're essentially
paying the costs
of waiting for this
connection to be
established for every request.
Connection pooling helps
reduce the overhead
of creating database connections
by creating a whole bunch
right off the bat.
The next requests come
in different connections
in the pool get allocated
to fulfill these requests.
By default, the driver will
create a connection pool
of 100 connections to share.
The default of
100 connections is
adequate for most applications.
Additionally, if we didn't
use a connection pool
and suddenly got a
whole lot of requests,
we might easily reach the limit
that our hardware and software
could handle, leading
to a lot of errors
and unhappy developers.
So just to recap,
connection pools
allow connections to be
recycled for new requests
to the database.
To the developer, this will
make database operations
look faster because the cost
to create a new connection
has already been paid.
In the Mongo drivers,
the default connection
pools 100 connections
large, which
should be fine for most
average applications.