In this lesson, we're
going to discuss
ways in which you can
make your application more
robust with respect to how it
communicates with the database.
So you've learned about
connection pooling all ready,
but it's very important
so we're going
to briefly cover it again.
Creating a new Mongo client for
every request of the database
might service your
application in the short term,
but it will eventually result
in the application consuming
and depleting available
resources that become
more and more scarce over time.
Connection pooling
reduces the total overhead
associated with creating these
new connections by allowing
the application to
recycle and reuse database
connections for new requests.
The M220 API you've
been given correctly
reuses the same class or object
for all client communication,
if you'd like to look at an
example of how we did it.
Another way to make a more
robust database client
is with the write
timeout or wtimeout.
No matter how well
we engineer a system,
we should always expect
application external resources
like queues, networks,
and databases
to take more time than expected.
For an application or
consumer critical operations,
a developer may choose
to write with w majority
to ensure that
acknowledged rights are
written to a majority
of nodes in the set.
But if there's a problem on
one of the secondary nodes,
we might not get an
acknowledgment back
from the server for a while.
If more writes than reads
are coming into the system,
and operations aren't
being acknowledged,
this will eventually
lead to system gridlock.
But we can avoid this
gridlock by using a wtimeout.
For any write operation
written with w majority,
always specify a write timeout.
The specific length
of a timeout will
need to be determined based
on your network and hardware,
but you should always
be setting timeouts
on these sorts of writes.
This wtimeout value is
determined in milliseconds.
So this would wait for 5
seconds before timing out
on a w majority operation.
And lastly, always handle the
server selection timeout error.
No ifs, ands, or buts about it.
By handling this error,
you also passively monitor
the health of your
application stack,
and also become quickly aware
of any hardware or software
problems that haven't recovered
in an adequate amount of time.
If one of these servers goes
down, the response we get back
might let us know what happened.
By default, the driver's
going to wait 30 seconds
before raising a server
selection timeout error,
but you could change this to
suit your application's needs.
By handling the [? server, ?]
we also passively monitor
the health of the
application stack,
and become quickly aware of any
hardware and software problems
that haven't been recovered
in an adequate amount of time.
Each driver and
programming language
has a specific way of
dealing with errors,
and we do handle this error in
particular in the [INAUDIBLE]
application.
So just to recap
here, always use
connection pooling,
which, by default,
will allow a connection
pool of 100 connections.
Always specify a write
timeout for majority
writes to make sure
that the server isn't
waiting for too long.
And always handles
serverSelectionTimeout errors.
This will make sure that the
application becomes quickly
aware of any hardware and
software problems that
haven't recovered in time.