Welcome to Chapter 4.
We are almost there.
Before we start
uncorking the champagne
and celebrating your course
completion certificate,
we need to go through the
last chapter of this course.
This chapter is all about
application resilience
and robustness.
We will be looking
to how to make
your applications resilient to a
variety of different situations
that may impact the
performance and availability
of your system.
Don't forget, we are living in
a distributive database world,
and therefore, we need to
prepare our application
to be robust and performant,
as well as scalable.
Hang tight.
This is going to be fun.