So in this list
we're going to talk
about the principle
of least privilege
and how we can apply it in
our own security practices.
So here's a short relevant
quote from Jerry Seltzer,
who is a domain expert within
security and distributed
networks.
And essentially
what the quote says
is that all programs
and users on a system
should only have the privileges
that are necessary to complete
their intended purposes.
We'll see what he means
by that in a second.
So to a certain extent
at the application layer,
we are already kind of doing
this for our mFlux users.
For example, we make sure
that only certain resources
and privileges are available to
users who have been logged in.
And even those users have
different permissions
from each other.
For example, a user only has the
permission once they're logged
in to delete their own
comments and no one else's.
So MongoDB actually
offers the same sort
of robust user management
at the database level.
So by creating a database
user specifically
for the application, we
can in a more granular way
select the privileges
and resources
that mFlux should
have access to.
So this kind of forces
us to ask the question,
should the application be able
to create indexes or create
new collections, or
should the application
be able to drop an
entire database?
Questions like these tend
to require some foresight
about what actions
the applications
should be able to perform
so they won't always
be easy to answer.
But they are very
important in order
to prevent the application from
accessing a resource that it
should never need.
If the application
has permission
to use an important collection
that it's not programmed
to ever use, than
that permission
exists only as a vulnerability
in our application,
and we should remove it.
So that's all for
now about security.
We highly recommend that
if you're interested,
you should take our
MongoDB security
course to learn more about
securing your MongoDB
deployments in production.
So just to recap, make sure
to engineer your systems
with the principle of
least privilege in mind.
In order to do this, we
have to first consider
what kinds of users
we'll have on our system
and what kind of
permissions they'll need.
This includes
application users who
will be using the
application itself
and database users who will
connect to and apply operations
against the database.