In this lesson, we will cover
change streams, a process that
allows applications to
access real-time data
changes without the complexity
and risk of tailing the oplog.
With change streams, you can
watch all the write operations,
or select a more
precise set of changes
that you're looking to
track in your database.
For this lesson, we're
going to make changes
to the comments collection.
Before we start watching
changes in our namespaces,
we're going to set up
a thread that writes
some data into our database.
First, if we want to
track the write changes
to the collection, we
can use a watch method.
This method activates a
change stream response,
which has the following
fields in it--
operation type that can have
any of the write operation
values, which includes insert,
update, delete, and replace.
Then the document that this
operation is affecting,
and the namespace that the
document is in, and so on.
We rarely want to
track all of the writes
to a given namespace.
So in our first example, we will
track all the insert operations
to our collection.
Change streams allow us
to express filters using
the aggregation framework.
Given so, we will create
an insert filter that
extracts the insert operation
type from the change
streams document, which is
created for each write event
that happens in the collection.
We will populate an array
of change stream documents
in order to verify that
the changes that we're
inflicting onto our
collection are correctly
tracked in the thread.
Our print statement
prints the documents
that the change
stream has picked up
while running the
insert process.
It looks like it picked up
all the documents that it was
supposed to, which is great.
Since change streams utilizes
the aggregation pipeline
framework, it allows us to
access very precise information
using that framework.
In this case, we want to track
only the documents in which
the even field value is 1.
For that, we need to
create a criteria that
matches a few fields
in the change event
so that we create a change
stream document only
for those select events.
Here we add a match stage to
the aggregation pipeline, which
now says that we are
interested in a document
if the operation type is insert,
and the document inserted
contains a field called
even with a value of 1.
Notice that, in
this case, we are
accessing the inserted document
both in the aggregation
pipeline and in the
print statement.
For that, we can use the
get full document method
on a change streams
object, which
is what we did in this
and previous test case.
We were expecting five even
documents to be inserted,
and our expectations were met.
This time, I want
to track updates.
How do we do that?
First, change the filter from
tracking insert operations
to update ones.
And to change it up, we now
want to only see the odd ones.
Then specify that you
are doing an update
lookup with full document
method in addition to watching.
If we don't specify that
we want the full document,
then the change event will
only contain the update object.
The question now is, do we
really need the whole updated
document?
After all, we're only updating
the value of one field.
In this test case, we will
print out only the information
that tells us about the
updates that occurred
in the updated document, a.k.a.
the update object
that we were avoiding
in the previous example.
To implement this, use
the get update description
in conjunction with the
change streams document.
Excellent.
We see that no
fields were removed,
and the i field was updated
with the value printed.
In this case, we were also
watching only the odd updates.
But we can change that filter
by modifying the aggregation
pipeline that we use.
These are some of the
applications of the change
streams functionality.
Use this newfound
knowledge responsibly.
And if you watched
the lectures in order,
congratulations on being
done with the lessons
in this course.
We hope you enjoyed it.