In this lesson, we're going
to talk about error handling.
We will consider a few
scenarios in error categories
and find ways to
fix those errors.
This way, we can ensure
that your application
is resilient to
issues that can occur
in concurrent and
distributed systems.
Concurrent systems
will most likely
have situations where
duplicate keys will occur,
while distributed systems
are prone to issues related
to network and concurrency.
While all of the errors
covered in this lesson
are not very likely
to occur, it is
helpful to know how
to deal with them
if and when they
manifest themselves.
First common error
can occur when
you're trying to insert a
document in place of an already
existing document.
In our example, there is
already a document with id
that equals 0.
So inserting another document
with the same id value
should cause a
duplicate key error.
Let's try and see
if this is true.
And it is true.
In this test case,
we are specifying
that we're expecting a
MongoWriteException error.
So since the
previous test passed,
it would be great to know
exactly what kind of error
we're getting.
So in this test case, you
can see that the error return
is specifically
DUPLICATE_KEY error, which
means that in order
to correct it,
we should not be trying
to insert a document
with an existing key.
Let's run it.
Excellent.
Now to fix the error,
simply change the _id value,
and that should do the trick.
Another error to be on the
lookout for is the timer error.
In this test case,
we're trying to avoid
breaking the application by
using the try and catch block.
This particular test case won't
cause the WriteConcernTimeout
error.
In fact, it is very hard to
induce a WriteConcernTimeout
error or any of
the errors covered
in this lesson on an application
that is running on Atlas.
But if that does happen,
then a try catch block
will help you identify
the situation.
To fix a WriteConcernTimeout
error issue,
you need to consider the
needs of your application.
And depending on that, you can
either reduce the durability
guarantees by changing
the WriteConcern value,
or increase the timeout and
keep the app durability.
Another possible error can occur
when the WriteConcern that is
requested cannot be fulfilled.
For example, our replica
set has three nodes
that were automatically
created by Atlas.
We can dictate the
type of write concern
that we want for our
write operations.
In this example, we're asking
for a 5 node acknowledgment,
which is impossible
in our situation.
As a result, we get a
WriteConcernException.
This error is easy to solve
by either assigning a majority
WriteConcern or a
number that is less than
or equal to 3, instead of 5.
Excellent.
That's it for our lesson
on error handling.
Enjoy the rest of the course.