Now, not all aggregation
stages are made equal.
There are ones that are more
complex than others in terms
either of their
type of operation
and the parameters they
may take to execute.
For example, $lookup stage takes
a fair amount more parameters
and options to execute than
a simple $addFields stage.
By comparing these
two, you can see
how they differ in
terms of complexity
and, obviously, what the
expected output is about.
To exemplify this
scenario, let's go ahead
and do the following.
Create facets of the
movie documents that
were produced in Portugal,
the facets on the cast
members of those same movies,
a facet on the genres count,
a list of the genres
and its count,
a facet on your bucket
matching the movies, year
bucket, all of which were
produced, again, in Portugal
exactly using the same filters.
What we were trying
to achieve in Java
would be something similar
to this aggregation.
Where we match
for each facet, we
are going to create a MongoDB
client facet object that
will express that same facet.
Now, a facet constructor
takes a facet name
and a variable argument, a
variable length arguments,
v args for short, of a
sub-pipeline that build up
to the expected facet values.
For the cast members, we need
to unwind the cast arrays
and use a group stage to
create the set of cast members.
So, here, what we are
doing is unwinding the cast
and then heading to
sets as an accumulator
on every single cast
member that we find.
So, actually, even the
group ID here will be empty.
So we're not filtering
in specific one.
We just want to
[? iterate ?] all of them
and create a single set
of all the cast members.
That will be our cast
member facet definition.
It takes on the unwind cast
and the group cast set.
All the following facets
will be having the same kind
of logics associated.
There will be sub-pipelines
that we need to build.
So in this case, the
facet genresCountFacet
will unwind first the
genres and then sort
by count giving us the
sorted order and the count
of each one of the genres.
For the yearBucketFacet we just
need to create a single stage
the BucketAuto, which
will give us the group
by the year in 10 buckets.
It will auto generate
that distribution for us,
which is very handy.
The Aggregates.facets
method also
takes a variable
set of facet objects
that composes the sub-pipelines
of each facet element.
So in this case
here, the facet stage
will be just basically a setting
up of all the different facets
which we previously defined.
Then, finally, we
can just create
a matchStage, the first
filter for all these facets
to be created.
Add that matchStage
to the pipeline.
Then add the facetStage.
Then iterate and
count on the results.
In this particular case, we
only have one single document
that gives the full facet.
We can look into the result
here for more detail on how
this is going to
be built. You can
scroll through the
list of results
here to see what the end
result of that pipeline
will be looking like.
Well, let's take
a moment to recap.
Aggregation pipelines are
composed of lists of Bson stage
documents objects.
We can use the driver
Aggregates builder class
to compose at different stages.
We can use accumulators,
sorts, filters, builders
to compose the different stage's
expressions and operations
that those stages will perform.
For complex
aggregation stages, we
can imply several different
supply plans and stage
arguments as well.