So in this lesson, we're going
to cover joins in MongoDB.
So joins are used
to combine data
from two or more collections,
which is true for all database
systems, but the
implementation is
going to be a little
different in MongoDB.
The join we're
going to do here is
between the movies and
comments collection
from the mflix database.
Each comment in mflix
is posted by a user,
and associated with
one specific movie.
And we want to count
how many comments
are associated with each movie.
Users use comments as a
way to discuss movies,
so we can think of this sort
of like a popularity contest.
You know, which movies
are being talked
about the most on our site.
We're going to use the new
expressive lookup in MongoDB
3.6, so we can express
a pipeline for the data
that we're joining.
This might not make
sense right now,
so we'll explore what
it means in a minute.
We're going to build
this pipeline in Compass,
and then use Compass'
export to language feature
to produce code that we can copy
directly into our application's
native language.
So here I'm just connected to
the mflix database in Compass.
And we're going to start our
aggregation from the movies
collection, and then join
from the comments collection.
Although it would probably work
the other way around, as well.
Just going to move
this Aggregations tab.
And I can select a new stage.
I'm going to add a match stage
to select only the movies that
came out in the 1980s.
And now that our match
stage is fully written out,
it looks like
Compass has already
loaded the documents that would
be returned by this query.
And it looks like all of these
movies came out in the 1980s.
So now here's the stage where
the join actually happens.
This is a look up stage
in the expressive version.
And there are four fields--
from, let, pipeline, and as.
From is going to
be the collection
that we're joining from.
So we're running this
aggregation from the movies
collection, and we want to join
from the comments collection.
So that's the one
I've specified here.
So let is when this starts
to get a little complicated,
so try to follow closely.
The pipeline we
write inside the join
has access to fields of
documents inside the comments
collection, because
that's the collection
that we're joining from.
But it doesn't have
access to the field
inside the movies collection,
unless we specify them in let.
So if we want to use the
underscore ID from the movies
documents inside
the pipeline, we
have to declare this
variable ID and assign it
to the dollar underscore ID
from the movies collection.
So if we look
inside the pipeline,
we can see that we refer to this
variable with two dollar signs,
because the variables
with one dollar signs
refer to fields inside
the comment documents.
This obviously can get
a little bit complicated
with all the dollar
signs, but just
remember that double dollar
sign means that the variable was
defined in the let statement.
The pipeline itself only has
one match stage right now,
and it's matching the
movie ID of the comment
to the underscore
ID from the movie.
We've set as to movie comments,
so that the movie document will
now have an array field
called movie documents that
contains a list of all
the comments associated
with that movie.
And we can check that that
field exists down here.
It looks like it did
create this movie comments
field, which is a type array.
And each element of the
array is its own document,
which look like the
exact comment documents
from the comments collection.
Now I embedded all the comment
documents inside each movie,
but all I really
wanted to figure out
was how many comments were
associated with each movie.
I don't really care what each
comment says, or who wrote it,
or when it was written.
I just care how many there are.
So here I've changed up our
look up stage a little bit
by adding this count
stage to the pipeline.
Count is just going to
count all the documents that
pass through this pipeline.
And since we already
used a match stage
to make sure that each
comment was associated only
with that movie, this
meets our needs perfectly.
And we can see we've ended
up with a single array field
with one value that just has a
count of the number of comments
associated with this movie.
So this pipeline in
the expressive lookup
is actually very
powerful, because it
allows us to transform the
comments documents returned
by a join on the server before
that data even gets embedded
inside this movies document.
And now that we've
written out our pipeline,
we can verify that
our output documents
look the way we expect.
We can export the pipeline
to a language that
suits our application's needs.
We have Python 3, C#, Node
JS, and Java available to us.
So just to recap,
expressive lookup
up allows us to pass
an aggregation pipeline
to the command that can
transform the data before
that data is actually joined.
And let allows us
to declare variables
in that pipeline that
refer to document fields
in our source collection.
Once we're done writing the
pipeline out in Compass,
we can use the export
to language feature
to produce the aggregation
in the language that's
native to our application.