In this lesson, we're going to
talk about update operators.
Imagine a scenario
where you have
a database of your
favorite artists,
and you're trying to keep
up with the public opinion
about them.
So you periodically
update the rating
of your favorite musicians
to match their public rating.
First, we set up
a test collection
in the documents that go in it.
We're calling this
test collection artists
and throwing Gorillaz and
Weird Al Yankovic in it
for testing purposes.
You may notice that
by some coincidence
the name of the band
Gorillaz is misspelled
with an extra z at the end.
We would definitely like
to fix that right away
and replace that value
with a proper spelling.
There is a method that allows
us to replace a document.
And it is called replaceOne.
Here's an example
of how to use it.
First, we establish a connection
to the artist collection
and retrieve the document
that we're interested in.
We make sure that the band
created in the database
is the same band
that we retrieved.
And then we can create a
document with the correct title
where Gorillaz is
spelled accurately
and simply replace the document
with our new replace band.
Let's test this.
It works!
However, it looks like
this replacement operation
annihilated all fields other
than the ID field and the title
field.
This is because when the
replace method is used,
it replaces entire documents.
And since the replacement
document that we created only
had the title and ID
fields, we ended up
losing a bunch of data such as
the number of albums, genre,
and rating, which
is unfortunate.
Instead of using a method
that replaces full documents,
we should use something that
can work with better precision
and change only the
field that is specified.
Sounds to me like
we should use set.
Let us take a look at
an example that uses set
when changing the band title.
When you use set, you want
to use the update method.
So you take the collection,
find the document
that you're looking to update,
and set the field to the value
that you're looking
to change it to.
Let's see if this works.
Success!
We updated the value
of the title field.
And the rest of
the fields remained
as they were without being
erased from existence,
which is great news.
This is exactly what
we were looking for.
Let us look at the slightly
different scenario now.
Suppose Weird Al and Gorillaz
are now equally more popular
than before.
And we want to update their
rating to the appropriate 9
from the measly 8 that
is in the database.
One way of doing that
is by using updateMany
in combination with set.
To use updateMany
simply create a query
that selects all
of the documents
that you're interested in.
In this case, we are
looking for rating 8.
So every document
with a rating of 8
will be now set to rating 9.
And you can use updateMany same
where you would use updateOne.
Let's run and see if it works.
Another success story!
However, there is still a better
way to make this update happen.
In this example, we are
working with numbers.
To be more specific we
are working with integers.
Let's look at an example of
how to achieve the same update
result using an
increment operator.
To use an increment
operator you can still
use updateMany or
updateOne, create
a query that will select
the documents that you're
interested in changing
field values for,
and then use inc that increments
the rating field by 1.
Let's run it.
And another success.
Finally, we should talk
about those moments
when you realize that some
data in your documents
is unnecessary.
Not only is that
data unnecessary,
but you simply don't
need the fields to be
present in the document at all.
Imagine that you realized
that you no longer care
about the public opinion and
you just like the music that you
like regardless of what the rest
of the world thinks about it.
So you go into your database
and you delete the rating field.
Here's an example of
how you would do that.
In this case, you can use
updateMany or updateOne.
We're going to find all the
documents that have the field
rating at all in them.
And we use unset and
specify the field
that we want to get rid of.
Let's see if it worked.
Wonderful!
It looks like everything worked.
OK, let's make sure
that all the test cases
that we used in this
lesson work as expected.
Fantastic.
And we're done with
update operators.
Let's quickly recap
what we learned.
You can replace entire
documents with replaceOne.
This operation may
cause you to lose data,
so it isn't recommended
for situations
when you need a simple update.
You can update a value
in a single document
using the updateOne,
set or inc operators.
You can update
multiple documents
that match your query using
updateMany in conjunction
with set or inc operators.
You can completely remove
the field from a document
by using updateOne or updateMany
with the unset operation.
For more update operators
and their use cases,
feel free to check out the
following documentation page.
You can also find a link
to this documentation page
below the video.
Use these tools wisely and
have fun building Mflix.