In this lesson, we are going
to review the different cursor
methods that the find
command provides,
as well as the alternative
aggregation framework stages
to similar or
equivalent functionality
within the context of
an aggregation pipeline.
We will cover things like
the FindIterable sort,
limit, and skip methods,
the aggregate method,
as well as briefly review
some of the builders
that we've already
been talking about,
like Sorts and Aggregates.
And just to clarify, we're going
to have a small 1,000-document
dummy collection
called sortable.
More often than not, the
results of our queries
are required to be sorted.
Databases do a good job
sorting those for us,
so that we don't have to
implement extra logic to sort
the results after they've been
sent back to the application.
In MongoDB, we can do
this by appending the sort
method to the FindIterable.
In this case I want to be
able to sort all my documents
by field 'i' descending.
We can start by defining
the sort criteria using
the Sorts.descending method and
placing that into a Bson object
sortBy_i_Descending.
Then what we can do
is a full table scan
by passing the sorting
arguments, the Bson
that we just created,
to the sort method.
Finally, what we
want to make sure
is that we got all
the results, the 1,000
documents in our
sortedArray, which we do,
and then check if the first
elements of this sortedArray
matches the highest
value of our collection
'i' documents, which is 999.
We run the test to make
sure that everything
is matching our assertions.
In addition to sorting
the query outputs,
we might be
interested in sections
of the results set instead of
retrieving the whole set all
the time.
So skip is another
cursor method that we can
call from the Iterable object.
Out of the 1,000 documents
that we have in our collection,
we might want to
skip the first 990.
For that we just need to
append the number of documents
we want to skip.
In this specific
case, we are not
specifying a particular
sort order to our documents.
This means that the
results will be returned
in their $natural
sort order, which
implies that the
documents will be returned
based on how they got stored or
created in the database server.
And we can see
the effect of this
if we try to remove
one of the documents.
In this case, the document
where 'i' matches the value
10 and inserting it back again.
If we rerun the query
with the same skip,
we will find that the highest
value of our array lists
will be the one which
has the value 'i' of 10.
This means that
using skip on its own
without determining a
particular sort order
may result in different
documents, given that they are
bound to the insertion
order of documents,
not the values of the
fields they represent.
But there is nothing stopping us
from sorting and then skipping
at the same time.
The order by which we define
the sort and skip instructions
is completely irrelevant.
By running the tests, we can
see that all of our sorts
match our expectation.
And the important thing
to understand about skip
is that the database
will still have
to iterate over all the
documents in the collection.
Only returns after the
skipped number of documents
has been reached.
However, it will
still need to traverse
the collection and indexes to
return the matching documents.
Another cursor method is limit.
The ability to define
how many documents
we want to retrieve from the
collection on a given query.
If we limit it here
to 10, the number
of expected results of our
collecting list should be 10.
One interesting
aspect of limits is
that we can use this to
influence the cursor batch
size.
The cursor batch size determines
the number of documents
returned in one cursor batch.
If our query hits 1 million
elements or documents,
you may not want to wait
till all of those elements
are returned to start
processing the result set.
Therefore each time we
open a cursor or iterable,
the results are sent back to the
application in smaller batches,
hence the cursor batch size.
By default the Java driver
will set the batch size
to 0, which means
the driver will
use the server defined
batchSize, which by default is
101 documents.
However, you can define your own
batchSize for a final operation
by specifying the batchSize,
calling the batchSize method.
Getting all the cursor
methods together
is done by appending
each one of those methods
to the resulting find iterable.
We run the tests.
Everything matches green.
Instead of cursor methods, we
can use the aggregation stages
to accomplish the same results.
Why do we need an
aggregation stage to do this?
Well, the need for intermediary
sort, limit, and skip stages
exist in multiple
pipeline executions,
so these stages are
readily available for usage
within the
aggregation pipelines.
Let's start with limits.
If we want to specify
in our movies dataset,
we can run the following query.
Now that we know how to
do it in the find command,
let's do it again within
our aggregation pipeline
by specifying the $limit stage.
We add the Aggregates.limit
to two results,
and then we execute
that same method
by calling aggregate with
the pipeline that we created.
And all of them are there.
Now let's look at the $sort
stage and sort method together.
To specify the $sort
stage, we can use again
the builder Aggregates.sort,
specifying the Sorts.ascending
on year.
And we can also
build a match stage
by calling the
Aggregates.match method.
Again, all the results
of these two lists
should match and be
exactly the same.
Now let's put it all together.
Now that we know that we can use
sort, limit, and skip methods
together by appending these
methods to the find command,
we should be able to do
exactly the same thing using
the aggregation stages, where we
can define the different stages
using the builder.
But there is a
significant distinction
between how we execute the find
command with the cursor methods
and how we execute the different
stages of our aggregation
pipeline.
For aggregation, the order
of stages in the pipeline
does matter.
Since we are setting
up a pipeline,
the results will vary
given the processing
order of the different stages.
If we execute this test, this
will be reflected in our sort.
Let's do a little
bit of a recap here.
Cursor methods have
equivalent aggregation stages.
The order by which
the cursor methods
are appended to
the find iterable
does not impact the results.
On the other hand,
the order by which
aggregation stages are
defined within the pipeline
does matter.