Hello and welcome to Chapter 2
of the M220 Developer Course.
I hope you've had success
developing the mflix
application into a
MongoDB database client.
Setting up the
driver to read data
from Mongo into your
application is fundamental.
And I hope you've enjoyed
building that crucial piece
of infrastructure.
Now that we do have a
connection from mflix to Mongo,
we can start really
leveraging the driver
to create a more functional
and durable backend.
In this chapter, we'll learn
why some complex queries are not
possible with the
query language alone
and how the aggregation
framework can actually
help us build these queries.
We'll start using the driver
to write data to MongoDB.
But not all those writes
are created equal.
We'll explore the
nature of these
writes to determine which are
critical to our application
and then use the
driver to increase
the durability of those writes.
As far as mflix is concerned,
the application's functionality
will grow immensely
in this chapter.
New users will be
able to join the site,
update their preferences,
and leave reviews
on the movies they
feel strongly about.
We'll even allow users to edit
or remove their own reviews,
but make sure they can't
mess with anyone else's.
All told, this is
a dynamite chapter
designed to make you comfortable
writing mflix data to Mongo.
At the end of the
chapter, mflix users
should be able to not only read
about their favorite movies,
but actually create a
community on the site.