In this lesson, we are
going to look into writing
new data into a collection.
Specifically, we are going
to review the insertOne,
insertMany, and update methods
with upsert true options
in the Java driver.
We are going to start
by instantiating
a collection called videoGames
from our test database.
Once we have a
collection to write to,
let's create a Document
object instance that
will hold some information.
In this case, we will
be having documents
that represents a video game.
We can start by setting up the
first key of that video game
right from the constructor.
And then we can add a new
set of document fields,
like year of the
launch of the game,
by appending a new key-value
pair using the .append method
of the document.
And another one using the
put method by putting label
equals Epic Games.
Now, these are
two different ways
of constructing our documents.
One is appending, which
sets a specific order
in our documents.
And the put will just replace
values if they already exist,
but keeping the order
of the original setting
of the document mapping.
Not really relevant
right now, but just
something to keep
in mind that you
can use both methods
to append or put values
into the document.
Then we can insert this document
by calling the collection
insertOne method.
As you probably noticed, the
insertOne method returns void.
So how do we know
if the document
has been correctly inserted?
If an error occurs during the
insert of a given document,
a MongoDB write exception will
be thrown, stating the origin
and cause of the error.
In later lessons, we'll look
into which kind of exceptions
we should be prepared
to handle and what
causes such exceptions.
Otherwise, everything
gets correctly written
and the document is
stored in the database.
However, the avid MongoDB
expert in you is wondering,
where can we see the _id
fields, our primary key.
We did not set one, so surely
it would still need to be set.
And you are right.
On insert, the driver will set
the _id field if it is not set
by the application, with the
default data type of ObjectId.
Then we can assert here that
it's not null after the insert.
This basically means that if
we try to recover the document
back from the database using the
_id value that not now we have,
we will get exactly the
same documents back from
the database.
By asserting that here
and running this query,
expressing the equality filter
_id with the document ObjectId
field, we can assert
that it is true.
So let's do that.
By running a test, we
can see that everything
passes with flying colors.
Another option to insert
new data into a collection
is to insert it in
bulk, or better saying
several documents at once.
In this case, I'm going to set
up a list of two documents.
This list is called
someGames and will
have two of those documents.
Here, I'm going to construct the
Hitman object of the video game
by just using the put
and the constructor.
And this one, I'm going to
use something a little bit
more elaborate by using
an HashMap, by setting all
the key-value pairs,
and then putting them
all into the second
doc2 document object.
All different ways of achieving
exactly the same result.
Once we have the
two documents, we
can add them to the list
of documents, someGames,
and, finally, insert all
of these documents using
insertMany.
The same logic
applies as in insert.
If an error occurs that prevents
documents to be inserted,
you will need to capture
the runtime exception.
If we look back into
the object references,
we can see that _id
fields are correctly set.
If we assert for
them for not null,
we will get those values
correctly asserted.
So let's go ahead
and list them here
into this list of
ObjectId fields.
If you want to guarantee
that those ObjectId fields,
those documents are
really in the database,
we can still search for
them by counting the number
of documents that match the
filter in condition of _id,
passing back those
list of _id fields.
And the expected
count should be 2.
After running the tests,
we can see that everything
is correctly asserted.