There are times
where we are not sure
if a document really
exists in the collection
and we just want to update
it if it already exists.
Something like update or
insert if it does not exist.
Well, MongoDB allows for that
in a very straightforward way.
Let's go ahead and
instantiate our documents
about Final Fantasy from our
good friends at Square Enix.
And instead of going to
the database, run a query,
and check if the
document already exists,
we are going to emit an update
command with the flag upsert
equals true.
We set the query predicate
that finds the video game based
on this title and
we try to update it.
If we do not provide
the upsert flag
and just set the document to
be updated based on the title,
if the document does not exist,
the number of match documents
should be zero.
So as the number of modified
counts of the documents.
On the other hand, if we
do provide an upsert flag
by setting the update options
document with the upsert flag
to true and adding those
options to the update method
by specifying it
on the updateOne.
In this case, our
number of modified count
is still going to be
0 given that there's
no documents in the
collection to be modified.
However, the upsert ID,
as a result of the insert,
will be set to not null and
should be of type object ID.
Another component of the
update or insert upsert
is that we can set
values just in case
we are inserting the document.
Let's say we add a field called
just insert if the document did
not exist before, but
do not set the field
if the document already exists.
Let's try to update Final
Fantasy, which already exists.
We need to set up an object that
defines the update operation,
sets the title, and appends
the field just inserted
with a string yes.
So that can be done
here, where we specify
update object one sets the
title to Final Fantasy 1,
and sets also an option here
set on insert just inserted
while the string
equals the string yes.
We specify the query filter
and run the updateOne.
In this case, the field
will not be present
when we query for this document
back from the database,
running exactly the
expected filter,
finding Final Fantasy 1 now,
and we retrieve the first.
We can see that no such
field just inserted exists.
On the other hand, if the
document is not updated
but inserted, like in this case
a new document called title
CS:GO, we specify the update
object as a set of documents
two and we specify as well a set
on insert of the same flag just
inserted with a flag
set to a string yes.
Once we run the
updateOne, then we
will see that the
field is correctly set,
querying the collection
using the upsert ID field
in the update result object.
In this case, we can
assert that, yes,
since the CS:GO game
did not exist before,
caught the flag just inserted.
Running the tests for
test upsert document,
everything gets
correctly tested.
But let's recap.
We can insert new documents
using both the insertOne
and insertMany
collection methods.
Update using a dollar
upsert flag set to true
allows us to insert
new documents on update
if they don't already
exist, and using set
on insert update
operator provides a way
to set specific fields
only in the case of insert.