In this lesson, we
are going to walk you
through how to build complex
aggregation framework
pipelines using the Java
driver aggregation builders.
But before we get into
the complex parts.
first, we are going to see
how to create a single stage
aggregation.
In this case, I would like
to know how many movies
have been produced in Portugal.
I can express a variable here
specifying the country that I
want to filter on, and
then what I'm going to do
is use an aggregation framework
to answer that question.
For that, what I'll
need to have is
a pipeline defined to hold
all of our aggregation stages.
In this particular case,
there will be just one stage
in our pipeline, the $match .
Stage The $match
stage will require
an expression, a filtering
criteria, a match criteria.
And in that case I'm going just
to say that the field countries
need to match, or be equals, to
the country that I'm defining
here, which is Portugal.
Now, instead of
manually constructing
the BSON document that
expresses the aggregation stage,
you should use the
Aggregates builder class.
Aggregates provides a set of
syntactic sugar class builders
and methods for each one of the
supported aggregation stages.
Although we can build
any aggregation stage
by appending
document, or our BSON
objects with their
respective expressions,
Aggregates allows us to be more
concise in the stage build up,
with less typing.
So, in this case here,
the $match method
takes in arguments, which
is a filter expression
that we defined previously.
And sets it into the
variable matchStage
I can then add to an
array pipeline of stages.
And once we have appended
the matchStage to the array
pipeline, we can then execute by
calling the collection command
aggregate.
As a result of the
aggregate method,
we get back an
aggregate iterable
Similar to the other
iterable, this object
allows us to iterate
over the result sets.
In this case, I'm
going to iterate
into buildMatchStageResults.
By running this, this
should be producing
a list of 152 movies
produced in Portugal.
So let's look into that.
And our assert is correct.
A single aggregation
pipeline, in particular,
the $match stage,
could be achieved
by using the find command.
So let's use something a
little bit more interesting,
which is exactly what we
should be using the aggregation
framework for.
So let's build here our
pipeline again of BSON objects.
And what I want to know now
is for all movies in Portugal,
sum the number of times a
particular cast member gets
to visit such a lovely place.
How many times has an
individual cast member
participated in a movie
produced in this country?
And of course, let's not forget
to return the results sorted
ascending regarding
the number of gigs,
and number of counts
of times that they
produced, or been part of a
movie produced in Portugal.
The aggregation command that
we would operate in the Mongo
shell should be something
similar to this,
where we match,
unwind, and then group
based on the sum of counts, and
then, at the end, sort on it.
So, the match stage will be very
similar to what we already done
before, where we have the
country, the filter equality,
and creating the
matchStage object.
Then we have to unwind using
Aggregates.unwind and passing
the field we want to unwind on.
Group based on the cast name,
and count the number of times
a cast member appears
in the result set.
So we need to first
specify what kind of field
we're going to use to group on.
It's going to be
called a groupIdcast.
Group operations are in place
to do some sort of completion
operation.
Operations like sum,
average, min, max,
are all good candidates be
used alongside with group
operations.
And there is a Java
builder for that.
The Accumulators class handles
all accumulation operations
within a group stage.
So we can use here the
Accumulators.sum method,
specifying the field name
where we want to collect
the values of the sum.
And, obviously, passing 1, which
in this case, we are summing 1.
But it could be any expression,
like for example, summing
all fields of a given value.
After that, we just need
to build our group stage
by calling Aggregates.group
and passing on the groupIdcast
and sum1 accumulation.
And finally, we want to sort.
And for sorting, we can just
call a Sorts expression,
the sort order, and
call the sort stage
by building it via
the Aggregates.sort
and passing on the sort order.
With all these
stages, we are now
ready to call our
aggregate method
with a bit more complex of a
pipeline than a single $match
stage.
So we need to add
all of those stages
to our pipeline in the order
that we want it to be executed,
and call the aggregate
method on the collection,
passing on that pipeline.
The aggregation
framework also provides
stages that combine
operations that are typically
expressed by several stages.
For example, $sortByCount
combines both the group,
with a sum accumulator,
with the source stage.
Don't believe me?
Well, let's check it out.
First of all, let's build
this shorter pipeline
variable, which is again,
an array of BSON objects.
Then, we need to build a
slightly shorter pipeline.
We have already built
our $match and $unwind,
so let's add them here.
And then we can create
the $sortByCount stage,
which should do exactly the same
thing as our group and our sort
stages that we defined before.
And in this case,
what we just need
to do is call the
Aggregates.sortByCount,
pass on the field
expression saying
that we want to do it on cast.
Then finally, we can
assert that both pipelines
provide the same results.
So let's check it out.
And that is absolutely correct.
Both results will
have the same, even
though they were built
with different stages
in their pipelines.