So in this lesson, we're
going to briefly cover
the Aggregation
framework in MongoDB.
We're going to use the
Aggregation builder in Compass
to export this pipeline to
the language of our choice.
So the first thing to know
about Aggregation in MongoDB
is that it's a pipeline
composed of one or more stages.
And within each stage,
we define expressions
that evaluate and transform the
data at that particular stage.
To use an analogy, documents
flow through the pipeline,
sort of like the widgets do
on a factory conveyor belt.
Each stage is like
an assembly station.
Documents enter, some
work is performed,
and then some output
is produced that gets
piped in as the input
to the following stage.
So in this example, we have
a stage that filters out
the colors we don't want.
Then we have a stage to
transform the shapes.
And then we have a stage
that collects all input
and gives us a
ratio of the colors.
So each one of those stages in
the pipeline used expressions.
And at their core,
expressions are functions.
So here we're going
to take a look
at the add function in
three different programming
languages, as well as the
Aggregation framework.
So here it is in Python--
simple function, has
two inputs, and returns
the sum of those two inputs.
So here in Java, we have a
little more strict typing.
So we've just specified that
the type of each of our input
has to extend this number
interface, which is to say
that we can add the two inputs.
But it's more or less
the same function.
And here it is in JavaScript.
It's about as short
as it is in Python,
but the syntax looks a
little bit like Java.
So now, here is the add
function in aggregation.
Essentially it's
this add expression,
to which we pass an array of the
values that we want to sum up.
So all expressions and stages
in the Aggregation framework
will have this dollar
sign before them.
And the dollar sign is just
how we refer to variables
within the expression.
We have a course that dives much
more deeply into Aggregation,
covering syntax and semantics
at almost every stage.
You can find more by looking
at the lesson handout.
Also included is a link to the
Aggregation quick reference.
So now, let's jump
into Compass and start
building some Aggregations.
So here I've just opened
up Compass and connected
to my Atlas cluster.
Currently I'm connected
to the movie's collection
on the MFlix database.
And I'm using the
Aggregations tab
so we can write a pipeline
against the movies collection.
The first stage
we're going to add
is a match stage to
only pick up movies that
were directed by Sam Raimi.
The way that we're
going to do that
is by specifying the field
and the value that we want.
And we can see this
is only returning
movies to us that have Sam
Raimi as a director in them.
So the way the match stage works
is actually very interesting
and somewhat subtle.
So here the director's
field actually has
an array as its value.
And that array has
all the directors
for that specific movie.
But we only need
to specify the one
that we want to match
against, and it will actually
parse the array out for us.
So now let's add another
stage to this pipeline.
We're going to try to
figure out the average IMDb
rating for all the movies
that Sam Raimi has directed.
Just going to add
a new stage here.
So here's a project
stage in our pipeline.
This is going to
essentially choose
which fields we want
to display and suppress
from the previous
stage in the pipeline.
I don't really care about the
underscore ID in this case.
So I'm gonna say I don't
want it with a zero.
I do want the
title of the movie.
And I need the IMDb rating
in order to find the average.
Now because rating is contained
within an IMDb object,
we have to use dot notation in
order to project that field.
And when we use dot notation,
we have to just surround
this in quotes.
And it looks like this did
what we wanted it to do.
We only got back the title and
the IMDb rating for each movie.
So now that we have
all the IMDb ratings,
we can find the average.
And to do so, we're going
to use a group stage.
So the group stage
can be used for a lot
of different purposes, but the
way we're using it right now
is to find the average of all of
the movies Sam Raimi directed.
We've already matched all the
movies that Sam Raimi directed,
so we don't need to
transform the input.
But we really do want to find
the average of all the movies.
So I've specified a 0 as
my underscore ID here.
And as the output
of this stage, which
is the last stage
in our pipeline,
we see the grouping
criteria, which was none,
and the average rating
value, which was 6.86.
Way to go, Sam Raimi.
So just to recap--
Aggregations in
MongoDB are pipelines
that are composed of
one or more stages.
And each stage uses
functions that we
write in the Aggregation syntax
to transform and evaluate
the data.