All right, so in
this lesson, we're
going to discuss
write concerns and how
they can provide a different
level of write durability
in our application.
If you're not sure right
now what write durability
is, no worries.
We'll cover it in this lesson.
So for right now, let's just
consider a small supermarket
application using a replica
set as its data source.
Whenever a customer puts
an item into their cart,
the application will send
a write statement over
to MongoDB, and
that write will be
received for that primary
node of the replica set.
So the first thing
the primary node's
going to do when it
receives this write
is it's going to apply the
write and its copy of the data.
And by default, as
soon as it's done
performing the write
in its database,
it's going to send an
acknowledgment back
to the client.
So at this point, the client has
received a write acknowledgment
back from the database,
and it considers the write
to be complete.
It assumes that the secondary
nodes will replicate the data
sometime soon, but
it doesn't actually
have any immediate proof of it
from this acknowledgment alone.
So that was an example of
a write with writeConcern--
.
The number 1 here
refers to the number
of nodes in this
set that must apply
the write before a client
gets an acknowledgment back
from the driver.
In this case, it
was just one node.
This is the default
behavior in MongoDB,
so if you send a write to
MongoDB without a writeConcern
specified, it will
use  by default.
So now let's consider
a different level
of write concern.
Our shopping cart application
sends a write statement
to the primary node,
and the primary
applies that write just
like it did before.
But this time, the primary
waits before sending
an acknowledgment
back to the client.
And what is it waiting for?
Well, before sending an
acknowledgment of the write
back to the client, the
primary will actually
wait for one of the secondary
nodes to replicate the data.
When the secondary
applies the write, it
will send an acknowledgment
back to the primary saying, hey,
I applied this write
to my copy of the data.
Once the primary
knows that in addition
to it having applied the write
itself, one of the secondaries
has also applied
the write, only then
will it send an acknowledgment
back to the client.
This write was sent
with w majority, which
means that the
client isn't going
to get an acknowledgment
back from the driver
until a majority of nodes in
the set have applied the write.
In this case, this
is a three-node set,
so we only needed two of the
nodes to apply the write.
You can think of w majority
as a contract with the client
that this write
will not be lost,
even in the event
of hosts going down.
If an application sends
a write with w majority
and gets an acknowledgment
back for that write,
it knows that even if
the current primary were
to go down, one of the
secondaries in the set
has also captured the write.
So with w majority,
the connection
is going to wait for
a majority of nodes
to apply the write before
sending an acknowledgment back
to the client.
For that reason, it
takes a little longer
and is subject to
replication lag.
But there's no additional
load on the server,
so the primary can still
perform the same number
of writes per second.
However, w majority essentially
guarantees to the client
that a write will not be
rolled back during fail over,
because the write was committed
to a majority of nodes.
This is useful when
some of our writes
are vital to the success
of the application.
A common example of this
is a new user on a website.
These types of
operations must succeed,
because without an account,
the user can't really
do anything else on the site.
So I just want to discuss
one more write concern, w 0.
By now, you must have realized
that when the value of w
is a number, it's
the number of nodes
that must apply a write
before the client receives
an acknowledgment.
We can pass any number
here to the w field,
but it will throw us an
error if this number is
higher than the total
number of nodes in the set.
Following that rule, when w's
0, none of the nodes in the set
actually need to apply a
write before the client gets
acknowledgment.
This means that when
we're w 0, there's
a chance that we
get acknowledgment
before any data has
actually been written.
So if the server crashes,
we might lose a few writes.
This type of write is referred
to as a fire and forget
operation, because
it sends the write
and doesn't really worry
about the response.
But this isn't entirely true,
because the acknowledgment
from a w 0 operation can also
alert us to network errors
and socket exceptions.
So the client can
implement some logic
to figure out if the
write was actually
received by the database.
In any case, writing
with w 0 is very fast
and can be useful
for less important
writes that occur frequently.
For example, if an
internet of things device
is sending a ping to
Mango every two minutes
to report its
status, it might be
OK to speed up every write
operation at the risk of losing
a few writes.
So to recap, w 1 is the
default write concern in Mongo,
and it commits a
write to one node
before sending an
acknowledgement back
to the client.
w majority will make sure
the write was applied
by a majority of the set before
sending an acknowledgment back
to the client.
This means the
application will have
to wait a little
longer for a response,
but it should not have a
performance impact so long
as you have enough
connections to the primary
to handle your requests.
w 0 does not commit
the write at all,
but sends an acknowledgement
back to the client immediately.
So there's a slightly
higher chance
that we lose data in the
event of a primary going down.