In this lesson, we
are going to check out
how to perform deletes and
remove documents that match
a particular query predicate.
For the purpose of
this lesson, I'm
going to go ahead and create a
sample collection, in my test
database, called sports.
And I instantiate it here.
And then I'll go ahead and
populate the sports collection
with a few examples of
sports, things like football,
basketball, F1, and whatnot.
The first thing to understand
is that a delete operation
is in fact a write
in database world.
Confused?
What I mean by this
that when a delete takes
place of a document
from our database,
we are actually
executing a state change
in the data that implies
a database write.
Deletes imply that several
different things will happen.
Collection data will be changed.
Indexes will be updated.
And entries in our oplog,
the replication mechanism,
will be added.
All the same operations
that an insert or an update
will originate.
But let's go ahead
and see this in action
with a single document delete.
Before I start deleting
data from my collection,
I'm going to count the number
of documents in the sports
collection.
And I'm going to place
it in this variable
here, nSportsBefore.
Now that I know how many sports
documents my collection holds,
I'm going to just delete one.
First, I need to define a query
predicate or a query filter.
In this case, I'm going to
just specify one that is empty,
which will be similar to
running the db.DeleteOne
without any query predicate
at all from the MongoDB shell.
Once I execute the
deleteOne method,
I can get a
DeleteResults object.
We can verify that
the delete was
successful by checking the
number of deleted documents
in our DeleteResult object, the
resulting object of the delete.
By asserting that the number
of deleted count is equal to 1,
we can verify that at least one
document was in fact deleted.
If I now count the
number of documents,
I can see that it has
been decreased by 1.
If I execute db.countDocuments
and subtract minus 1
to nSportsBefore, I can see
that this search matches.
Wait, but which
document did I just
remove from the collection?
Well, in this case,
MongoDB will select
the first $natural document it
encounters in the collection
and delete that one.
Given that the insertMany
inserts documents in order,
the document that
I had just deleted
will be the one with
the "name" = "football,"
which makes me very sad.
Let's just run this test
altogether to see the results.
And as we can see,
one of those certs
matches and our test passes.
A delete that takes the first
element of the collection
$natural order tends to
be a less than usual thing
that you will be doing
in your application.
So let's use something a
little bit more elaborate.
Let's say that I'd like
to delete a document that
matches a particular name.
Let's delete the first
sport where the fieldName
starts with a string "bas".
To do that, I can express
a single regex pattern
in string format and call
the Filters.regex method.
The query in the
MongoDB shell should
be something like the following,
where db.sports.delete = name
and the expression of our
regex that matches that name.
To do that, I can just, again,
use the filters.regex, bassing,
the name of the field,
and the pattern.
Once we execute it, we get the
results on the DeleteResults.
After running the delete
method and capturing
the DeleteResults,
we can confirm
that one sport was
deleted by asserting
the delete count matches 1.
Now, which one
did I just delete?
Again, the same logic
will be applied.
The first element that can be
found in the collection that
matches the query predicate
will be the one to get deleted.
That means that our dear
"basketball" no longer
resides in the collection
after this delete.
And we can Assert for
that by trying to find it
and actually getting no
from the iterator tryNext.
This actually raises
an important aspect
about deleting one element of
a multi-document match query.
To run this operation
safely, this
means deleting the exact
document we are looking for.
The match should be done
using the primary key
of the documents.
Otherwise, you will
be deleting documents
based on their initial
insert/update order, which
can be very, very widely.
Obviously, deleting
one single document
at a time when
what we want to do
is delete all documents
that match a query predicate
will be very slow.
Therefore, MongoDB
also allows you
to delete all documents
that match a given criteria.
This time around, I would like
to delete all documents that
have a particular field.
Not interested in
the kind of value
that they represented with,
but more with the leading
all documents that
have such field.
If the field exists,
the document has to go.
Something similar to this
will be expressed in a shell,
where "note," for
example, "$exists" = 1.
Let's create the delete criteria
where if the field note exists,
we want to delete
all those documents.
Using the Filters builder,
that will be done like this.
Bson criteria = Filters.exists
and the fieldName.
Running the deleteMany
method with this criteria
will result in three
documents being deleted.
So let's run it to make sure
that this is exactly correct.
And it is.
All of our tests pass.
One last method that allows
us to remove documents
from our collection is
our findAndDelete method.
Comparing this with
deleteOne method,
the difference will
reside in the what
object is returned
by the method.
In the case of
deleteOne, we get back
the DeleteResult
object that tells us
if the command was
acknowledged and the number
of documents deleted.
In the case of findAndDeleteOne,
what we get back
is the document that
was just deleted.
This method might be
very useful in cases
where we need to return
back the last state
of the document
for post-processing
by the application.
Think about Q's or
something that needs
to be done with that document
after it's gotten deleted.
If we tried to delete
the sport with the named
"table tennis" Using the
findOneAndDelete method,
expressing the
query predicate, we
get back a document,
which is the deletedSport.
We can assert that
it's NotNull and we
can assert that the ObjectId
will be set in this object.
If we run the tests, we can
see that everything is green,
just like we like it.
Well, let's recap.
Deleting data is just another
write operation database.
We can delete one document
at a time with deleteOne.
Or we can deleteMany
documents in one go.
The method
findAndDeleteOne returns
the state of the document
before the delete command
got executed.
And running all the
tests in this lesson,
we see that everything passes.