Now let's take a look
at updating documents.
Before we get started,
I'd like to look
at the movieDetails data
set in Compass in just
a little bit more detail.
This data set
includes the fields
that you might expect, like
title, year, and the MPAA
rating.
But it also includes
fields that are
important for building a
website designed for movie buffs
and others who just have a
genuine interest in movies.
There's a field for the
countries in which the movie
was filmed, who the writers
were, the actors, of course,
and even a field
for the movie poster
to provide a way of getting
access to some visuals.
In addition, we have
the Rotten Tomatoes data
for viewer ratings and
awards that a given movie
may have won.
So for a movie's
website, we can use
this data to provide a
really nice picture of what
went into making this movie.
As I mentioned, while not
all movies in this data set
include this field, many
include a poster field.
Let's take a look at one
that doesn't actually
include a poster.
So here we have the
movie The Martian.
And as you can see
on a quick scan
of the fields for this document,
there is no poster field.
And in fact, there's
no awards field either.
Now, we won't spend
too much time on this,
but the difference
between The Martian
and other movies we've
looked at illustrates
something that
sets MongoDB apart
from relational databases.
It's possible for documents
in the same collection
to have different schemas.
And we take advantage of that
in MongoDB in a variety of ways.
This is an important difference
from relational database tables
in which all records
must have exactly
the same set of columns.
One of the simplest ways in
which we use this in a MongoDB
database is that for
documents for which we
have no data for a
field, we don't need
to include the field at all.
Going a bit further, many
movies have not received awards.
The flexibility of
MongoDB's data model
allows us to easily model awards
for just those movies that
have them without creating a
second table or a collection
that we must then join together
in queries in order to get
all necessary data for a movie.
Now, there does, in fact, exist
a movie poster for The Martian.
And The Martian did
win several awards.
So as an example of updating
documents in MongoDB,
we're going to fix this
document by adding a poster
field and an awards field.
Now, an application might
do this type of update
as the poster becomes available
in an electronic form for use
on the site or even in response
to user-contributed and
moderated content.
In the MongoDB query
language, the method
for updating a single
document is called updateOne.
Now, of course, we could
add this field in Compass
by simply editing the document.
But for most update
use cases, you're
going to be writing updates as
part of your application logic,
and not performing
updates by hand,
as we would in a GUI
tool like Compass.
So here's our call to updateOne.
Let's talk briefly
about the syntax.
The basic idea here with
updateOne and the other two
update methods is that you
first specify a filter.
As with find, this will identify
the document or documents
that we want to update.
updateOne will simply
update the first document
matching our filter.
For example, if we had
put something in here
like year 1999, there would
be dozens of documents
that match in this collection.
The first one
retrieved by MongoDB
would be the one
that got updated.
In this case, there
is just one movie
that is titled The Martian.
Now, of course, in a
web app, update script,
or other software application,
we'd be using a unique
identifier such as the _id in
order to specify the document
to update.
We're using the title here just
so it's obvious exactly what
movie we are updating.
The second argument to
updateOne specifies how
we want to update the document.
You must apply an update
operator of some kind.
In this case, we're
using the $set operator.
$set takes a document
as an argument.
It's expecting a document that
has one or more fields listed.
$set updates the document
matching the filter
such that all key value
pairs in the update document
are reflected in the new
version of the document
we are updating.
For this call to updateOne,
$set will add a field
called poster, with
this URL as the value.
If there was an existing
poster field in the document,
this would modify its value.
Now let's go ahead
and copy this command,
and run it in our shell.
In this shell, we're connected
to our Atlas sandbox cluster,
and are using the video
database so that we can access
the movieDetails collection.
The response we
get back tells us
that the update was
acknowledged by the database.
We matched just one
document, as expected.
If we had matched more,
we'd get that count here.
And then the response
indicates how many
documents were modified.
For updateOne, this value
should always be 1 or 0.
Let's take a look
at the document
now to see what
changes were made.
And if I refresh
the document, I can
see that now, in fact,
there is a poster field.
Update operators, as
you might imagine,
aren't limited to
scalar updates,
like we just performed.
We can update fields
with any legal value.
As a quick example,
let's go ahead
and supply the awards
field for The Martian.
Now, we can go ahead and
execute this call to updateOne.
And note that here,
we're doing something
very similar to what we did in
our previous call to updateOne.
But in this case,
our $set operator
is going to set an
awards field such
that the value of the awards
key will be this document.
Now, if we go
ahead and run this,
we see that, again, we matched
one document and modified one
document.
Going back and taking a look
at this document in Compass,
we can see that our
awards field is here,
with the values specified
in our call to updateOne.
And with that, we've
covered the fundamentals
of using updateOne.