In many cases, we have
multiple documents
that we would like to insert
at once in some sort of batch
operation.
The MongoDB query
language has a method
for this called Insert Many.
Let's take a look at an
example of this command.
I have it here in a text editor.
I'm going to insert
a few documents
into videos dot movies scratch.
This is just so I can easily
do a little bit of noodling
around here demonstrating
this command,
and then just get rid
of this collection
without corrupting any data that
I actually want to maintain,
with regard to movies.
See the handouts for
this lesson to download
the examples here so that you
can try them for yourself.
Now instead of passing a single
document as the first argument,
as we did to Insert One, with
Insert Many, we pass an array.
In this example, the array
begins here and ends here.
And you can see that
the elements are each
a document that we would like
to insert into this collection.
Now there are additional
options for Insert Many.
And we'll take a look at
those a little bit later on.
For now, let's run this command.
I'm just going to copy and
paste it into our shell.
In this shell, I'm connected
to my Sandbox Atlas cluster.
And we can see what happens here
is about what you would expect,
given our understanding
of how inserting documents
into MongoDB works.
Let's take a closer
look at this operation.
So our command is Insert Many.
And we have 1, 2,
3, 4, 5 documents
we're attempting to insert.
Note, however, that these
two documents are identical.
With a bulk insert,
it's possible
that there will be an error
or an exception thrown
for one of the documents that
you're inserting, especially
if we're doing something like
a data cleaning operation
where there is lots of noise in
the data or errors of some kind
in our data set.
To handle these
issues gracefully,
there are a couple of different
options for Insert Many
that you should know about.
You can choose to
do either ordered
inserts or unordered inserts.
The default is ordered inserts.
This provides a good
example, in that
we're using IMDB values as our
underscore ID for each document
in this Insert Many call.
Again, these two
documents are identical.
But most importantly, it is
their underscore ID values
that are identical.
And we know that in an
individual collection,
the underscore ID values
must all be unique.
So if we scroll
down and see what
happened with this
command, we can
see that we've got a
duplicate key error.
And the error is on the
Wrath of Khan movie.
We can also see, if we look
a little bit further down
in the output, that the number
of documents inserted was two,
even though we have five
documents in this Insert
Many call.
And if we go over to
Compass and refresh,
we see that there's one
Star Trek movie and one
Wrath of Khan movie
in this collection.
So indeed, just two documents
got inserted out of the five
that we attempted to insert.
Now let's go back to our shell.
As I mentioned, Insert Many
does an ordered insert,
meaning that as soon as
it encounters an error,
it will stop
inserting documents.
Because it encountered
an error here,
only these two documents were
inserted into this collection
with this call.
Now in many applications,
we might simply
want our app to keep
going if it encounters
an error, because either we're
fine with the documents that
errored out not
being inserted, or we
have a separate process
for dealing with them
some other way.
To support this use case, we
can specify a second argument
to our Insert Many method.
So returning to our
text editor, the array
is the first argument
to Insert Many.
As a second argument,
I can supply
a document that specifies
a value of False
for the key ordered.
This Options document allows us
to change the default behavior.
And in this case, rather
than doing an ordered insert,
I'm going to do an
unordered insert.
Let's go ahead and run this now.
Now here, we actually
see three write errors.
There are three
duplicate key errors--
one for the Wrath of
Khan, one for Star Trek,
and another for
the Wrath of Khan.
Let's take a look
at our query again.
So these three insertions
caused a duplicate key error.
Why is that?
Well, if you'll
remember, these two
were already in the collection
from our previous attempt
to use Insert Many.
So an attempt to insert
this one and this one again
got duplicate key errors because
of that previous insertion.
This one, of course, has
exactly the same idea
as this, so fails for the same
reason that this document did.
What's interesting here is
that rather than just error
out and stop executing
inserts, Insert Many continued
and inserted these
two documents--
Star Trek Into Darkness and
Star Trek First Contact.
If we go to Compass and
refresh our collection view,
we can see that now
there are four documents
in this collection--
Wrath of Khan, Star Trek,
Star Trek into Darkness,
and Star Trek First Contact.
So by specifying Ordered
False, even though there
were, in this case, three
duplicate key errors,
Insert Many continued
inserting documents.
And ended up inserting
those last two
in our list of documents that
we passed to Insert Many.
In this lesson, we looked at
Insert Many and the ordered
and unordered versions of
an Insert Many operation.
Insert One and Insert Many
are two primary ways in which
we can create documents.
There are a couple of
other ways in which
we can create documents through
the use of update operations.
Update commands can result
in documents being inserted.
We call these
operations Upserts.
We discuss Upserts in
detail in another lesson.
So with this, we've
discussed, in some detail,
the primary ways in which we
create documents in MongoDB
and hinted at the third way
in which data can be inserted
into a MongoDB collection.
And with that, we've
addressed the Create portion
of our CRUD operations.