OK.
Let's talk about the situations
in which update operators can
actually create new documents.
We call these
operations upserts.
As I was creating the
data set for this lesson,
I actually made use of
the upsert functionality
in MongoDB to create our
movie details collection.
I'm going to walk
through an example of how
I built this collection.
Now, I did this in
a script, but I'll
take a look at the
same basic steps
I went through here
in this example.
So imagine that we have
this detail object.
In the script that I wrote, I
essentially looped through data
that I was bringing
into the database,
but I wanted to make sure
that I didn't introduce
any duplicate movie entries.
So the way I dealt
with this was by using
a command that looks like this.
The process that I used to
collect the data that I wanted
to put into the movie
details collection
was such that I couldn't
guarantee only retrieving
movies not already present in
the movie details collection.
So what I decided to do was to
make use of the $set operator.
The net effect of this was
that, if the document already
existed, I essentially
replaced it
with exactly the
same detail data.
If it didn't already exist,
updateOne performed an upsert.
Using updateOne with
the upsert option
meant that I didn't
need to first query
the collection to see
whether the document already
existed and then do a
second query to insert.
I let MongoDB do
all the work for me.
The trick here is that I'm
using this third parameter
to updateOne, setting
upsert to true.
This means that if
this filter doesn't
match any documents in my
collection, this document--
which, for the Martian
example, would be this one--
will be inserted
in the collection.
And that's the basic
idea for upserts.
Update documents
matching the filter.
If there are none, insert
the update document
as a new document
in the collection.