Projections reduce network
overhead and processing
requirements by limiting
the fields that are
returned in results documents.
By default, MongoDB
returns all fields
in all matching
documents for queries.
You can define a projection
as the second argument
to the find method.
If I want to limit my result
documents so that they just
contain a title, I can do that
using the following syntax,
or almost.
So using this syntax, I
can create a projection
where results from
this query will
return just the
title and, actually,
the title and the underscore ID.
And we'll talk about
that in just a sec.
So again, use the
filter as usual.
But in this case, because we'd
like to just have the title,
we're also adding a projection
as the second argument
that we passed to find.
Now, I get the title
and the underscore ID.
I get the underscore ID
field because underscore ID
is returned by default
for all projections,
unless I explicitly exclude
it from the projection.
The projection syntax allows
me to explicitly include
fields in documents returned.
I can also explicitly
exclude fields.
I explicitly include
fields using a one,
and exclude using a zero.
If I don't want to see the
underscore ID field, then,
to my projection, I need
to add underscore ID zero.
Let's run this.
And now we can see that we
do, in fact, just have titles.
Now if we have the reverse
situation, where we actually
want to explicitly exclude
a couple of fields,
we can do that as follows.
So let's say that rather
than include title,
I'm going to exclude viewer
rating, viewer votes, and run
time.
And let's pretty that up.
Now my results
contain all fields
except for the ones I
explicitly excluded here.
Note that there is no
viewer rating, no viewer
votes, and no run time
in these documents.
And just for the
sake of comparison,
if I drop the
projection, then we
see the viewer rating, viewer
votes, and run time coming
back in for those documents
that have a run time,
such as this one.
So, if you need to limit
the fields returned
by your queries, projection
is the tool to use.
You zeros to explicitly
exclude fields
that you don't need to
see in your result set.
And use one to
explicitly include fields
and exclude all others.