Three of the four
CRUD operations
are right operations,
create, update, and delete.
All three of these
involve changing the data
in a collection in
one way or another.
You only have read access
to our class Atlas cluster.
Fortunately, with the
Atlas free tier option
we have a means of creating
a sandbox MongoDB cluster
in minutes and at no cost.
The Atlas free tier is ideal
for proof of concept projects
and in the early stages
of developing a software
application.
It's also great for testing
and for educational purposes.
Please follow along and create
your own Atlas free tier
cluster.
You'll be using this throughout
the rest of this chapter.
I've also included instructions
for creating your sandbox
cluster in the lab
that immediately
follows this lesson.
OK, here we need to complete
the registration form.
Once you've completed
the registration form,
go ahead and click continue.
Upon completing
the form, you'll be
asked to specify a group name.
Groups or how we manage
access to Atlas clusters.
I'm simply going to specify
shannon-m001 as my group name,
and create the group.
Once you've created a group,
go ahead and build a cluster.
You might get a notification
from the intercom integration
that we have here when you do
this, feel free to ignore it.
Also, don't be scared by what
you see when this first pops up
with respect to pricing.
Free tier is truly free.
We simply need to select
the M0 instance size,
and you'll note that the
price has changed to zero.
Then we'll need to enter
a username and password.
Once you've entered your
username and password,
you can go ahead and
deploy your cluster.
Now again, the cluster is free.
No credit card is
required for any of this.
Please make sure you remember
the user name and password
that you entered.
You will need it later.
Now once you've
deployed your cluster,
you'll need to wait
just a minute or two
for the cluster to come up.
Once deployed, the cluster
is ready for connections.
But before we connect, we need
to change one security setting
to make it easy for us to access
the cluster from anywhere.
Click on the Security tab, and
then on the IP Whitelist tab.
Click Add IP Address, and
Allow Access From Anywhere.
It'll take just a moment to
update our security settings
in the cluster.
While that's happening,
let me stress
that making a cluster
accessible from anywhere
is not a best practice.
You should be as
restrictive as possible
with respect to IP
Whitelisting when
configuring an Atlas cluster.
However, for purposes
of this class
this is fine, and will
save us wasted time
debugging network issues.