Let's connect to the Atlas
Cluster for this class, the one
that we've all been
using together.
I'll show you how
to do that here,
but please see the lecture notes
for the exact connection string
and other parameters
you should pass to Mongo
in order to connect
to our Atlas Cluster.
We might need to change this
information from time to time
as we make updates.
The lecture notes
will be updated
as well so that you have
the necessary details
to connect to this cluster
from the Mongo Shell.
I'll paste those
details here, and then
let's talk about this
command a little bit.
I want to point out a
couple of things here.
The first is that because
we're connecting to a cluster,
we wanted to give the
Mongo Shell the name of all
the servers in this cluster.
Those are listed
here through here.
MongoDB is designed to provide
high availability access
to your data.
It does this by
enabling you to maintain
redundant copies of your data in
a cluster called a replica set.
We configured our Atlas Cluster
to be a three-server replica
set in order to help ensure
you will always have access
to the data.
There are thousands of
students taking this class.
In the event that the
primary server goes
down due to a software
or hardware failure,
one of the other
servers will step in
to continue serving
data to clients.
If you'd like to know more
about how replica sets work,
please see the
MongoDB documentation.
One other thing I'd like to
point out about this command
is that at the very
end here, we can
see the word test immediately
following this slash.
That indicates that we're going
to connect to this cluster
and we're going to connect
it to a database called test.
Now if we would
prefer to connect
to a different database,
we can change this
to one of the databases we
know is available in our Atlas
Cluster.
Let's do the 100-year
weather database.
And if you'll
remember, that database
has a collection
in it called data
where all of the weather
readings are found.
Finally, the last thing I'd like
to point out about this command
is the fact that we're
making a secure connection
to this cluster.
As we did when
connecting with Compass,
we're using an encrypted
connection via SSL
and supplying the same
username and password
we did to connect with Compass.
So let's go ahead and
connect to our Atlas Cluster
with the Mongo Shell.
We'll see a prompt
that indicates
that we're connected to the
primary for this cluster.
The shell will always connect
to the primary for a cluster
as specified here, because it's
the primary to which most reads
are typically directed and to
which all writes for a MongoDB
cluster must be directed.
Only primaries in a
cluster can accept
writes and for
any cluster, there
is one and only one primary.
Now remember, we connected to
the 100-year weather database.
If we type show
collections, sure enough,
we see the data collection,
because we have connected
to this particular database.
If instead we'd prefer to
access the video collection,
we can use the use
command and use video.
And then, if we show
collections here,
we'll see our movies collection.
Now I'm going to show you
just one more command,
and that is just so we
can see the documents that
are in this movies collection.
OK?
And here, these should
look familiar to you
given that we've
already looked at a lot
of this data in Compass.