Compass doesn't yet fully
support the entire MongoDB
query language.
So in order to do some of
the lessons in this course,
we're going to need to
use the mongo shell.
The mongo shell is
a text-based client
that fully supports all
MongoDB CRUD operations.
In this lesson, I'm
going to walk you
through installing the mongo
shell on a Windows machine.
Here we have a Windows
10 environment.
I'll also show you some
of the subtle differences
you'll encounter when
installing on Windows 7.
There aren't many and you
should be fine on Windows 10
or on older versions of
Windows, provided they
are 64-bit versions of Windows.
Now to install the
mongo shell, we're
actually going to
install MongoDB itself.
We're going to install
the enterprise server.
The shell comes
packaged with the server
as part of the download from
the MongoDB Download Center.
So please navigate to
the Download Center.
And then instead of
Community Server,
let's click the
Enterprise Server tab,
and I will select Windows.
Now this is very important.
Even if you already
have MongoDB installed,
please go through these steps.
Earlier versions of
MongoDB in the shell
did not provide support
for SSL, and we're
going to need SSL support in
order to connect to our Atlas
cluster.
So select Windows 64
and then Download.
Now if you haven't previously
accessed the Download Center,
you'll be asked to
complete a download form.
Please just enter your details
there and then move through
to downloading the Windows MSI.
Now we're presented
with two options
here, either archive or MSI.
Please select MSI.
And again, it's Enterprise
Server, Windows 64, and then
MSI.
And we'll just wait
for that to download.
And once it does,
we can install.
And once the MSI downloads,
we can click it, and then
use the installation
wizard to install MongoDB.
Select Complete
and then Install.
Allow the app to make changes to
our device, and then we finish.
Now it's important that you
understand where MongoDB
was installed on your computer.
So if you click Windows
Explorer and then scroll down
to Local Disk, on your
machine the download location
should be something
like the following.
C:, Program Files,
MongoDB, Server, 3.4.
And then if we click
the 3.4 directory,
we'll see that there's
some license information,
but most importantly
is this bin directory.
The bin directory contains
all of the executables
that are distributed
with MongoDB server.
The one we're
interested in is mongo.
Now note that it's very
similar in name to mongo
d, which is the executable
for the MongoDB server.
For this course, we will be
using the mongo shell, which is
run from the mongo executable.
OK, before we can
run mongo, we're
going to need to
open a command shell.
Now regardless of whether
you're working on a Windows 10
machine or an older
version of Windows,
you have a text box
you can type in.
And if you type cmd, you'll
note that the command
prompt is suggested for us.
If we hit Enter,
then what pops up
is a command line
interface from which we
will execute the mongo shell.
Again, the mongo shell is
a text-based environment.
I can do something very
similar on Windows 7
by clicking the start button and
then in the search box typing
cmd and hitting Enter.
And again, I get a command
shell that pops up.
Switching back to
Windows 10, everything I
do here you can also do on
earlier versions of Windows,
such as Windows 7.
The command shell
is largely the same
in most versions of the
Windows operating system.
At least it's the same for
our purposes in the ways
that we will be using it.
So if you take a look at what's
been printed in the shell,
you'll see it says C: backslash
Users backslash shannon.
This is simply a folder in
the file system for my Windows
machine, and I can find
that folder if I look
in C:, Users, shannon.
So C:, Users, shannon
is exactly this folder.
C:, Users, shannon.
Now if I want to
run the mongo shell
on many versions of Windows, I
need to do one additional step,
and that is I need
to set up my path.
If you've never
done this before,
don't be worried about it.
It's a pretty
straightforward process.
But it is down in the
weeds a little bit.
So we'll take it
one step at a time.
So to do this, I can
type system environment,
and just to be
complete, variables.
And long before
that, Windows will
have suggested this operation,
Edit the system environment
variables.
If I click on
that, what I'll see
is a window that pops up
for System Properties,
and the Advanced tab
is already selected.
If I click
Environment Variables,
then you'll see that I
have user environment
variables for shannon, and
system environment variables.
The one we're interested
in is this one, Path.
And if we select
Path and click Edit,
we'll see a list of folders.
These folders contain
executable files or programs
that can be run on
this Windows machine.
Now on Windows 10, it's
probably not strictly necessary
that we update the
environment variables.
But on many versions of
Windows, it is necessary.
So I'm going to show
you how to do it here.
Now as we said previously,
MongoDB is installed in C:,
Program Files, MongoDB, Server,
3.4, and all of the executables
are in the bin directory.
So again, that's C:, Program
Files, MongoDB, Server, 3.4,
bin.
The way that that
folder structure
is represented in our path is
by separating each component
of the path with a backslash.
So for our path,
that looks like this.
C: backslash Program Files
backslash MongoDB backslash
Server backslash
3.4 backslash bin.
Finally, what I'd like to
do before we finish editing
this environment variable
is move this to the top.
In order to understand
why I wanted to do that,
let's talk a little bit
about how the path is used.
When I'm in the shell and I type
a command, like mongo-- again,
remember, mongo is the name of
the mongo shell executable--
Windows will look for
programs with that name
in each one of the
folders listed here.
And it does so in order.
So it will first check this
path to see if there are
any executables located there.
In this case, it will find one
called mongo and execute it.
The reason why I wanted to
place the MongoDB installation
directory first is
just in case you
have an older version
of MongoDB installed
because if you have an older
version of MongoDB installed,
chances are it's in your path
and you might accidentally
end up running that version
of the mongo shell instead.
Again, earlier versions
of the mongo shell
did not include support for
SSL, and we need that here.
So we really need to
be running the latest
version of the mongo shell,
which you can download
from the MongoDB Download
Center as part of the MongoDB
Enterprise Package.
So we can click OK here.
And now you'll note
that our path has
been updated to include
that individual path
that we just added, and
it's added at the front.
And note that it's separated
from the next item in the path
by a semicolon here.
This is one of those difference
points from Windows 7.
And by that I mean in
editing a path in Windows 10
you have this nice list
of items in your path.
In Windows 7, it's a
little bit more arcane,
for lack of a better
word, because in order
to change the
environment variable,
we actually need to
edit a string that
includes all of the components
of a path in one line.
So here I can do exactly
the same thing, system,
environment, and before
I'm even finished
typing Windows is suggesting
the right thing to me.
I click on it.
Again, it's System
Properties, Advanced tab
selected, I click on
Environment Variables.
And then if I scroll down here,
I can open my Path and Edit.
And see here, this
is what I mean.
We just have one line of text.
These are all of the same
elements of the path that we
saw in Windows 10.
But rather than being
on separate lines,
they're all in one line.
In order to update a
path using this older UI,
I can copy in my C: Program
Files MongoDB Server 3.4 bin
path, and then
type a semicolon so
that it is separated from
the next item in my path.
With that, I can
click OK, OK, OK.
And then I've updated
my path on Windows 7.
Returning to Windows 10, I
want to do the same thing.
Click OK.
And then what I want to
do is restart the Command
prompt because on many
versions of Windows,
it's only after I restart
the Command prompt
that those changes I made to
the path environment variable
will be reflected.
So I'm going to close that.
And I'll just start it the same
way, typing command and then
hitting Enter.
And now I'll be able to
execute the mongo shell.
So to verify that we've
installed it correctly
and that we've set up our path
correctly, what I'm going to do
is type mongo dash dash no db.
Now dash dash no db simply means
that we're just starting up
the mongo shell without
attempting to connect
to any MongoDB database.
We're doing this
simply as a means
of verifying that we've
installed the mongo
shell correctly and that we've
setup our path correctly.
And if you see a
message, such as this,
MongoDB shell version 3.4.6--
or later, depending on
when you're actually doing
this install.
As we roll out the
next version of MongoDB
your version number may change.
But you should see a message
very similar to this.
You have successfully
installed the mongo shell
and launched it correctly.
To quit the mongo shell
you can simply type, quit.
You can run the function Quit.
And that's it for
installing the mongo shell
and getting setup to do a number
of different CRUD operations
in the mongo shell.
For the sake of
completeness, I'll
do the same thing in Windows 7.
So I close the Command
prompt, launch it again,
and run mongo dash dash no db.
And here we can see that we have
a slightly different startup
message.
This is pointing
you to documentation
and to Google Groups where
you can ask questions.
For this class,
please make sure you
direct your questions to the
MongoDB discussion forum.
If you post in Google Groups,
we will just direct you
to the discussion forum anyway.
Before we close out, I
want to say one last thing.
If for any reason you have
trouble installing MongoDB,
please visit the
MongoDB documentation
for installing MongoDB
Enterprise on Windows.
This is a simple
Google query away,
and there is extensive
documentation for how
to install MongoDB on Windows.
You can, of course, also ask for
help in the discussion forum.
But before posting,
please make sure
you do a search in
the forum to see
whether your
question has already
been asked and answered.