Now let's connect Compass to
your Atlas sandbox cluster.
In order to do this, you'll
want to look at the cluster
view for your sandbox cluster.
And click through the
cluster name here.
You might have named your
cluster something else,
but this is where you find
the name of your cluster.
Click through it.
And then what we're looking
for here is the primary.
Compass currently only allows
us to specify a single hostname
in the Form field.
It does a little
bit to help us out
if we have a connection URI.
For our purposes,
it's going to be
simplest to simply
identify the primary,
and then click through to it.
This is the hostname we want.
Your hostname will be
different because you
have your own sandbox cluster.
But for mine, this
is the hostname.
You can find yours in exactly
the same place in the Compass
UI.
Copy it.
Go back into Compass, and
paste it into the Hostname box.
The port is already
provided for us by default.
So at this point,
what we'll need to do
is simply specify the
username and password.
Now if you followed the
instructions for setting up
your sandbox cluster, to
create an administrative user
with the requested username
and password, then here
you should enter, for
username, m001-students,
and for password
m001-mongodb-basics.
The rest of the
defaults should be fine.
But you probably want
to create a favorite.
Then we can click Connect.
And here we see that as
we saw with show DBs,
we have three databases.
The one of interest
is the video database.
And in the video database,
you should see a movie details
collection with 2,295 documents.
We can click through
to that and look
at documents in the same
way we could and can
with the class Atlas cluster.
So that is how you
connect Compass
to your Atlas sandbox cluster.