Now let's begin to explore some
basic CRUD operations concepts.
In MongoDB, we
typically talk about
create operations as inserting
documents, or simply inserts.
Let's look at how to
do this with Compass.
So here I am connected
to the free tier Atlas
cluster I created.
Again, this is a sandbox
that's perfect for developing
a proof of concept or
the type of demonstration
and testing I'm
doing in this course.
Please follow along
in your own cluster.
We're going to create
some data in this lesson.
First, I'd like to create a
few simple movie documents.
These will mostly be throwaway.
So I'm going to put them
in a collection called
moviesScratch.
Using the Compass database
view, I can create a collection.
If I click on the
video database,
I can view the collections
this database contains.
Note, that the moviesDetails
collection we already created
is here.
If I want to create a second
collection by clicking
the Create Collection button.
I name my collection
and create it.
If I click through
to this collection,
I see that it currently
has zero documents.
But I can create one by clicking
the Insert Document button.
Let's create a document with
the title Rocky, the year 1976.
And we'll even supply the
Internet Movie Database ID,
or IMDB ID of tt0075148.
The Compass UI enables me to
tab through the keys and values,
so entering this data is
actually pretty quick.
Now for the year, I need
to change the value type
to integer, more
specifically Int32.
Now we can click Insert, and we
see that this document is now
in the collection.
Collection has a total
document count of one document.
Let's add another--
title Creed, year 2015.
And for IMDB, the
identifier is tt3076658.
Now, I can go back in and
edit a document if I need to.
In this case, I forgot to change
the type of the year to Int32.
So if I click Edit,
I'm right back
where I was and can change
the value type for year.
I click Update, and my
document is updated.
We can perform exactly the same
operation in the Mongo shell.
To do that, we'll need to learn
our first method in the MongoDB
query language.
That method is insertOne.
insertOne is a method on the
collection class in MongoDB.
To use it, we need to first
specify which database to use.
And we'll use the
video database.
Now you see what
happened here is
that when I first attempted
to use the video database,
I got a network error.
What happened here
is that because I
left the shell inactive, it
had terminated the connection.
So when I first tried to issue a
command that requires a network
connection, I get an error.
But the shell also automatically
reconnects to the cluster.
So here, where I attempted to
use video for a second time,
I was successful.
If I show collections,
we can see
that I have both my
moviesDetails collection as
well as moviesScratch.
Now let's use insertOne to
create another movie document
in the moviesScratch collection.
I'm already using
the video database,
so db refers to
the video database.
If I type db.movies, then
I'm specifying the full name
space for the collection.
And as I said, insertOne is a
method on the collection class,
so I can call it like this.
Here we'll use
insertOne to create yet
another document in the
moviesScratch collection.
So db.moviesScratch
insertOne and we
pass it the document
we wish to insert.
The response from calling this
method is itself a document.
acknowledge true
means that we were
successful in making the insert.
And note that the
unique identifier
for this document as
created by MongoDB
is provided to us as well.
Now, insertOne
creates a document
in the collection we specify.
This method will also
create a collection
if the document did
not already exist.
Now, let's do a bit
of experimentation.
Having inserted the
document, we can
see in the documents
view of Compass
that this ID value was created
in the document for us.
Here it is, 5956a ba0 at the
end, 5956a ba0 at the end.
All documents in MongoDB must
contain an underscore ID field.
This is the unique
identifier for a given
document within a collection.
Therefore, all
underscore ID values
within a single
collection are unique.
If we don't supply
an underscore ID,
MongoDB or the
client we're using
will create one for us,
as we saw happen here.
If an idea is created for us, it
will be of the type object ID.
Due to the way they
are created, object IDs
are guaranteed to be unique
for a given collection
and monotonically increasing.
We can also insert a document
and provide the ID value
ourselves.
Let's do an example of that.
Going back to the
shell, rather than let
MongoDB create the underscore ID
value for us, we'll supply one.
Here, I'm simply
going to use the IMDB
value for this document.
And I'm going to leave
everything else the same,
even this field,
even the IMDB field
for reasons that I
think will become
clear a little bit later.
If I hit Enter, we
see that, again, we
get an acknowledgement that
the insert was successful.
And we also see
that the inserted ID
is the one that we
supplied rather than one
that was automatically created.
Going back to our
Compass interface,
if we refresh the
collection, we can
see that we have
two documents that
have exactly the
same data in them
but with different
underscore ID values.
In practice, you
wouldn't actually
have two different documents
that contain the same data
but simply had different
underscored values.
And in practice, you'd
want to make sure
that your underscore
ID values were
of the same form in
a given collection.
So you wouldn't want to have
strings as the underscore ID
value for some of your
documents and object IDs
as the underscore
ID value for others.
Now in this lesson, we've looked
at how to insert documents
into MongoDB one
document at a time
and explored how to do this both
in Compass and the Mongo shell.
In another lesson,
we'll look at how
to do bulk inserts in
MongoDB using insertMany.