Now let's look at loading
data into your Atlas sandbox
cluster.
So here we have
a shell connected
to the sandbox cluster.
Let's see what's there.
We can look at what
databases are currently
in this cluster by
typing show dbs.
And we can see that
there's an admin
database and a local database.
What we'd like to do here
is add a video database
that will contain a more
detailed version of the movie's
data-set that we've seen
in the class Atlas cluster.
Now again, here, I am connected
to my Atlas sandbox cluster,
not the class Atlas cluster.
To follow along, you should
connect to your own Atlas
sandbox cluster.
So in order to make things
just a little bit easier, what
I'd like to do is
encourage you to set up
a small folder on
your local computer
where you can put the handout
that we'll use for this lesson.
When you download and unzip
the handout for this lesson,
you should have a directory
titled LoadMovieDetailsDataset.
And it should be in your
downloads directory.
The same will be true if you're
running on a Windows machine,
as we can see here.
What I'd like to
encourage you to do
is navigate to
your home directory
and create a new
folder called M001.
And then copy that folder,
LoadMovieDetailsDataset,
into your M001 folder.
When complete, you
should see that folder
inside the M001 folder
in your home directory.
Doing the same thing on Windows
looks something like this.
On your local hard drive,
look for users and then
your home directory.
In this case, it's
Shannon, for me.
And what I'm going to do here
is create a new folder called
M001, and then copy
and paste that folder
into my new M001 folder.
With this setup, it
will be much easier
for us to load our data
into our Atlast cluster.
Now from here on
in this lesson, I'm
simply going to use the terminal
application here on my Mac.
OK, so what I'm
going to do now is
I'm going to quit
the shell, because I
want to navigate to the
location where I just saved
that movie details data-set.
And I should point out that the
directory that I copied over
contains a js file that will end
up running in the Mongo shell.
Same thing, of course,
is true on Windows.
So now, in order to navigate to
this directory, when I start up
my terminal
application, I'm going
to be in my home directory.
If I type pwd, this
will print the directory
I'm currently located in.
And as expected, it's my
home directory on the Mac.
If I do a directory listing
using the ls command,
I can see that M001 directory
that I created right here.
And I can cd, or change
directory, into M001
by typing cd and then the
name of the directory.
Again, doing a
directory listing,
I can see the Download
folder that I put in there.
And again, I can cd
into that folder.
And then with a final
directory listing,
I can see the js file here.
OK, doing something similar
on Windows, quitting my shell.
And I can see from the
prompt that I'm actually
in my home directory here.
Now the way I do a
directory listing on Windows
is with DIR, which is an
abbreviation of directory.
I see M001 here.
As with the terminal application
on the Mac and other bash
shells, I can change directory,
do another directory listing.
And there, I see
the same js file.
Now a couple of
things to point out.
One is that I've been using tab
completion so that I don't have
to type the entire directory.
If you type a few
characters then
hit Tab, if there's
only one directory
or file with that name--
for example, loa,
if I type tab--
because that's the only
directory with that name here,
the command prompt will
complete the name for me
so that I don't have to type it.
It's just a convenience.
The exact same thing works
in the terminal application
on the Mac and in
most other shells.
The other thing that I
want to point out here
is that by using arrow
keys, we can go back
through the history of
commands we've executed,
including when we launched
the Mongo shell in the command
prompt.
And again, exactly the same
thing works on the Mac.
Now the cool thing is that if
I launch the Mongo shell here
from the folder in which
I've saved my js file, then
when I launch the Mongo
shell, the Mongo shell
has as its working
directory the directory that
contains that js file.
Now, the Mongo shell is a
fully-functional JavaScript
interpreter.
And if I take a look
at that js file,
I can see that I have a
number of JavaScript commands
here, including this last one,
which loads a bunch of data.
The way we're going to get
data into your sandbox cluster
is by running this
JavaScript file.
But we're going to do
it from the Mongo shell.
And I can execute this
file using the load command
that the shell provides to me.
So, I simply need to
type load-- this is a.
Function.
I call the load function.
And in parentheses, I pass
it the name of our js file
in quotes.
Now remember, currently, we
only have admin and local here.
If I run this
command, now we can
see that a video
database has been added.
And if I want to access
the data in this database,
then I can use
the video database
and take a look at what
collections are there using
the show collections command.
You can follow exactly
these same steps in Windows
to load the data set,
because the shell works
more or less the same
across different platforms.
And if I want to take a look
at the data that's here,
I can do that by
running this command.
And we'll talk a whole lot more
about the find command as we
dive in to the MongoDB
query language.