Now let's talk about exact
matches for array fields.
Again, we're setting
the stage here
for a complete understanding
of the MongoDB query language,
including using a
variety of operators
that allow us to
do a number of very
sophisticated types of queries.
So in considering equality
matches on arrays,
we can consider matches on
the entire array, matches
based on any element
in the array,
and those based on
a specific element,
say, matching only arrays
whose first element matches
a specific criteria.
We can also look at more
complex matches using operators.
We'll do that in other lessons.
Here we're looking at our
video database in Compass.
Let's take a look at this same
database in the Mongo shell.
OK, so here, in the
Mongo shell, I'm
connected to our
class Atlas cluster.
Let's use the video
database, and then,
in this first example, we'll
filter for an exact match
to an array.
Now for these types of
filters, matching documents
must have a value that
is exactly what we've
entered as the array.
So for the query cast, and
then looking for Jeff Bridges
and Tim Robbins--
and let me pretty that up--
matching documents
will have a cast field
that has as its value an array
with exactly two elements--
Jeff Bridges, followed by
Tim Robbins, in that order.
There's just one movie that
matches these criteria.
It's a documentary called
"Making of Arlington Road."
Note that the array field
matches our filter exactly.
Also note that, due to
the semantics of array
matches, the movie "Arlington
Road" itself does not match,
because it also lists Joan
Cusack and Hope Davis,
in addition to Jeff Bridges
and Tim Robbins, in the cast.
Let's do a quick
query for that one.
And here we can see that Joan
Cusack and Hope Davis are also
listed in the cast.
Since our original
query specified
that we want cast to
be exactly this array,
this particular
document does not match.
Now it's more common that we
filter for a single element
of an array field.
To do this in
MongoDB, we can simply
filter for, say, Jeff
Bridges, like this.
Matching documents
contain the string
Jeff Bridges as one element
of the array field cast.
We can see Jeff Bridges is here.
If we scroll through
the array documents,
he appears in every single
one of the cast arrays,
sometimes as the first
actor listed, and sometimes
in other positions, as in here.
What's nice about this syntax
is that it's exactly the same
as selectors for scalar values.
In some situations,
we want to match
a specific element of an array.
Actors are frequently listed
in order of precedence,
with those whose
contributions to a film
that are highest occurring
earlier in the list.
For example, the
star of a movie will
appear before supporting
actors, as we see
in the document for "Iron Man."
In this movie, Robert
Downey Jr. is the star,
with Jeff Bridges playing
a supporting role,
so Robert Downey
Jr. appears first.
The MongoDB query
language enables
us to specify that we want to
match array elements occurring
in a specific
position in an array.
To query for those movies in
which Jeff Bridges was listed
first among cast members,
we can use dot notation
and specify an array index.
For this, it's going to
be a little bit easier
to see the difference if
we go back to Compass.
So here in Compass, a
query for cast Jeff Bridges
gives us 114 documents.
But if we query for Jeff
Bridges in position 0
for the cast field, then
we have just 56 documents,
and we can see that
in each and every one
of these returned results,
Jeff Bridges is appearing first
in the cast array.
Now again, just to
remind you, if we
want to do this type of
query in the Mongo shell,
it's going to be necessary
to enclose our key in quotes.
And again, here
we can see quickly
that Jeff Bridges is listed
first for all of these.
Now we've looked
at equality matches
on arrays against
the entire array,
matching any element
of the array,
and then those based on a
specific element of the array.
You should now have
a solid understanding
of the syntax for the most
common read operations
on arrays.