In this lesson, we
are going to look
into the replaceOne commands.
But before we go into
the actual details of how
to use this command, the
syntax, and semantics,
let's have a look
to the outset first.
In my video.movieDetails
collection,
I can find a documents,
a movie documents,
which matches the
title, House, M.D.,
Season Four, New Beginnings,
a very popular TV series
around here.
Once I execute that find
in my Compass interface,
I can see the structure
of my document.
In here, I have
all the information
about this particular movie.
Now, one thing that
I'm noticing here
is that the poster
information is set to null,
and the genres information
here is only composed
by Documentary and Short.
That indicates to me that
I actually have information
that needs to be updated.
I do have information
for the poster,
and I would like to
extend the genres
field by including the
TV series as a genre
for this particular movie.
And for that, I'm going to
use the replaceOne method.
Now, you've already seen
a couple of other methods
to write, like
inserts and updates.
And this one is just
another extension
of that same
capability that we have
for either writing data,
updating data, or recording
data.
And we're going
to look into this
from the context
of an application.
Now, we're going to use
the Mongo shell, which
is a JavaScript interpreter.
That allows us to mimic
what the natural behavior
of an application will be like.
First thing I'm going to
do is specify the filter
by which I want to
find a document that I
want to replace.
In this case, it's the title
House M.D., Season Four,
New Beginnings-- perfect.
And then I'm going to use the
movieDetails.findOne method
to retrieve only one document
back that matches that filter.
Let's go ahead and do
that on the Mongo shell.
Once I'm connected
to the Mongo shell
into my movies collection,
I can specify the filter,
which determines what
am I looking for,
what documents which matches
title I'm interested on.
And then using the findOne
method on my moviesDetails,
passing along that filter,
I get back a variable--
or I can set a variable-- called
doc with that same information.
When I look into it, I can see
all the information, including
the fact that
poster is not there,
and the genres is only opposed
by Short and Documentary.
Now that I know that, I have
to go to my poster fields
and specify the
value of that poster
to that particular string
that represents the poster
information that
I want to attach.
Great, now I'm setting
up the poster field
with that information.
The next step is to
look into my genres.
And I can see that this is an
array composed of two string
values.
Now what I would like to
do is push to that array
a new one, TV Series.
Once I do that, and I
look into my genres again,
I can see that now the array
has been updated, appended
a new value.
Right now, my doc is fully
set with all the information
that I want-- the
poster and the genres.
But this is only in the context
of the Mongo shell currently.
The database has not
yet been updated,
because we haven't
told it to be updated.
One way to do that would be
to use the replacement method.
The replacement method
will take a filter.
We're going to use exactly
the same one as before, where
the title equals House
M.D., whatever, whatever.
And we're going to use the
same variable that we've
been changing throughout the
execution of this Mongo shell
with the settings that we
want, like setting the poster
and appending a new TV
series value to the genres.
Once I execute that,
what will happen
is that MongoDB will
receive this document,
match it with whatever document
it finds defined by the filter,
and replace it with this
particular structure.
Now, in case, we
defined a filter that
contains more than
one document, or we'll
be matching more
than one document,
it will just replace the
first one that it would find.
This is why just
only replacing one.
As we can see, as in the
output of this execution,
we acknowledged
it, which is great.
We matched one documents
for our update,
and we modified
that same document.
Once we execute the query
again and retrieved again
the same document now
from the database,
we can see that my
poster is no longer null,
and the documentaries are
set with exact information
that I want.
Now, why would you use
replaceOne instead,
for example, of updateOne?
updateOne is designed
to, for example,
update a specific set of
values into a document.
replaceOne will completely
replace the documents.
In one hand, replaceOne
and updateOne
do exactly the same
thing, except for the fact
that we are passing the full
payload of our new document.
All the changes will go back
and forth from your application
to the server,
while updateOne you
can specify only the sets
or field set operators
that you are interested on.