To begin our discussion of read
operations in the MongoDB query
language, we'll discuss
equality filters.
This discussion
will set the stage
for our more sophisticated
types of queries involving
the rich set of operators
provided by the MongoDB query
language.
You've already seen some
examples of equality filters
from our work with
filters in Compass.
Let's look at another
filter in Compass first,
and then we'll dive into
the methods that make up
the MongoDB query language as
it is implemented in the mongo
shell.
For this lesson I'd like
to look at movie data.
Let's use a Compass to filter
our video.movies collection
for films rated PG-13.
The rating we're
interested in is
stored in the mpaaRating
field for documents
in this collection.
In this filter I'm
specifying that I simply
want to see documents
that have PG-13
as their value for this field.
Applying the filter here
in the Documents tab,
we can see that each
document returned
is in fact rated PG-13.
Note that only 5,297 of the
more than one million documents
in this collection
match this filter.
We can restrict the
result set further
by adding additional selectors
to our query document.
Applying this
filter significantly
reduces the number of
documents that are results set.
So what's important
to notice here
is that selectors
in MongoDB filters
are anded together
by default, meaning
that only documents matching
both of these criteria
are retrieved.
In other lessons we
consider query operators
that allow us to express
filters that match
any of two or more conditions.
Rather than all of two or more
conditions as we have here,
but that is for another lesson.
Now let's take a look at how to
perform this same type of query
in the mongo shell.
The method for performing read
operations in the MongoDB query
language is called, Find.
To find films in our
movies.videos collection rated
PG-13, we need to first
use our video database,
and then call find on
the movie's collection.
And we can pretty
that up a little bit
using the pretty command.
And here as we
saw in Compass, we
can see that all of our results
have an mpaaRating of PG-13.
Again, as we did
in Compass, we can
add an additional
selector for year,
and restrict our results
set to PG-13 movies
from the year 2009.
And again, we see that
indeed all of these documents
match both of those criteria.
Now that we know how to create
quality filters on top level
fields, let's turn
our attention to how
we can match for equality
against embedded documents.
For this let's look at our
100 year weather data set.
The weather readings
in this data
set capture quite a
few details about wind.
Note that the wind field has the
value type document, or Object,
as it's called in the
documents view in Compass.
If we expand wind,
the wind field
describes the overall
wind conditions.
A value of c for
wind type indicates
that the wind
conditions were calm
when this reading was taken.
In the going to
be query language
our filter would have this form.
And having applied
that filter, let's
take a look at a couple
of matching documents.
We can see here that in
fact, wind type is c.
And likewise for this
document and all others
in this result set.
Taking a closer look
at our query syntax,
we're using what we call
dot notation in order
to identify a field
of a document nested
within the field wind.
Now the dot notation works for
documents nested at any level.
For this let's go a
level deeper, and look
at wind direction angle.
So rather than
window type, we'll
express our filter as
wind.direction.angle.
And because angle is an
integer valued field,
let's do 290 and then
apply our filter.
Taking a look at the results,
wind, direction, angle,
we can see that in fact,
documents in the result set
match this query
using dot notation.
One thing I very much like
about the MongoDB query language
is that it's intuitive
in many respects.
Dot notation is in my
opinion, one example.
Now the Compass is a
little bit more flexible
about syntax than the shell.
Note that we are not specifying
quotes around the key here.
However, when using dot
notation in the shell,
you must enclose the key in
quotes applying the same filter
in the MongoDB shell.
First, we use the
100 year database,
and then use find to
express our filter.
If we try to do this we're going
to get an error because as I
mentioned, quotes are
required around keys
that use dot notation
in the mongo shell.
And here we can see
that in fact, documents
matching this query do you
have the wind.direction.angle
of 290.
To sum up, to drive down the
hierarchy of nested documents
you reach into documents at
each additional level of nesting
by stringing field names
together using dot notation,
and in the shell don't
forget the quotes.