The find method
returns a cursor.
A cursor is essentially a
pointer to the current location
in a result set.
For queries that return more
than just a few documents,
MongoDB will return the results
in batches to our client.
And remember that the
mongo shell is a client.
We use the cursor in our client
to iterate through the results.
In the shell, the
cursor is automatically
iterated up to 20 times to
print an initial set of search
results, as we see here
in response to this query.
So when this query was issued,
the server returned a cursor
to the shell, and the shell
requested the next item
in the result set from
the cursor 20 times.
So what we'll see above here,
if we were to scroll up,
are the first 20
results from this query.
Now, as we iterate
through a cursor
and reached the end of a
batch of query results,
if there are more results,
iterating the cursor
will trigger a getMore
operation to retrieve
the next batch of results.
In this way, we can iterate
through an entire set
of search results.
Now, in this particular
case, the shell
provides a convenience, and
that is that after it displays
the first 20 results
we have an opportunity
to look at more of
them by typing it,
which is short for iterate.
And that will give us the next
20 results in our result set.
And we can continue to do this
until we exhaust the cursor.
So in this way, we can
iterate through an entire set
of search results.