We've been working
with updateOne.
All of the same principles
apply to updateMany.
UpdateMany is our second update
operator in the MongoDB query
language.
The difference between
updateOne and updateMany
is that updateMany will
make the same modification
to all documents that
match the filter.
Let's take a look at an example.
I'd like to work
through a data cleaning
example for updateMany.
I happen to know that
in our movie details
data set there are some
fields in some documents that
are set to null.
What I'd like to do is
just eliminate null fields
from documents in
this collection.
We can see a few
of these documents
with this simple filter.
Here, we're just
pulling in all documents
that have null for the rated
field and null for the poster
field.
Note that there's 1,202
documents matching
these criteria.
If we just look for those
with rated equal to null,
we get quite a few more.
UpdateMany enables us
to modify many documents
at once, all of which
match the same criteria.
What I'd like to
do then is update
this collection
eliminating the rated field
where its value is null.
We'll do that using
this call to updateMany.
Here, we're using
the unset operator,
and the unset operator will
remove all fields listed here.
In this case, we've only
listed one field to remove
and that is rated.
Now, it doesn't really
matter what value we use here
as the value for the rated
key in the document we're
passing to our unset operator.
I just tend to use
an empty string.
From the results of
running this command,
we can see that we
modified 1,599 documents.
And if you'll remember,
that is the number
of documents for which
rated was set to null.
This wraps up our
discussion of updateMany.
The principles of filtering
and the use of update operators
are the same for updateMany
as they are for updateOne.
Again, I encourage you to
experiment, but be careful.
UpdateMany will modify all
documents matching the filter.
Good luck.