Now it's time to
dive in, and learn
the MongoDB query language.
Regardless of the
app you're building,
this is going to be important
as you work to get data
into and out of MongoDB.
We've already had a sample of
the query language in our work
with Compass so far.
In this chapter,
we'll do a deeper dive
so that you're fully prepared
to work with MongoDB data.
We'll cover CRUD operations.
If you're not familiar
with that acronym,
it simply stands for create,
read, update, and delete.
It's these four
types of operations
that we'll be discussing
in this chapter.
In addition to MongoDB Compass,
we'll be using the mongo shell.
Like compass, the mongo
shell is a MongoDB client.
However, the mongo shell is
text based, rather than visual.
It also provides a number
of administrative functions
in addition to supporting
the MongoDB query language.
We'll be using the shell
throughout this chapter
because it provides full
support for the query language.
Let's dive in.