OK.
Now let's look at the last
of our CRUD operations,
Delete operations.
The MongoDB query language
supports two different delete
methods, deleteOne
and deleteMany.
These are similar to insertOne,
insertMany, updateOne,
updateMany in the sense
that the first argument is
a filter that we're using
to identify the document
or documents that
we want to delete.
So suppose we're developing
a web application
and we want to add
two additional pieces
of functionality, one being
that users of our website
can delete reviews
they've made of movies,
and that when necessary
we can delete all
of the reviews for
an individual user,
say for example if they choose
to delete their account.
Now again, we're going to
work in the MongoDB shell
just as a demonstration of the
use of deleteOne and deleteMany
in this type of
hypothetical application.
And in order to work
through this example,
I'd like to introduce
an additional data set,
and that is small
data set of reviews.
Now, as we did with the
movie details data set,
we can load this reviews data
set using the Mongo shell.
In the handouts for
this lesson, I've
provided a script called
loadReviewsDataset.js.
You can use the Mongo shell
to execute this script,
and the script will load
the reviews collection
into whatever host you specify.
Now here, I've specified the
hosts for my Atlas Sandbox
cluster and provided my username
and password, although I
have hidden the password here.
Again, for you to do
this for yourself,
you will need to supply your
own Atlas cluster hostnames,
username, and password.
And again, this is the
administrative username
and password that you
created when you set up
your Atlas Sandbox cluster.
Now, one last thing that
I want to point out here
is that I'm specifying
the video database.
So when I connect
here, I'm going
to use the video database,
and load reviews data
set will therefore
create a collection
in the video database.
Now, we know enough about
the MongoDB query language
to actually understand
how this script works.
It's actually quite simple.
We make a call to
insertMany, passing it
an array of reviews documents.
Again, db should be a
reference to the video database
and will be if you specified
video as the database
to connect to when
you run this script.
OK.
So let's take a look at
this collection in Compass.
You can get a pretty
good sense for what
the structure of
the documents is.
Note that there are
20 documents total,
and I want to draw your
attention to this object ID.
In order to delete reviews,
one way of doing that
is by its unique identifier.
And in fact, for this
call to deleteOne,
that's exactly what
we're going to do--
595b, 9b3b.
In fact, our
deleteOne statement is
going to delete this first
document from our collection.
So now let's go
ahead and execute
this deleteOne statement
in our Mongo shell.
Here, I'm connected to
my Atlas Sandbox cluster,
and I'm going to run deleteOne.
And we can see from the output
that my delete was successful
and that I deleted one document.
If we go back to
Compass and refresh,
we can see that we're
now down to 19 documents
and that first document is gone.
Now let's go ahead and execute
this deleteMany statement.
Now, here what
we're going to do is
delete all of the reviews that
were created by reviewer 795
and so on.
So let's find this reviewer
in our Compass data set.
So if I add this
filter and apply,
we can see that I have
three documents all of them
created by reviewer Emile T all
with the same unique identifier
for reviewer ID.
So if I run this method
in the Mongo shell,
we see that I have a
deleted count of three,
so my delete was successful.
And if I go back to
Compass and refresh,
this filter no longer
matches any documents.
And in fact, if I reset and
look at all of the documents
in this collection,
I can see that I'm
now down to 16 documents.
So I deleted one document
with my deleteOne statement
and then three more with
my deleteMany statement,
taking me from 20
documents down to 16.
And that is delete
operations in MongoDB,
using deleteOne and deleteMany.