What I'd like to
do now is give you
a sense for the different
types of field update operators
that we have available to us.
We used dollar set.
This completely replaces
or adds each field
specified in its parameter as
we saw in earlier examples.
Let's take a look at
what other options
we have for update operators.
And to do this, I'm looking
at the update operator's page
in the MongoDB documentation.
In addition to set,
there's also unset.
This will completely
remove the field
that we specify from a document.
Others here include min and max.
These allow us to update a
field based on comparison
with another value taking
the min of the two values
or the max of the two values.
As we scroll
through here, we can
see there are a number
of other operators.
As an exercise, I'd like to ask
you to please visit the MongoDB
documentation on
update operators
and try a few of
these for yourself.
They are all fairly
self-explanatory
and there's good
documentation on each of them.
But before you do that, let's
take a look at a couple more
of these operators as we
continue moving through
our examples here.
Now, updates have several
different use cases.
They're used to correct
errors and over time keep
our data current.
For movie data, much of
what's there is static.
We've got directors,
writers, actors, et cetera.
Other content, however,
such as reviews and ratings,
will need to be updated as
users take action creating
new reviews or ratings.
We could use $set to make
these kinds of updates.
But that's an error
prone approach.
It's too easy to do the
arithmetic incorrectly or make
other types of errors.
Instead, we have a number
of operators that support
numeric updates of data.
Now as I mentioned,
we've got min and max.
But there's also $inc. This
increments the value stored
in the field we pass to it.
Let's take a look at an example
of using the $inc operator
to update reviews.
Here what we're going to do is,
again working with the Martian,
increment the
tomato.reviews by three
and the tomato
user reviews by 25.
And in case you're not
familiar with Rotten Tomatoes,
in each of our movie
details documents
there's a tomato field.
And the tomato field
reflects the rating
for this movie from
Rotten Tomatoes.
Rotten Tomatoes is a aggregator
of user ratings for movies.
So people who have seen
a movie drop in a rating.
Those are aggregated together
into a tomato rating.
So here we're
simulating the situation
in which we've received
three additional reviews
for the Martian.
If we run this and take a look
at the output, as expected
our update was successful.
And if we look at the
document before the update
for tomato.reviews
and tomato.userReviews
and then refresh, we see that
tomato.reviews went to 283.
And user reviews got
up above 105,000.
Now let's turn to array fields.
As you might imagine,
there are a number
of situations in which we
want to update array values.
MongoDB provides many
update operators for arrays.
Add to set will update
an array with new values
only if the value isn't
already contained in the array.
I can pull off the first
or last item of an array
depending on my parameters
to the pop operator.
I can remove all
values that match
some criteria with pull all.
And of course, I can
push on new values.
Now again, I encourage
you to take a look
at the documentation
for update operators--
in m the array update operators.
But let's take a
look at a couple
of examples in which we're going
to need to update array fields.
For most web applications,
we have a desire
to structure our
data in such a way
that we can get all
the data we need
to render an individual page
with as few database queries as
possible.
For reviews, comments, and
other user contributions,
we recommend that some
portion of your reviews--
often these are the most
recent or most useful--
are included as
embedded documents.
Following this
best practice, what
we might do for movie reviews
is something like the following.
Now you can largely ignore this
portion other than the fact
that it's a review.
But let me call your attention
to the updateOne method call.
This, called updateOne, will
create a key called reviews,
create an array as the
value for this key,
and then push this
review onto the array.
Remember that our Martian
document doesn't actually
have a field called reviews.
The reason why this works is
because push creates an array
if one does not already exist.
Let's take a look
at the document now.
Here we can see our
reviews field added
and reviews is an array.
And this array has
one element, which
is the review that we
specified in our update.
Now let's add a
few more reviews.
Again I'm creating review text.
And in this case I'm
creating several of them.
But let's take a look
at our updateOne.
Again, we're using $push.
And as expected, we're pushing
onto the reviews array.
But here we're using the
each modifier for push.
Some of our update operators--
particularly those having
to do with arrays--
have modifiers
associated with them.
This modifier means
that $push will
add each one of these documents
as individual elements
to the reviews array.
If we don't use $each
here, then the entire array
specified in our
use of $push would
be added as a single
element in that array.
In some circumstances that
might be what we want,
but not in this case.
So let's run this
command and then look
at our Martian document.
And here we can see
that we have in fact
added seven additional reviews.
And with that, we've
concluded our overview
of update operators.
We reviewed a number of the
operators that are available
and worked through
a few examples.
Please feel free to experiment
for yourself using the movie
details collection.
I encourage you to try out
as many update operators
as you can using the MongoDB
documentation as a guide.