now that we've created a sandbox cluster
let's connect the Mongo shell to this
cluster now in case it's not 100% clear
to you from this point on we're going to
be using two different Atlas clusters
one is the class Atlas cluster that you
were using in Chapter one where we were
connecting from compass and exploring
datasets in this chapter as we explore
them on going to be query language we
will be using that same cluster from
time to time but we will also be using
the sandbox cluster that you've just
created in Atlas the sandbox cluster
because you have full administrative
access will allow you to issue rights to
the datasets that are in this cluster or
more precisely to the datasets that we
will load into this cluster so at this
point please visit your sandbox cluster
in Atlas connecting to the sandbox
cluster is a pretty straightforward
operation
given what Atlas provides to us from the
Atlas view we simply need to click the
connect button and then scroll down to
the instructions for connecting with the
Mongo shell now it's pretty easy to be
confused about whether to use this
connection command or this connection
string for our purposes we will
completely ignore the URI connection
string here at the top of this modal do
not use this connection string to
connect to your Atlas sandbox cluster
instead scroll to the bottom of this
modal where we find a section connect
with the Mongo shell here you'll see
instructions for connecting via the
Mongo shell to this Atlas cluster we
have almost the entire command that
we'll need in order to do this now your
command will differ slightly because you
will have a different host name for each
of the nodes in your replica set for
your sandbox cluster so while these are
the host names for my Atlas cluster
yours will be different
however if you simply click copy here
and then jump into your command line
interface whether it's the terminal
application on a Mac or the command
shell on a Windows machine or some other
command-line interface on say a Linux
machine of some kind regardless of which
CLI you're using given that we've set up
our path this command should work for
you with one change you simply need to
change the password to m001-mongodb-basics. Now sometimes the captioning for
these videos doesn't reflect what we're
typing on the screen exactly so please
pay attention to what I'm actually
showing you here on the screen with this
command I can connect my Mongo shell to
my atlas cluster you can use a very
similar command that again you get from
the Atlas UI here to connect to your own
sandbox cluster the only difference for
you should be in what hosts are listed
here everything else should be the same
including the Mongo command and each of
the command line parameters that were
passing to Mongo again please make sure
you don't use this URI connection string
here but do use this Mongo command
provided for us in the connect with the
Mongo shell section of this modal now if
I run this command then I will see a few
different responses printed out as the
Mongo shell starts up but at the end
what we're looking for is a prompt that
looks something like this that indicates
we have connected to the primary I can
do exactly the same thing on Windows
copying the same command in and changing
the password to m001-mongodb-basics and see that I have successfully
connected to my Atlas sandbox cluster
and that is how we connect to our
sandbox cluster from the Mongo shell