hi I'm will cross and welcome to m3 12
MongoDB diagnostics and debugging I'll
be the primary instructor for this
course in this course we'll be exploring
how to diagnose problems with your
server and how to respond when issues
are discovered this course will contain
several chapters with each chapter there
will be a new set of lesson videos after
most of these lessons there will be a
quiz to assess your learning of the
material in each chapter there will also
be a set of related lab exercises when
you've completed all other course
material there will be a final exam that
covers all material in the course now to
go over a few logistics first this is an
advanced course this means it has a
heavy DBA focus you're expected to know
a lot about MongoDB features including a
solid understanding of MongoDB server
administration replication sharding and
indexes second we should talk a bit
about grading as I said in this course
we'll have quizzes labs and a final exam
quizzes are ungraded and exist to make
sure that your understanding the content
of the lesson your overall grade in the
class will be determined by how well you
do on the weekly labs and on the final
your average lab score will be half of
your grade and the other half will be
your final exam will combine these two
get your final grade students with a
grade of sixty-five percent or greater
will pass and receive its certificate of
completion if you have any questions
suggestions for us or if you'd like to
have a discussion on one of the topics
of the course you should check out our
discussion forum there you'll find
plenty of other students many of whom
can help answer your questions and help
you to find other good resources plus
we'll have a teaching assistant to help
moderate the forums and help when other
students can't based on our experience
we've seen that students who perform
best in the course are those who are
active in the course discussion forum by
the end of m31 to you should be able to
both investigate and fix the most common
issues that arise in mongodb deployments
good luck and enjoy the course