OK.
So we've seen how vanilla
replica sets usually
work with the write
concern of majority.
With that in mind, what
could possibly go wrong?
Not much unless we switch out
a secondary for an arbiter.
Now I've only got one path
to get my data acknowledged.
This still works, but only as
long as nothing goes wrong.
If a partition occurs between
my primary and secondary then
my primary can't acknowledge any
writes until the partition is
resolved.
Similarly, if that
secondary goes down
then my writes won't
get acknowledged
until that secondary's back up.
Keep this in mind, a
replica set with an arbiter
in place of a data
bearing server
is better than an even
number of replica set members
but it can also
cause bad situations
when anything else goes wrong.
Let's go back to the situation
with three data bearing members
but ask what happens
with a delayed secondary.
A delayed secondary
is only about as good
as an arbiter for purposes of
ensuring that your W majority
rights go through.
That's because you need to
add your delay to any time
for a write to occur
and get acknowledged.
So if a secondary is
delayed by five hours
then that secondary won't
acknowledge any of the writes
for 5 hours, which
will be a problem
if my theoretically up-to-date
secondary goes down.
Of course you're always better
off with a larger replica set.
So this brings up an
interesting point.
You should always go
through the routine
of calculating how
many servers you
need at minimum for a majority.
Remember, this is about write
concern not your ability
to elect a primary.
Don't count an arbiter
if you have one,
since it can't hold data.
Don't count delayed secondaries.
You want to know
how many servers you
need to write to before you
can get that acknowledged.
And you want to know how many of
them can be out of the picture
either because they're down or
because of network partitions.
Then figure out how
robust your system
is to your standard
servers going down.