In this lesson, we'll be talking
about connection management,
especially around closing
and dropping connections.
First we will be
talking about greed.
No, not Wall Street
kind of greed,
that's a matter of discussion
for another type of class.
Today, what we are
going to be focusing on
is discussing how resource
greedy applications
and keeping connections for
extended periods of time
while leaving them idle,
most importantly, what
resource allocation, especially
memory, will be looking like.
We will also be looking
into how to detect poorly
connect configured
hosts regarding
connectivity,
related pedometers.
So we're going to be
looking into how these
can affect your deployment.
And finally, we are
going to be looking
into what happens when
the new primaries election
within the replica set.
This is not
necessarily a problem.
But once an election
takes place,
what happens to your application
from the connection perspective
and how to then handle
the subsequent connection
operations that will be
affected by that election.
Let's consider
greedy connections
that your applications might
have or might be configured
and how to see their effects.
In the hand outs of this lesson,
you will find a script called,
make lots of connections
to servers.py.
If you want to follow
up with this lesson,
you should download this
into your vagrant environment
shared folder.
So in my case, I have it
here for my m312 vagrant
environment.
Now what this script will do
is simulate one of the worst
scenarios possible.
One that creates several
different connections
from an application
to a database
that end up not doing much.
And actually in this
case, we are just creating
the connection and that's it.
We are not even
reading anything from
this particular application.
We're just going to throw a
bunch of threads or processes,
all of them will create a
bunch of different connections.
And they will idle for
a long period of time.
Now first to understand
what's going on,
we will need to use
a couple of tools.
We're going to be using
Mongostats, that as you know
allows us to see what's
going on from a real time
perspective on our server.
We'll definitely be
using serverStatus
to get some information
of a couple of parameters
that we're going
to be looking into.
From the OS perspective,
we're going to be using free.
And obviously, you're going
to be tailing and catting
and seeing what the
log file has to offer
in terms of information
of what's going
on when we have such a setup.