So your application
is chugging along,
and then some
connectivity issues arise.
What do you see in
your application
that tells you that your problem
is an issue with connectivity?
So most likely what
you're going to see
are timeouts and
connection errors.
Some might be detected on
the client side, others
on the server side.
And it's also
possible that you'll
see long hangs that
potentially don't
result in timeouts depending on
how your application is set up.
Your application should be
smart about these issues.
It should be able to turn
a long hang into an error
that it catches, and it
should log a message somewhere
describing the type of issue.
Finally, it should also
generate a notification
for you, the DBA.
But let's be realistic.
We live in an imperfect
world, developers
work under constraints, and
things aren't always set up
to be the way we'd
like them to be.
So we may need to
do some digging
to find out the root cause.
What might it be?
Well, it could be any
of the following--
incorrect URIs, interference
from firewalls, or just
things out of your control.
Why might you have
an incorrect URI?
Well, maybe some of your
servers have valid URIs
for one another, which don't
resolve from the point of view
of the application.
The servers can all see each
other and everything works
until your primary goes
down, and your application
loses contact with the
entire replica set.
Alternatively,
maybe your servers
have non-static IP
addresses, so restarts
cause you to lose servers
unless you intervene.
Besides issues with
URIs, you might also
have a problem with a firewall.
Usually, the most
basic firewall issues
are caught early,
'cause they often
prevent your system from getting
set up until they're fixed.
But sometimes you
might have a situation
where your IP whitelist
only permits the application
to see some of the database
servers and not others.
Again, the issue arises when
the wrong server goes down.
Or maybe it's something
out of your control.
Maybe a DDoS is
hammering your servers,
or your ISP isn't doing
its job and packets just
aren't getting through.
We'll take a closer look at
these issues and similar ones
in this chapter.
Let's get started.