Our max time milliseconds value.
For this, I'm going to be
using the help of my friends.
I'm going to import them
into our data sets, test,
and a collection called friends.
Once this is fully
imported, I'm going
to be able to do some queries
using my maxTimeMS parameter.
I'm going to connect
to my primary.
And here, I'm going to
express the following query.
I'm going to find from
my friends everyone that
has an e, h value
within their email.
But I'm going to set the special
parameter called maxTimeMS
and I'm going to say,
anything above one
millisecond, if it
takes more to complete,
I don't want to know about it.
I want it to be killed.
And I don't want to have
anything to do with that.
So I'm going to throw
that into a cursor.
And I'm going to iterate
over the full amount
of the results of my cursor.
Boom, I get an
operation exceeded time,
exceeded time limit code.
And this will result in an
execution timeout error.
I can still see
some of the results.
And this is because the
cursor will act in batches.
So the first batch will
be very, very quick
because data will be in memory.
But then after that,
a few pages will
need to be fetched from
disk or some new indexes
will need to be traversed
to get the result back.
And some of those
operations will
take more than the expected
one millisecond maxTimeMS.
And therefore I will
get that error back.
From the application, we will
need to manage these timeouts.
And they are a
signal that we may
want to change our
settings, maybe having
less aggressive
timeouts for maxTimeMS
or do something about our query
that will not get into trouble
more than our SLA, for
example, will require.
So a few things that
we've learned today,
timeouts generate
some exceptions.
We've seen that.
Your application needs to be
ready to catch those timeouts.
So if your developers
come up to you
and say that they are
seeing those kinds of errors
and asking why,
you should explain
what those mean for
their application and how
they should be treating them.
And timeouts should be
set so they happen rarely,
so that your application
can respond properly.