We've been drawing diagrams
up until this point.
Let's see all of this in action.
I'll spin up a replica set
with three members in my VM.
Next, I'll run a script I
wrote to test write concern.
It performs a set of
writes, 10 by default,
with a write concern I
can specify using majority
by default. Let's run 100 tests
with write concern majority,
and see what the average time to
get our write acknowledged is.
That took an average
time of 2.6 milliseconds.
Pretty fast, but
that makes sense;
I'm just doing
this on local host.
Now let's see what happens
when I try to do this
with a write concern of four.
So that's good.
If I try to use a
write concern of four,
then it will throw this
write concern error --
Not enough data-bearing nodes.
So it knows that when I have
a three member replica set,
but want a write
concern of four,
that I'm asking
for the impossible,
and it will just tell me no.
The problem is that it's not
as obvious to your system
if one of your
servers is just down.
I'll disconnect, and
run my script again,
this time with a
write concern of three
and a wTimeOut of one second.
And as I can see it timed out
after that one second delay.
So, this wTimeOut will
let my replica set
know that it should throw
an error if it takes
more than a second to
replicate the data,
in this case to the three
members since W equals three.
Be aware that, if you don't
have that timeout set,
my write concern won't
even get that error.
And it just hangs, because by
default, there is no wTimeOut.
The application won't move
on without acknowledgment,
but it will wait for that
acknowledgement for as long
as it takes.
I'm going to use
control-C to kill this.
And just to be clear,
the write occurred,
it's just not getting to all
three servers as specified
in my write concern.
So, it's definitely
important to use a wTimeOut,
but as we'll see, we don't
want to set it too low either.
Let's use mlaunch to shut
down my two remaining servers,
and then restart the whole set.
Now, let's see how
long things take
for a write concern of three.
And let's see what
happens if I set
my wTimeOut to 1 millisecond.
Even on local host, it
can take more than one
millisecond in order for
a write to propagate.
Keep in mind, this
script uses W majority
by default, so, for a
three member replica set,
that's the same as W two.
For a wTimeOut of
2 milliseconds,
it looks like some of them went
through, and then one of them
failed on this machine.
Your results may differ.
What if I had a replica set
with two nodes plus an arbiter?
Let's change our
configuration and find out.
And let's connect.
When I look at my rs.conf, I
can see that my second member
has this arbiter only flag set.
That means it's an arbiter,
it's not carrying data.
Now what if a member goes down?
I've killed my secondary.
Let's run this with W
majority by default.
I lost just one server of what
I thought of as a three member
replica set, and what my write
concern thinks of as a three
member replica set.
I still have a primary, but it
can't handle W majority at all.
So what have we talked about?
We've discussed how arbiters
and delayed secondaries
can cause problems with write
concerns of greater than one.
We've talked about
the importance
of being mindful
of your majority,
and we've seen how this plays
out in action with wTimeOut.
And that's a quick tour
of unexpected problems
that can arise
from write concern.