OK.
So we see that
there's a correlation
between number of connections
and virtual size being
allocated.
That's fine.
So let's use a system
tool, in our case,
we're going to be using
free command which gives us
the indication of how is
our memory being used.
A particular command
that I really
like to use in conjunction
with free is watch.
In this case, I'm going to watch
this output every two seconds.
So I can see here, what's my
current utilization every two
seconds of my memory.
Which is great.
Right now, I have nearly
four gigabytes in total,
I'm using 1.2, and I have 2.73.
Awesome!
Once I run again my system
with the 600 different threads
in it, and if I
watch my free again,
I can see that the
values increase rapidly
and they stick with that
increase for a while.
So now instead of a few
1.2 gigabytes of memory,
I'm actually allocating
three gigabytes of data
because everything is
running on this same box.
Python will require memory
to launch all the processes.
MongoDB also runs on
memory, so we also
need some memory
to be allocated,
and then there's the per
connection allocation that will
be reflected on this increase.
Once the system
stops, after a minute,
we go back to 1.2
gigabytes of utilization.
Now if you're starting to
wonder if this is a good thing
or not let me reassure
you one thing,
this is not the normal behavior
for a well written application.
What we need to realize is that
for each connection that we
establish from our application
or from the threads
of our application,
will require memory.
And since everything in
our current demonstration
runs on the same box,
it will be allocated
on both sides, not only
on the MongoDB side
but also in the
application side.
So it's important to determine
how many connections you allow
your applications to
establish considering
that each connection
require resources
and when you have
a lot of them, they
can add up to a very
big number in terms
of resource requirements.
But I'm feeling bold so let's
not stick around with only 600,
let's go ahead and try
and push the envelope
to 2000 connections
and see what happens.
Now obviously our memory
keeps on increasing
at the dramatic stage,
and it would eventually
be running into a couple
of nasty situations.
Like, for example,
our processes not
being able to be
allocated because there
is no memory left.
This will be done on
the application side.
So next time we try to fork
the process and launch a new
process from our main script,
the make lots of connection
server, the OS will tell my
applications a no you cannot do
that go away and launches OS
error saying that there is no
memory available
for being allocated.
So if you don't manage it
well the requirements in terms
of your application
resources, especially memory,
and if you keep your
connections for a long time
without releasing them,
regardless of the paralyzation
that you want to do
in your application,
you might end up with problems.
Where the server does not
have any memory or that
your own MongoDB will
not be able to allocate
more connections
than what is feasible
for that particular box.
Now, there's a particular
setting of your system
that also interferes a lot
with the number of connections
that you will be able
to set from your MongoDB
and that's your ulimits.
Now MongoDB allows
you by default
to reach up to 65,536
connections per MongoDB
if only your system is
actually capable of doing so.
If your ulimits value
actually allows you to do so.
Let's check out
this particular box
that we've been using
the ulimits value.
To do that, we
just need ulimit-a,
give us all the different
ulimits that we can set up.
And in particular, one
that is quite important,
is my ulimits of open files.
And here I can only open
up to 1,024 different files
in this box for this
particular user.
This value will impact the
number of allowed connections
and the number of
collection and indexes
that our system will
be able to have.
Since every single connection,
index, and collection
will be a file for
MongoDB to operate with
or will be considered a file
that it needs to work with.
We will reach a limit
if we have a bunch
of different connections plus a
bunch of different collections
and a bunch of different
indexes operating
under the same MongoDB, under
the same user with this setting
of ulimits.
Now if I connect
to my MongoDB and I
look for my service
status and in particular,
the number of connections, I can
see a couple different values
here.
This MongoDB is allowed
to establish up to 800
in 18 different connections.
So the ulimits
configuration will
affect the number of
available connections
that your MongoDB will
be actually allowing
you to set regardless of
the default maximum value
and regardless of the number
of incoming maximum connections
that you set.
Given that we have
1,024, my MongoDB
will only have available
818 because there's
a bunch of other
files that MongoDB
needs to operate
with that also are
going to be reducing the number
of available connections.
But then again, I think that
818 is a very small number.
So what I'm going to do is shut
down my server for a second,
bring it down, I'm going
to change my ulimit value.
I'm going to set up the number
of allowed open files to 2,048
duplicating this amount, I'm
going to bring back my MongoDB,
and connect to get
into that instance.
Once I connect it, If
I do my server status
again looking for
the connections,
I can see that my available
connections are also
immediately increased as a
factor of the ulimits value.
So keep track of your
ulimits because this
might affect a lot the
amount of open files
that a given process
is able to establish
and therefore, limit your
connectivity of your system.