Apart from the make lots of
connections to servers file,
in the handouts of
this lesson, you're
also going to see this CFG file,
connections_singlenode file.
Make sure you also
place that into shared,
so we can use it from
our m312-vagrant-env box.
Once you have it,
the next step to do
is basically connect
to our bigger machine.
Once we are in our vagrant box,
let's just spin up a mongod,
passing on as parameter,
then -f and the configuration
file that we recently downloaded
from the lessons handout.
Now, what this script
does is sets up a mongod
that listens on port 27000--
27,000.
Now, it's time to connect
our super inefficient file,
our make lots of
connections to servers.py,
which, in turn, takes a
few parameters to operate.
As you can see here, we need
to specify a host, the ports,
and if we were using a
replica set name, and then
a number of connections.
OK, we can do that.
But before we do that,
let's open another tab,
and within our mongo
m312 vagrant box,
let's start our mongostat
to start capturing
some traffic on this box.
So we know that our mongod
is listening on port 27000.
And we know that
mongostat can do that.
Now, this is pretty,
pretty noisy over here,
so there's a lot of
different statistics being
collected that I'm probably
not that interested in.
Let's filter out some of that
by just outputting a few,
like the number of commands,
the number of dirty memory,
used memory, virtual size,
residence size, connections,
and the time stamp.
Once we do that, we are going to
get a much, much cleaner output
of our mongostat.
OK, let me jump
back to our main tab
where I can go ahead
and run my script,
my make_lots_of_connections
script.
We're going to connect
27000, and we're
going to launch 100
different connections.
Actually, we're
going to be launching
100 different processes of
this make lots of connections
to servers script.
Once I run this, and if I
go back to our mongo stats,
we will see that our dirty and
used memory are pretty low,
around 0%.
This is because we are not
really allocating any data
into our cache.
We're basically just
connecting to the instance.
However, on the virtual
size and the residence size
we do see a bit of a bump.
Once this script finishes,
and I can see here
is a drop between 102
connections to 2 connections,
there's been a slight
drop on the virtual size.
The residence size, however,
continues to be allocated.
We're going to see about
that in just a few moments.
So we've seen that there's
a bump on virtual size
and residence size.
Obviously, as well in the
number of connections.
So let's play around with
this a little bit more.
Let's go ahead,
instead of connecting
to 100 different processes,
let's put 200 in place.
Once I do that, I can see that
now I have a significant bump
again on my virtual size.
So connections do
occupy space in memory,
especially in virtual size,
but also in my residence size.
So there is, in
fact, an increase
in the amount of
memory that I need
to allocate some incoming
connections of my system.
So let's increase it
once more, the number
of processes and
connections that I'm
going to do to my server.
Let's bring it up to 600.
And here is something a little
bit odd that is happening.
Although I have
requested for 600,
the number of connections that
I see established to my mongod
does not increase more than 200.
Why is that?
What is going on?
Why such a low value?
By default, MongoDB allows
incoming connections up
to 65,536.
This is the maximum
amount of connections
that a single node
can establish.
But 200 is far from this value.
So what is going on?
Why my connections
value is only 200?
Let's get out of my mongostat,
and let's tail my log file.
OK?
I see that a lot of
connections ended.
Let's bring back our process
to life, again, to see
and capture what's going on.
All right, now my logs
are telling me a couple
of important messages here.
First of all, I'm
starting new threads,
and I'm getting
connections being refused.
This comes with a
nice message saying
that I'm refusing
connections because I may not
open more than 200.
Now, we know that the default
allows us to go to 65,000-plus
connections.
We probably can't afford to do
that on this virtual machine.
That's fine.
But 200 is still
a very low value.
So what can be the root
cause of this issue?
And this brings us
to a particular set
that I would like to
raise up-- how to detect
poorly configured hosts.
The first place to look for
would not be our log file.
It will probably be
our configuration file.
So let's have a look to
that /shared/connections
singlenode.cfg file that we are
currently using in our system.
Now, as you can see
here, we are artificially
capping the maximum amount of
incoming connections to 200.
So even if we have
an application trying
to establish more than 200
connections, those plus 200
will be refused, which is a
good thing, because we are
specifically saying
to the system,
hey, do not allow more
than 200 connections.
So you might
consider that what's
limiting our ability in this
particular case of establishing
more connections is
our own configuration.
So be aware of this
value if you're
trying to debug why your
application is not enabled
to provide more
connections than the ones
that you are seeing
through the mongostat.
So if we want to
get rid of that,
let's just remove the max
incoming connections to 200
from the configuration file.
Let's go into our mongod,
and let's shut down
the server in a clean fashion.
And let's bring our
along with you back again
with the new
configuration place.
Sweet, we now have removed
that limitation of 200
from our configuration file.
Let's bring our
mongostat command
back again so we can see that
now we have our mongod up
and running again.
And let's try again to
launch 600 connections
from this script.
Great!
We can see that our mongod
has 600 new connections
established.
And we see a bump, as well,
in the virtual size memory
allocation.
Now, my question to you guys--
is that a good thing?
Should we have close
to a gigabyte of memory
allocated for 600 connections
that literally are not
doing much?
They're just been established.
We're going to talk about
that on the following lesson.