Timeouts are one of those
things that sometimes are just
neglected, either
because we believe
that they are mythical
creatures that don't exist,
or because we don't think
they are very important.
But I can assure you, that they
are very, very real, and very
important.
Timeouts are not a
bad thing, per se.
They are actually a guarantee
that a given operation does not
take forever.
Either the communication
between one
node and another for the
network, or an operation
going on, or even just a
process calling a task,
like an IO task
or a network task,
or just calling
some other process
to do something that it needs.
In either case, timeouts
are not the problem,
they are guarantees.
However, when they
do happen, that
means that something
in our system
is not responding, or
taking longer than expected,
or longer than acceptable.
In a MongoDB cluster, there are
a few timeouts that can occur,
and they are reported in
the form of timeout errors.
We're going to have Server
Selection Timeout, which
can occur on our client side,
where no MongoDB server is
available after connection.
So if we have an established
connection to a MongoDB,
and we write, or do an insert
operation, but in the meantime
that node became
idle or not present,
or the network was
simply gone, we
will get back a MongoDB Server
Selection Timeout error.
WTimeout is a flag
of our write concern
that applications can set
to acknowledge writes.
We can use it to
specify that, given
an insert or write operation, if
we require that operation to be
confirmed by all nodes
involved in the W node flag,
if they do not comply within
the specified wTimeout,
a wTimeout error is sent back
within the response saying
well, you know what, we
tried, but we could not
comply with the timeout for
that write acknowledge across,
in this case, all three nodes
within two milliseconds.
Now that does not necessarily
mean that our write operation
did not complete it.
We will see about the
details in a few seconds.
Another time out that we can
set from the application side
is max timeout in milliseconds
parameter for a given cursor
operation.
While wTimeout is related
with write concern,
max time milliseconds is a
cursor operations parameter,
which means that if we
extend a given operation more
than the specified
max time ms, we
are going to get back
an execution timeout.
Our operation could not complete
on the expected maximum time
for it to be accomplished.
So if we have a connection,
percent in operation,
and if it doesn't complete by
then, we will get a timeout.
And finally, we have
a network timeout,
which occurs while a connection,
or even an instruction,
takes longer than the
admissible expected time
to complete at network level.
It can be related with
socket timeouts, networks,
impairments, some
wobbly switches
not deciding in due time what to
connect and when to connect to.
Those are generally out
of control of MongoDB,
they are mostly related with
network configuration itself.
But now let's see some of
these, especially wTimeout
and execution timeout in action.