MongoDB runs on a
distributed cluster.
A replica set is composed
by different hosts,
and inside those
hosts we're going
to have instances of mongod
that belong to a replica set.
The same applies to sharded
cluster which also can
be composed of different nodes.
Now any of these hosts
might have different ways
by which you can reach them.
They can have different NICs,
network interface controllers,
or network interface cards.
They can have
different DNS names
provided by a DNS server
inside of your network.
Or it also can have different
established, fully qualified
domain names also
established by your DNS,
or even just configured
on your host files,
a manual to find
list of addresses
that will contain which
IP address complies
with each machine name.
Now once we have a configuration
of a replica set where
one of the hosts is a primary
and then the following ones are
secondaries, if we don't
configure things well given
this set of different
names by which we can reach
the machines and the
different interface cards
that we might have in
our different hosts,
things can get a little messy.
And in this lesson,
we will be looking
to how to get us out
of a messy situation,
and how to identify clusters
which are poorly configured
given the different
ways that we have
to reach to those machines.
To help us out here with
the handouts of this lesson,
you will find this nodes
vagrant environment.
So go ahead.
I generally put
it on some folder
like this, where I have my
home folder, university,
the course I'm in, and obviously
all the handouts and material
that were made available.
So in this environment,
what I'm going
to have is three
different machines,
three different virtual
machines, each one of them
having a mongod in
them, and they all
belong to the same replica set.
If I connect one of the machines
and ask for the replica set
status, I can see
the fully configured
three-node configuration
of that replica set.
There will be a secondary,
a primary, and finally
another secondary.
Now the way that I'm
connecting to this machine
is by simply knowing an IP
address of one of the hosts
and connecting to
the default port.
Here we'll just ask
for the rs.status,
and that will give me the
status of the nodes that
belong to the replica set, which
include this particular machine
that I know of.
But I also know that
this particular node
belongs to M312, the
name of the replica set.
So a good way of
connecting to this machine,
or a proper way to
connect to this machine,
is by appending the
name of the replica set.
Therefore I will have the
list of different nodes
that belong to the
replica set, and I'll
be able to connect directly
to the primary machine
of that particular set.
So if I do so, I end
up in a bad state.
Here my local machine,
my local laptop,
is trying to connect to a
virtual machine that basically
doesn't know who it is.
I am able to connect
to one of the members
by a [? cell's ?]
direct connection.
But once I want to connect
using the replicas set,
since I do not know or I cannot
reach by the name defined
in the replica set,
the primary node,
I cannot establish
it during connection.
If I look into the
replica set status again,
and if I look for the
configuration of my primary,
I will see that
my primary node is
configured using
m2.university.mongodb
at port 27017.
For me to understand if
I can reach this machine
or not, by simply
pinging the box
I would be able to
check that I do not
in fact know who this node is.
And that will bring us to
the important question here.
How well should my local
machine be connected
to that replica set in place?
Do I need just one
node or should I
know all of the nodes of
the replica set in its own?
Because if I connect
directly to the node
that I know of, which
in my case is my m1 box,
and if I tried to connect
to my replica set,
I'm able to connect
with no frills.
System connects, all
things worked well.
If I use the machine
itself, my m1 itself,
I'm still able to be
correctly redirected
to the primary,
which in this case
is my m2 university.mongodb.
If I want one application to
be able to connect correctly
to this replica set
in place, it should
be able to connect to all
configured nodes of the replica
set itself, which in
this particular case
are configured by
their simple name, m3,
by their fully qualified
name, m2 university mongodb,
and even by their
own IP address,
in this case will be m1.
Now as you can see here,
these three different ways
which this host can be
reached can cause problems
for your applications
to connect to.
Because if one of the nodes
would eventually be primary
and I would not know
how to reach them,
my application will not
be able to connect to him
while a failover is taking
place or a new election
is taking place.