Another event that might
cause connections to drop
is the high availability
mechanism itself, especially
around elections.
When we elect a new
primary, something happens.
And you should, at the very
least, drop some corrections.
Let's see about that.
Replica sets exist to allow our
application to remain active
in case of server failure.
Once our primary
is disconnected,
either for maintenance or due
to unplanned system shut down,
our application is
capable of staying up
because there's an election
process in place where
a new member of the node
will become the primary.
And the application will
know who to connect to.
Now, there is something
that happens here
that the application
needs to be aware of.
The previous primary
is no longer available.
So you should know about it
and connect to the new primary.
So let's see this in action.
And let's simulate
in an environment
where we have a
replica set to do that.
First thing I'm going to do
is create a folder called,
conns replica set, or
connsrepl, in this case, where
I'm going to hold all the
data of my replica nodes.
Second step is to create the
replica set using a launch.
Then I'm going to
name here, conns.
And I'm going to
store all that data
in this newly created folder.
On a separate tab, I can
launch my mongostats with dash,
dash, discover to allow
me to connect to a node
and then discover
all the replica set,
or even shared member
that are affected
to this particular node
that I'm connecting to.
So here, once I
connect to this node,
I can see that there's
a repl status here
that allows me to know one
of these particular nodes
is a primary, another
secondary, another secondary.
Now what I'm going to
do is pick up my script
and create a connection
to this replica set.
So I'm seeing 600
different connections.
So I can see that all
my nodes are going
to be connected by this script.
If I go into the system and ask
for, who is primary right now,
I can see it's 27,000.
Once I know who my primary
is, which is 27,000,
I will tell it to step down.
So you will no longer
become primary.
You will relinquish that role
to another member of the set.
After we step down, we can
see that, in our application,
a few errors have been merged.
Now what the system will
tell us one of two things.
Either it will not
be able to complete
the operation it's trying to
do because this node is not
master.
So it will attempt
to run an operation
against the secondary.
So the previous machine was
a primary, no longer primary,
needs to reconnect.
But all in-flight
operations will either
get a not master
error or will get
an out to reconnect exception
on your client application.
By throwing you this not master
error or the out to reconnect
exception, is mode is
basically telling you,
hey, you are no longer
connected to a primary.
What do you want to do now?
All subsequent connections,
or instructions let's say,
will go through no problem.
Because the system will know
who to reconnect after getting
the first error message.
So the driver will take
care of that for you.
For all in-flight
operations, those
will need to be decided
by the application what
to do with them.
So look for those kind of error
messages from in your code
if you're a developer.
Or if you are dba, please
make sure your developers know
about this and not
assuming that mongodb
will handle all things related
with in-flight operations.
Again, mongodb will not
try to outsmart you.
One thing that we could do
is making our application
aware of the exceptions by
capturing those and doing
something about it.
In this case, we will
just need to say,
well I can handle
this no problem
since we are only reading.
But if you imagine
any right that
could appear within
this block of code,
we will need to know what
do we want to do about it.
Do we want to retry
the operation?
Do we just want to discard
it and try it later?
Or are we just not going
to be dealing with that?
Mongodb will not be smarter
than you on those situations.
It will let you decide
what you want to do.
Keep that in mind
for your application
building in a future.