Obviously a way to fix this
would be to edit my hosts file.
In this case, in
my local machine,
where I have my application,
which in this case
is just my mongo shell.
But it will serve
the same needs.
I will just need to make sure
that it knows how to identify
m2.university.mongodb.
And also m2 because
this is also something
that the machine will need
to know in the future.
But would that be enough?
Would just knowing
one of the nodes,
or two of the
nodes in this case,
and by the names and
configuration details
that are configured in the
replica set definition.
Would that be enough?
Well let's try it out.
Now I know I can
reach the machine
because I configured my
hosts file that responds
to m2.university.mongodb.
Let's test it out.
Yes I can.
Here we are.
We can connect.
Everything is great.
Can I reach it through, for the
previous IP address my m1 IP
address, which is also part of
the configuration of my replica
set.
In this case, I also can do
so because both of those IP
addresses are known.
But now let's see what happens
when the configuration changes.
So essentially what
we were setting up
in the previous
configuration was
that, although our replica
set is fully well configured,
in this case using the IP
address, in that other case
using the fully qualified
name, and this one using m3,
I would not know what m2
and its fully qualified name
would be looking like.
So it would effectively
be out of reach for those.
And once that machine
will be brought down,
if was a primary or
not, since I would not
be able to reach
those machines, I
could not failover to the
existing nodes, defeating
the purpose of having multiple
nodes for high availability.
If I only can reach one, if I
cannot reach the other members
of the node, then I don't have
any availability whatsoever.
Once I do add the
second member by adding
my fully qualified name of m2
and if I express my mongodb
URI, specifying more than
one member that I know of,
if one of them is down it will
try the other one to connect.
And if it can
understand what it is,
and how it's reachable
from the machines,
and if it's
configured properly, I
will be able to
establish a failover
operation to that new node.