One of the other
things that can happen
is, although one or two
machines can reach each other,
there might be a
misconfiguration
between two pair of nodes
in your replica set.
Let's see this in action.
Let's go ahead and
connect to my m1 box.
And let's do something weird
into the configuration.
Let's say to the system
that, instead of having m3,
I only know the machine by
its fully-qualified name.
Once I do this--
and if I connect to
the running host--
if I get a rs.status, I will see
that my configuration are all
up and running perfectly well.
So there's a majority of nodes
that know about each other.
Notice how I connect to the
machine using the replica set.
I'll get an information warning
stating, well, connecting
to this box, getting
address of m3 failed.
No name or service known to the
machine that I'm connecting.
This is from my own
m1 box, from whom
we removed the definition m3.
We just keep the
fully-qualified name here.
And once we try to connect to
[? ourselves ?] replica set,
we will see that there's an
error message, or a warning
message, saying, hey, watch
out I do not know who m3 is.
So look for errors
like those to make sure
that all of your nodes
can reach each other
and know about each other,
regardless of the way
that we configured them.
And obviously, if there's
an election in place,
like if we tell m2 to
step down, and relinquish
the primary role, if
we connect once more,
and if m3 is not reachable
by this local machine,
we will get into a
state where there's
no way we can elect a primary.
So basically, we end
up in the situation
where our primary gets
disconnected, or steps down.
We have a secondary that can
be reached by this old primary.
He knows about m3.
But this configured machine
does not know who M3 is.
So ending up in a situation
where we cannot elect,
because this node will
not know who that one is.
Let's avoid doing that.
So let's fix the
order of the world,
making sure that all nodes
know about each other,
and they are aware of
each other's IP addresses.
But if you think about it,
for example, in a cloud
environment, where machines
can be brought down,
and if we configure them
with their IP addresses.
And since that can be renewed,
you can get into a messy state
with machines that are in
the sets can be reached,
but not by their
current IP address,
or not by their old DNS
name, because they cannot be
identified exactly in the
same way they are configured
in their replicas
and configuration.
So we should have some
good practices in place,
or some best
networking practice.
All right.
Because that nodes should be
addressable from the client
host, and other
replica set hosts.
All mongoses in a
cluster should also
be addressable by all
client applications
into all replica sets.
We urge you to use DNS names
instead of IP addresses
to avoid IP address renew
resolution conflicts.
If we define good DNS
names to our machines,
it will be easier
to move those nodes
into other different hardware
physical boxes, which is OK.
If we use fixed IP
addresses, it might
be more tricky to move
those machines around.
And every time we renew
the IP address of a node,
we might lose accessibility
and readability from that node,
causing internal problems
in terms of configuration.
Make sure you use ping
and other networking
commands to reach
machines, and to make sure
that they can reach each other.
And use telnet as well to see
if the ports that we are using
are reachable, and they
are properly configured.
That's all we have for you in
terms of making sure your hosts
and cluster configurations
match, and are well set up.