OK.
Let's talk about
some issues that
can arise in the
context of sharding.
The most obvious
thing to keep in mind
is that after MongoDB 3.4,
you can have up to one
migration per pair of shards,
one sourcing the chunk and one
receiving it.
Here, we can see
exactly that happening.
And, if you have six
shards, you could
have as many as three
chunks in flight.
If three of your servers
have too many chunks
and the other three have too
few, one problem that can arise
is if you end up
getting jumbo chunks.
If a chunk grows large
enough without being split,
it becomes a jumbo chunk.
The sharded cluster
won't try to move it
as the chunk could be
in flight for too long.
MongoDB will also stop
trying to split the chunk.
Jumbo chunks often
come from having
a shard key with
insufficient cardinality,
meaning that there is no shard
key value it can split on.
By default, in a
sharded cluster,
the chunks should be
split at 64 megabytes.
Let's do an example.
We're setting up a sharded
cluster with three shards.
Each shard is a replica
set with three members.
Great.
Let's connect and
shard a collection.
We'll enable sharding and shard
on last name comma first name
for the example collection.
Great!
Let's look at sh.status.
So all of my data, such as
it is, is in a single chunk
but that chunk is empty.
Let's insert a
bunch of documents
all with the same shard key
and create a jumbo chunk.
I'm going to make the
documents one megabyte each
by creating a string that's
one megabyte in length.
OK.
So all of my data is
now in a single chunk
and it can't be
split because it all
has the same shard key values.
Let's look at sh.status.
There it is, one chunk.
Obviously, this
is a bad shard key
if I can do this, but let's
deal with some of the fallout.
We'll try adding some more data,
this time on a different value.
We'll use the name
Norberto Leite.
OK.
So now I have 200 documents
of about a megabyte each
and if I look at
sh.status, I can
see that I've still only
got one chunk on one shard.
All of my reads and writes are
going to hit this one shard
and none of them will hit
either of the other shards,
so I've got an imbalance.
Let's see what's going
on in our server logs.
OK.
I can see the sharded
cluster is starting out,
request split points.
If I scroll down
a bit, request it,
possible low cardinality key
detected in m312.example,
key is last name
Cross, first name Will.
OK.
So the server already knows
I have a bad shard key.
Now I've got a couple
of choices here,
I can try to manually split
the chunks, say with sh.splitAt
or I can increase
the chunk size.
First, I'm going to
split it manually.
Great.
Let's look at sh.status.
OK.
So now I have two chunks,
each of them are 100 megabytes
and I'm still not
balancing them.
They're both just
staying on my one shard.
To fix this issue, I'm going to
try to move a chunk manually.
And MongoDB is telling me
no, the chunk is too big.
OK.
Let's try to increase
the chunk size.
We can do this by modifying
the chunk size directly.
Usually, when we do
things like this,
we would use a helper function
but as of this recording,
we need to actually
modify the configdb.
Something that isn't to
be done lightly but it
is necessary in this case.
I'm going to set the
value at 150 megabytes.
Good.
Once again, let's
look at sh.status.
My chunks still
haven't migrated.
Let's do one more split to
wake it up and get it going.
And we'll look at sh.status.
OK.
And if I do that again, great,
three chunks and they're
distributed.
Now just to be clear, one of
those chunks contains no data
and I was able to
migrate my jumbo chunks
by changing my chunk size.
This isn't going to help if
I have a bad shard key like I
do here because I'll just
continue adding documents
to the shard key values, but
that's something you can do
in cases where you get stuck.
Now, let's create
a bunch of chunks
and let the cluster
distribute them.
Sh.status Whole lot of chunks
and it's distributing them.
And after a few moments, I
have a nicely balanced cluster
with 10, 9, and 9
chunks respectively
on each of those shards.
But of course, my data
isn't evenly distributed.
There's a great helper
function in the shell
to assist us with looking
at our data distribution.
It's called
db.collection.getshard
distribution.
Let's check it out.
OK, so what am I looking at?
Shard02 seems to have 200
megabytes, shard03 none,
total 200 megabytes, 200
chunks, there you go.
Shard02 contains 100% of
the data in the cluster.
I can use this
information to figure out
if I need to split
chunks on my own,
figure it out if I've got a
problem with my shard key, etc.
And that's how to look for
and fix some basic issues
in a sharded cluster.