OK, let's talk about something
that doesn't come up often,
but which does come up.
The interaction between
write concern and throughput.
When using write concern, which
you almost certainly should do,
the server must acknowledge
each write back to the driver.
That acknowledgement can
be delayed, or otherwise
not returned, for any
number of reasons,
but it's possible to create
cluster architectures that
can outright prevent
acknowledgement when
even a single server goes down.
It's also possible
to set things up
so that reasonable
delays in acknowledgement
result in errors.
Let's take a look.
In write concern, we
have a W parameter.
It specifies how
many servers need
to perform the write before
it gets acknowledged.
In write concern, we
have this W parameter.
It specifies how
many servers need
to perform the write before
it gets acknowledged.
The default write
concern is w: 1.
This means that the driver
receives acknowledgement
from the primary
once it, the primary,
has performed the write.
This is acceptable
for some use cases,
but it's mathematically
possible for that server
to go down before the write has
made it to any other servers.
In cases where the
application needs
to be robust against any
single point of failure,
it's necessary to use a
write concern of two or more.
Under almost all such cases,
the preferred write concern
is majority.
This ensures that acknowledged
writes will be durable,
except in cases where you lose
a majority of your servers.
Note that I'm being very
precise about my language.
It doesn't necessarily
guarantee that your writes will
get acknowledged, even if
your primary, which requires
a majority of votes, is up.
At least not for all
architectures, as we'll see.
By the way, I'm going to
focus on write concern,
but this applies to
read concern as well,
for architectures that use it.
Let's dig in a little deeper.
Starting with w: 1.
First, our driver
sends out a write,
then the server
performs the write,
but the acknowledgement
hasn't yet been sent.
This situation
doesn't last long,
because the acknowledgement
is sent back
as fast as the server
can make it happen.
When acknowledgment
occurs, the data
could be in this state
written to just your primary,
or perhaps it's made it
to one of the secondaries
by the time it
gets acknowledged.
I'm just showing you all of the
possibilities for completeness.
Now, what if the write
concern is majority?
Now things get a little
more interesting.
For a three member
replica set, a majority
means two copies of the data,
each on different servers.
So a write has to propagate
beyond the primary,
and then that fact has
to get communicated back
to the primary before
it can be acknowledged.
So, after we write
to the primary,
the secondary
performs the write,
then the secondary
lets the primary know
it's got the write, and then
the primary can acknowledge
that write to the driver.
Obviously, it could go to
the other secondary first,
or to both.
Now what if there's a partition?
It still works fine, because
it has the other secondary.
So, a network partition,
or a secondary going down,
won't cause much of a
problem, in and of itself,
for this vanilla setup.
Obviously, things get even
more complicated when you're
dealing with, say, a
five member replica set,
and a write concern of
majority, but we're not
going to go into that
level of detail here.
OK, so that's a description
of how things generally
work in vanilla replica sets.
Now we'll talk about
what can go wrong.