I'm going to connect to my
Vagrant box, my m312 vagrant
environment, and I'm going
to launch a replica set
that I'm going to call
timeouts with three nodes
and where their data sets
will going to be specified
on this folder that I
just created as well,
called timeouts and
starting on port 27000.
Once my replica
set is initiated,
I'll connect to one of
the nodes and express
the following command.
Here, I'm going to insert
this document, Hello World,
with a write concern expecting
three nodes to acknowledge this
write within one millisecond.
So anything that
takes more than one
millisecond, I will come back
with an error saying hey,
I could not confirm that three
nodes of your replica set
were able to acknowledge the
write within one millisecond
in total.
So if I do so,
and since I'm very
bullish about this
expected timeout,
I actually get back a
write concern failed
error saying well you
know what we tried
but we were not able to get
the confirmation within one
millisecond that all
three nodes actually
got that write operation.
Now this happens because we
just launched our replica set.
Everything is in the same box
but once we launch and write
something to that
newly boot up MongoD,
it will need to do
a couple of things
like writing into an index
or creating index files
into the collection files.
So those probably are
going to take more than one
millisecond alone.
Therefore, I can not
guarantee that that
write was acknowledged by three
nodes within one millisecond.
That would be pretty
awesome, wouldn't it?
If I try the exact same
instruction, new document
with the same set of parameters,
but after all the files have
been initialized and all, I will
actually be able to insert it.
Once everything is
initialized and I
have everything up and
running, actually, the nodes
are able to communicate
back that they acknowledged
the writes below one
millisecond, which
is pretty awesome.
The important thing
here is that we
need to make sure
we understand what's
going on under the covers.
As I can see here, I
attempted three inserts
and got all of them, is
that although I was not
able to confirm that all three
nodes were able to acknowledge
below one millisecond,
the write is still
acknowledged in the primary.
We will always notify you
back to the application saying
what you expected was
not able to be met.
But, that doesn't mean that
the write will be rolled back
or will not succeed on
the primary nodes or even
the secondary
nodes, it just means
it doesn't succeed within the
time I'm expecting the system
to comply with.
So, if by anytime
your developers
start seeing messages
like this, make
sure they realize
what is going on
and be assuring them that
the data is safely stored
in the primaries at least, just
that their expectations are not
able to be met.
And let's not get confused
by some other aspect
of this write concern which is
not related with the w timeout
itself.
Let's go ahead and connect to
one of the secondary nodes that
is listening on port 27001 and
let's shut down this server.
And let me connect back
to my test database
where I was inserting my data.
In this case, the
message will be the same
but even if we increase
the w timeout, just
let's say 100
milliseconds, we will still
get write concern failed
within the replication timeout.
This is only due to the fact
that if one of our nodes
is completely down,
it is impossible,
regardless of the number
of w timeout value
that we set, to comply back
because until it gets up
and running probably,
it will be more time
than 100 milliseconds.
A slight variation will be to
request a number of nodes that
pure and simply isn't there.
In this case, we can not satisfy
concern will be sent back
because there's not enough
data bearing nodes to actually
comply with our request.
Our data will still be stored
in the primary and all living
secondaries but regardless
of the w timeout.
We are expecting
more nodes than what
our current configuration
of the replica set
has in terms of
data bearing nodes.
So this will not be satisfied
not because of the w timeout,
but because we are requesting
something that's purely simply
not possible.
These are the kind of errors
that your developers might see
in a production environment.
Make sure they
understand clearly
what those messages refer of
and how they can deal with those
from the application side.
Now that we've seen
what w timeout is,
let's look into
another nice timeout
error that can be controlled
and set by the application.