By the way, what about a query
that doesn't use the shard key.
Let's create another
index and query on it.
We'll create our index
on user.phonenumber.
We'll do a little query
that doesn't use an index
and which gives us a
phone number initially.
We'll run a query that
counts the number of users
with that phone number.
OK, we're going to
find a phone number.
There we go.
OK, so we're going to create
an index on user.phonenumber.
We're going to find a
single phone number.
And we're going to count
the number of users
with that phone number.
And it's just the one.
All right, let's
look at index stats.
Here, I'm querying just for
the phone numbers statistics.
And I can see that I
have accessed it twice--
one actually in
querying that first time
to get our phone
number, and then
a second time for
that phone number.
You can see these queries
hit all of our shards.
So even though I only wanted
one document which is only
on one server, the query
hit every single one
of my servers, which it
has to because this query
doesn't use the shard key.
It's a scatter gather query.
We don't know which
shard has the document.
So for queries that
don't use the shard key,
you can just count
the number of times
they appear on any server.
If it hits one,
it hits them all.
The moral is that if
you're using index stats,
you need to keep
track of servers,
even for a replica set
because you want to know
when your primary steps down.
For sharded cluster, it's
even more complicated,
and you really need to be aware
of what it is you're measuring.
You have to know,
for each query,
how many servers it hits.
This is simple for exact
match queries on a shard key
where it hits only one server.
And it's also simple for
scatter gather queries which
have to hit all the servers.
Range-based queries
on the shard key
though can hit one,
many, or all servers.
OK, what have we learned?
Well, we've learned
how to use index stats
and look at the
accesses.ops field
to see what queries are
hitting what indexes.
We've also learned how
to be careful of the host
field for replica sets.
And we've learned that
for charted clusters,
a query can be executed by
one, several, or all servers.
And that's how you
use index stats.