In this lesson, we'll be
talking about a set of tools
that you should be aware
of when debugging issues
with your MongoDB deployment.
The set of tools is
called the Mtools package.
Mtools was developed by
our support team, started
by our very own
Thomas Ryeckstiess
to analyze and debug issues
with MongoDB deployments
in an easy and elegant way.
It's use to identify
and reproduce
issues that arise in customers
production deployments.
This set of command line tools
is made available publicly,
but they're not supported by
MongoDB Inc. Mtools is not
part of our official
offering, but it
is a set of tools and scripts
that we maintain and develop
to help individuals
analyze and debug issues
that they find in
MongoDB deployments
and it's open source.
You're welcome to use
them for [INAUDIBLE],
generate pull requests
if you make improvements
to the tool kit.
Mtools is written
in Python, so you'll
need to have Python
installed on your machine
to run its associated scripts.
The package is available
through common Python package
management tools, like
pip and Easy Install.
The course VM will come
with them already installed.
The set of tools are,
first, mlogfilter.
This tool slices
log files by time,
combines them, filters for slow
queries, finds table scans,
shortens log lines,
filters by attributes,
and converts your log
entries into a JSON format.
Next up is mloginfo,
which returns
information about log files--
things like start and end
times for the log, the MongoDB
version, and special sections,
like restarts, connections,
and distinct accounts of common
events found in the logs.
There's also
mplotqueries, queries
which we can use to
visualize log files
with different types of plots.
This tool requires that you
install additional graphics
libraries.
These may not be
trivial for your system.
This is mlogvis, which creates
a self-contained HTML file that
shows an interactive
visualization in a web browser
as an alternative
to mplot queries.
For the course VM, you can
send this to the shared folder
and access the HTML
file on your computer
where you can then view
it in a web browser.
We'll see that later.
One of my personal
favorites is mlaunch,
a script to quickly spin up test
deployments on your local host,
including replica sets
and charted clusters.
This requires PyMongo,
the Python driver
library for MongoDB, which I've
also pre-installed on your VM.
One of the really interesting
ones from a testing standpoint
is mgenerate, which
creates data sets
with random data based
on a template for testing
and reproducing issues.
All of these tools together
will help analyze, simulate,
and debug issues with
MongoDB deployments.
We'll be using these tools
throughout the course
when looking at
concrete use cases.
In essence, you can associate
each individual tool
with a specific feature at
a specific point in time
in the creation of a scenario.
Mlaunch will bring
up very quickly
clusters and deployments
for developing and testing
on your local machine.
And mgenerate will allow
us to produce server loads
in a test environment that
will mimic a production load.
This will insert one document.
By providing a
simple JSON document,
we can then generate many
documents of a given shape
to be inserted
into a collection.
The idea is to produce
these data sets
in a very simple
one-line instruction
command with an easily
reproducible data set.
Mlaunch and mgenerate are tools
designed to either simulate
or get a very close
approximation of situations
we might want to debug.
Think of these two as
our debugging tools
from the package.
On the other side of things,
mlogfilter, mloginfo,
mplotqueries, and mlogvis will
help us to analyze log files.
Once we've got a
log file, we can
filter for relevant
information with mlogfilter,
plot and visualize the
execution of given commands
and operations, and
retrieve information
from the logs on specific events
like restarts, connections,
and others.
These four tools can be
seen as diagnostics tools.
We can get general
information with mloginfo.
Select only a subset
of the components
to analyze with mlogfilter.
Notice that all of
these entries now
have the replication component.
And we can plot and visualize
the execution of operations
with either mlogvis
or mplotqueries.
We won't bother to
look at that now.
I haven't done anything
interesting yet with a MongoDB.
Obviously, since all of
these are command line tools,
we can also construct pipelines
to visualize filter and group
outputs from the
different tools.
In short, the Mtools package
is a great set of easy helpers
that we will utilize
throughout the course.
You should definitely have
all of them at your fingertips
to analyze debug and
even reproduce issues
detected on your deployments.