Let's get a sense of
the tools we're going
to be using in this course.
When we look at
scenarios going forward,
this will be a basic
set of MongoDB tools
that we'll use to figure
out what's going on
and what we need to
do to fix things.
These tools are
the main ones you
should go to when
a problem arises,
and if you'll be diagnosing and
debugging problems in MongoDB,
you'll want to be
familiar with all of them.
First, let's look
at the server tools.
When I say server tools, these
are some helpware programs
that come with MongoDB.
The list includes the
following programs--
mongostat, which shows incoming
operations in real time;
mongotop, which
lets us know which
collections we're spending time
reading from and writing to;
mongoreplay, a very useful
tool, which is used to monitor,
record, and replay
network traffic
for diagnostic and
debugging purposes;
and last but not least, mongo,
our administrative shell,
which is the main command
line administration interface
of MongoDB.
You've already been
using it to learn
some of the basics
of MongoDB, and we'll
be showing you some of the
functionality that can help you
with diagnostics and debugging,
including information
about your indexes, the
state of the server,
and finding and managing
long-running operations.
We'll also be using the
database profiler, which
logs queries for us,
as well as MongoDB
Compass, our graphical
user interface, which
can be used to look at the
current state of your database,
and also has its own tools
to help you explore what's
happening on your server in
terms of real-time performance
metrics.
We'll also be using
a suite of programs
that fall under the name
of mtools, a public GitHub
repo created by our very
own Martin Rueckstiess.
These tools give you the
ability to spin-up replica
sets and sharded clusters
locally for testing purposes,
and also include a number
of log analysis tools
to help you find issues, and
workload generation tools that
can help with load testing.
Finally, while we won't be
able to spend time on them
in this course,
you should at least
be aware of MongoDB
Cloud Manager and Ops
Manager, the MongoDB solutions
for cluster management.
If you're interested, you
can take our sister course--
M122.
You'll find a link
in the lecture notes.
In this chapter, we're
going to give you
an overview of these
important tools.
Later on, we'll dive
deep into each of them
while we're exploring
simulated issues.
Let's get started.