Let's take a look
at a marvelous tool
that many databases including
MongoDB have built in--
the profiler.
Technically, the profiler
isn't so much of a tool
as it is a mode that your
MongoDB database can be running
in and when in this
mode the server will
store every operation
that it sees
coming in into that database.
These operations
will be written into
the system.profile collection,
a capped collection.
Its size is 1
megabyte by default,
and it will store one
document per operation.
The profiler is off by
default because having it on
can be quite expensive.
It turns every read
into a read plus
insert, and every write query
into a write plus insert.
Unless your production
server is very
overpowered for
its workload, you
should be very
cautious about turning
the profiler on as it can
quickly overpower your server
with writes, helping to saturate
your I/O. So don't leave it on.
That said, it can be very
useful for a limited time
in order to figure
out what's going on.
We'll go into the administrative
shell to see this.
This is a command to tell us
what profiling level we're at.
Right now, we're at zero, which
means that the profiler is not
capturing any queries.
At level 1, we would
capture any queries
that take longer than
100 milliseconds.
That's useful, but keep
in mind that we already
capture some information on
those queries in the server
logs.
At level 2, however,
we capture every query.
This can be quite useful.
We can find out the actual
load we've got coming in,
for example.
Keep in mind that
as of MongoDB 3.4,
Mongo replay is another way
to capture those queries.
But for now, let's check
out the profiler in action.
So my profiler is
now set to level 2.
If this were a
production server,
it would now be writing
massive amounts of inserts--
one per query it gets.
Now let's exit and create
a small workload for it.
Here's a script I
wrote to do just that.
It builds an index and then
performs this loop 100 times.
Each time, it performs
several operations--
inserting, reading,
updating, and deleting.
This isn't a very realistic
workload simulator,
but it's just to illustrate
what we're doing.
Not all of the queries will
find a document, by the way.
They may look for a
document that we've deleted.
OK.
Let's run it.
And as always, let's be sure
to set the profiling level back
to zero.
OK.
Now let's see what we've got.
So our 100 loops involved 2
inserts, 2 finds, an update,
and a delete each.
That gives us 600
documents, and I see 601.
Let's see what these
entries look like.
That's a lot to parse so
let's take a look at some
of the more important fields.
Scrolling up, we
see this op field.
This one's an insert.
Let's look at what we've done
by grouping these operations
together with the
aggregation pipeline
and see how many
of each we've got.
So there are
different operations,
each of them counted up.
There is also a command there.
Let's see what that was.
Ah, this was the
drop command that we
did when we were done inserting
documents and reading.
Now if we look just at
our queries with op query,
we have a number of
interesting fields.
You can see that we're
capturing some execution
stats for each query.
Our plan summary is
another interesting field
as this will tell us whether
or not we're using an index.
This was a collection scan.
Let's iterate over our documents
and see what the plan summary
looks like for each.
And sure enough,
we're alternating
between using an index
and not using an index.
We'll go deeper into
the profiler later on,
but for now, that's
how you use it.
Also, remember that
turning on the profiler
will add an insert operation
to the capped collection
for every read or write.
So I've been asked
by our support team
to remind you to always
remember to turn it off
in production environments.