let's look at MongoDB cloud manager
here's the landing page there are a
number of automation monitoring and
backup features that cloud manager and
ops manager use and as a knowledgeable
DBA you should be aware of them most of
the monitoring features by the way are
things that you could write a script to
do using server status calls to the
database plus some system tools
obviously you can also perform your own
backups security etc however all of
those are much easier to do with cloud
manager and ops manager in this lesson
I'll be focusing on the monitoring
features that our server management
tools provide some of these features can
also help you to see problems before
they arrive in this lesson we're going
to do a quick signup and look at what's
available so that you're aware by the
way I'll briefly mention the
similarities and differences between
cloud and ops manager both use
monitoring backup and automation in the
same way the only difference is that if
you're using cloud manager MongoDB
stores your encrypted backups and hold
your metadata on a combination of our
hosted servers and AWS if you're using
ops manager then you have full control
over the data and metadata on your own
infrastructure no one else sees anything
ok let's do this
here's the landing page I can sign up
for a cloud manager or Atlas here I'll
sign up for a new account once I've put
in my information and agree to the Terms
of Service I can continue I'll create a
group name and it's setting up my
account now I can deploy a cluster
either on my hardware or out in the
cloud but I'm going to show you how to
do it locally I'll build new deploy
locally and create a replica set I'll
name it and continue so let's talk about
backups backups are an important part of
the DBAs job but I'm just looking at
Diagnostics and debugging information
today so I'm going to skip that next I'm
going to install an automation agent
once running this agent will spit up my
deployment for me I'm going to do this
on my VM so
all download the ubuntu 14
I'll go into the VM install the package
edit the config file
create my data directory give it
appropriate permissions and start the
agent at this point I click verify agent
to be sure it's connecting to our cloud
manager servers and when I see agents
verified I know I'm good to go