In this lesson, we're going
to talk about the MongoDB
shell, also known as Mongo.
It comes with the
MongoDB software package.
For this course, we assume that
you're familiar with the shell,
most likely because
you've already been using
it to learn about MongoDB.
But in a nutshell,
the Mongo shell
is our default server command
line administration tool.
From the Mongo
shell, we can perform
any administrative command
that MongoDB provides.
This includes
things that will be
useful from a diagnostics
and debugging perspective.
Throughout the course, we'll
be using the Mongo shell
for many tasks, including
things like analyzing
queries, enabling profiling,
and changing server settings.
Another interesting
aspect of the shell
is the fact that we
can write JavaScript
that can be used to automate
administrative tasks.
We do have other tools
that provide or build
on this functionality
like Ops Manager,
but the Mongo shell remains
a powerful low-level tool
that can help in
finding and solving
many of the administrative
tasks that you face.