OK, this mgenerate_userdata.json
is going to be passed
to mgenerate, and it's going
to create some user data based
on this document here.
Let's make it happen.
And wait a few minutes
for it to finish.
That only took a few seconds.
OK, let's connect.
OK, I'm in the right database.
Let's look at our index
stats before we do anything.
OK, so this is a
lot of information.
We have four shards,
and each index
is represented on each shard.
So even though we only
have two indexes on _ID
and user.name.last, it's
giving us eight documents--
one per index on each server.
And we haven't done
any queries yet,
so the ops field is 0 for each
of these 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0,
0.
Good, let's run a query.
We'll find a document
using the shard key.
OK, and we'll look
at the index stats.
OK, so the ops remain 0 for
the _id field and 0 for most
of the servers.
But this server on port
30001 has run the query
and touched that index.
That was an exact match query,
and it hit only one chunk.
And my router knows
it's only on one server
and routed to the
appropriate server,
but that won't
always be the case.
Let's do a range query.
User.name.last is less
than or equal to d.
Get my results, and we
will look at index stats.
Once again, our _id ops are
still 0 but 1111 for this
user.name.last.
What happened was this
query actually touched
the other three shards that
hadn't seen the first query.
That's just a coincidence.
The important thing is that
three servers had chunks
that match the query, and
all three of those servers
incremented their ops
counter for that index.
A range query like this
can touch one, some,
or all of your servers depending
on what the chunk ranges are.