Now, the nice thing about
index stats is that it's free.
It's done by the
server automatically,
and it includes a surprising
amount of data about my access
patterns.
Let's look at that full
index stats document again.
We'll eliminate our project
stage, and there we go.
So one of the
things you'll notice
is that we have this
host field here,
seems to be the same for
all three of my indexes.
Why are we putting that
in every single document?
Well, the problem is that I
might have servers go down,
and a secondary
will become primary.
Suddenly, all of our counters
start out at some other number,
because each server looks
at its own ops independently
and counts them up.
Let's see this in action.
OK, my primary is
now a secondary.
I happen to know that
the server on port 30001
will be stepping up.
And sure enough,
it's now primary.
And I'll look at those index
stats, and what do you know,
the ops are 0 for each
of my three indexes.
That's because I haven't
performed any queries
on this server on port 30001.
All right, so that's bad
enough for a replica set,
but things get really
interesting when we're
dealing with a sharded cluster.
Now that you're familiar with
the basics of index stats,
let's make it even
more interesting.
We've stopped our set.
Let's blow away
our data, and let's
create a sharded cluster
with four shards, each
with three replica sets.
We'll connect to our
MongoS, and let's do
some interesting stuff.
We're going to use mgenerate
to create some data,
and this might take
a little while.
It's not terribly efficient.
I don't want a bunch of chunks
moving around on their own
very slowly, so let's start
by sharding our collection
and pre-splitting
some of the chunks.
We'll create an index and
shard that collection.
Create the index,
shard the collection.
And I'm going to write a little
script to pre-split my data.
To find a variable I'm going
to use, pre-split my data,
and when I look at
sh.status status,
initially, all of my
chunks are on one shard.
And a few moments later,
it started to move around.
Several seconds later,
they're evenly distributed.
Great, let's disconnect
and create some data.