Two useful database methods are
dB.currentOp, and dB.killOp.
Let's go into the shell and
take a look at currentOp.
First, we'll spin
up our cluster--
great.
We'll go into the shell,
and we'll run currentOp.
This is a large document,
so let's scroll to the top.
CurrentOp will tell you
what the server is doing,
that is, what its
current operations are.
You can scroll down
to this inprog array,
and you can see that each
operation has its own document.
The document tells you
all kinds of information
about the operation, but let's
focus on just a few fields.
First, you've got this
"seconds running" field.
That'll let you know how long
the thread has been operating.
Here, it's basically zero.
Next, you've got
this "op" field,
which is telling us that
we're looking at a command.
And you've got your "opID"
field, which is a number.
If you have an operation
that's running for a long time,
and you'd like to
kill it, you can
pass that opID to dB.killOp.
let's do an example.
I'm going to need three
shell connections to do this.
So let's open up a few
terminal tabs and VagrantSSH
on each of them.
OK, so now I have one,
two, three shell instances
connected, and I'm
back at the first one.
I've written this
function, insertDocs,
and what it's going to do
is it's going to hammer
the database with inserts.
Each document containing a
string full of filler text.
Each document is going to be
just a hair over 80 kilobytes,
and most of that is
just this filler field.
Let's get it started.
We'll let that run
for a few seconds,
and then we're going
to do a find query
that is really inefficient.
Let's go to a different shell
terminal and run it there.
All this function
is going to do is
it's going to run this find
query, which uses regex.
It's going to search
for the ASDF string
somewhere in that
big filler field,
and it's not going to find it.
I have this little
try except clause,
so that we can print out
the error that we get,
and that's all that it does.
Let's start it up.
While those are going on--
our document insertion
and our query--
I'm going to go to a third
connection to the database,
and I'm going to
use dB.currentOp.
OK, I have this "op"
query on this namespace.
It's a collections scan,
filler ASDF, regex.
Great, it's been
running for 29 seconds,
and it's opID is 25963.
Let's kill it.
OK, and if I go back to my
query, that long-running find
is no longer being executed.
Instead, I've got this
"operation was interrupted"
error, and the query is done.
And that's how you use
currentOp and killOp.