One of the cool new
features of Compass
is the ability to see real
time performance statistics
for the node I'm connected to.
And so if I click on
the Performance tab
up at the top
here, what I'll see
is I actually get four
charts presented back
to me in the interface
that represent
key metrics that are occurring
on the MongoDB server
right now.
And so you can see
in the top chart here
we actually have an
Operations chart.
It's made up of inserts,
queries, updates,
deletes, commands,
and get mores.
And then we have a chart that
represents read and write
load on the server plus any
network load or memory usage
on the machine.
On the right-hand side here
what we see is two tables.
One represents the hottest
collections in the server
right now, and we'll
see for example
that actually a MongoDB
database and fan club
collection is at 0% usage.
This is a test box and
there's no traffic going on
on this machine right now.
But if there were you would see
a percentage increase of read
and write traffic
displayed on this bar here.
If there are any slow operations
going on on the server,
they'll be listed here, too.
And what we effectively
see is the output
from DB dot current up, which is
a core server internal command
that you can run to get an
understanding of any operations
that are occurring at
that time on the server.
And they'll be displayed
here in a table form,
and you'll be able to see
the type of operation,
whether it's a query or a
insert, and the operation ID,
and specifically what
the operation is.
You'll notice that the
data in these charts
moves fairly quickly.
These charts represent
roughly about 30-second window
of metric collection.
Now it may be that we
see a spike that we
want to drill into,
and we may want
to drill into it before we see
it disappearing off the window.
What we can do is actually
hit the Pause button
in the top right up
here to pause the charts
from adding any more data points
in before our spike ages out.
And when we're ready
we can actually
hover over and take
a look, and you'll
notice there's a trend line
down between all the charts
to indicate that this moment
in time was happening.
And we can take a
look, see if there's
anything interesting for
us to take a look at there.
When we're ready we can go
ahead and click Play again,
and the charts will simply catch
back up to the present time.