now we're going to look at a stage in
the aggregation pipeline that's very
useful index stats first let's spin up a
replica set from our VM and connect next
let's insert a couple of documents we'll
also need some indexes as you probably
inferred from the lesson title great now
suppose we've got a production system
it's going along and we want to know
which indexes we're using we have a
number of options we could turn on the
profiler but that's got some big
downsides especially in production I
could use Mongo replay but that's going
to take a long time to set up and it
might be overkill because I'll have to
explain all of my queries anyway the
logs only help for long-running queries
what I really want is a tool that we
built into the aggregation pipeline
index stats this will tell us what
indexes are getting touched and how
often let's take a look okay so here's
our output what are we looking at well
we've got three indexes and we can see
one document per index in each we have
the indexes name we have the key we have
the host we're on and then we have this
interesting field accesses this shows us
how many times we've accessed the index
for as long as the server has been
keeping track the relevant number is
this ops subfield and the value is
currently zero
it's zero because I haven't yet accessed
any of these indexes you can see that
it's zero for all three of them let's do
a query that uses the underscore ID
field and let's also use the features of
the aggregation pipeline to just look at
the interesting stuff found my document
and here's the aggregation I'm going to
do I'm going to just look at the key and
the accesses ops field okay and we have
one two three documents that middle
document on underscore ID is all in one
line but you can see that for the
underscore I
d field we now have an OPS of one rather
than zero that's from that fine one that
I just ran what if I do a query that
doesn't find any documents well that
still use the index so ops was
incremented yet again what if I do a
collection scan well that didn't use any
of my indexes so it didn't increment the
ops field that's a good limitation to
keep in mind index stats is not going to
help me find collection scans for any
reasonable workload however you
shouldn't be having collection scans and
if you do have them most likely they're
going to be appearing in the logs by the
way this counter starts at zero when the
server process starts up or if the index
doesn't yet exist it starts when the
index gets built if we look at the
accesses since field we can see when
these indexes were built