The MongoDB download comes
with a set of different tools,
apart from the obvious
MongoD and MongoS binaries.
I've downloaded the tarball
for the distribution
into the shared directory.
Let's unpack it and
see what's there.
We can find tools to
import and export our data,
like mongoimport
and mongoexport.
We can also have tools like
mongodump and mongorestore,
which import binary format
data files and export them.
We've got bsondump, which
converts BSON dump files
into more human readable
JSON, and mongouplog,
which allows us to pull
a replica set uplog
and apply it to a local server.
There's also a helper tool
for GridFS called mongofiles.
But more important
for this course,
we have server diagnostic
tools, mongostat, mongotop,
mongoreplay, mongoperf,
and mongoldap.
Mongoldap allows us to validate
the ldap configuration settings
for our MongoD.
You point it at an LDAP
server, either directly
or by pointing it to a
MongoDB configuration file,
so it can test the
connectivity and validation
of the configuration
against a given LDAP server.
This tool is used only
to validate and diagnose
LDAP configuration issues.
You can learn more about it
in our security course M310,
so I won't go into it here.
Mongoperf is a
performance testing tool.
This tool tests your server's
disk I/O performance.
Given a set of conditions
reflected in a config file,
the tool will subject your
server to an I/O test.
This tool has limited
reach and should
be used only for basic I/O
assessments of your disk
subsystem.
Take any results
with a grain of salt.
This test may show how much
I/O per second your disks
are capable of
doing under a very
specific set of conditions.
But in real world
situations, other operations,
like rebalancing indexes,
navigating b-trees,
and allocating resources to
other applications running
in your server can affect
your disk performance.
And mongoperf can't
fully measure the effect
of those other factors.
Next up is mongoreplay,
a network diagnostics
and analysis tool.
It allows us to do
three important things,
monitor, record, and playback
network traffic for analysis
and debugging purposes.
This is an excellent
tool that allows
QA teams to test
production traffic
and see how it changes
in the deployment,
like different hardware,
different cluster
configurations, and different
choices of storage engine
will affect performance.
After the fact
analysis of events
for debugging purposes,
or even fault injection,
can be done by capturing
traffic and later
replaying it to understand the
system tolerance to failure.
Let's spin up some servers.
And mongoreplay is going to need
some extra privileges in order
to do its job, so we'll
sudo this command.
Using mongoreplay, we can
see the traffic exchange
between our MongoD primary
and the other servers
in the replica set.
We would also see
network traffic
to a shell or
application via a driver.
We'll see more about MongoDB
replay later in the course.
And finally, we have
our two classic server
diagnostic tools,
mongostat and mongotop.
Here's mongostat.
It's a real time
statistics tool.
The font is big enough that
it's wrapping on the stream,
but you get the idea.
It provides quite an
overview of the stats
of a currently running MongoD
or MongoS per time interval.
By default, it's
sampling once per second.
We have inserts, queries,
updates, deletes, and others.
It's also capable of providing
a global view of the statistics
on all servers in a
cluster by specifying
the minus minus discover flag.
The way mongostat
works is it connects
to the servers it's monitoring,
periodically sending the server
status command,
parsing the results,
calculating the difference
between the relevant values
in the server status documents
during each sampling interval,
and printing it out
for later use to see.
Mongotop does a
very simple analysis
of the time consumed per second
on different name spaces.
This tool measures
the amount of time
spent reading, writing,
and their total aggregate
per sampling unit,
default one second,
on the various
different name spaces.
It's a nice tool to get a
sense of what type of work load
is hitting the different
databases in collections.
Maybe you have some
with more reads, some
with more rights, et cetera.
Right now, I'm not
doing anything,
so everything is zero.
So those are the server
tools we use for analysis.
No single tool is usually
going to be enough to give us
a good diagnosis of a problem,
so we'll use multiple tools
when we look at a
problem in order
to form hypotheses,
and either validate,
or reject them as appropriate.