In this lesson, we'll be looking
into the server status command.
Service status does a lot.
It's used under the hood of
several tools and services
that help manage and
monitor a MongoDB instance.
Tools like Cloud Manager,
and Ops Manager, Compass,
and MongoStat, all
use this command
to create snapshots or real
time series data of the instance
utilization and status.
Server status is a MongoDB
administrative command
that gives us an overview
of the important metrics
about our database.
As you can see, it's an
absolutely huge document.
But the output of this
command can be grouped
into a few different sections--
instance information, asserts,
connections and network,
locking, operation stats,
security, replication stats,
storage engine
stats, and metrics.
These sections span everything
from overall information,
like the instance
in information,
to very specific information on
operation counters and storage
engine stats.
We're going to go on a
whirlwind tour, so buckle up.
Since this command gives
us so much information,
we'll focus on the most
relevant data for debugging
and diagnostics, like asserts,
connections and network,
operation stats,
locking, and metrics.
Given the server status
can be a bit overwhelming,
and to minimize the pixel
real estate on our screen,
we can also suppress any of the
root level server status output
document fields, much like
we would when projecting
information in a find query.
You can see that we're
going to the admin server
and doing run command.
That's what this
admin command means.
We do this by running the
server status command directly.
In this command, we're
removing from the output, all
of the replication metrics
and WiredTiger information,
and explicitly including
locks information.
It's still a huge document.
A good way to keep track of the
keys for such a huge document
is with the
object.keys function.
This is just a
JavaScript function
that tells us what the
keys of JSON object are.
OK, let's dig into how
server status works.
To provide server
status information,
the MongoDB process keeps
track of a set of counters
and statistics, all
of them counting up
since that very
MongoDB server process
first started up, potentially
quite some time ago.
These counters will be reflected
in this command output.
Tools that run this command
will be able to plot or provide
statistical information,
let's say, inserts per second,
for a given instance
by calculating
the difference between two
calls to server status.
I'm going to go to another shell
connected to the same server.
Here, I'm going to set
some inserts running.
I'm telling it to
insert 10 documents,
then wait one second,
and just repeat forever.
Looks like it had to reconnect.
And were good.
Here we're looking at the
opcounters.insert field,
and the value is
282 inserts that
have occurred since the
server was started up.
If we run this again, ah, we can
see that it's a little higher.
And if I start doing
this every second or so,
I can see that it's counting
up by 10 per second.
Obviously, I'm a
bad judge of what
a second is, so they
aren't totally consistent,
but you get the idea.
By finding the difference
between the opcounters.insert
field one second apart, you
can get the inserts that
would be shown in MongoStat.
Let's look into some
of the information
in the output of server status.
We can get the hostname, the
version number, the process,
which would be either a MongoDB
server or a MongoS router,
the process ID on the
system, and a set of values
like how long the server
has been running in seconds,
milliseconds, and what time
the server thinks it is
when you ask for server status.
Server status also
gathers information
on current established
connections
and the number of
available connections.
This value will be related
to the Unix ulimit values
set for this host.
Ulimits are set at the
operating system level,
and they control the maximum
number of open files.
Unix systems need one
open file per connection.
Ulimits isn't the only
factor that controls
the available connections.
You can also limit it in the
configuration of your MongoDB
instance where we can
control the number
of allowed connections by
setting the configuration
option minus minus max cons.
Let's exit the shell,
kill our process,
and run it with a lower
number of maximum connections.
Here's my MongoD on port 27017.
I have copied the command.
It's process ID is 26620--
killing it-- and starting
up with max connections
of, let's say, 10.
We'll go back in the shell.
OK, we've become primary again.
And now we have five
connections total because we're
part of a replica set.
And I'm connected
with the shell.
We have five available,
and five have been created.
The connections field
of server status
will be useful when we look at
configuration and networking
issues.