Let's talk about
the server logs.
Imagine that
something goes wrong
and you suspect the problem
is with your deployment.
Maybe your query is just taking
unexpectedly long to answer,
or maybe you're suddenly
missing a collection,
or a server goes down
and you're not sure why.
The server logs are going to
be the first place you look
once you're aware of a problem.
They're taken continuously,
and with them, you
can look into the past to
figure out what went wrong.
When people contact our
technical services team
asking for help with a
problem, this is typically
the first thing we ask for.
Let's jump in and see
what the logs look like.
I haven't been running
this mongod very long,
but that's OK.
From the moment the
server starts up,
it begins recording
its story in the logs.
It starts by telling us
that it is starting up
and logs some information.
You can see this in the
messages on the right.
MongoDB starting.
Here's my process ID.
Here's the port
I'm listening on.
Here's my path.
Here's some information
that I was built from.
These logs are the story our
database tells about itself
and its environment.
And already, you have a
sense of the basic format.
On the left, you
see a time stamp.
It's in ISO 8601 local
format for those of you
who are curious.
Next, you see the severity.
These are all I, so the
severity is "informational."
In other words, each of
these entries is normal
and this is the
information that the server
records in normal operations.
After that, you
have the component.
Starts with control here.
You can see a few
of them say storage.
Following that is the
context in square brackets.
Finally, on the right, you
get the informational message
itself.
Let's filter out all the control
lines and also the time stamp
at the beginning and
get to the component.
I can see storage, FTDC,
Replication, Network.
Here's the full list--
access, command, control,
geo, index, network, query,
replication, sharding,
storage, journal, and write.
This helps us narrow down
what we're looking at.
We'll be looking into these
a bit more as they come up
during the course, but
definitely be aware of the fact
that you can use these to
filter things down a bit
and to figure out what it is
exactly you're looking at.
It's also probably worth
talking for a moment
about the severity.
F is for a fatal error.
This would have to come from an
uncaught server exception that
crashed the process.
It's pretty hard to trigger.
E is error, an internal
uncaught server
error that doesn't result
in the server crashing.
W is Warning-- something that
might indicate a problem,
but it doesn't prevent the
server from doing its job.
I is informational, which is
everything logged by default.
And d is diagnostic.
This comes up when you set the
verbosity level above zero,
which we don't
generally recommend
on production databases.
So how can you find the
important log entries
you might be looking for?
Obviously, if you know
when things went wrong,
you can find events immediately
before or after that event.
Here's our server process.
Let's kill it and see
what the logs record--
9332, 9332.
This is going to be
a hard kill signal.
We wouldn't recommend
this generally.
And our process is down.
Let's start it up again.
Great.
Let's look at the logs.
Here, we can see that it
was moving along doing
its normal operations.
And boom-- server restarted.
And if we look for
it, we should also
be able to find its
transition back to primary.
And there it is.
And close by, you can see the
things that were happening just
before and just afterwards.
Let's go back to the terminal.
And by the way, if
you find that you're
wanting to capture
a lot more, you
can always run your system
with maximum verbosity.
Now I can see these diagnostic
entries appearing in my log.
Usually, this will
be overkill, as it'll
be doing extra logging for
a lot of internal processes.
Our server engineers like this
feature when they roll out
code changes to
the server and they
want to make sure
everything is working,
but we wouldn't recommend doing
this by default on your end.
If something is useful, we log
it at the default verbosity.
You can find more information
in the documentation.
There will be a link
in the lecture notes.
We're going to go
into more detail
with the server logs when we
look at individual scenarios,
but already, you know
how to find your logs
and parse a bit of
what they're saying.