Asserts is a
document that reports
the number of assertion
errors raised since the server
process started.
Asserts are relatively
rare, and for that reason,
we want to keep an
eye on these counters.
Because when they
start going up,
they're signaling that
something has gone wrong.
The server is counting
both internal asserts
and user asserts.
We have three internal asserts--
regular, warning, and msg,
or message, all of which
are internal to
the server process.
Operations that
can raise asserts
like these are insert conflicts
and back-off operations.
All of these assert operations
get noted in the server
logs as well.
User asserts are
the ones that we'll
be focusing on in more detail.
These asserts are caused
by a system configuration
or application-driven operation.
This can capture a lot.
If we try to insert a
document with a duplicate key
and a unique index,
it goes up by one.
If the instance runs out of disk
space, It also goes up by one.
In this example, if we try to
insert two different documents
with the same underscore ID,
we get a duplicate key error.
As you can see, the
server increments
the user asserts counter.
These counters will
be important when
we want to analyze
provisioning and configuration
issues of both the application
and your MongoDB cluster.
Locks is a relatively
large document,
although not too large.
It shows the different
locks on the database.
Now, there are a few different
granularities for the locks--
global, database, collection,
metadata, and oplog.
And these logs can be
of different types.
Big R and big W are for shared
lock and exclusive lock,
respectively, while
little r and little w
are intent shared lock
and intent exclusive lock,
respectively.
The r and w come from the
days before WiredTiger
when we didn't have the
currency protocols at all.
Right locks were exclusive,
while read locks were shared,
hence the r and w notations.
If all of this is new
to you, don't worry.
We'll dive into more detail on
the impact and causes for locks
later on.
Server status also provides
the operation counters.
Up counters gives us the
information regarding
the number of inserts, queries,
updates, deletes, getMores,
and commands acknowledged
by the instance.
Opcounters.repl will give us
the same types of counters,
but as a result of the
replication process.
Op latencies provide information
on operation latencies
for the instance
globally in microseconds.
So once you hit seven digits,
that's one second total.
The WiredTiger information
is a huge document.
Most of these
statistics are only
relevant for MongoDB internal
utilization of the storage
engine, so we don't
care about most of them.
But there are a few interesting
ones worth mentioning.
Scrolling through, we
have this cache field,
and within that, maximum
bytes configured.
This is a value that indicates
the size of the WiredTiger
cache.
"Bytes currently in the
cache" is an interesting one
that tracks what we've got
in the cache currently.
Cache.EvectionCallsToGetaPage
and cache.EvictionCa
llsToGetaPageFoundQueueEmpty
are an interesting pair.
These give us an idea of
how much work WiredTiger is
doing to find pages, and to find
pages to evict from the cache.
I just restarted this server, so
the numbers are zero currently.
When these numbers
start going up fast,
you know that your working
set is outgrowing your cache.
It might be time to look
at optimizing your schema,
scaling up, or
possibly scaling out.
I haven't been hammering
this server very hard,
so they're still at zero.
The memory section,
mem, allows us
to understand what
the current memory
utilization of the server is.
We'll get information on the
bit architecture, the amount
of allocated, resident,
and virtual memory,
and in the case of using mmapv1,
will get the amount of mapped
and mapped with journal memory.
These don't apply if you're
using the default storage
engine, so they'll stay
at zero on this server.
Metrics is another big one.
It gives us a lot of
statistics that'll
tell us relevant
information for debugging.
One interesting field
it has is the breakdown
of the types of commands
received by the instance,
such as cursors and
document counters.
Here we can see the number
of finds, getLog, getMore, et
cetera.
Here we have metrics.documents
and op counters.
Let's talk about what
they mean, and what
the difference between them is.
Opcounters accounts for
the number of operations,
regardless of the number
of documents affected,
but metrics.documents keeps
track of the actual documents
affected by those operations.
A simple example would be
an update of many documents.
This will be counted as a
single update operation,
but the number of
documents updated
would be the number
of affected documents.
When I insert documents, my
opcounters' insert counter
goes up by one per document.
I inserted five documents,
it went up by five.
Metrics.document.inserted
Inserted went up by five.
This is because each
insert is one command.
On the other hand, when
it comes to updates,
opcounters only go up
one per update command,
while the
metrics.document.updated
goes up by one per
document affected.
OK, so that's a quick
overview of server status.
We'll be making use of all of
this information going forward.
But for now, you
should have a sense
of the range of what's
available, and how to find it.