at this point I'm going to deploy my new
replica set and it's spinning up my
Mongo deep processes now and we can see
them here here here back to the UI by
clicking on metrics I can see what's
going on so I'm in cloud manager looking
at my deployment and I have a cluster
set up on my VM so I can look at
monitoring for my replica set I can see
up counters connections page faults all
of these by default and if I scroll down
I can decide what I'm monitoring as I
click on these I can see them appear in
my monitoring window I can get
historical monitoring information and I
can choose how granular that information
is I can choose my zoom and there's the
granularity obviously I just spend this
up so I'm not going to be able to see
things that happened five years ago but
you get the idea for shorter time
windows like one hour you can also have
a shorter granularity this is all just a
quick overview for more information on
the features take a look at em one to
two are a cloud and ops manager of
course we're on University we'll add a
link in the lecture notes finally there
are a lot more features in these
products but one that I really want to
draw your attention to is the fact that
we can set up alerts with these we can
get an email or text whenever something
exceeds a certain threshold
here I can create one win disk space
utilization goes above 90% send me an
email and a text message and save
we can also add alerts for billing by
the way if our bill exceeds a certain
amount okay so what did we learn we
learned the basics of what cloud
managers automation and monitoring
agents can do we learned how to use
automation to spin up our cluster and we
learned how to look at monitoring and
some of the things that we can monitor
finally we found out where we can set up
alerts and that's a quick overview of
cloud and ops manager