OK, now that we've seen
this for some small queries,
let's do it for a
whole bunch of queries.
Whoops-- ran it too quick.
Basically, it finds a single
query and runs it 100 times.
We should see the index stat
incrementing for each query.
And when I look at my
index stats, there it is.
My last name, first
name index was
incremented 100 times
because we used it
for each of those 100 queries.
I also want you to
notice that this
used last name and
first name, and I
have an index that's
only on first name, which
could have been used,
but it's not optimal.
But MongoDB only used the other
index to fulfill the query,
so it didn't increment the
operations on this first name
index.
So $indexStats is going to
do a good job of telling us
which indexes we're using
and which ones we're not.
By looking at the change in
that ops field from one time
to the next that
we use $indexStats,
we can get a pretty good sense
of which indexes are never
being used, meaning they're
good candidates for deletion.
Why?
Well, recall that indexes will
reduce the speed of inserts
because you have to
insert a document
and add an index key for each
index in that collection.
By the way, it's worth
asking the question,
when does it
increment the field?
Notice that, right
now, my indexes
have a value of 0, 2, and 100.
Let's insert one
more document and see
what our index stats look like.
0, 2, and 100.
It did not increment any of
them from inserting a document.
What about an update?
OK, I performed a single update.
We matched one document
and modified it.
Let's look at our index stats--
0, 2, and 101.
OK, it used this last
name, first name index
to fulfill that update.
That's because an update
is a combination of a find
and a write, and since I used
the index to find the document,
it's incremented.
By way, MongoDB will
increment the ops field
even if I don't update anything.
I'll run the same update,
setting the same field,
but it will recognize that
no update is necessary
since we're already in the state
the update is trying to create.
Update one set,
address, same field--
matched one document,
didn't modify it.
But when I look at the
index stats, there we go--
incremented the ops field.
We had to use the index to find
the document even though we
didn't write to that document.
Any time I use the index
to find a document,
MongoDB will increment that
index counter in the ops field.