In this lesson, we'll explore
some of the scalar data types
MongoDB supports,
and how to determine
the value type of a particular
field using the Compass schema
view.
We look at array, document, and
what I often call special value
types in other lessons.
Here, we are looking
at the schema
view for the video
movies collection.
Now, I have collapsed
the nav pane
to the left using
this control so
that we have a little bit
more screen real estate
to work with.
As we scroll through
the main panel,
you should see a
number of fields here.
In the schema view, a
field is represented
by its name, its
type, and a graph
that reflects the
range of values
for that field in
this collection
and what fraction of
documents have a given value.
As an example, let's take
a look in more detail
at the genre field.
For this field, we
see the name genre.
Immediately below
is a description
of the value type for
this field as determined
by sampling documents
in this collection.
Throughout the Compass schema
view, hovering over elements
provides more detail.
If we hover over
the bar immediately
below the value type specifier,
you should see the value 100%.
This tells us that 100% of the
documents in this collection
contain a string
value for this field.
To the right of
the name and type
is a graph that shows both a
range of values for this field
and what fraction of
documents in this collection
hold specific values.
Skimming through
the values gives us
an idea of all the values this
field has within documents
in this collection.
And if we hover over any
specific element of this graph,
we can see what
fraction of documents
have a specific value.
Here we can see that 10% of
documents in this collection
describe movies in
the genre documentary.
It is important to keep in
mind that the value range
and fraction of documents
with a given value,
as reported by Compass, is
based on a sample of documents
in the collection.
In this example, the
sample is large enough
that you should see
an accurate summary,
but there is a chance the
summary will change slightly
from one viewing to another.
As we scroll through
the rest of the schema
view for this
collection, you can
see that Compass provides the
name, a value type description,
and a summary of the range and
fraction of documents having
a specific value for all
fields found within documents
in a collection.
In addition to strings,
other common values
for MongoDB documents include
integers, floating point
values, and dates.
Let's look at the
year field next.
You can see from the schema
view that values for this field
are int32, meaning they
are 32-bit integers.
Looking at the
value graph, we can
see that the min value is 1,897,
and the max value is 2,017.
We can also see that
the number of movies
in this collection
for more recent years
is much greater than for time
periods 100 years ago or more.
As we skim through
the bars here,
we can see that each represents
a period of about five years.
Now let's look at some
floating point values.
If we scroll up to the
viewer rating field,
you will see a range of
values from 1.8 to nine,
which seems reasonable for a
viewer rating scale for movies.
And again, we can see that
the majority of values
are somewhere in
this mediocre range,
with far fewer ratings being
extremely low or very, very
high.
The data type
double is one option
for representing
floating point values.
As you're probably aware,
floating point arithmetic,
while good enough for many
applications, is imprecise.
MongoDB also provides
a decimal data
type for financial transactions
and other applications
that require precise
floating point arithmetic.
Now you might be wondering why
we're seeing multiple value
types listed for viewer rating.
In fact, we have both
some double values
and some int32
values, as well as
a proportion of documents for
which this field is actually
undefined.
One of the real advantages
of the Compass schema view
is that it gives
you a sense for what
values fields in your
collection actually have.
And for a collection
that's this large,
this can be extremely handy
when you're going through tasks
such as data cleaning.
This indicates that we might
have a little bit of work
to do in order to make sure
that all viewer ratings are
of the same data type.
The fact that, for many movies,
viewer rating is undefined,
is not necessarily a problem
because we simply might not
have data on viewer ratings
for a sizable fraction
of our dataset.
The important takeaway
here is that Compass
identifies fields for which
there is a mix of value types.
This is valuable for developers
or administrators who
might be trying to
debug an issue that
has to do with the data
type for a particular field.
It's also useful
in considering what
needs to be done
from a scripting
standpoint, for
example, when it becomes
necessary to migrate
a data model from one
schema to another.
In this lesson, we've looked at
scalar value types in MongoDB
and how to use Compass
to determine value
types for a field and to get a
sense for the range of values
in that field for
documents in a collection.
The examples we've
looked at in the lesson
do not provide a comprehensive
overview of the scalar value
types MongoDB supports.
However, they are
the most common.
Before we close this
lesson, let's take a look
at one additional value type.
I'd like to look at a field that
shows us an example of dates.
The last updated field provides
a record of when the data--
ratings and such-- for
a given movie document
was last updated, that is,
when a document was last
written to the collection.
For date values, Compass does
something really valuable.
You can see here
that Compass provides
the range of date values in a
way that indicates something
like the density of values
at each date in the range.
Just above this,
you can see a report
of what fraction of date values
for the field in question fall
on each day, here, and at
what time of day, here.
In this lesson, we've looked at
scalar value types in MongoDB
and how to use Compass
to determine value
types for a field and get a
sense for the range of values
in that field for
documents in a collection.
The examples we've
looked at in this lesson
do not provide a comprehensive
overview of the scalar value
types MongoDB supports.
However, these are
the most common--
int32, double, string, and date.
We complete a more complete
review of MongoDB data types
in another lesson on the
binary format in which MongoDB
stores documents.