In this lesson, we'll
look at aggregate value
types MongoDB supports,
and also discuss support
for geospatial data.
In Compass, let's look
at the 100 year weather
data set, by navigating
to the 100 Year Weather
dot data name space
in our Atlas cluster.
We can do that as follows.
First we click on the database,
and then the collection.
Let's look at the schema
view for this collection.
Now, this dataset
provides weather readings
for locations
throughout the world.
For this dataset, it's
important to understand
that all readings are recorded
with both a value and quality
assessment, to provide
a sense for how
reliable the measurement was
determined to be when taken.
As an example, let's scroll down
and look at the air temperature
field.
Note that the type specified
for this field in the Compass UI
is document.
To the right of
the field name, you
should see a description
that says document
with two nested fields.
In addition to scalar
values, such as strings,
integers, and doubles, MongoDB
supports nesting a document
as the value of a field
within another document.
Air temperature is an example.
When expanded, we can see the
nested fields for quality,
and the air temperature value.
So here I've expanded
air temperature
by clicking this caret.
The value of air
temperature is actually
a nested document with two
fields, quality and value.
Quality is a string,
and value is a number.
For many applications,
it's important to be able
to model data, not just as a
flat set of keys and values,
but as hierarchical
data structures
that reflect the way
a developer needs
to work with the data
in their application.
If it's appropriate
to your application,
you can nest documents
two or more levels deep.
As an example, let's take a
look at the atmospheric pressure
observation field.
Atmospheric pressure
tells us the weight
of the air at a given location.
As an aside,
atmospheric pressure
affects how weather systems
move across the surface
of the Earth.
It's one factor
meteorologists use
to predict the
next day's weather.
If we expand the atmospheric
pressure observation field,
we can see that this
field has a value that
is a document with two fields.
Each of those fields are
themselves nested documents,
as we can see here by the
type Compass provides to us.
If we expand each of them,
we see a reading and quality
measure for the
height above sea level
at which the measure was taken,
designated as the altimeter
setting, and the actual
atmospheric pressure reading
and quality measure.
With these documents
expanded in this way,
we can see that atmospheric
pressure is modeled using
two levels of nested documents.
MongoDB's query language
provides full support
for filtering documents
based on the values of fields
in nested documents.
MongoDB is designed to provide
a great deal of flexibility
in modeling your
data, so that you
can design a schema
that is performant
for your application's
data access patterns.
Your data model should support
efficient handling of the reads
and writes your
application requires.
Now, we address these
aspects of data modeling
and the MongoDB query language
in detail in other lessons.
At this point, I'm simply
laying the groundwork
for the flexibility you have
in designing data models.