Now let's look at
how to query MongoDB
so that we can locate just
those documents that match
a specific set of filters.
In doing this, we'll be sending
a request to our MongoDB
cluster and MongoDB will find
in return only those documents
that meet our stated criteria.
Compass provides a rich
point and click interface
for filtering collections.
Let's look at some examples
of filtering collections using
the citibike.trips collection.
This dataset contains
documents recording trips
taken within New York
City using the Citi Bike
network of publicly accessible
bicycles and stations.
The documents in this
collection provide
details on the start and end
stations, duration, start
and end day and time for
trips taken using a city bike.
There's also a very small amount
of demographic information,
including birth year and gender.
Now as you're aware,
the graph to the right
for each field in the
Compass schema view
provides a summary of
the range of values
found within a given field for
documents in the collection.
If we hover over
a graph element,
we can see what values
that element represents.
Now if we click on
a graph element,
we open up a whole new area
of Compass functionality.
As an example, I've clicked on
this bar within the end station
name graph.
At first you might notice only
that the bar changed color.
But if you look here, in
the schema view for Compass,
you should see that the filter
form element in this view
has been updated.
Let's take a minute
to talk about this.
Chances are you're already
familiar with JavaScript Object
Notation, also known
by its acronym JSON.
That's J-S-O-N. As you become
more experienced in your use
of MongoDB, much of your
interaction with the database
will be through JSON documents
of one type or another.
Though Compass is a
GUI client, a little
of the JSON
orientation of MongoDB
comes through in this aspect
of the Compass interface.
We explore JSON in greater
detail in another lesson.
For now, you only really need
to know a few simple facts
about JSON documents.
First, JSON documents begin
and end with curly braces.
Second, JSON documents
are composed of fields.
In the example we're
looking at here,
this document has one field.
And finally, fields
have two parts.
A key and a value.
The key is a string, and
must be enclosed in quotes,
as we see here.
The value can be any valid
JavaScript data type, including
a nested JSON document.
The value of the
field in this document
is Broadway and
East 22nd Street.
Within a field, the key and
value are separated by a colon.
For now, that's all you really
need to know about JSON.
In this lesson,
we'll see a couple
of different examples
of JSON documents
as we look at
filtering collections.
Now, let's apply our filter.
The filter we've just applied
can be expressed as follows.
Show me all documents
for which the end station
name has the value Broadway
and East 22nd Street.
Note that rather than the nearly
2 million documents reported
by Compass for the
entire collection,
upon applying the
filter, Compass
reports a little more
than 13,000 documents
matching our query.
Before we move on, it
is important for me
to mention that the type of
filter we have applied here
is called an equality filter.
This simply means
that we're looking
for documents with this exact
value in the end station name
field.
Now let's look at a
different type of filter
for situations in
which we want to select
documents that fall into a
particular range of values.
A good example for
us to work with here
is the birth year field of
the city bike collection.
Note that when hovering on
any of the bars in the summary
graph, that each bar
represents a range of values.
At the far left are birth
years less than 1940,
and the other bars represent
a range of five years each.
Let's click on the
bar from 1985 to 1990.
Note the filter document
created for us here.
This filter stipulates
a constraint that
can be expressed as follows.
Show me all the documents for
which the birth year field has
a value that is greater
than or equal to 1985,
and less than 1990.
Instead of a single value, as
we had for the equality filter,
this filter specifies
a range of values.
There are two
things to note here.
One is that the value
for the birth year
field in our filtered document
is a nested JSON document.
It follows all the
rules of JSON documents
with respect to the
fields, and the key value
pairs this document contains.
The second thing to note
is that the fields together
to find a range of
values because of the use
of a couple of special keys.
$gte and $lt. In
MongoDB this type of key
is called an operator.
MongoDB defines many operators
in its query language.
In other lessons we'll go
into detail on operators,
and all other aspects of
the MongoDB query language.
Applying this filter, we can
see that about 343,000 documents
match the range we've
specified here for birth year.
Now that we have a
better understanding
of range filters,
let's experiment a bit
to get a sense for what's
possible with Compass and range
filters.
Rather than clicking on
just one bar in the summary
graph for birth year,
let's click and hold
the mouse button, and select
several bars in this graph.
Note that the
filter document now
expresses a much broader
range of birth years.
If we apply this filter, MongoDB
will return all documents
that have a birth year value
that is greater than or equal
to '70, and less than 1990.
Before we move on
from range filters,
let's take a look
at one last example.
After resetting our
filter, let's scroll down
to the bottom of
the schema view.
Here we'll find a field
called trip duration.
Trip duration stores the
length of the trip in seconds.
Let's just select a
region of this graph
and apply the filter.
Here I've selected
a trip duration
in the range 2,000 to 4,000.
In this example, we can see
one reason why Compass--
even though it's a visual tool--
gives a JSON filter to work
with, in addition to the point,
click, drag interface.
For fields that have values
that are this granular,
sometimes it's just faster to
edit the JSON filter directly
to get what we want.
For example, say
we want to filter
for trips that have a duration
of between 10 and 20 minutes.
We can simply edit the
JSON filter directly
to be greater than 600 seconds,
and less than 1,200 seconds,
like this.
And if we apply
this filter, we can
see that more than 600,000
documents match our query.
Scrolling down to the
trip duration field,
we can see that the range
of values in the schema view
now reflects just those
documents matching our query.
The min is 600, and
the max is 1,199.
In this lesson
we've reviewed how
to use the Compass
interface to complete
queries involving equality
filters and range filters.
We've also taken a
look at JSON documents
that represent
these filters, as we
begin to get comfortable
interacting with MongoDB
using JSON syntax.
In other lessons in this course,
we go much deeper on JSON,
queries, and a number
of other operations
essential to using MongoDB.