In addition to nested
documents, MongoDB also
supports array
values for fields.
In this data set, we can
see an example of array
in the section's field.
For this example,
it's going to be
best if we look at the
Documents tab, in Compass.
In this tab, we see
not just a summary
view of the schema for
documents in a collection,
but we can look at the actual
documents our 100 Year Weather
collection contains.
Documents in this
data set contain
measurements for a consistent
set of meteorological readings.
These include air temperature,
pressure, wind, etc.
But there are more
than 100 other readings
that might be available as
well, depending on the weather
station.
Supplementary values,
such as these,
are labeled using
a three to four
character code following
a standard established
for meteorological data.
Because MongoDB has a
flexible data model,
all documents don't
have to contain
exactly the same fields.
So in this data set, the
supplementary readings
available in a
specific document are
stored in the section's
field in this data set.
Since the available readings
will vary from one document
to the next, it makes
sense to provide a summary
list of what
supplemental readings are
available in a given document.
An array is a good choice
for this in MongoDB.
The MongoDB query
language supports
queries on array
fields that make
it easy for us to
filter documents
containing a particular set
of supplementary fields.
And the advantage of noting
the supplementary data this way
is that we simply need to
build an index on sections,
and can then very
quickly look up
documents containing a specific
set of supplementary data.