Hi, I'm Shannon.
And I'll be guiding you
through the basics of MongoDB
in this introductory course.
MongoDB eliminates a number
of technical challenges
that slow the pace of
application development.
In this course, we'll go
through the fundamentals
so that you can get up
and running with MongoDB.
First, we'll introduce
you to MongoDB Compass.
Compass is a visual
interface to MongoDB
that we'll use for many
lessons in this course.
It allows us to
configure a database
and explore the
data it contains.
We'll use Compass to
explore a few data-sets
and talk about the important
design features such as support
for flexible schemas and
the range of benefits
that it provides to
application developers.
Then we'll dive into the
MongoDB query language
to give you plenty
of preparation
as you begin to think about
building your own MongoDB
application.
Throughout the
course, we'll make
use of Atlas, which is MongoDB's
database as a service offering.
We've created a database
cluster in Atlas
specifically for
use in this course.
You'll be connecting
to and using it
for many lessons and labs.
As you begin moving
through this course,
please take advantage
of the discussion forum.
Feel free to ask any
questions you have
about lessons or assignments.
Many students also ask questions
about more general MongoDB
questions, and that's OK too.
We have teaching assistants
monitoring the discussion forum
to help you.
In addition, other
students frequently
jump in with great
advice and answers
if you get stuck on a lab.
We're almost ready to begin.
But before we do, I wanted to
make you aware of the MongoDB
University app.
Many learners like to
download lesson videos
to watch on their commute
or in other situations
where internet
bandwidth is unreliable.
The MongoDB University
app available on both iOS
and Android makes this easy.
Search the App Store or Google
Play for MongoDB University
and give the app a try.
Most of our learners use it
for at least some portion
of every course.
OK, that's all the information
you need to get started.
If you have any questions or
comments about the course,
again, please feel
free to post something
in the discussion forum.
We're happy to
have you on board.
Thanks for learning
with us, and good luck.