Once connected, you should see
a screen that looks like this.
Here in the main
panel, we can see
a list of the databases
contained in this cluster.
In MongoDB, a database serves
as a namespace for collections.
Collections store individual
records called documents.
This graphic illustrates the
relationship between databases,
collections, and documents.
This hierarchy allows us
to group together records
of similar items
within collections,
and group collections required
for the same application
within the same database.
We can also establish security
policies that authorize users
with different roles
and different levels
of access at the database,
or collection, level.
MongoDB does not currently
support authorization settings
specific to
individual documents.
Each database and collection
combination define a namespace.
We typically reference
a specific collection
by expressing the name of the
database, followed by a dot,
followed by the name
of the collection.
Returning to
Compass, here we have
a listing of all the
databases in this cluster.
With a little bit of information
about the size of the database,
the number of
collections it contains,
and the number of indexes
on these collections.
We won't say too much about
indexes in this course.
You'll want to take the MongoDB
performance course for that.
Just look for M201 on the
MongoDB university website.
By the way, if the list
of databases you're seeing
differs a little bit from
what I'm showing here,
don't worry about that.
We update this cluster from time to time with new datasets.