Much of our interaction
with MongoDB
will require an
understanding of JSON.
MongoDB is a document
database, and we frequently
discuss data models looking
at JSON representations
of documents.
In addition, the
MongoDB query language,
and much of the
administration of MongoDB,
requires some level of
understanding of JSON.
JSON, which is an acronym for
JavaScript Object Notation,
is a popular format for
representing documents.
As an example,
here is a document
representing a popular movie.
When discussing
MongoDB, we typically
use the term JSON document
to refer to such structures.
But JSON object is
equally correct.
JSON is a widely
used data format
because it is both
easy for humans
to read and edit and easy for
computers to parse and output.
JSON documents begin and
end with curly braces.
They're composed of
fields, and each field
has a key and a value.
In other programming
languages, JSON documents
are analogous to objects,
structs, maps, or dictionaries.
One big advantage
of using MongoDB
is that the data model
used by the database
closely resembles
the data structures
you work with in your
programming language of choice.
This has a number
of advantages, which
we discuss at some
length in other lessons.
Returning to our
example document,
we can see that there are
fields for title, year, cast,
viewer rating, and plot, in
addition to a number of others.
This example illustrates a
few additional requirements
of the JSON grammar.
The first is that all keys must
be surrounded in double quotes.
You can see that all keys here
have double quotes around them.
Keys and values must
be separated by colons.
And again, we see that
for each field here.
Fields are separated
from one another
by commas, as we see at the end
of each field in this document.
JSON documents support
a number of value types.
There are strings, which must
be surrounded by double quotes.
Also, note that inside
strings is the only time
when white space is significant
within a JSON document.
New lines and other white
space outside of quotes
is not really part
of the JSON document.
In addition to
strings, JSON values
can be floating point
numbers, Boolean values,
and the null value.
Finally, arrays and objects
can themselves be values
and nested in any combination.
JSON arrays are defined
by square brackets.
Arrays contain an ordered,
comma separated list of values.
JSON arrays are analogous
to arrays lists, vectors,
or sequences found in other
programming languages,
such as Java,
Python, C Sharp, etc.
This example happens
to include an array
as the value for the cast field.
This array contains one element
for each cast member of note
in this movie or, I should
say, each cast member
captured in this
particular collection.
Note that three of the
elements are strings,
but the fourth is actually
an embedded document.
This records the stage
name of Billy Zane
as well as his birth name.
This array illustrates
the last thing about JSON
that I really want
you to walk away with,
that being that Jason
documents support
any level of hierarchy
that is appropriate to
your application's data model.
MongoDB is designed from the
ground up to support this.
The query language, indexes,
and internal data structures
are designed to support a
wide variety of data models.
Now, let's take a look at
the Compass representation
for documents such as these.
Here we're looking at the
video.movies collection
and the Documents tab
for this collection.
And if we scroll
through here, we
can see a number of
documents in this collection.
Using the filter
functionality and Compass,
we can construct a filter that
will find all movies where
the title is Titanic.
Applying this filter, we'll see
that we have eight documents
with the title Titanic.
Scrolling down, we
can find the document
we were just looking at
it in its raw JSON form
as it's represented in Compass.
Now, unlike the schema
view in Compass,
this is not a summary
representation
of the data in this collection
but the individual documents
themselves.
For the sake of a cleaner
UI, compass does not
depict documents as JSON.
Rather, for each document,
it simply lists the fields.
For aggregate values, such as
arrays and embedded documents,
it shows a tree view
that you can click on
to expand the value of the
field, as we see for cast.
It uses this mechanism
for any level of hierarchy
within documents.
You can expand successive
values to drive down
into any documents you wish.
Here, we'll expand the Billy
Zane element of this array
to see the full document
or object as it's
stored in this document.
And with that, we've
concluded our overview of JSON
and it's importance in MongoDB.
For more information about
the JSON document format,
feel free to read about
it in detail www.JSON.org.