OK, now let's browse some of
the collections in this cluster.
If you look to the left
in the Compass interface,
you'll see a navigation
panel containing
a list of all databases in the
cluster we are connected to,
with the collections
those databases contain
nested below them.
Note that you can return
to this view at any point
by clicking the Home icon.
Right now however, we want to
dive into the collections here.
We have quite a
few databases here.
These are the collections we'll
use throughout the course.
They contain a variety
of types of data,
and a range of data models,
so that we can illustrate
different features of MongoDB.
To access documents
within any collection,
simply locate the collection
in this navigation panel
and click.
As an example, let's take a
look at the movies collection
of the videos database.
As you click on
this collection, you
should see a schema
view for the collection
appear in the main panel.
The schema view provides
a list of the fields
found in documents
within this collection.
As you might expect
for movies, we
have fields for
director, genre, plot,
and a number of other
features relevant to movies.
As we scroll through, we can see
all fields found in documents
in this collection.
Again, this view
provides a summary
of the schema, or data
model, for documents
in this collection.
We have the list of
fields, their data types,
and a summary of the range
of values for each field
found throughout the
documents in the collection.
We'll return to a more detailed
walkthrough of this information
in a later lesson.
For now, let's dig into
this collection a bit,
and look at a few
specific documents.
If we click the
Documents tab, you
should see a list of documents
within this collection.
This view gives us the ability
to browse the actual data found
in this collection.
Here we can see a document
recording the details
for a one minute long
film called Carmencita
that was produced in 1894.
As we scroll through this view,
we can see other documents
in this collection.
In later lessons,
we'll look at how
to query this data
to find documents
matching a specific
set of filter criteria.
We'll also learn how to
insert new documents,
and update existing
ones, with new data.
Go ahead and explore
this data a bit,
and peek in on the other
collections in this Atlas cluster. And then, move on
to the next lesson.
And then, move on