OK, so far we've looked
at document valued fields,
and array valued fields.
One last thing I'd like
to show, with respect
to these types of
aggregate data structures,
is an example of mixing the two.
To do that, let's
look at this document.
And I want to point out
that this document contains
a field called sky cover layer.
This is one of those
supplementary pieces
of data that can appear in our
documents in this collection.
Sky cover layer is an
array valued field.
But in contrast to
our previous example,
if we expand sky
cover layer, we see
that this array contains, as
its elements, nested documents.
So for this particular
document, sky cover layer
has a value that is
an array containing
three elements, where each
element is a document.
And each of those documents
contains a value and quality
measure.
Something you should be aware
of in working with Compass,
and in general with
MongoDB, is that we
tend to use the terms object
and document interchangeably.
The reason for this
terminology is something
that we dive into
in other lessons.
As another example of
mixing documents and arrays,
let's take a look at
the position field
for this document.
Now here, we have a nested
document that has two fields,
and one of those
fields is an array.
So in the example before,
we saw an array field
that had nested documents
as its elements.
In this case, we
have a nested object
that has an array as the
value of one of its fields.
For this document, type
has a string value.
And as we've said,
coordinates is an array
containing two elements.
MongoDB supports a range
of scalar value types,
including string, null, integer,
double, and decimal, as well
as document values,
and array values.
You may use any
supported value type
for any field value or array
element in a MongoDB document.
One last thing before
we conclude this lesson.
As you've probably guessed, the
position field in this example
stores a point in a
geospatial coordinate system.
While geospatial is not
a value type per se,
using document structures--
such as the one we're looking
at here--
MongoDB provides far reaching
support for geospatial data,
enabling you to store
a variety of shapes,
calculate the distance
between points,
filter for documents that
are within a specified
radius of another
point, and perform
a number of other operations.
Compass provides some
nice conveniences
for working with
geospatial data.
We can see an example
with this collection,
if we visit the Schema
tab and scroll down
to the position field.
Jumping back to the Schema tab,
if we scroll down to position,
we can see that Compass plots
the positions of readings
on a map of the Earth.
We have full pan, zoom
functionality here.
In other lessons,
we look at using
this UI to filter collections
for documents expressing
locations within a specified
distance of a reference point.