In this lesson, we'll begin
our exploration of MongoDB.
To do this we'll
use Compass, which
is the MongoDB GUI client.
If you've not already done
so, please open Compass
and follow along as we
move through this lesson.
I've included instructions for
download and launch of Compass
in the lecture notes
for this lesson.
Compass provides a UI for
viewing MongoDB databases
and the documents they contain.
It also supports the
MongoDB query language,
and enables us to
read and write data
using a number of conveniences
for building queries.
Here we're looking at
Compass's connection screen.
On the left side, you
should see a navigation bar,
with sections for Favorites
and Recent Connections.
In the center view
here, you should
see a form we can use to
establish a connection
to a MongoDB cluster.
Please note that Compass
is actively developed.
There might be differences
between the UI I show here
and what you are seeing now.
In a moment, we'll connect
to a MongoDB cluster
we have set up for this class.
This cluster is
running in Atlas,
which is MongoDB's hosted
MongoDB as a service platform.
See the lecture notes for more
information on MongoDB Atlas.
Also don't worry about my
use of the term cluster.
If it is unfamiliar to you.
For now, it's not important.
In a later lesson, we'll dive
into what a MongoDB cluster is.
OK, so now we're
ready to connect.
You can see the hostname
for our cluster here.
I've also included it in
the lecture notes below.
We will connect on the
default port of 27017.
As the authentication method,
we'll use username password.
Please use the
username m001-student.
And the password
m001-mongodb-basics
We'll use admin as the
authentication database,
and specify Use System CA slash
Atlas Deployment for the SSL
field.
This simply means that we will
encrypt traffic between Compass
and our Atlas cluster.
Finally, before we press
the connect button,
please create a favorite
for this connection
that you can easily get back to.
Now click Connect, and load
the databases in the M001 class
MongoDB deployment.