As we get started
with this course,
I'd like to talk about grading
and a few other logistics
just to make sure you know
how this course works.
You'll see three different types
of exercises in this course--
quizzes, labs--
which we also call
homework-- and a final exam.
You'll see quizzes after most
lesson videos in this course.
All quizzes are ungraded.
They're there to allow you
to test your understanding
of the lesson material.
You'll see labs-- or homework,
as we sometimes call them--
throughout each chapter.
The scores you get
on your labs make up
50% of your final grade.
Then at the very end of
the course is a final exam.
This makes up the other
50% of your grade.
In terms of a course
schedule, in the first week
of this course, we
release chapter one.
We release chapter two
in the second week,
and then in the third
week of the course,
we release both chapter
three and the final exam.
And don't worry--
these two together
are short enough that you
should be able to complete them
all in week three.
Please make sure you
check the course syllabus
for the exact release dates
for weeks one, two, and three.
In the syllabus, you'll
also find due dates
for when the labs or homework
are due for each week.
Once we've passed the due
date for the final exam,
if you've achieved a
grade of 65% or better,
you'll receive a statement of
completion for this course.
And again, we generate the
statements of completion
after the due date
for the final exam.
That's it for the
essential course logistics.
We're glad you're learning
with us, and good luck.