So in this lesson we're going
to discuss bulk writes, which
is a different kind
of write in MongoDB,
and we're going to talk about
the performance application
of these kinds of writes.
So oftentimes our
applications will
encounter situations
in which they
need to perform a series
of writes at once.
And in some cases,
these writes have
a causal effect on one another.
One of them failing
or succeeding
may affect the
application logic.
So in this case, a customer is
on our supermarket application
and they're purchasing
items from the store.
We want to update the
database to reflect
the new quantities of that
food that we have in stock.
So they bought two apples,
so we want to decrease
the total quantity by two.
They bought four
sticks of butter,
one slice of bread, et cetera.
When our application received
these writes, one option it has
is to send each of them to
the database one at a time.
So it would send
the first write,
and then some time later, it
will receive an acknowledgment
back from the database.
Nice.
Now we'll see the
next write over.
So we send the next write,
wait for acknowledgment.
So we just performed
two write operations,
and it required two round
trips to the database.
We need to send the
operation, and then
receive an acknowledgment
back from the database.
That's round trip to the
database for each operation.
But if we already knew all the
writes we wanted to perform,
why is our client sending
them each one at a time?
So you can probably see
where this is going.
So what we can do instead is
batch these writes together
and then send them in bulk.
The exact method of
grouping documents
together is implemented
differently in each driver,
just because the data
structures are different.
But the general
idea is the same.
Package a bunch of
writes into a batch,
usually a list or an
array-- but again,
the implementation is
different in every language--
and then send that
whole batch to MongoDB
and get one acknowledgment
back from the server.
This is an
implementation of bulk
writes in the Mongols
shell, and you
can copy this from the handout
if you want to try it out.
But this will look different
and your chosen programming
language, so just
bear that in mind.
When a client
sends a bulk write,
it gets one acknowledgment
back from the database
for the whole batch.
And this is a benefit to our
application's performance
because it limits
the effect of latency
on the overall speed
of the operation.
If it takes one second
for each round trip,
then setting each write one at
a time takes four total seconds.
But if we can send all
four writes in one trip,
then sending four writes
only takes one second.
Now the default
behavior of a bulk
write in Mongo is an ordered
execution of these writes.
In the order bulk
write, any failure
will stop the execution
of the rest of the batch.
This benefits us in this case
because these writes might
be causally related, like
if two different update
operations want to buy sticks
of butter but there's only one
left.
In that situation, the
first operation in the batch
you get the last
stick of butter,
and the second operation
should error out.
That's why we need
these executed in order.
The bulk rate would
throw some sort of error
on the update
statement, and then
return an acknowledgment
back to the client
before trying to
purchase any more items.
The acknowledgment we
get back would tell us
if something errored out.
So bulk writes in MongoDB
will be ordered by default.
That means that
even though we sent
all the writes at the same time,
the replica set will apply them
in the order that
they were sent.
Sending an ordered
bulk write implies
that each write in the batch
depends on all the writes
that occurred before it.
So if a write operation
results in error,
all subsequent
writes will not be
executed, because Mongo
assumes that those
writes were expecting the
ones before to succeed.
But there's a chance that
the writes in our batch
are not dependent on each other.
In this case, we've just
received a shipment of food
to the warehouse and we
want to update the new food
quantities in stock.
Because all these
operations are additive,
we don't need them to
be executed in order.
So I passed this order
of false flag to the bulk
write command which will
execute them in parallel.
If some of them fail
for whatever reason,
we can still continue
on with the execution
of the other operations
in the batch.
And when we get an
acknowledgment back
from the server, it'll let us
know if any of the operations
fail.
So if the writes
in our batch don't
have any sort of
causal relationship,
then the client can send them
over in an unordered bulk
write.
This will execute the write
operations in parallel
so the writes are non-blocking.
And as a result,
a single failure
won't prevent any of the
other writes from succeeding.
Now those writes might
fail on their own,
but their execution is
not tied to the success
of any of the other writes.
So in conclusion,
bulk writes make
it more efficient
to update or insert
in many documents in a database
by setting them all in batches.
These bulk writes can be
ordered, which means writes
are executed in the
order in which they
were sent to the
database and any errors
will prevent subsequent
writes from executing.
They can also be
unordered, which
means the writes are
executed in parallel,
and errors don't affect the
execution of other writes.
Now one small thing to note.
In a shorted collection,
ordered bulk rates
are expected to
take a little longer
because write operations need
to be routed to the designated
shards.
And unordered bulk write might
reach the mongos in one batch,
but then it has to be serialized
across each designated shard.
Regardless of the
designated shard,
the write operation
needs to be evaluated
to see if we should
continue or exit
the execution of the
rest of the batch.