In this lesson, we're
going to discuss
read concerns in MongoDB.
So read concerns
are similar write
concerns, in that they both
involve how many nodes have
applied a database operation.
While write concerns affect
the acknowledgment received
by the driver after a
write, read concerns
affect the data returned
by a read operation.
Different read concerns are
referred to as different levels
of read isolation because
you can essentially
isolate a read from the
rest of the database
if the data being read
has only been written
to one of the nodes in the set.
If data can be read by
clients before that data
has been replicated to
a majority of nodes,
it's considered a low
level of read isolation.
The read concern you
choose will depend
on how consistent your view
of the database needs to be.
So by default,
when an application
sends a read to Mongo, Mongo
will use Read Concern Local.
From the perspective
of the database client,
the data read using Read
Concerned Local has only been
written to the primary node.
In the vast majority
of cases, the data
will also have been written to
the secondary nodes in the set.
But the client only
has proof that this one
note applied the write.
This means that there's
a chance, however slim,
that the data returned by
this read will be rolled back.
This would happen if sometime
after this data is returned,
the primary goes down and
the secondaries haven't
replicated the data yet.
That means that when
one of these two nodes
becomes the primary, this
primary will be secondary.
And it'll be rolled back to
match the state of whichever
node became the new primary.
So the default read
concern MongoDB
is Local, which reads
whatever copy of the data
exists on the primary node,
regardless of whether or not
the other nodes have
replicated that data.
And for the vast
majority of reads,
Read Concern Local is just fine.
But we might want a higher
level of consistency
on some of our reads, which
we can achieve with a read
concern called Majority.
When a database client sends a
read to Mongo with Read Concern
Majority, it can
verifiably claim
that the data it
gets back has been
replicated to a majority
of nodes in the set.
The benefit of this
read concern level
is that once data
has been replicated
to majority of nodes, it's
very durable in the event
of a failure.
Even if the current
primary fails,
this secondary can
be elected primary,
and then the data
will get rolled back.
One thing to note here,
if these secondaries
aren't done replicating
data at the time
that this primary
receives the read, then
whenever the copy
of the data has
been copied to a
majority of nodes,
will be returned to the client.
This means that if my
age in the primary is 66
but the secondaries
still think that I'm 65,
the age returned to
the client will be 65
because in a
three-node replica set,
two members are required
to constitute a majority.
So clearly, Read
Concern Majority
might return
slightly stale data,
but provides a higher
level of read isolation.
So you can be more
confident the data you
received won't get rolled back.
For this reason, it's
most useful in reading
mission-critical data, because
lower levels of read isolation
have slightly higher
chance of being rolled back
in an emergency.
If your application's
core functionality
depends on one read, like
checking a user's account
balance, then you
probably want that read
to have a higher durability.
So just to recap, issuing a
read with Read Concern Local
will return whatever
copy of the data
exists on the primary
node in the set.
Issuing a read with
Read Concern Majority
will return whatever
copy of data
has been replicated to a
majority of nodes in the set.