Pipelines.
You'll hear us mention
pipelines quite
a bit throughout the course,
so let's take a few minutes
to discuss what they are.
Pipelines can be thought of as
a conveyor belt in a factory.
Along the line, there are
different assembly stations.
These assembly
stations are stages.
Depending on what we
want to accomplish,
we may have only one stage,
or we may have many stages.
Pipelines work like this.
Documents, represented by these
squares, enter our pipeline
and begin to flow
into our first stage.
This stage is called
$match, which you'll
be introduced to very soon.
We set this stage up so that
only red and blue squares
make it through.
Next, they flow
through our pipeline
and enter the second stage.
In this example, we'll
call this stage $project.
We set this stage up to
transform our squares
into circles.
This is a small representation
of the power the aggregation
framework offers.
We can transform our data
in almost any way we desire.
We'll be covering the
$project stage in great detail
in later lessons.
This stage represents one of the
many powerful analysis stages
available, and it
is called $group.
Here, we have
configured the stage
to gather all of the documents
that are flowing into it
and produce a
single document that
gives us the ratio of
red to blue circles.
We'll cover $group, and
many other powerful data
analysis stages,
later in the course.
There you have it.
A high-level overview
of what pipelines are.
At the most basic level, they
are a composition of stages,
from one to many, that we
can arrange and configure
in almost any way we like.
The aggregation
framework provides
many stages to allow us to
filter and transform our data.
All we have to do is
compose the pipeline.
Some key takeaways to remember.
Pipelines are a
composition of stages.
Stages are
configurable to produce
desired transformations.
Documents flow
through the stages
like parts in an assembly
line or water through a pipe.
Finally, with only
a few exceptions,
which we'll cover
later, stages can
be arranged in any way we like
and as many as we require.