Before we dive into
the course, let's
discuss some
prerequisites and walk
through connecting to
the infrastructure that
is going to support the class.
The course prerequisites
are minimal.
All that is required is a
modern 64-bit operating system
and an internet connection
and your participation.
One note-- you'll also need
to be able to make a TCP
connection on port 27017.
This is easy to test.
Visit portquiz.net:27017.
You should see a page that
looks a lot like this.
And make sure that you see
something like this here
that says you've reached
this page on port 27017.
If you don't see
this page, please
contact your network
administrator
about opening up this port.
Additionally, make sure
you post in the forums
so that we can help you
until this issue is resolved.
As you've seen myself and other
instructors use new aggregation
operators throughout
the course, you
are highly encouraged to pause
the video and follow along.
All collections will
perform operations on
will be available to you
in the Class Atlas cluster.
So what's Atlas?
Atlas is MongoDB's
cloud-hosting service.
We'll let MongoDB worry about
optimizing storage, security,
and backing up our
data for this course.
Signing up for Atlas
is easy and free.
Visit mongodb.com/cloud/atlas
and click the Get Started Free
button.
After clicking the
button, go ahead
and fill out your information
and click Get Started Free
again.
And for now, that's it.
We'll be revisiting Atlas
later on in the course.
Next, let's ensure we
have MongoDB installed.
Visit mongodb.com and
click the Download button.
Navigate over to
Enterprise and select
the download that's appropriate
for your operating system.
Enterprise is free
to test and evaluate,
so we'll be using it
throughout the course.
While that's
downloading, let's click
Resources and Documentation.
Click on Tutorials and
click MongoDB Enterprise.
Scroll down and
find the tutorial
for installing
MongoDB Enterprise
on your specific
operating system.
Lastly, we need to test our
connection to the class Atlas
cluster.
Open a terminal and
paste the information
you find below this video.
Go ahead and type
show dbs to see
all of the available databases
available on the cluster.
Typing show collections
will show collections
within the
aggregations database.
And that's it for the
course prerequisites
in connecting to Atlas.