Let's take a few minutes to talk
about the structure and syntax
of the aggregation framework.
The aggregation framework has
a simple and reliable structure
and repeatable syntax.
Pipelines may contain
one or more stages.
Each stage is a JSON
object of key value pairs.
With only a few exceptions,
we can have as many stages
as we like.
Additionally, options
may be passed in.
For example, specifying
whether to allow disk use
for large aggregations, or
to view the explain plan
of the aggregation to see
whether it is using indexes,
or if the server
optimized the pipeline.
Let's take a look at a very
simple, but very real pipeline
and discuss the syntax.
Here, we have a match
stage that checks
whether the atmoshperic
composition contains oxygen
or not.
And if the mean temperature
falls within this range.
Then, we have a project stage
that reshapes the document
and calculates the new value.
More on this in a moment.
Lastly, this is
our options object.
Each stage is composed of
either operators or expressions.
As we continue
through the course,
you'll be introduced
to many of these.
Make sure you bookmark the
Aggregation Pipeline Quick
Reference page that's
linked below this video.
Throughout the course, we'll
be using the terms operator
and expression, and it's vital
that you can quickly access
the documentation for these.
So what's an operator?
For this course, when
we say operators,
we mean either query operators
or aggregation stages.
In this example,
$match and $project
are aggregation operators,
and $in, $gte, and $lte,
are query operators.
As a general rule,
operators always
appear in the key
position of a document.
$match is a little special and
we'll learn about it later.
What's an expression?
Expressions act a
lot like functions.
We provide arguments and they
provide a computed output.
And just like
functions, expressions
can be composed to form powerful
new data transformations.
MongoDB provides expressions
for working with and producing
values for many types of values.
In the project stage,
$gt is an expression.
And its arguments are
supplied in ths array.
This $number of of moons,
surrounded by the quotes,
is also an expression that
you'll learn about in a moment.
An easy way to remember
how to use expressions
is that it will always
appear in a value position.
Let's run this now
to see the output.
Here, we see the result
of the calculated field.
It looks like Earth isn't
the only planet that
has oxygen. It's a relatively
comfortable temperature
and it does indeed have moons.
One more important
thing to cover.
We may encounter
syntax like this.
The first is a field
path expression
and it's used to access
the value of a field
in the document, like number
of moves in the first example.
The second, with
two dollar signs
followed by an uppercase word,
is a system level variable.
$current refers to
the current document.
And you can find the meaning of
others on the quick reference
page.
The last with two dollar signs
followed by a lowercase word
is a user variable.
expressions let us temporarily
bind a value to a name,
or provide us a special
name, to access some data.
And there we go.
The aggregation framework
structure and syntax.
We highly recommend
that you use an add that
has bracket matching while
constructing your pipelines
to make noticing errors easier.
There's just a few
things to remember.
Pipelines are always an
array of one or more stages.
Stages are composed of one
or more aggregation operators
or expressions.
Expressions may take
a single argument
or an array of arguments.
See you in the next lesson.