Hi, I'm Nathan.
Welcome to M121, the MongoDB
Aggregation Framework.
I'll be one of your
instructors for this course.
Throughout this
course, we're going
to discuss the
aggregation framework,
a key feature of MongoDB.
You'll learn about expressive
filtering, powerful data
transformation, statistical
utilities and data analysis,
and how to do much more work
with a single operation.
This course is
seven chapters long.
With each chapter, there will
be a new set of lesson videos.
After most of these
lessons, there
will be a quiz to assess your
learning of the material.
At the end of each
chapter, there
will be a set of
related lab exercises.
Let's go over a few of
the course logistics.
The target audience-- this
is a beginner's course
focused on developer practices.
If you're coming
from an operations
background, fear not,
young grasshopper,
we have something for you too.
It is expected that you are
familiar with the MongoDB query
language.
If you aren't, we recommend you
taking our definitive beginner
course, M001, before
attempting M121.
How does grading work?
There are quizzes,
labs, and a final exam.
Quizzes are ungraded and
exist to make sure that you're
understanding the content.
Your grade in the
class, however,
will be based on how well you do
on the labs and the final exam,
each of these being worth
50% of your total grade.
Students with a grade
of 65% or greater
will receive a passing
grade and will get
a certificate of completion.
Finally, I'd highly
encourage you to participate
in the discussion forum.
We have knowledgeable teaching
assistants who are there
to answer your questions.
We also have your
classmates who can also
contribute to answering
your questions
and are often beneficial
and knowledgeable resources.
The labs in this course
can be challenging.
Based on our
experience, we've seen
that students who perform
best in the course
are those who are most active
in the discussion forum.
By the end of this
course, you should
be familiar with how to
transform data, perform data
analysis, and reallocate work
to the server from your client
application.
With all of that said,
we're excited to have you
as a student in this course.
Best of luck.