Now, configuring your
MongoDB instance, given
the number of different options
that you have for your MongoDB
configuration files to
properly connect to LDAP,
might get a little
bit tricky, not
only because of the number
of different options,
but also considering that the
confirmation of LDAP servers
might be very well-defined
and very extensive,
in terms of number of users and
different configuration options
that it might have.
Testing this settings on
itself comes on handy.
It makes this much
more effective,
doing that before setting up
our MongoDB instance itself.
So, for that, with
3.4 we are shipping
a new tool called Mongo LDAP.
Now, what Mongo LDAP will do is
test your configuration options
for MongoDB against the running
LDAP server or set of servers.
Let's see how it works.
Now, in this particular
Vagrant machine,
here, I have been playing
around with MongoDB 3.4.
I also have a running LDAP
server on a different machine--
here it is-- configured
with the set of users
that we've been looking
into throughout the course.
Now, the first
thing that I can do
is check if Mongo LDAP
is actually configured.
And let's have a look to
what configuration options
we have available for
this particular tool.
Now, the first thing
I have is the option
of setting up a
configuration file that
will allow me to test, given
a MongoDB configuration
file, all the options
that are LDAP-related.
I will tell exactly
which user I'm
going to be trying to
connect with, its password,
and I can even set it in a
different-colored output, which
is lovely.
If I don't want to set up any
configuration file on its own,
I can test individual
LDAP module options.
Like, if the LDAP servers are
up, if the transport security
setting, or if I'm
using TLS or none,
is actually set up, or any of
the other LDAP-related options
that MongoDB ships with it.
So, in my case, I do
have a configuration
file that I want to test.
That configuration file
has a bunch of options.
In this case, I'll
have a server that I
want to connect to--
this other machine,
running on my local host.
I have a query template.
I'm going to fully replace
the user for whatever I'm
passing on to MongoDB.
And also going to have,
like, the transportSecurity
set to "none."
I'm not using TLS at the
moment-- neither a bind method.
But I am going to do a
transformation of the user
that I'm receiving to
a distinguished name.
And this is done by
the userToDNMapping.
And I specify, here,
what's the transformation.
I'm going to pick
up whatever user
I'm passing to
connect to MongoDB
and replace it with this
VN mapping, over here.
So, basically, I'm going
to set uid to whatever I'm
passing [? to ?] the user.
So let's see if my configuration
file is correctly set up, given
a user.
To do that, what I'm going to do
is basically tell MongoDB that
I have a file-- the file that
I've previously shown you,
with all the options, which
is called "mongod_ldap.cnf."
And I'm going to test the
connection using user "alice"
and passing on its
respective password.
Once I run this
particular process,
I'll have the full set
of steps that MongoD
will try to execute, given
the credentials that I'm
passing to connect.
It will check if the
LDAP servers are found,
if we can connect to them,
if the mapping are valid,
if we successfully authenticate
against the LDAP server,
if we can get the configuration,
the query templates, and so on.
So, in essence, we are shipping
MongoDB 3.4 with this utility
helper to avoid having
you drilling down
the logs of the normal
execution of MongoDB
to find out any connection
misconfigurations
on your configuration file.