There are two main components
that we need to configure.
On one side, we're going
to have our LDAP server.
On the other side, we're
going to have our MongoDB LDAP
configuration options.
They're going to set in our
MongoDB configuration file.
Let's start by analyzing a
sample LDAP configuration file.
Note that the actual LDAP server
configuration details are out
of scope for this lesson.
This is something that
you need to catch up.
To configure LDAP servers,
we'll be using ldif files.
ldif is a standard
plain data interchange
formats for representing LDAP
directory content and update
requests, conveys directory
content as a set of records,
one record for each object.
It also represents
update requests
such as heading, modifying,
deleting, or even renaming
operations as a set of records.
Now let's assume that we have
this ldif file as supporting
configuration for LDAP servers.
We have a set of groups-- in
this case mongodb.com-- users
NDBA.
And we're going to also
have a set of users
or a couple of users in
this case-- Alice and BOB.
There are several
different types
of [INAUDIBLE],
groups, and users
that we can define using ldifs.
For now, we are just going to be
using this example for the time
being.
For MongoDB configuration,
we have a large set
of different options available
to configure our server.
We'll start with
the LDAP servers,
a comma separated string of
one or more LDAP servers.
We're going to have
LDAP transport security.
It's an option whether
or not to secure
the communications between
LDAP servers and MongoDB.
Accepted values are
going to be TLS or none.
ldapAuthzQueryTemplate-- this
is an rfc4516 formatted URL
of the LDAP Quarry to execute
in order to obtain LDAP groups.
In this URL, the placeholder
token string user
will be replaced with
the queried distinguished
name of the user.
If not set, MongoDB will not
use LDAP for authorization.
Also have LDAP
timeout milliseconds,
the amount of time that MongoDB
should wait for an LDP server
to respond to a request.
The default is 10 seconds.
ldapBindSASLMechanisms--
the SASL mechanisms MongoDB
will attempt to authenticate
with against LDAP server
while binding.
If MongoDB is using
SASL authentication,
it will bind using DIGEST-MD5
by default. ldapQueryUser-- this
is the LDAP entity
distinguished name
that MongoDB will bind as when
connecting to an LDAP server.
And we're also going to
have its password set
by ldapQueryPassword--
again, the password which
MongoDB will use to bind when
connecting to that same LDAP
server.
We also have an
important one-- LDAP user
to distinguish name mapping.
This is an adjacent array
of ordered transformations
that MongoDB will apply to
authenticate MongoDB user
names to match their
distinguished names in LDAP--
useful for when we are using
alternative authentication
method or if user names passed
to MongoDB for authentication
do not match the LDAP DN.
If not defined,
MongoDB will directly
use whatever username you
pass it through to the DN.
This is intended to
allow LDAP authorization
to work automatically.
We're also going to have
LDAP user cache invalidation
interval.
MongoDB will hold the cache
of authenticated users.
During this interval,
it will determine
how much time MongoDB
will [INAUDIBLE]
to wait for external user
caches to be flushed.
The default is 30 seconds.
ldapBindWithOSDefaults
will perform queries
to the service accounts'
username and password.
It's useful for single sign-on
on where you are already
authenticate against
your OS and you just
want to avoid passing
your username and password
continuously to MongoDB.
Although that said, it is
incompatible with ldapCoreUser
and ldapCorePassword.
For demo purposes,
we'll be using
a very simple configuration.
I'm going to start by defining
and setting the list of LDAP
servers that I'm going to use.
We're going to be setting up a
query template, which is going
to be user member of and base.
We are going to define user
distinguish names mapping
option with a match,
regular expression,
and its substitution string.
In this example,
we are not going
to be using any
transport security
and the binding mechanism is
going to be set to simple.
And since we are using
LDAP for both authorization
and authentication, I'm setting
the authentication mechanism
to plain, which is the
respective authentication
mechanism for LDAP.
Once we have this
configuration in place,
both on LDAP and MongoDB
configuration files,
it will be time to
validate this setup.
But let's talk about that
in the following lesson.