In this video, I want to cover
a couple of important issues.
First, the way we use TLS/SSL
between MongoDB and LDAP
server.
Second one is how LDAP
configuration differences
between different
LDAP providers and how
this can affect the MongoDB
configuration settings.
Now the use of the TLS
between MongoDB and LDAP
server is enforced by default.
You can, however, disable it,
but we will strongly
recommend it to our users
to keep it enabled.
We can also bind a
node to a given user.
This will mean that all requests
exchanged between MongoDB
and the LDAP server will be
bound to a username password.
You can also define with the
bind mechanism which mechanism
to use enforcing that bind.
By default, it's set to play.
Now regarding
different LDAP servers,
we will check the most common
used ones-- Active Directory
and OpenLDAP.
To simplify our examples--
the ones used in this course--
we have been playing
around with OpenLDAP.
The labs, the
demonstrations, and some
of the configuration
code snippets
have all been around OpenLDAP.
But there are slight differences
in format and configuration
options depending on which
system we are bound to use.
The most common
MongoDB LDAP deployment
is using Active Directory
as our LDAP server.
This has a set of
different variations
when compared with OpenLDAP.
The first difference resides on
the user definition attributes.
OpenLDAP that assumes
that users will
be defined by UID attributes,
while Active Directory allows
users to be configured using
a common name-- CN attribute.
This might seem a small,
insignificant difference,
but can cause some headaches
when debugging configuration
validation.
The other major significant is
around MongoDB configuration
option-- security LDAP
authz query template.
Active Directory
allows us to define
the complete distinguished
name structure
and just replace the username
on the user placeholder.
For example, our query template
can be something like cn=
the placeholder and then the
rest of our distinguished name
definition.
In OpenLDAP, this
is not possible.
We need to use a
full replacement
and use a full
distinguished name.
While in OpenLDAP this is
not possible to achieve
relying alone on the
query template definition,
we can still do this
by applying a user
to DN mapping substitution
on a regular expression.
User to DN option
matching a substitution
and matching regular expression
is the way to get it done.
Why this is important?
If we want users to log in to
MongoDB just passing a user
credential and not the complete
LDAP credentials-- like,
for example, when we have Alice,
or when we have to pass along
UID=Alice and so forth in
the distinguished name.
Which, as you can
imagine, tends to be
a much more pleasant usage.