Now let's talk about
how to configure
MongoDB to use
X.509 certificates
for authentication.
It's important to remember
that X.509 certificate
authentication requires
a secured TLS connection.
So make sure you're
running a build of MongoDB
that has TLS enabled.
You can easily tell if your
version of MongoDB was compiled
with TLS support by
running mongod--version.
And as you can tell, we
have OpenSSL version.
When we see OpenSSL here,
we know yes, this binary
was compiled with TLS support.
I went ahead, and for the
purpose of this demonstration,
I have already created
my certificate files.
I have the public certificate,
a MyCertificate authority
in the ca.pem file.
And then I have pem files for
both the client and server,
each of these containing
both the public certificate
and the corresponding
private key.
Here's the command for running
MongoDB with X.509 support.
If you're familiar with enabling
TLS on a [? mongod, ?] then
you've already seen
these options before.
There is no difference between
enabling TLS and enabling
X.509 authentication,
because X.509 authentication
is enabled by
default. We just need
to set the server to use TLS.
So if you look here, you can see
that I'm specifying an sslMode.
And here I'm using
requireSSL, but you
could use any mode that
isn't, well, just disabled.
And here I'm providing the
sslPEMKeyFile for the server.
And this is so that we
can prove to the client
that we are who we say we are.
And then I'm specifying
the sslCAFile.
And this is so that
we know the client is
who they say they are.
And there we go.
We're up and running
with no errors.
Let's go to another shell
and try and connect.
But before we connect
to the server,
we first need to figure out
what the subject of our client
certificate is.
Here we have our
client.pem file.
And inside of this pem file, we
have our private key and public
certificate.
Inside that certificate,
there's a subject line
that describes who the
owner of the certificate is,
or rather who the
certificate was issued to.
We can run the following command
to read the subject line.
Here we're saying
that we're dealing
with an X.509 certificate.
We're providing an in parameter
of the client.pem file.
The input format is PEM,
we want to get the subject.
The nameopt, we're
going to use RFC2253.
This allows us to
transform the subject name
from the representation that
is stored in the certificate
into a string.
And then finally we
say no out, because we
want to suppress outputting
the entire certificate,
because we just
want the subject.
And when we run this, we can
see that here is the subject.
It's this right there.
Pretty straightforward.
We're going to want to
go ahead and copy this
because we're going to use
the subject line to identify
the user when we create
an account for them
in the database.
Now we can go ahead and connect
to the server with the Mongo
shell.
Here I'm saying --ssl because
our server is requiring SSL.
And specifying the
PEMKeyFile option
so that the server
knows who we are.
And I'm still saying
the ca because we
want to make sure
that the server is
who they say they are.
And now that we're
connected, you'll
see that we have unrestricted
access to the server.
And it's because we didn't pass
the --off option to mongod.
So let's go ahead and go back
here and restart the server
with --off.
And now if we go back
here and reconnect,
we should be reconnected now.
Cool.
And now if we do
show dbs, you'll
see that we get "not authorized
on admin to execute command,"
which is what we'd expect.
We now have
authorization enabled.
And now we need to
go ahead and take
advantage of the
local host exception
and create our first user.
And here's the command.
We're going to say,
db.getSiblingDB, external.
And this is because
X.509 is technically
an external
authentication mechanism
just because the credentials
aren't stored directly
in MongoDB.
Then we do runCommand.
And we say we want
to create a user.
Here is that subject
line that we had before.
And then we're going to go ahead
and give this user the root
role on the admin database.
And we can see that
it ran successfully.
And now that our
user's been created,
we can go and authenticate
them in a similar fashion.
Here we're going to use getting
the external database again.
And we run auth.
And here I'm passing in
that subject line again
and I'm specifying that
the mechanism is X.509.
And awesome.
We have asked successfully
authenticated using
X.509 certificate
authentication with MongoDB.