SCRAM-SHA-1 is one of the five
mechanisms for authentication
to MongoDB as a client user.
It's also the default
authentication mechanism
for MongoDB.
SCRAM-SHA-1 is a client response
mechanism for authentication.
In the case of MongoDB, it's
a username and password way
to authenticate to MongoDB.
Just remember that when
we say SCRAM-SHA-1,
we're talking about
authenticating
via your username and password.
SCRAM-SHA-1 is an internet
engineering task force
standard.
It defines best practice
methods for implementation
of challenge/response mechanisms
for authenticating users
with passwords.
I don't want to get into
the nitty gritty details
of SCRAM-SHA-1, but you can
know that it'll protect you
from the following attacks.
First there's eavesdropping.
This is where an
attacker can read
all the traffic exchanged
between the client
and the server.
To protect against
this, a client
never sends their password as
plain text over the network.
Then we have replay.
This is where an attacker
can resend the client's
valid responses to the server.
This is mitigated because
each authentication session is
made up by unique [INAUDIBLE],
so that each protocol
messages are only valid
for a single session.
Database compromise.
This is where an
attacker can read
the contents of the
servers persistent memory.
SCRAM-SHA-1 mitigates this
by salting and iteratively
hashing the passwords
before storing them.
With SCRAM-SHA-1, an attacker
is unable to pose as a server
without the knowledge of
a client's credentials,
therefore completely mitigating
the malicious server attack.
MongoDB-CR is another
one of the five client
or user authentication
mechanisms
supported by MongoDB.
MongoDB-CR is another
challenge/response
authentication mechanism.
It is also another user name
and password authentication
mechanism.
With the release of 3.0,
SCRAM-SHA-1 has effectively
replaced MongoDB-CR.
This means that, as of 3.0,
MongoDB-CR has been deprecated.
You will only
encounter MongoDB-CR
on versions of MongoDB
older than 3.0 or on servers
that were upgraded from
a previous version to 3.0
or above.
If you do encounter
MongoDB-Cr in production,
it's highly recommended that you
upgrade to a version of MongoDB
where SCRAM-SHA-1 is
supported, and that you then
migrate this old users from
MongoDB-CR to SCRAM-SHA-1.
We'll have a lesson that walks
you through this process later
in the course.
Another commonly used
authentication mechanism
by MongoDB is X.509.
X.509 is a certificate-based
authentication mechanism.
It became an authentication
option as of version 2.6.
With X.509, you are required
to have a TLS connection.
If you're using MongoDB
3.2.6 or greater,
then your version of
MongoDB is already
compiled with TLS support.
If it's not, then it's easy
to compile a version that
has TLS support included.
LDAP is yet another
authentication mechanism
for client authentication
with MongoDB.
It stands for Lightweight
Directory Access Protocol.
It's important to note
that LDAP support is only
provided in the Enterprise
version of MongoDB.
LDAP is a directory service
protocol commonly used
within companies.
It provides a mechanism for
accessing and maintaining
distributed directory
information.
LDAP provides a mechanism
for accessing and maintaining
distributed directory
information over a network.
This protocol is
thus frequently used
by email and other programs
to look up information
from a server.
With LDAP of
authentication support,
users can authenticate
to MongoDB
using their LDAP credentials.
This makes LDAP an external
authentication mechanism.
This means that the
actual credentials
used to authenticate
the client are not
stored directly in MongoDB.
Kerberos is the last client
authentication mechanism
for MongoDB.
It's important to note that like
LDAP, Kerberos authentication
support is only provided in the
Enterprise version of MongoDB.
Developed at MIT,
Kerberos is an industry
standard authentication
protocol for large client server
systems.
Kerberos is widely accepted to
be a very secure authentication
mechanism.
Kerberos differs
from LDAP in that
it was designed specifically for
the purpose of authentication.
LDAP, on the other hand,
wasn't designed specifically
for authentication but
rather for storing metadata
about users in an organization.
Like LDAP, Kerberos
authentication support
can authenticate a user to
MongoDB using their Kerberos
credentials.
Again, this makes Kerberos
an external authentication
mechanism.
This means that the
actual credentials
used to authenticate the client
are not stored in MongoDB.
Not only is it important to
ensure that your clients can
securely connect to MongoDB,
but it's also important
that the nodes in a replica
set or sharded cluster
are able to
communicate securely.
If your MongoDB
replica set or sharded
cluster spans multiple
data centers or touches
the internet in any
way, it's very important
that you enable
internal authentication.
However, even while
most internal networks
are considered to be
secure, enabling internal
authentication is still highly
recommended in closed networks
to prevent attacks where a
network becomes compromised.
MongoDB currently supports
two internal authentication
mechanisms.
There's keyfile authentication
which uses SCRAM-SHA-1
and X.509 authentication.
With keyfile authentication,
the contents of your keyfile
essentially act as
a shared password
between the members of your
replica set or sharded cluster.
The same keyfile must be
present on each member that
talks to one another.
Because of this,
it's highly important
that you keep this file secure.
The actual contents
of your keyfile
must be between 6
and 1,024 characters,
and may only contain characters
in the Base64 character set.
It's important to note that
all whitespace characters are
ignored.
So my password and mypassword
are effectively the same.
X.509 is another internal
authentication mechanism.
And it utilizes certificates
to authenticate members
to one another.
While you can use the same
certificate on all members,
it is highly
recommended that you
issue a different
certificate to each member.
This way, if one of the
certificates is compromised,
you'll only need to
reissue and deploy
that one certificate
instead of having
to update your entire cluster.
Finally, it's important to
note that whenever you enable
internal authentication, either
with X.509 or with keyfile
based authentication,
this automatically will
enable client authentication.