In this video we're going to
talk about Kerberos and how
to configure MongoDB to
enable Kerberos authentication
support.
As we said before,
Kerberos is an industry
standard authentication
protocol.
Before talking about
how Kerberos works,
I want to mention that Kerberos
calls users principles,
and this is because
a Kerberos principal
is a unique identity to which
Kerberos can assign tickets.
So when I say principal in
the context of authenticating
to MongoDB, think user.
Kerberos authentication
support works
by creating a service
principle for MongoDB
inside of the Kerberos KDC.
This enables among
MongoDB driver
to request tickets from the
Kerberos KDC's ticket grading
service, and then once the
driver has that ticket,
it can then use that ticket
to authenticate to MongoDB.
Let's go ahead and look
at how to enable Kerberos
authentication support.
Here I'm running
a VM that already
has Kerberos installed on it.
I've already created
a user on the KDC.
Let's go ahead,
and check it out.
Here I'm running the
tool kadmin.local.
This allows us to
directly modify
the Kerberos KDC's database.
Now here we can go ahead
and list all the principles
on this machine.
Here's the command to
do so-- listprincs,
which is short for principles.
And as you can see, I've
already created a principal
for kirby-- kirby@MONGODB.COM.
Now we need to go ahead and
add a principal for MongoDB so
that we can issue
tickets to our users,
so they can authenticate
with MongoDB.
And here's the command to do so.
I'm going to go ahead
and add a principal.
I'm going to generate a
random key for this principle.
And the naming here of the
principle is very important.
The first is the name of
the service-- in this case,
MongoDB-- followed by a slash,
and then after the slash,
we have the host name
of the server that
is running our database.
Now that we have our
principal created for MongoDB,
we can generate a key
tab, which is a file that
will contain our shared secret.
We'll eventually put this
on our database server
so that MongoDB and Kerberos
can share the secret.
Here's the command to
generate the key tab-- key
tab add dash k, the
name of the key tab
file-- in this case, the
MongoDB dot key tab-- and then
the name of our principal.
Now we can go and
close kadmin.local,
and you can see our file.
And here is our key tab, and I'm
going to go ahead and copy this
over to our database server.
I'm now on our database
server, and here's my key tab
that we just generated
on the other server.
I'm now going to
store its location
in an environmental
variable called KRB5_KTNAME,
and this is so that
MongoDB actually
knows where this file is.
Great, now the last thing
we do before starting
MongoDB is just to configure
this server to talk to our KDC.
I've already installed
the basic program
to authenticate to
Kerberos with apt-get.
We just need to modify
the configuration file.
And here's the
location of the file.
Etc krb5.conf.
I'm going to use them to edit
it and run sudo because we're
operating with a NetC file.
And there's a lot of
stuff going on in here,
but we only need to modify
three places-- libdefaults,
where we want to change our
default realm to MONGODB.COM.
Awesome.
The second place
is under realms.
Here we want to go ahead and add
the information for our MongoDB
realm.
Great, and here's
this information.
We have the KDC, the
host name of our KDC,
which is in this case
is infrastructure.m
310.university.mongodb.com
This is the server
that we just ran
the other commands
to generate our key tab file.
And then obviously
the admin server,
which again is on
the same machine.
And the last bit that we need
to add is the domain realm.
And here we specify .mongodb.com
is equal to MONGODB.COM,
and mongodb.com
equals MONGODB.COM.
All of this stuff is case
sensitive, by the way.
Let's go ahead and
save this file.
Now he can go ahead and
enable Kerberos authentication
with MongoDB.
And here's the command to do so.
We're going to go ahead
and enable authentication,
and then we're going to
set the authentication
mechanism to GSSAPI.
API And this is the mechanism
that is used by Kerberos.
Our server is now
up and running,
and we can go ahead and
connect with the MongoDB shell
and create our Kerberos
principal user.
First we want to switch
to the external database,
and now that we're on
the external database,
we can go ahead and
create our user.
And here's the command
to do so-- db.createUser.
I pass in kirby@MONGODB.COM,
our principal user as our user.
I do not specify a password,
and then I give them
whatever rules I want.
In this case,
userAdminAnyDatabase.
Awesome.
Our user has now been
successfully added.
Now if I go ahead and
try to run db.auth,
specifying the GSSAPI mechanism
with my principal name,
you'll see that this failed.
And this is because we haven't
yet authenticated to Kerberos.
So let's go ahead and
exit out of the shell
and authenticate to Kerberos.
We authenticate
Kerberos with kinit
and then my principal
name, which is just kirby.
And it'll now asked me
for kirby's password,
which I happen to know because
I created it on the KDC.
I've now authenticated
it with Kerberos,
and we can now go
ahead and try again
to authenticate to MongoDB
using my Kerberos credentials.
Again, we'll have to switch
the external database,
and again we can
try to run db.auth
with the GSSAPI mechanism
with my principal name.
And there we go.
We have now successfully
authenticated to MongoDB
using our Kerberos credentials.