Now that you understand
at a high level
the different
authentication mechanisms
supported in MongoDB, let's
see what that actually
looks like via the Mongo
shell and the Mongo server.
I already have MongoDB
installed on this computer.
To begin, we'll start
the Mongo server using
mongod with the --auth option.
This will enable authorization.
But in order for the
server to properly identify
a client's level of
access, this will
force all clients to
authenticate to the server
before they can
perform any actions.
You'll see that if I
start the Mongo shell,
I'm not able to do anything.
If I try and run
show dbs, I'll get
this "not authorized on admin to
execute command" error message.
This is because I have
not authenticated yet
to the database.
But this is a new database.
There are no users
in this database.
So if I'm not authorized
to do anything,
how do I create a user?
Well, there is one
exception to this rule,
and it's called the
localhost exception.
The first thing you
are allowed to do
when connected to an
authenticated Mongo server
is you're allowed to create
the first user in the database.
With that first user, you
can then create other users.
That means we're
going to want to give
that user the ability or the
role who has the privilege
to create other users.
So let's go ahead and do that.
We'll switch to
the admin database,
and then we'll create our user.
In this case, I'm creating
a user whose username
will be kirby, whose
password will be password,
who has a role of
userAdminAnyDatabase
on the admin
database, which means
they'll be able to
administrate any database.
You'll notice that we're still
not allowed to do anything.
Show dbs will fail, as will
trying to create another user.
This is because the
localhost exception only
applies for the first
user in a database.
After you've created the
first user in a database,
or if a user already
exists in the database,
the localhost exception
will not apply.
I should also mention that
the localhost exception only
applies when you're
connected to the database
via the localhost interface,
meaning if you're not
on the same computer,
you will not
be able to utilize
localhost exception.
From here, we can go ahead
and authenticate with db.auth,
passing in my username of kirby,
whose password is password.
And then I can run
db.system.users.find,
and see we have the kirby
user on the admin database.
And here's all of that
goodness, like with the role
userAdminAnyDatabase.