Let's talk about
LDAP authentication
with the Enterprise
version of MongoDB.
LDAP, the Lightweight
Directory Access Protocol,
is a direct use service protocol
commonly used within companies.
With LDAP
authentication support,
users can authenticate
to MongoDB
using their LDAP credentials.
MongoDB communicates to an LDAP
server via the saslauthd proxy
service.
We'll configure
saslauthd such that it
can connect to our LDAP server.
And that way we'll connect our
mongod to the sasl via Unix
socket.
It's important to note that
MongoDB uses the sasl plane
mechanism for communicating
with the clients,
thus sending and receiving
data over plain text.
You can configure how
saslauthd communicates
to the LDAP server, but
by default this will also
communicate via plain text.
This means it's in
our best interest
to run this set up on a trusted
channel such as a connection
that's encrypted with TLS or
over our trusted wired network.
I'm going to assume
you already have
MongoDB Enterprise
installed and have an LDAP
server up and running.
I'd like to point out that
my LDAP server in mongod
will be running on the same
machine for this demonstration.
I'm currently SSH'd
into an Ubuntu machine,
so keep in mind that
some of my commands
will be slightly different
from yours depending
on your flavor of Linux.
Let's go ahead and
install saslauthd.
Here I'm running apt-get.
And I'm installing
saslauth2-bin.
And we're going to say yes.
And this will install saslauthd.
Cool.
Now that that's
been installed, we
can go ahead and configure
saslauthd to talk to LDAP.
Here I'm using vim to modify
my saslauthd configuration.
And I'm running vim under sudo.
And that's because we're
modifying something
that's in the etc directory.
And from here, we need
to go ahead and say
that we want start to be yes.
And after that, we want to
change this mechanism from pam
to LDAP.
Awesome.
Now let's go out
and save this file.
Now that saslauthd is
configured to talk to LDAP,
we need to go ahead and specify
some specifics about our setup.
Here I'm going to
go ahead and create
a file called saslauthd.config
underneath etc.
And I'm going to, again,
need to use sudo because it's
under the etc directory.
So in here, we can go ahead
and configure some stuff.
So since my LDAP server is
loading on a local machine,
it's local host, answering
on the default port.
And my search space, I'm going
to specify it as mongodb.com.
And then for my
actual LDAP filter,
my users are going to
be filtered by UID.
We can go ahead and save this.
And now we can go ahead and
start the saslauthd service.
And here's the command to do so.
And now the daemon's
been started.
Now that we have our
configuration all set up,
we can go ahead and do the
next thing, which is change
the permissions on this folder.
And I had to run
sudo, by the way,
because this is
another special folder.
And this folder is
special because there's
this file called mux.
And this mux is
actually a Unix socket.
And this is the
socket that will allow
mongod to communicate
with saslauthd,
which will then forward
our messages over
to our LDAP server.
So we'll go ahead and run
chmod on this folder
so that mongod
can actually access this mux.
Awesome.
Now that we have
changed permissions,
we can go ahead and
verify that saslauthd
can communicate
with our LDAP server
by running testsaslauthd.
And here I'm going
to run saslauthd.
And on my LDAP server,
I have a user named
Kirby whose password is LDAP.
And then I'm
specifying that mux.
And we get, OK, success.
Awesome.
Now that we verified
that saslauthd
can talk to our LDAP
server, let's go ahead
and configure MongoDB to
talk to this saslauthd.
Now that we have
everything configured,
we can go ahead and get MongoDB
up and running with LDAP
authentication enabled.
Here's the command to do so.
We're going to go ahead
and enable authorization.
and set a parameter.
We can set the authentication
mechanism to plain.
Going to set saslauthdPath
to the mux we've been using.
And then, of course,
dpath, logpath, and fork.
Awesome.
Now that our server
is up and running,
go ahead and connect to it.
Now we should be able to run
show dbs, and get an error.
And we do, as expected.
And now we can go ahead and take
advantage of the localhost
exception and create
our first user.
Here I'm going to use
the external database
because LDAP is an external
authentication mechanism.
And I'm going to create a user
called Kirby, because that's
the user we were using.
And he's going to be a
root on the admin database.
Sweet.
User's been created.
And now we can go ahead
and try and authenticate.
I'm first going to
try with a password
that we know is incorrect.
We know that my
passwords LDAP, but I'm
going to use the password LDAP2.
And we get
authentication failed.
And now I'm going
to run it again,
but with my correct
password being LDAP.
And we see that it
ran successfully.
Awesome.
We now have a MongoDB
Enterprise server
up and running with LDAP
authentication enabled.