So for this particular setup,
what we are going to do
is boot up our MongoDB
instance, our mongod,
in a virtual machine.
And I have a LDAP
server booted up
in a second virtual machine
that will be supporting
both authentication
and authorization
that MongoDB requires.
So in essence, all users and
all authentication credentials
will be both managed
by LDAP server
and accessed by our mongod.
So now what we're going to do
is set up a couple of things.
First I'm going to
have my mongod running
on this particular machine,
my m034 vagrant instance
that you have accessed through
the handouts of this lesson.
And also a vagrant LDAP
instance that basically just has
an LDAP configuration
on it so you
can boot up a LDAP server from
this particular setup here.
First thing that I'm
going to show you
is what configuration am I
going to run from my mongod.
Now I have this
file here, shared
mongod dot cnf, which will
hold all my configuration
for MongoDB.
What I have here is a
simple configuration
with the typical
options, like which port
am I going to listen it to.
I'm going to fork the process
to run it on the background.
I'm going to have a systemLog
defined, a storage dbPath where
I'm going to store
all my data, and then
the particular configuration
details of my LDAP setup.
So first of all,
I'm going to say
that authorization is enabled.
I'm going to
specify which server
is going to hold my
LDAP configuration,
or which server will
have the LDAP running.
I'm going to need to
specify query templates.
And here, this is the query,
following the LDAP query
syntax, that I'm going
to use to match my users
and also retrieve any
sort of attributes
that they are related with.
In this case, I'm going
to be using the DN base,
so I'm going to only
look for users which
match this particular
distinguished name base, which
is ou users, dc mongodb, dc com.
I'm only going to look
for one level down,
so anything that is like
Alice, users, mongodb, and com,
I'll find them.
But anything that
is above one level,
I will not be looking for those.
And obviously I'm going to
be looking for anything that
is going to be matching
the user keyword here,
or the placeholder.
Now this is an open LDAP server.
So I'll need to
make sure that I'm
doing the userToDNMapping
syntax substitution.
So I'm going to pass a
username, a simple Alice user
name, and then I'm going to
apply the actual open LDAP DN
syntax to it.
So basically I'm
going to replace here
on the first elements of the
substitution string whatever
comes from my user credentials,
and then pass it along
with this queryTemplate.
So apart from
that, I'm not going
to be using any
security right now.
This is just for demo.
I'm not going to be using
any binding whatsoever.
And my authentication
mechanism--
since I'm having LDAP supporting
both my authentication
and my authorization, the
authentication mechanism
also needs to be set up to
reflect that configuration.
Great.
On the other hand, I also have
my LDAP server configuration
which has my base dn.
Again, the users, mongodb, com.
I also have users
defined, like Alice,
and I also have a
few other setups
like this particular group
here, which Alice belongs to.
Now if you'll look
closely, we will
need to reflect this particular
user, and more concrete
its full distinguished
name, to a particular thing
that now we need to set up with
mongodb authorization on three
dot four.
So let's stay
tuned for this one.
Let's go back to
our mongod instance.
Now before we boot up
our MongoDB server,
it is a good practice to check
the configurations for the LDAP
settings.
So this is why we
have mongodb LDAP,
or mongoldap in this case, and
pass along the configuration
file that we want
to validate against.
Don't forget to
obviously pass along
the user that is required
to validate against,
and obviously its password.
Otherwise, the LDAP
server will not
know what to do with
this particular set.
Once we run this, and
if we have everything
OK and nice green lines here,
and we can also successfully
acquire the following roles,
and this is an important one, cn
admins, users, dc
mongodb, dc com at admin,
you see here that
the mongoldap utility
is expecting this role
that doesn't exist yet
to be attributed and specified
on the admin database.
This is an important thing.
Let's keep a note for
the next set of steps
that we're going to do.
All right?
So now it's time for us to
set up our MongoDB server.
We just need to pass along
the configuration options,
and we're good to go.
All right.
Now that we have our MongoDB
server up and running,
it's time for us to
connect to the system
by specifying the port that
we are going to connect
to and start operating with it.
Now right now, we have
connected to this instance
without specifying any
credentials whatsoever, which
is totally fine in MongoDB.
It just means that we
can't do much with it.
The first thing
that we need to do,
and since we have authentication
supported by LDAP,
is authenticate against LDAP.
For that, we connect to
our external database,
getSiblingDB.
The method to do that,
passing along the credentials,
in this case Alice,
the password.
But also don't forget
to specify the mechanism
by which we are authenticating
this particular user,
which in this case is PLAIN.
Great.
We got it.
We are authenticated.
Now we can't do much with it.
If we ask to show collections,
for example, the system's
going to tell us that
we are not authorized.
Now the first thing
that comes to mind
is, well how is
this even possible.
Because the user
is authenticated,
but there's no notion of the
user on this instance here.
Since we rely on LDAP to
hold all of authentication
credentials, but also
authorization credentials,
the definition of the
user is actually based out
of LDIF configuration.
So we don't have the need
to have the user created
on MongoDB instance.
So prior to three or four, the
first thing you should be doing
is basically
creating a user that
will have some
privileged role that
will allow you to do
the administrative roles
like creating users,
creating other resources that
will be needed for the system.
This will be possible because
we are using the local host
exception to do this.
We are connecting through our
local instances to this mongod,
so we could create
this user, no problem.
But now that we have everything
defined on the LDAP server,
we do not need to
create the user at all.
Because all the
definition of the user
is actually defined in
the LDAP configuration.
So after we authenticate,
what we actually need to do
is create a role on
the admin database that
will match the
roles that the LDAP
server is expecting us to have.
This meaning that on
our LDAP configuration,
Alice actually
belongs to a group,
and MongoDB will
interpret this group
as a role that expects it to be
created on our MongoDB server.
Now this is only possible
to do because the local host
exception on three dot
four has been extended
to allow us to create a role
that would enable the user
Alice, or any user that belongs
to this particular LDAP group,
to actually inherit
the role privileges
of userAdminAnyDatabase.
So in this particular
concrete example,
we are going to be
creating a role, which
the name of the role will be the
matching DN name of the group
that Alice belongs to.
We will not be setting
any specific privileges.
And we are going
to be inheriting
the userAdminAnyDatabase
built-in role that MongoDB
contains.
So once we have
the role defined,
we can basically manage
all the privileges
of admin user AnyDatabase, which
includes, for example, granting
roles to other roles.
So if I want to extend my own
role of cn admins, ou users, dc
mongodb and dc com,
and extending the role
to read and write
on database test,
I could obviously use test now,
and I could just, for example,
insert on my collection
notes a message
where I can define that
LDAP authorization is great.
All of this without creating
a single user in my MongoDB
instance.