Now that we actually understand
what authentication is,
we can talk about the different
authentication mechanisms that
are supported with MongoDB.
We can divide these different
authentication mechanisms
into two categories-- There's
client and user authentication,
which deals with how
clients of the database
authenticate MongoDB.
And then there's
internal authentication,
which is how different
members of a replica
set or sharded cluster
authenticate with one another.
Here are all of the different
authentication mechanisms
currently supported
with MongoDB.
In the later video,
we'll go into each
of these with much more detail.
Of the five different mechanisms
that we currently support,
three of them are a part of the
Community version of MongoDB.
Whereas, these last
two, LDAP and Kerberos,
are only a part of the
Enterprise version.
Furthermore, SCRAM-SHA-1
and MONGODB-CR
are considered
challenge-response mechanisms.
Whereas, X.509 is
a certificate-based
authentication mechanism.
And LDAP and Kerberos are
both external mechanisms.