Before we get
started talking about
the different
authentication mechanisms
the MongoDB supports,
I want to clarify
a common point of confusion.
Authentication and
authorization are commonly
interchanged with one
another, but they're actually
two very different things.
Authentication is
the process by which
we verify the
identity of a user,
whereas authorization is the
process by which we verify
the privileges of a user.
The best way to think about it
is that authentication answers
the question, who are you?
Whereas authorization
answers the question,
what do you have access to?
I can be authenticated
to a system,
but I might not be authorized
to control a certain resource.
Authentication enables
us to do authorization.
Once we know who you
are, we can then ask,
what do you have access to?