By now, you should have a pretty
good, high-level understanding
of the different authentication
mechanisms and methods
that MongoDB supports.
We've also talked about some
important topics related
to authentication, like
the localhost exception,
internal authentication
mechanisms,
as well as how authentication
works on a sharded cluster.
In the next several
videos, we're
going to actually see how
to configure authentication
on MongoDB for each of
the different mechanisms
that we've explored
in prior videos.
In this first video,
I'm going to show you
how to set up the most
common authentication
mechanism, SCRAM-SHA-1.
As you know, SCRAM-SHA-1
is the default mechanism
for password-based
authentication with MongoDB.
Let's go ahead and set
up a mongod instance
with SCRAM-SHA-1, and connect
our server with a mongo shell.
Since SCRAM-SHA-1 is the default
authentication mechanism,
it really is this easy.
We just pass the --auth option
to the mongod command line
tool.
When I start running this,
our server is started.
I can then start a new shell.
I just type in mongo
to have the mongo shell
connect to our mongod instance.
This is a clean database.
So I'm going to go ahead and
switch to the admin database.
While on the admin database, I'm
going to run the db.createUser
command, specifying kirby as the
user, password as the password,
and I'm going to go ahead and
use his handy little helper
and just give myself
the role of root,
which gives me all privileges.
I run this.
It successfully added the user.
Now we can either use
db.auth, or close this shell
and start a new one, and
use command line arguments.
Let's go ahead
and do the former.
You can see, just as
we've done before,
I use db.auth, passing
in kirby and password,
and I'm successfully
authenticated.
Of course, if we want, we
can use a configuration
file to enable SCRAM-SHA-1
on a mongod instead
of passing in the information
via the command line options.
Configuration files for
MongoDB are in the YAML format,
and are passed to mongod
using the --config option.
Here we're going to create a
file called config using vim.
You can use any text
editor that you want.
As you can see, in
this config file,
we have this high-level
security key,
followed by this
authorization key
where I've set
authorization to be enabled.
We can then save this file.
And we can now run mongod with
our new configuration file.
We can confirm the
authentication is enabled
by connecting to the
server via the mongo shell,
and running show dbs
without any authentication.
As you can see, the server is
using our configuration file,
enabling authentication,
and preventing us
from executing the
show dbs command.
This command successfully failed
because our configuration file
has successfully enabled
SCRAM-SHA-1 authentication.