in previous videos we've talked about
the different authentication mechanisms
the MongoDB supports in this video I
like to discuss the different
authentication methods that MongoDB
supports by authentication method I mean
the different ways we can actually
authenticate directly with the database
MongoDB supports two different
authentication methods the first is via
the command line we can just pass in
Kerby and password via the - you for
user and - P for password options - the
Mongo shell command-line tool when we
try to run this it will fail to connect
this is because by default the Mongo
shell will automatically connect to the
test database if you remember correctly
we created our user on the admin
database so that means we're going to
want to authenticate to that database
not the test database if he wants to
successfully connect to Munga to be will
need to specify the admin database as
the database that we want to connect to
by specifying admin after the Mongo
shell command and then obviously still
passing in Kerby and password as our
username and password we're specifying
that we want to connect directly to the
admin database instead of the default
test database this also means that will
authenticate with the admin database and
when we run this we are able to
successfully connect to the database we
can verify that I'm authenticated by
running show DB's as you can tell we
have successfully authenticated to the
database sometimes we're going to want
to connect to a database that differs
from the database that our user was
created on or the debates that we're
going to need to authenticate to when
this happens we can use the - -
authentication database option for the
Mongo shell so in this case since we
haven't specified a database that we
want to connect to
we'll connect to the default test
database we'll connect with the username
Kirby and the password password and
we'll authenticate these credentials
against the admin database so as you can
see we have connected to the test
database but I've successfully
authenticated because I can run show
DB's the other authentication methods
supported by mom
DB is to use db2 auth inside of the
Mongo shell we'll go ahead and connect
to the Mongo shell without specifying
any parameters will then switch to the
admin database because that's the
database we want to authenticate with
and then we'll run DB de auth passing
and Kirby and password as parameters to
the DB auth function as you can see we
got a 1 so we know that I'm successfully
authenticated we can verify this again
by running show DBS
it's important to understand that users
are created relative to a database if
I'm authenticated as a user admin like I
am right now I can switch to the test
database and create a user with the
username we'll since we'll was created
on the test database he's only gonna be
able to authenticate via this test
database now that's not to say that the
user isn't authorized to have access to
other databases on the server but the
user must authenticate against the
database that they were created on so if
I try to run the Mongo shell passing in
the admin database passing in will and
password then we'll we'll try to
authenticate against the admin database
which we know will fail because we'll
was created on the test database if we
try again without specifying a database
we will successfully connect because
we'll was created on the test database
and that's the database that we will
default to connect to and yes both users
could have had the same username
I just wanted to use two different
usernames to distinguish the two of them
for this exercise but as a DBA your life
will be much easier if you ensure that
the same username isn't used across
different databases