When a user tries to
authenticate against MongoDB,
we will do a few steps, given
the new LDAP authorization
mechanism.
The first step is to
perform the authentication
of those credentials.
Now again, MongoDB has
several different ways
of authenticating users.
We can use LDAP, Kerberos,
X509, and SCRAM one.
But now, we are going to
be focusing on the ones
that LDAP authorization
mechanism allows.
Basically this
authentication will
be performed via an external
authentication mechanism.
And those will be LDAP,
Kerberos, and X509.
So in this step, we'll pick
up the user credentials
and match it against the
external mechanism defined
for this particular user.
It might be Kerberos
server, LDAP server,
or even a certificate.
Now, the fact that we are
enabling LDAP for authorization
does not mean that we
have to have an LDAP
server for authentication.
Any of the external
authentication mechanisms
can be used--
authenticate the users,
although the LDAP server will
be used for the authorization
components.
So first step, step
number one, authentication
of the credentials
passed to MongoDB back
to the external system in place.
Now, for step
number two, we need
to consider that we might
have different authentication
credentials for the
authorization component
that needs to be
transformed to match
the ones set for authorization.
So if you think about
a very common set
up, like having Kerberos
server for authentication,
validating the users, and
having the new configuration
of MongoDB that authorizes
users using an LDAP server,
these users define on the
different systems might vary.
They will not have the
same formats for Kerberos
or for LDAP server.
So a step that
needs to be done is
to transform the credentials
passed along by the user
to MongoDB to validate
and authenticate
to be able to validate
against authorization.
So once we get a valid
notification, for example,
from Kerberos saying
that our user is valid,
we will need to
transform that user
so it can be matched
against the LDAP
server for the
authorization component.
By default, the
transformation will do nothing
and the authentication username
will be passed to the LDAP
for authorization.
Then step three will
be to actually validate
the authorization.
Now obviously, if we have
the internal authentication
mechanism of MongoDB
for authorizing,
we will not be passing
along to an LDAP observer.
But this lesson is all about
LDAP server for authorization.
So let's have a look to that.
After we transformed
whatever user credential
that we received and having it
validated by the server that
is authenticating it, and only
if needed, because not always
the authorization mechanism
requires a transformation.
By default, it doesn't
do that transformation.
But once it has its final
stage after transformation
or just passing along
the direct user,
this needs to be sent in a
query that will query the LDAP
server for retrieving back all
the distinguished names related
to that user.
Now, our configuration
file, we'll
find a query template, which
will have a curly brackets user
token that will replace by
the transformed credential
to validate against LDAP server.
In this step, MongoDB
will do a query
to retrieve the LDAP
group information.
If the query requests
attributes from an entity,
the attribute values will be
treated as the user groups.
If the query returns
entities, these entities
and distinguished names will
be treated as the user groups.
Our fourth step will determine
that if LDAP authorization is
enabled, the default behavior
determines that each acquired,
distinguished name
will be treated
as the name of a role
on the admin database.
Due to the fact that MongoDB
supports roles [INAUDIBLE],
roles may be created that are
entirely made of other roles
that a given user may possess.
This will facilitate
the creation
of access control
[INAUDIBLE] for our users
and the roles associated
with those users.