Now we're going to talk
about authentication
on a sharded cluster.
For the most part,
this is exactly
the same as authentication
on a standalone server.
However, there are a
few key differences
that you should
be made aware of.
First of all, since we're
dealing with a sharded cluster
instead of a standalone
server, we're
going to want to connect to
a mongos instead of a mongod.
Similarly, when our clients
want to authenticate and connect
to our sharded cluster, they'll
connect and authenticate
through a mongos instance.
In order to go ahead and
set up this sharded cluster,
I'm going to use a really
helpful set of tools
called mtools.
Mtools is, as you can see,
a collection of scripts
to set up MongoDB
test environments,
and parse individualized
MongoDB logs.
So in mtools, there's
this handy utility
called mlaunch, which is a
script to quickly spin up
local test environments,
including replica
sets and sharded systems.
So we'll go ahead
and use mlaunch
to set up our replica set.
So you can see here's mlaunch.
And we're saying that
we want to set up
a sharded cluster
with three shards,
each shard being a replica
set with three nodes.
And we want three
configuration servers.
And we want authentication
to be enabled.
So this will set
up that cluster.
It'll take a second.
We can go ahead
and use ps and pipe
the output into grep to
see what commands were ran
to set up this sharded cluster.
And as you can see
here, we're just
setting up nine different
mongods in the typical fashion,
and then specifying that
we want to use keyFile
for internal authentication
between the nine
different mongods.
And of course,
there's also a mongos.
And that mongos passes in the
different configuration data
to the configuration servers.
And that's how
mlaunch set it all up.
But if we want to go ahead
and connect to this server,
we can just run mongo, and
see that we're connected.
Now, when we try
to run show dbs,
we're not authorized
to run this command
because internal
authentication has now
been enabled on the
server because we're
using keyfile-based
authentication, which
uses internal authentication,
which will automatically
enable client authentication.
The localhost exception does
not apply to us right now
because we used mlaunch.
If we would have set up
this cluster on our own,
we wouldn't have this issue.
But mlaunch
actually, by default,
will set up a user
with the name user,
and the password password.
So we can go ahead and
authenticate against that user
right now.
We're now authenticated
to our sharded cluster,
and we can run commands
like db.system.users.find,
and see the different
users in our system.
And that's pretty much
how authentication
works on a sharded cluster.
Basically, what we do is we
use internal authentication
to automatically enable
client-based authentication
on the sharded cluster.
So there's something I
want to point out here.
As of MongoDB 2.6, user
information like this
is no longer stored
on either the mongos
or on any of our three shards.
This information is actually
all stored on our configuration
servers.
So that's really
important to keep in mind.
So there's another
important thing
I want to point out
to you, and that
is that we still
have the ability
to connect directly to a
mongod in our sharded cluster.
And you're going
to want to do this
at times when you need to
do administrative task,
like cleaning up orphans
or compacting your data
or reconfiguring a
replica set or something.
But this is really
important to point out
because while
authentication is still
applicable on this
individual mongod
because we're using internal
authentication, which
as we know,
automatically enables
client-based authentication,
which prevents me from running
show dbs-- I'm not authorized
to execute this command-- it's
important to realize that
the localhost exception still
applies.
So there are no users on this
individual mongod because,
like I said before, all
the user data is stored
on the configuration servers.
There are no users on
this individual mongod.
So that means that the
localhost exception still
applies if I'm
connected locally, which
means I can just create a user.
So in this case, I can just
create this localAdmin user,
who is a root user.
And now I can
authenticate against them.
And now I have access
to any information
that I want on this shard.
It's important to realize
that this gotcha exists,
and it's probably a good idea to
disable the localhost exception
on your individual shards.
So if you wanted
to do this, you'd
do it via a
setParameter for mongod.
So to show you what
that looks like,
that would look like this.
You would say mongod
--setParameter
enableLocalhostAuthBypass, and
you'd set it equal to false.
And then, of course,
you would still
pass in keyFile and
all the other stuff
that you would use to set
up your sharded cluster.
I'm assuming you're
not using mlaunch.
It's important to
realize that you probably
are going to want to disable
the localhost exception
on your individual mongods
in your sharded cluster
to prevent the risk that
somebody could directly connect
to one of them, and then
do whatever they wanted
on that individual mongod.