Hi there.
Today I'm going to introduce
you to LDAP authorization--
a feature introduced in
3.4 that enhances MongoDB
overall integration with LDAP.
Prior versions to 3.4
already supported LDAP
for authentication purposes.
This meant that MongoDB
could be configured
to authenticate users using an
external mechanism to MongoDB--
a separate service like LDAP.
Now we can also configure
MongoDB to integrate with LDAP
at authorization level.
Before, we could
validate with LDAP
who the user claimed to be.
Now we can use LDAP to
determine what the user is
allowed to do within MongoDB.
Enabling LDAP for authorization
will allow authentication
via any of the existing external
authentication mechanisms
that MongoDB already supports.
This means that we
can set up MongoDB
to use LDAP authorization.
But we can use an alternate
authentication mechanism--
like Kerberos or x509
certificates-- apart
from the obvious LDAP
for both authentication
and authorization.
With MongoDB 3.4, we also
remove the dependency on SASL
proxy for authentication
with LDAP-- except when
users use PAM mechanism.
For integration with popular
single sign on solutions
like Centerfire and Quest.
In these cases, we still
need to use SASL proxy.
Now let's have a look into the
LDAP authorization mechanism
steps.