Let's walk through how to
migrate from MONGODB-CR
to SCRAM-SHA-1.
SCRAM-SHA-1 is highly
recommended over MONGODB-CR.
And you should
only ever encounter
MONGODB-CR on a system
something greater than 3.0
if that system used to be on
an order system, less than 3.0,
and that system was migrated
to a 3.0 or greater system.
The users that were created
on that older system
will still be using MONGODB-CR
until you actually migrate them
over to SCRAM-SHA-1.
All your new users will
still be using SCRAM-SHA-1
on your upgraded system.
Many legacy users will
still be using MONGODB-CR.
So in this video,
we're going to walk you
through the process of how to
migrate those old MONGODB-CR
users over to using
SCRAM-SHA-1, which
is the much more recommended
authentication mechanism.
It's important to point
out that upgrading
from MONGODB-CR to
SCRAM-SHA-1 might require
you to upgrade your drivers.
Just make sure
that you understand
what version of drivers
you're currently using
and what authentication
mechanisms those currently
support.
It's just a good thing to
keep in the back of your mind
when going through this process.
Let's go ahead and connect
to our MONGOD instance
and walk you through
the process of how
to migrate over
your old MONGODB-CR
users to SCRAM-SHA-1.
On this computer, I
was recently running
a version of MongoDB 2.6.
On the 2.6 server, I
created a user called Kirby
whose password is password.
I then upgraded
the server to 3.2.
So we should now have a user
in this 3.2 server's database
that is currently using
MONGODB-CR, which is not cool.
We would much rather it
be using SCRAM-SHA-1.
Let's go ahead and switch
to the admin database
and authenticate.
I'm now authenticated.
Let's go ahead and verify
that this user is still
using MONGODB-CR.
In the system.users collection,
we can run find and see
that the Kirby user is
still using MONGODB-CR.
In order to migrate
over all these users--
in this case just one user--
over to using SCRAM-SHA-1,
we just need to run the
command db.adminCommand(
).
And in running so, it says done.
OK.
And if we look at
our users, we can
see that Kirby is no
longer using MONGODB-CR,
but is rather using SCRAM-SHA-1.
And that's how you migrate
users from using MONGODB-CR
to SCRAM-SHA-1.
As a result of this,
MONGODB-CR is now
completely disabled
on this database.
It is impossible to
create users that use
MONGODB-CR on this database.