Previously we mentioned
there is a step which
concerns a transformation
of the username
and credentials
passed to MongoDB
so they can be validated against
the authentication mechanism.
But also we validate against
the authorization mechanism--
in this case LDAP.
So what will happen
is that MongoDB
will transform
authentication users
into their corresponding
distinguished
names if necessary.
This will be done
by using ordered
lists of regular expressions
and substitution pairs.
Now these lists are
configured by providing
a string representation
of a JSON array
that will contain such pairs.
Now there's a bit more of
process associated with this.
Let's have a look on exactly how
this process is accomplished.
Now let's consider the
following set of scenarios
represented by a decision tree.
We will have initial
set of pairs,
each containing its
expression and substitution.
Now we pick one of these pairs
and analyze the expression
against the credentials
passed on to MongoDB
and validated by the
authentication mechanism.
Now if the expression matches,
we will track all groups
and insert it into
a substitution.
If the situation has attributes,
the transformation is complete.
If it doesn't have
any attributes,
we will check if
our substitution is
represented by an LDAP query.
If so, we'll execute
the substitution query
against the LDAP server
and parse the results.
If we get exactly one match,
our transformation is done.
If we get none, the
expression will fail,
and we'll pick the
next one from the set.
If we get more than one, the
system will automatically fail,
and the transformation
will fail--
meaning that the
expression's set are not
valid for our
transformations step.
That
If all regular
expressions substitution
pairs have been
compared and none
has been successfully matched or
applied a valid transformation,
then our transformation
will also fail.