Now let's take a
moment and discuss
how to configure MongoDB
for internal authentication
between the members of a
replica set or sharded cluster.
There are two methods for
internal authentication
between nodes with MongoDB,
key file based authentication,
and X509 certificate
based authentication.
Let's first walk through
how to set MongoDB to use
key file based authentication.
If you recall
correctly, key files
use the scram shaw
one, challenge response
authentication mechanism.
The key files between the
members of our replica
set act as a shared pass route
between each of the members.
Key files can be between 6
and 1024 characters in length.
And can only contain
characters in the Base 64 set.
Let's go ahead and
generic our key file.
Here I'm going to use the
open SSL command to generate
a random 1024 character string,
random characters, Base 64 set.
755 ends up being 1024
characters with the Base 64
set.
And then we just
redirect this output
to a key file called
MongoDB dash key file.
Now this key file
has been created,
the next thing we want to do is
set this file to be read only.
So here I'm using chmod.
Saying 400 for read only.
And then Mongo DB key file,
they key file we just created.
Now that we have our
key file ready to go,
we can go ahead and create the
members of our replica set.
The first thing we're
going to want to do
is create a folder
for each database.
Here we have replica
set 1, 2, and 3.
Each of which will have
a subfolder called DB.
The -p option for mkdir
will automatically
create folders if there is
some kind of dependency that
doesn't exist.
Now that these folders
have been created,
we can go ahead and
start our first member
in our replica set.
Here is the command to
start our first node.
We're saying MongoD.
We're saying the
repl set option,
giving a name to our replica
set called my repl set.
Of course, we're going
to use db path, log path.
Since we are going to have three
members in our replica set,
we're going to go ahead and
specify ports for each of them.
I'm going to start with 27 0 17.
We're going to pass in the fork.
And then, of course, we're
going to pass in our key file
that we just created.
The first process is
started successfully.
Here's the second member
of our replica set.
The only thing I'd change here
was the file path and the port.
And now we can start
our last member.
Here is the last
member of our replica
set I just changed the
path again and the port
number again.
And all three of our
members are now started.
We can now go ahead
and use the Mongo shell
to initiate the replica set.
Since I used the default port
for our first member of 27 0
17, the Mongo
shell automatically
is going to connect
to that first number.
And from here, we can go ahead
and initialize the replica
set with RS initiate.
The replica set has
now been initiated.
But if we try to add members to
our replica set, we will fail.
And this is because internal
authentication automatically
enables client authorization.
So let's go ahead and
use the locals exception
to create our first user
and then authenticate
against that user.
So we need to switch
the admin database.
And then we can go ahead
and create our user.
I'm creating a user called Kirby
whose password is password.
With a root roll.
It was successfully added.
And now can go ahead and
authenticate against Kirby.
Here we go.
I'm going to use db.auth.
[? pass the end ?]
Kirby, and password.
And you can see we've
successfully authenticated.
And now we can go ahead and add
the members of our replica set.
So here I'm using
replica set add
specifying the
host of my machine
and the port of our second
member which is 27 0 18.
You can see that it
was successfully added.
I can just go ahead and add
the third member of our replica
set.
Awesome.
So now all the members
of our replica set
are using a shared key
file for authentication.
And we can verify
that everything
is good by running rs status.
Here we go.
Here are all the different
members of our replica set.
There is number
one, the primary,
and we have our two secondaries.