We can also use
X.509 certificates
to authenticate the members of a
replica set or sharded cluster.
Like with client base
X.509 authentication,
it's required that we use a
version of MongoDB compiled
with support for TLS/SSL.
For the purposes of
this demonstration,
I've already created my
own X.509 certificates
for the servers.
As you can see here, I have
my certificate authority
public key, a key
file for my client,
and then certificates for each
of the members of my replica
set.
Let's go ahead and
start up a replica
set with X.509 internal
authentication enabled.
The first thing we're
going to need to do
is create the folders
for our servers.
Like before, I'm using mkdir,
passing in the tack p option
with replica set 1, 2, and
3, each with a subfolder
called db.
We can now go ahead and start
up the first member of a replica
set.
Here is the command to start
the first member of our replica
set.
You can see that I'm saying
mongod, specifying the replica
set called myReplSet.
Of course, dbpath, logpath,
and the default port of 27017,
fork.
I'm going to require
ssl since we're
using X.509 authentication.
I'm going to specify
X.509 authentication
as the authorization mode.
And then I'm going to pass
in the first certificate
for this member.
And then our ca file.
Our first member
is up and running.
We can now go ahead and
start the second member.
Here's the command
for the second member.
It's the same as the
last, except we've
changed the dbpath,
logpath, port,
and of course member file.
Our second member
is up and running.
And now we can finally
start the third member.
Here's the third
member's command.
Same as before, except
changing dbpath, logpath, port,
and keyfile.
All three members are
now successfully started.
As you would expect, you can
now connect to these members
and initialise and add
each of the members
like we did in the
previous lesson.
So as you can see, the commands
to start each of our members
are getting kind of long.
It's a little bit hard to read.
Now is a great time to take
advantage of configuration
files to configure each of the
members of our replica set.
I'm going to go ahead and show
you what one configuration
file would kind of look like.
The configuration file
looks pretty much exactly
as you expect.
We have a top level
security field
where we specify the
authorization mode.
We then have another
top level field
called net, which
has a subfield called
ssl, which has three
subfields called mode, CAFile,
and clusterfile.
Just like before.
We can now save this file
and start up our MongoDB
using the --config option,
passing in our configuration
file.
And you could use these
configuration files
again and again and again.
And it will save
you a lot of time.
And it'll actually
prevent you from making
a lot of simple mistakes.