Hi I'm Kirby and I'll be your
instructor for this course.
Security is a key aspect of any
mission critical application
and enterprise environment.
During this course we're going
to cover what security features
MongoDB has to offer,
and the best practices
associated with administering
a secure deployment.
This course is three weeks long.
Each week we'll release a
new lesson video, typically
accompanied by a quiz to assess
your learning of the material.
At the end of each
week there will
be a set of homework exercises.
Let's go ahead and cover
a few of the logistics
of this course.
Target audience.
This is considered
an advanced course.
It's expected that you already
have an understanding of how
to install and run MongoDB,
set up a replica set or sharded
cluster, and have a good
understanding of the MongoDB
query language.
How does grading work?
There are quizzes,
homeworks, and a final exam
as deliverables on your
part of the course.
Quizzes exist as a
formative measure
to make sure you
understand the content.
But your grade will be
based on how well you
do on the homeworks and on the
final exam, each of these being
worth 50% of your final grade.
I'd highly recommend you take
advantage of the discussion
forums.
We have very experienced
teaching assistants
who are there to help
answer your questions.
And your fellow
classmates are also there
to help answer your
questions and are very often
helpful and
knowledgeable resources.
Based on our
experience, we've seen
that students who perform
best in the course
are those who take advantage
of the discussion forums.
As far as course
content is concerned,
we'll take a deep dive into
the different authentication
mechanisms that
MongoDB provides.
We'll talk about MongoDB's
different authorization models
and how to configure
it to your needs.
We'll then cover how
to configure and enable
encryption for your database.
After that we'll discuss
auditing capabilities
that MongoDb provides.
And finally, we'll
discuss some security
best practices that anyone
running a production system
should follow.
By the end of this course,
you should feel confident
that you can deploy a secure
MongoDB deployment where
you can configure the
role based authorization
model to your needs, set up
encryption, do proper auditing,
and follow security
best practices.
With all that being said,
we're super excited to have you
as a student in this course.
Best of luck.