In this lesson, we're going to
discuss a new feature in Atlas
called the Sample Data Set.
Atlas now exposes
some sample data
that you can load
directly into Atlas
for users who want to
explore data immediately
after creating their cluster.
Some users create Atlas
clusters for production use,
and they know exactly what
data they want to work with.
Those users might
already have their data
in a bsondump or a JSON file.
So they can use the
command-line tools
mongorestore and mongoimport
to load that data into Atlas.
And until this release,
those command-line tools
were the only means of
getting data into Atlas.
But this requires users
to leave the Atlas site,
open a terminal window or
command prompt, and then use
a command-line tool, which
can be time consuming.
Another caveat of using
the command-line tools
is that you already
have some sample
data that you want to import.
Finding good sample
data, the kind
that facilitates exploration,
can be difficult.
And we want to make sure
users can explore data
right off the bat.
So we've released
a new feature that
allows users to load a sample
data set into Atlas directly
from the Atlas UI.
This sample data set
was curated internally,
and it's intended to give users
a decently large-sized data set
to play around with.
So we can load the
sample data set as soon
as we've created a cluster.
If we navigate to
the Collections tab,
Atlas will notice that
there's no data in here,
and it'll give us two options.
The first is to load the sample
data set into our cluster,
and the other option will allow
us to manually create data
using the Atlas Data Explorer.
Choosing to load
the sample data set
shows us this modal,
which has a link
to the docs page explaining
the different collections
in the sample data set.
And this docs page is
very detailed with respect
to sample documents
from the collection,
the indexes in each collection.
If we look in the
Airbnb listings,
we can see the indexes
that have already
been created on this data set
as well as a sample document
from the collection.
So we can actually learn
a bit about this data
before we even import it.
But we're just doing some
exploration on free tier
so we can load this
without actually worrying.
So here, I'm just going
to click the option
to load the sample data set.
It should take a minute.
So after loading
the data set, we
can immediately explore the
data using the Atlas Data
Explorer, which is very similar
to the interface provided
by Compass.
One of the reasons
this is so powerful
is because it allows us to
start exploring data in MongoDB
without ever leaving
the Atlas site.
And if we get the motivation to
write some application backed
by this Atlas
cluster, we'll already
know a bit about this data.
This data set
contains a diverse set
of data spanning a few
different industries, including
movies in the mflix data set,
weather in the weatherdata data
set, and housing data
in the Airbnb data set.
The collections contain
a few different document
shapes with varying
degrees of complexity
and just about every data
type that we allow in MongoDB.
This data set is intended to
be a playground for newcomers
or really anyone interested
in exploring data on MongoDB.
We hope that it will cultivate
the kind of exploration that
excites users about MongoDB
without ever leaving their web
browser.
So just to recap, this
new sample data set
can be loaded directly
from the Atlas website,
mitigating the need for
a command-line tool.
The data set is intended to
facilitate data explorations,
so it contains a few
different collections
that vary in
industry, data types,
as well as document shapes.