Welcome back.
We've made some improvements
to cloud providers snapshots
in Atlas.
Atlas now supports
Cloud Provider Snapshots
from Microsoft Azure, Amazon
Web Services, and Google Cloud
Platform-backed clusters.
Previously, there
were some restrictions
in the functionality we had
available for Google Cloud
Platform.
We've added incremental backup
functionality using snapshots
in GCP--
that is to say that we
only store a copy which
contains the documents
which have been altered
since the last full backup.
It's important to
note that we're
utilizing the cloud provider's
native capabilities of taking
a snapshot.
These snapshots are
effectively a disk image,
and taking these snapshots is
handled by the cloud provider.
The incremental
approach means that you
incur less cost
due to there being
less data stored per snapshot.
As the incremental
approach only requires
us to store the delta between
these snapshots as opposed
to storing a full
copy of the snapshot,
incremental backups allow you
to store multiple snapshots
without the disk
space requirements
of a non-incremental approach.
This means Atlas now
supports incremental backups
on GCP and AWS using
Cloud Provider Snapshots.
At present, Azure doesn't
offer this incremental backup
capability.
You can now also use GCP
for multi-region backups.
So how does this work?
Atlas selects the primary
member of the cluster
at the time you enable
snapshots for said cluster.
Atlas stores the snapshot
in the same region
as the primary member, and
Atlas retains the snapshots
based on your retention policy.
So Atlas continues
to use that member
and its corresponding region for
snapshots and snapshot storage,
even if that member
is no longer primary.
We automatically create a
new snapshot storage volume
if the existing snapshot storage
volume runs out of disk space.
We then create a new
volume in the same region
as the cluster's
current primary.
Atlas then takes a
full-copy snapshot
to maintain backup
availability and continues
using that member and
its corresponding region
for further
incremental snapshots.
Let's jump into the UI
and configure snapshot
storage for a Google
Cloud-hosted cluster.
Each backup policy
consists of a snapshot time
and one or more policy items.
The backup policy time
specifies the time of day in UTC
that Atlas takes a snapshot
for the backup policy.
Snapshots taken for
the Hourly policy item
may occur multiple
times each day
depending on the frequency
interval specified.
Each backup policy item
specifies a frequency unit
and an interval and
a retention time.
For example, the
default backup policy
specifies a snapshot
time of 1800 UTC,
an Hourly snapshot with
an interval of one hour
and a retention of two
days, daily snapshots
with a retention of seven
days, weekly snapshots
with an interval of Saturday
and a retention of four days,
and monthly snapshots
with an interval
of the last day of the month
and a retention of 12 months.
So another improvement to our
cloud provider snapshot feature
is the ability to encrypt your
Cloud Provider Snapshots using
your own KMIP server.
This effectively means that
you can bring your own key
to encrypt and
decrypt your backups
through the configured KMS
service for the Atlas project.
As we recently added this
feature to Google Cloud
Platform, this is now supported
across all three cloud
providers.
So let's recap.
Atlas now supports
incremental backups
on Google Cloud
Platform and AWS.
You can now perform cross-region
backups on all three cloud
providers, and you can also
integrate your own KMIP server
and use your own key to encrypt
and decrypt your Cloud Provider
Snapshots.