All right welcome back.
In this lesson,
we'll be discussing
analytics nodes and
the brand new tag
that we can use
for them on Atlas.
So to understand why these
analytics nodes are useful,
we'll start with a replica set
under a typical applications
workload.
The application sends
writes periodically,
and even if the exact amount
of writes vary every day or so,
we know the general trends of
writes over a period of time.
And ideally, our
cluster is built
to support the amount of writes
they will receive at peak time,
regardless of when that
peak time actually occurs.
However, our cluster
is not necessarily
built to handle the workload
from analytics queries.
Analytics are a vital
part of any organization,
and metrics about
a company's product
can completely change
that product's trajectory.
But while reporting is
invaluable to the organization,
it provides some
complications to the database.
Analytics or reporting
queries do not
come from the core
application, and the workload
associated with these
queries is distinctly
different from the workload
of those application queries.
These queries can have a
very large workload that
occurs only every few weeks
or so, and for this reason,
their memory foot print tends
to be considerably larger.
An analytics query could be
an aggregation pipeline run
against one of our
biggest collections,
and for this reason,
these queries
have the potential to
slow down the response
time for the server, and they
could even block other database
operations.
So one of the ways
we can mitigate
this is by sending
these analytics
queries directly to a secondary
node in a replica set.
This won't change the
total number of reads
and writes in the whole
system, because the same number
of reads and writes will come
in and out of the cluster,
but as long as this secondary
that we're sending our queries
does not become the primary,
the acting primary node will
experience fewer
reads as a result.
What will be really ideal
is if we could prevent
this secondary that we're
querying from ever becoming
the primary to ensure sure that
this analytics workload will
always be isolated from
the operational workload.
With the new analytics
node an Atlas,
we can direct our queries to
a read-only secondary that
can't vote and cannot
become the primary node.
Because this analytics node
can't vote in elections,
the total number of
voting members in our set
has not been affected.
And we've essentially
dedicated this secondary node
to analytics and reporting,
so we can create any indexes
that we need on this
node to accommodate
those types of queries.
One caveat of using a secondary
node for any analytics queries
is that we're OK
reading stale data.
The query that we're running
against the secondary could
take a long time and the
primary could receive
writes while this query is
still running on the secondary.
But typically, with
analytics queries,
we're aggregating over
a large amount of data
and we're OK missing out on
that small amount of writes.
So now that we've seen the
value of an analytics node,
we'll see how to add
one to our cluster.
So here if I want to start
building a new cluster.
So this feature is only
available on cluster tiers M10
and up, so the first
thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to change the
cluster tier to M10 here.
And then under Cloud
provider and region,
we can choose Advanced
replication options,
and it will ask us if
we want to add any more
electable nodes,
anymore read-only nodes,
or any more analytics nodes.
So I can add a
region here, and then
say I want to add one
analytics node to my cluster.
I can hit Create
cluster, and we can
see that it's
provisioning 4 servers,
3 or those are voting
members in our replica set,
and the fourth one is
our analytics node.
So now that we've just
created an analytics node
in our cluster, this is
showing the URI options
that we use to connect
directly to the analytics node.
Let's say we built out
our reporting system
in some application.
If we wanted to direct all
that applications traffic
to the analytics node,
we'd add these two options
to the URI string.
We specify that we want to
read from a secondary node,
and then we specify that we
want the tag to read, analytics.
Using these two
options in conjunction
means that if we had more
than one analytics node
and one of them went down,
we could automatically
connect to the other analytics
node that was healthy.
One use case of an analytics
node is with charts.
Charts queries are closely
associated with reporting,
and these types of queries
have a similar workload.
With the Data Sources
tab and charts,
we can specify analytics
to target with our query.
So I'll just choose a
new data source here,
and I'll point of the
cluster I just created,
and I just loaded some
sample data in here.
I'm going to create a chart for
the sample mflix data source.
Published the data source.
So let's say I'm working
on the chart for the movies
collection I can actually
change the configuration here
to edit the read preference.
Change from a
standard secondary,
to an analytics node.
By choosing analytics
node, we can
isolate the workload
of charts queries
from our operational workload.
Just to recap, in
this lesson, we
cover the value of dedicating
nodes for analytics queries
in MongoDB.
These new analytics nodes
cannot vote or become primary,
which supports workload
isolation from our operational
workload.
Now Atlas supports the creation
of these nodes through the UI,
and we can target analytics
nodes with a read preference
option.
We can also specify
an analytics node
when querying through charts.