Let's answer some concerns the
usage of patterns may arise.
Patterns are a way to get the
best out of your data model.
Often, the main goal is
to optimize your schema
to respond to some
performance operation
or optimize it for a given
use case or access pattern.
Although like many
things in life,
good things come at a cost.
Many patterns lead
to some situations
that would require some
additional actions.
For example, duplicating data
across documents, accepting
staleness in some
pieces of data,
writing extra
application side logic
to ensure referential integrity.
Choosing a pattern to be
applied to your schema
requires taking into account
these three concerns.
If these concerns
are more important
than the potential simplicity
of performance gains provided
by the pattern, you should
not use the pattern.