The attribute pattern.
Polymorphic, one of the most
frequent schema design patterns
used in MongoDB.
Polymorphic is when you
put different products,
like these three examples, in
one collection without going
through relational acrobatics.
Our products should
have an identification
like manufacturer, brand,
sub-brand, enterprise
that are common across
the majority of products.
Products' additional
fields that are
common across many products,
like color and size--
either these values may
have different units
and means different things
for the different products.
For example the
size of a beverage
made in the US maybe
measured as ounces,
while the same
drink in Europe will
be measured in milliliters.
As for MongoDB
charger, well, the size
is measured according
to its three dimensions.
For the size of a
Cherry Coke six-pack,
we would say 12 ounces for
a single can, six times
12 ounces, or 72 ounces to
count the full six-pack.
Ultimately we could list
the physical dimension
and report the amount of
the liquid in that field.
Note that physical
dimensions for a beverage
make sense if your
main concern is
the storage or transportation
of the product, not
the drinking of it.
Then there is the
third list of fields,
the set of fields
that are not going
to exist in all the products.
You may not even know
where they are in advance.
They may exist in
the new description
that your supplier
is providing you.
For a sugary drink, you may want
to know the type of sweetener,
while for a battery,
you are more
interested in its
specifications,
like the amount of
electricity provides.
For the characteristics that
are almost always present,
we keep them as fields those
qualify as the common schema
part.
Schema and indexing may appear
in the third list of fields.
To search effectively
on one of those fields,
you need an index.
For example, searching on
the capacity for my battery
would require an index.
Searching on the voltage
output of my battery
would also require an index.
If you have tons of fields,
you may have a lot of indexes.
Remember some of
the characteristics
may be very specific to a few
products and the list of fields
may be unpredictable.
Each addition or discovery
of a new characteristic
may require you to add an index,
modify your schema validators,
and modify your user interface
to show the new information.
For this case you want to
use the attribute pattern.
To use the attribute
pattern you start
by identifying the list of
fields you want to transpose.
Here we transpose the fields
input, output, and capacity.
Then for each field
in associated value,
we create that pair.
The name of the keys for
those pairs do not matter.
Only for consistency, let's
use K for key and V for value,
as some of our
aggregation functions do.
Under the field name K, we put
the name of the original field
as the value.
For the first one, the
field was named "input,"
so that became the value for
K. Then the value for input
was five volts or
1,300 milliamps,
so this is the value
for the field V.
Repeating the same thing for
the original field's output
and capacity, we get three
documents, each adding a K
and a V in them.
Because of their
similar shape it
is easy to place them
together under an "add_specs"
for additional specs array.
Note that for the
third field, not only
do I transpose it
to a key value pair,
but that also added a
third field called U
to store some units separately.
This third field qualifies
the relationship between K
and the V. The last
thing to do is to create
an index for all that info.
This is done by creating
an index on "add_specs.k"
and "add_specs.v."
Let's look at another scenario.
Let's say we have a document
representing a movie.
In the document, there
are several fields
to keep track of when
the movie was released.
In this case, we keep
track of the dates
when a movie was released in
the USA, in Mexico, and France,
and when it appears in the
San Jose movie festival--
a very nice festival.
You should check it out.
One thing to observe
with those fields
is that they share the
same type of value.
In this case, the type, date--
more conceptually,
a release date.
What if we want to find all
the movies released between two
dates across all countries?
I would have to list
all the countries
in the festival
for each of these,
run a separate query
for the given range,
and aggregate all my results.
Using the attribute pattern
and transforming those release
dates to an array
of field pairs,
we can change the query to this.
We can now issue the
following simple query
to find all movies
released in July 2017.
For the sake of simplicity,
I'm using strings
to illustrate the example.
In practice, you
will save the date
as "date" or "isodate" objects.
Let's reorganize a little
bit around what we've been
describing and illustrating.
The attribute pattern
addresses the problem
of having a lot of similar
fields in a document.
Often, those fields have
similar value types.
Or there's a need to search
across many of those fields
at once.
This pattern is
also helpful when
only a subset of the documents
have many similar fields.
The solution would be to
transform fields from the field
value form into a sub-document
with two fields, a sub-document
of two key value pairs.
And the range contains
these sub-documents.
And then you can
create a single index
to catalog all those attributes.
In this lesson, we spoke
about two typical examples
where we often
observe this pattern.
The first would be
characteristics of a product,
while the second highlights
situations where the type was
the same for many fields.
And then, for
example, with movies,
where a different location can
have different release dates.
The main benefit of using
the attribute pattern
is that it becomes more
straightforward to index
all of these fields.
It allows for non
deterministic field names
meaning we don't need to
know all the possible field
names in advance.
We can get new ones on the
fly and still use an index
to optimize the queries.
Finally, another
advantage is the ability
to qualify a relationship
between a key and a value
by adding a third
member in our documents,
representing the transformation.
Here we go.
This is the attribute pattern.
In summary, the
attribute pattern
is orthogonal to polymorphic.
It helps to organize
fields that have
either common characteristics
you want to search across,
or fields that are
rare, or when you
need to manage an influx of
unpredictable properties.
It potentially reduces
the number of indexes.
To use it, transpose
the key/values
of the desired properties
into an array of documents.