Do you have nightmares about
long and complex SQL queries
performing too many joins?
Even if you migrated from a
10 tables relational model
in the tabular database to a 3
collections model in MongoDB,
you might still
find yourself doing
a lot of queries that
need to join data
from different collections.
For sure, your MongoDB
queries are nowhere
going to be as
complicated as in SQL.
But in the world of big data,
anything you do too often
can become a liability
for your performance.
There are a few ways you
can do joins in MongoDB.
Before the MongoDB
servers supported
any joining facilities,
the only possible way
was to do the joins in
the application side.
You retrieve a document
from one collection
and perform a second query that
retrieved the linked documents
in the second collection.
Now the aggregation
framework supports
joins through the
$lookup operation.
There is also a
$graphLookup operator
to perform recursive queries
over the same collection,
a recursive self-join,
similar to the ones you
find in graphed other bases.
But wait.
There is one more
method, and it is
to avoid doing a physical join.
You can embed a one-to-many
relationship on the one side.
Now, what if the join is
coming from the opposite side?
We want to join the one
side into the many side.
An example will be a
collection of orders
which have a many-to-one
relationship with a customer.
One customer can
have many orders,
and one order belongs
to one customer.
A many-to-one
relationship is, in fact,
a one-to-many
relationship looked
at from the opposite side.
Let's say that our applications
focus is on order management
and fulfillment.
And we will query
for specific orders
way more often than
query all the orders
for a given customer.
In other words, the
center of attention
is more often the order
for this type of query.
If we want to embed the
information from one side,
for example, the address of
the customer, into the order,
we are duplicating this
info in all orders.
The preferred way to
do this duplication,
which we identify as our
extended reference pattern,
is only to copy the fields
you need to access frequently,
leaving the rest of the
information in the source
collection.
Basically, instead of
adding a simple reference
from the document in
the invoice collection
to this one in the
customer collection,
we built an extended
reference, meaning
the reference is rich
enough, that we will not
need to perform the
join most of the time.
Every time we talk
about duplicating data,
it is worth understanding
the consequence.
The first thing to understand
is how to minimize duplication.
The extended reference
pattern will work best
if you select fields
that do not change often.
For example, the
user ID of a person
can be complemented by
his name, as people rarely
change their name.
Also, only bring
the fields you need.
When we look up
an invoice, we may
want to see the list of products
with their supplier name.
But there is little reason
to show the phone number
of the supplier at this point.
If we want additional
information,
we can solve the
supplier collection.
Then, when the source
field is updated,
identify what should
be change, meaning
the list of extended
references, and the
when should they be changed.
For example, it may be necessary
to update them right away.
However, sometimes it is OK to
leave the data alone and update
it later in a batch, when
you have available resources.
For example,
changing the ranking
of my best-selling
products does not
require me to instantly update
all the products that spell out
the rank of the
product on their page.
Interesting enough,
the example we
use with invoices
and addresses is
a case where duplication
is not a problem,
but rather the right solution.
When the invoice was
created, the customer
may have lived in one location,
and they have moved since.
If we were to keep the last
address of the customer
in a reference in
the invoice, we
will be pointing to the new
address, not where the products
of this invoice were shipped.
In this case, we
want the invoice
to keep pointing
to the old address.
The characteristic of the
invoice that make it work well
are the fact that the
invoice is created
at a given time in the
timeline, and the invoice
remains static over time.
Any other entity
sharing those characters
is likely to work the
same way, in the sense
that duplication is not an
issue, but a good thing.
Time to formalize our
extended reference pattern.
The problem the extended
reference pattern addresses
is avoiding joining too many
pieces of data at query time.
If the query is frequent
enough and generates
a considerable
amount of lookups,
pre-joining the data can be
done by applying this pattern.
The solution is to
identify the fields you
are interested in on
the looked up side
and make a copy of those
fields in the main object.
You will see this
pattern often used
in catalogs, mobile
applications,
and real-time analytics.
The common thread here is to
reduce the latency of your read
operations or avoid round
trips or avoid touching too
many pieces of data.
You will get faster
reads, due to the reduced
number of joints and lookups.
The price you will pay for
the improvement in performance
is the fact that you
may have to manage
a fair amount of
duplication, especially
if you embed Many-to-One
relationships,
where the fields
change or mutate a lot.
Here you go.
This is our extended
reference pattern.