Let's start with the
concern of duplication.
Why do we have duplication?
It is usually the result
of embedding information
in a given document
for faster access.
The concern is that it
makes handling changes
to duplicated information
a challenge for correctness
and consistency, where
multiple documents
across different collections
may need to be updated.
There is this
general misconception
that duplication
should not exist.
In some cases, duplication is
better than no duplication.
However, not all
pieces of information
are affected in the
same way by duplication.
Let's start with a situation
where duplicating information
is better than not doing it.
Let's link orders of products
to the address of the customer
that placed the order by using
a reference to a customer
document.
Updating the address for this
customer updates information
for the already
fulfilled shipments,
order that have been already
delivered to the customer.
This is not the
desired behavior.
The shipments were made
to the customer's address
at that point in time, either
when the order was made
or before the customer
changed their address.
So the address reference
in a given order
is unlikely to be changed.
Embedding a copy of the address
within the shipment document
will ensure we keep
the correct value.
When the customer moves, we
add another shipping address
on file.
Using this new address
for new orders,
does not affect the
already shipped orders.
The next duplication
situation to consider
is when the copy data
does not ever change.
Let's say we want to
model movies and actors.
Movies have many actors and
actors play in many movies.
So this is a typical
many-to-many relationship.
Avoiding duplication in a
many-to-many relationship
requires us to keep
two collections
and create references between
the documents in the two
collections.
If we list the actors in
a given movie document,
we are creating duplication.
However, once the movie is
released, the list of actors
does not change.
So duplication on this
unchanging information
is also perfectly acceptable.
This leaves us with the
last duplication situation,
the duplication of a
piece of information
that needs to or may
change with time.
For this example,
let's use the revenues
for a given movie, which
is stored within the movie,
and the revenues
earned per screening.
Oh, yeah, with said duplication
add to be a single value in two
locations.
In this case, we
have duplication
between the sum store in the
movie document and the revenue
store in the screening documents
used to compute the total sum.
This type of situation, where
we must keep multiple values
in sync over time, makes
us ask the question is
the benefit of having
this sum precomputed
surpassing the cost and
trouble of keeping it in sync?
If yes, then use this
computed pattern.
If not, don't use it.
Here, if we want the
sum to be synchronized,
it may be the responsibility
of the application
to keep it in sync.
Meaning, whenever the
application writes
a new document to the
collection or updates
the value of an
existing document,
it must update the sum.
Alternatively, we could add
another application or job
to do it.
But how often should we
actually recalculate the sum?
This brings us to
the next concern
we must consider when
using patterns, staleness.