Hello.
In this lesson, we're
going to go over
how to use the JSON
validator tool for the labs
for this and the
following chapters.
Please download the handout
from the lecture notes
below this video.
Make sure to download the
handout that corresponds
to your operating system.
In this case, we're downloading
the Mac OS X handout,
which as the first link in the
lecture notes below this video.
When the download is done, you
might see a warning message.
Select to keep the download.
Navigate to the directory
where the download is stored.
Here, we created an m320
folder for this course,
so we moved the
downloaded file there.
Now, the last thing
that we need to do
to be able to start
validating the upcoming
labs in this course is to change
the permissions in this file
to read and execute.
You can do that by running this
command in the command line.
If you are using
Windows, you do not
need to perform the operation.
From now on, we will be
able to run this validator
from our m320 directory.
Here, you will also see
an example JSON document
that we will use to demonstrate
how our lab validation
tool works.
Our assignment says that the
old document structure no longer
works for our application and
that we need to change it.
Let's start by creating a
JSON file with this schema
so we can modify it
as the task requires.
We just created a new empty JSON
file called answer schema JSON.
We can now copy the old
schema and paste it into here.
Let's save it.
Now, let's run the validator
to see what happens.
Looks like we're
getting an error.
You might want to
figure out what
went wrong without additional
hints, but you don't have to.
To get more details on
what exactly went wrong,
we can add the verbose option,
which will give us more detail.
It says that in-house must be
one of the following-- bool.
Now that we know
what went wrong,
let's do what a
good student does
and read the actual
assignment carefully.
It says here that the updated
version of the application
is expecting to
receive a Boolean
value for the in-house
field instead of an integer,
which seems to match what the
validator error was returning.
Just to make sure that we get
it right this time around,
we're going to click on
this useful link listing
all the valid BSON types.
These are the data types from
the MongoDB query language
which happens to also be
the type that our validator
understands and is able
to process, spelled
exactly the way they are, in the
right column, case sensitive.
Looks like we need to spell
out bool in our solution
as the in-house field value.
Here, as I'm making
a change I'll
accidentally forget to
close the curly bracket
at the end of the document,
which results an invalid JSON.
Let's see if our validator
is able to recognize that.
Looks like it does-- wonderful.
Time to fix this solution
and get the validation code.
Here it is, the curly
bracket back in the file.
Now that I've added the
curly bracket back in,
we have a valid JSON file.
Let's run the validator.
Success.
Here's the validation
code that we can now
copy-paste into the
submission field in the lab.
It is important to note
that this answer document is
a valid JSON document.
But it is also a custom
notation for schema definition,
much like JSON schema,
a link to which you
can find in the lecture
notes below this video.
We opted out of using JSON
schema for this course
because it can be too
verbose for our purposes.