In the previous
chapters, we went
over the basis of data
modeling for MongoDB,
from defining a
flexible methodology
to identifying the different
representation for modeling
relationships.
You should now have
all the knowledge
needed to attack this
week's chapter on patterns.
Patterns are very
exciting because they
are the most powerful
tool for designing schemas
for MongoDB and NoSQL.
This chapter is going to help
you produce solution that can
scale and perform under stress.
Before we go any
further, let me tell you
how we define the word
pattern in our course.
Patterns are not full
solution to problems.
Those are called full solutions.
Patterns are a smaller
section of those solutions.
They are reusable
units of knowledge.
For those of you who are
familiar with software
architecture
design, you probably
know the Design Patterns
book from the Gang of Four.
This book is doing for software
design what our patterns will
do for data modeling and schema
design for document databases.
The patterns we'll go
over in this chapter
will become a cookbook of
powerful transformation
to unleash the power
of MongoDB schemas.
We will see how to optimize
when faced with large documents
with a subset pattern, use
the computed pattern to avoid
repeated computations,
structure similar fields
with the attribute
pattern, handle changes
to your deployment without
downtime with the schema
versioning pattern,
and much more.
Those patterns will also
serve as a common language
for your teams working
on schema designs.
Finally, having
well-defined patterns
and understanding when
and how to use them
will remove a little
bit of the are in data
modeling for MongoDB and make
the process more predictable.
This chapter will have a lesson
to introduce each pattern.
Then we will follow
with a lab to have
you put in practice the
pattern you just learned about.
There is a lot to cover.
However, it will be fun,
and you should profit a lot.
So let's get going.