When you see a
message on your phone
or your laptop telling you that
you're running out of memory,
this is your personal device
being very communicative.
However, your database server
is unlikely to be that direct.
Also you would expect
a database server
to do a better
management of resources
than to simply
run out of memory,
and reporting such message.
MongoDB tries to
optimize the use of RAM
by pulling in memory only
the document that it needs
from the disk through the RAM.
When there is no more
memory available,
it evicts pages that contains
the document it doesn't need
anymore to make room
for more document it
needs to process at the moment.
This [? mechanism ?] allows to
have the hardware configuration
that does less RAM than the
total size of the data on disk.
As long as the size of your
working set fits in RAM,
you get good performance.
The working set
refers to the amount
of space taken by the documents
and the portions of indexes
that are frequently accessed.
Either if you get
into a situation
where the working set
is larger than RAM--
in this picture, the
four red documents
that are needed all the
time, may not fit in memory.
So the server finds itself
often dropping documents.
It will soon have to
fetch back from disk.
This process, of constantly
ejecting documents that
should stay in memory, is bad--
pretty, pretty bad.
The fix can be either one of
the following three solution.
A, add more RAM--
In other terms, scale your
infrastructure vertically.
B-- either start
sharding, or add
more shards if you already
have a sharded cluster.
Sharding has a
similar effect as A,
since you provide more
RAM to the cluster
overall, through
adding machines to it.
This is also called
scaling horizontally.
Or C-- reduce the size
of the working set.
This last solution tries
to resolve the problem
without throwing money at it.
For the purpose
of this lesson, we
are going to consider reducing
the size of the working set.
The key to that is breaking up
huge documents, which we only
need a fraction of it.
For
Example, let's say
we have a system that
keeps a lot of movies in
memory, and each of these movies
is taking a fair
amount of memory.
Maybe there are some information
that we don't need to use that
often in those documents.
For example, most
of the time users
want to see the top actors
and the top reviews,
rather than all of them.
As for the fields here at
the bottom-- comments, quote,
and release--
it's also unlikely that you need
all of them, most of the time.
We could keep only 20 of the
cast members, the main actors--
and also 20 of each of
those comments, quote,
release, and reviews.
The rest of the information can
go into a separate collection.
It means if you start with a
document that has all the info
in it, a field that has a
one-to-one relationship--
for example, the full script--
could be moved to
a new collection.
And you could access this
information through the dollar
lockup operator.
As for a field that has
a one-to-N relationship,
you can move most of those
objects to another collection
and keep only a subset
of the N relationship
in the main document.
The result on the working
set is the following.
Here, each document
has been split
into the part that is
frequently accessed
and the part that
is rarely accessed.
Now that the
documents are smaller,
the whole working set
can fit in memory.
And we have additional memory
to bring in the data we only
need to rotate.
Let's organize what we've been
describing and illustrating
a little bit.
The problem to the
subset pattern addresses
is that too many frequently
use pieces of information--
or I checked it
from memory, which
can be identified by observing
a working set that this
too big to fit in memory.
Digging into the majority
of documents in memory,
we can observe that
we only make use
of a small subset of
information in those documents.
So a large part of those
documents is rarely needed.
Our solution is to break
apart the documents that are
taking too much space in RAM.
We will divide the fields of
information into two camps--
the field that are often
required by our system,
and the ones that
are rarely required.
This division is frequently used
for one-to-many or many-to-many
relationship, for
which you only want
to keep a subset of the
many associated document.
In which type of
applications or situation
are we likely to
apply this pattern?
A list of reviews for a product,
a movie, or news articles--
well, anything that can
be discussed or reviewed.
List of anything
that can be long
and carries much
more data than anyone
can or wants to process or read.
If this list takes a
substantial amount of memory,
they are good candidates to be
offload to another collection.
As a result of applying
the subset pattern,
our working set will
not only be smaller,
but it will make retrieving
additional documents faster
since they will be smaller.
On the other hand, there
are some trade-offs.
First, you have more
documents to retrieve,
which means that
you may have to make
more round trips between the
application and the server.
And second, the fact that
you break documents in two
and duplicate some info
means that the database
will require a little
bit more space on disk.
However, this is not a
big issue as this space
is much cheaper than RAM.
That's it.
This is how the
subset pattern works.
In summary, the subset
pattern is a great pattern
to help you reduce the size of
your working set by splitting
information that you
want to keep in memory,
versus information that
you fetch on demand.