Staleness is about
facing a piece of data
to a user that may
have been out of date.
We now live in a world
that has more staleness
than a few years ago.
Due to globalization and
the world being flatter,
systems are now accessed by
millions of concurrent users,
impacting the ability to display
up-to-the-second data to all
these users more challenging.
For example, the
availability of a product
that is shown to
a user may still
have to be confirmed
at checkout time.
The same goes for prices of
plane tickets or hotel rooms
that change right
before you book them.
Why do we get this staleness?
New events come along at such
a fast rate that updating data
constantly can cause
performance issues.
The main concern when
solving this issue
is data quality and reliability.
We want to be able to
trust the data that
is stored in the database.
The right question
is, for how long
can the user tolerate not
seeing the most up-to-date value
for a specific field.
For example, the
user's threshold
for seeing if something
is still available to buy
is lower than knowing how
many people view or purchase
a given item.
When performing
analytic the queries
it is often understood
that the data may be stale
and that the data being analyzed
is based on some past snapshot.
Analytic queries are often run
on the secondary node, which
often may have stale data.
It may be a fraction of a second
or a few seconds out of date.
However, it is enough
to break any guarantee
that we're looking at the latest
data recorded by the system.
The solution to
resolve staleness
in the world of big data
is to batch updates.
As long as the
updates are run within
the acceptable
thresholds, staleness
is not a significant problem.
So, yes, every piece
of data has a threshold
for acceptable
staleness that goes
from 0 to whatever makes sense
for given piece of information.
A common a way to
refresh stale data
is to use a Change
Stream to see what
has changed in some
documents and derive
a list of dependent piece
of data to be updated.
Change Stream's
a new application
to access and respond to data
changes, either in real time
or in a delayed mode.
Please consult our docs
for a complete description
of this MongoDB feature.