Our third concern,
when using patterns,
is referential integrity.
Referential integrity has some
similarities to staleness.
It may be OK for the system
to have some extra or missing
links, as long as they get
corrected within the given
period of time.
Why do we get referential
integrity issues?
Frequently, it may be
the result of deleting
a piece of information
[INAUDIBLE]
document-- for example, without
deleting the references to it.
In the big data
world, we can also
associate referential
integrity issues
to adding distributed
system, where
a related piece of information
live on different machines.
At this time, the MongoDB server
does not support foreign keys
and associated cascading
deletes and updates
responsible for keeping
referential integrity.
It is the responsibility of
the application to do so.
Here again, the main concern is
data quality and reliability.
For delayed
referential integrity,
we can, again, rely
on change streams.
For keeping the referential
integrity [INAUDIBLE],,
we can avoid using references
by embedding information
in a single document,
instead of linking it.
Or we can use MongoDB with be
multi-document transactions
to update multiple documents
at once [INAUDIBLE]..
To recap, we can tame these
three concerns-- duplication,
staleness, and
referential integrity--
by understanding the
following for every piece
of data in your database.
Should or could the information
be duplicated or not?
And if it has to be duplicated
and consistently updated,
resolve the duplication
with bulk updates.
What is the tolerated
or acceptable staleness?
Resolve with updates
based on change streams.
Which pieces of data require
referential integrity?
Resolve or prevent
inconsistencies
with change streams
or transactions.