Now that we understand
the basics of Explain,
let's take a quick look a
slightly more complex example,
running Explain on
a sharded cluster.
Here I'm using
mlaunch from mtools
to set up my sharded cluster.
Now that my cluster's up and
running, let's enable sharding.
First, I'm going to enable
sharding on the m201 database
and then I'm going to go ahead
and shard the people collection
on the _id index.
Now, this is a
brand new database.
So let's go ahead and
import some documents.
And here's our good old
mongoimport command.
And from here, we can go
ahead and check that we
have data on multiple shards.
And as you can see I have
most of my data on shard one,
and a little bit of
my data on shard two.
And that's fine for
this demonstration.
Now, when this query
is ran on the mongos,
not much is happening
on that mongos itself.
The mongos is going to send
the query to each shard
and then each shard is
going to evaluate the query,
select a plan, and then
all that information
will be aggregated
back on the mongos.
So most of the time, we would
expect that the same plan
be chosen for each shard.
But it may happen that a shard
chose a different plan simply
because it had less or
more data to process.
And this output is very similar
to what we've been seeing.
If we go up to the
winningPlan, we
will see that the last stage
is to this shard merge.
And so when we drill
in here, we can
see that we have
this shards array,
and we first have shard 1.
And shard 1 has a
winning plan which
was to do a collection scan.
And then there's also shard
2, whose winning plan was also
to do a collection scan.
So all those documents
were passed back up
to the mongos, where they
were merged together.
Now that we've
done the hard work
at looking at the
full Explain output,
let's see how we can browse this
information in an easier way.
And for that, we're
going to use Compass.
And so here's Compass
and I'm already
on the people collection.
And I can go ahead and
click this Explain Plan tab.
And from here, I
can go ahead and run
the query we've been running.
And this is really
cool because we
get this awesome visual output
where we can see our index scan
followed by our fetch stage.
And we can also see all
the important information
that we've been looking at.
And now if we want to drill
into any information that
isn't highlighted up here, we
can just click this Raw JSON
tab, and we're going to see
this JSON object that we've been
looking at this whole time.
And we have the ability to
hide the different fields
we don't care about, and open
up fields that we do care about.
It's pretty slick.
In summary, we've seen
that the Explain command
is extremely powerful in helping
us troubleshoot slow queries.
Its output is quite rich.
However, there's a few
pieces of common information
that we'll be looking at.
Things like execution time,
the number of keys read,
documents read, and
documents returned,
and obviously, the
plans that were selected
and the ones that were rejected.
Let's recap what we've learned.
We've extensively looked
at all the information
that's Explain provides us.
We've talked about how it works,
and the different arguments
that we can pass in.
We've seen what Explain outputs
look like on a sharded cluster.
And we've also seen
the awesome view
that MongoDB Compass
gives us into Explain.