Now, most of these
tools can be run by you
or you can just review
the published results.
That's all fine.
You can pick a tool of
choice and run tests
on MongoDB or any
other database.
But let's make sure that you
understand the conditions
by which those tools and those
tests are going to be run.
Again, majority of the tooling
for benchmarking existing today
had been built with
relational systems in mind.
And those conditions not
always apply to MongoDB
and other modern databases.
Now, if you're only interested
on doing a small set of testing
using read and write
ratios from MongoDB,
my good friend, John Page,
this young, attractive fellow
over here, built the POC driver.
It's a small project
written in Java
that allows you to put
to test your MondoDB
cluster to a set of
conditions and a set
of different variations that
you can set by yourself.
All of the previous are great.
You can run it yourself.
You can just run the tests
which are genetically available
online, or even use
John Page's POC driver.
But sometimes they are
not really what we need,
perhaps because they do not
capture the essence of your use
case or they are missing out
on some specific functionality
of MongoDB that you
are interested in.
But let's not forget about
benchmarking anti-patterns.
Because if you're running
you're testing yourself,
let's make sure you do it right.
Now, those anti-patterns can
be things like database swap
replace.
Let's say, for example, that
we are comparing MongoDB
with a relational system where
your relational system would
be something like this where
you have some sort of relations
and tables and the relationships
between those tables.
Now, if you are expecting to
replace the exact same schema
from your relational world
to MongoDB collection world,
probably a one-by-one
one relationship
between tables and
collections might not
be the best way to go forward.
This may not be reflecting
MongoDB's capabilities
and, therefore, will not
be a truly comparison
between two different systems.
You need to think
a little bit more
about how you're
going to operate data,
how are you going to insert,
how are you going to read,
how you're going to
structure your documents.
All of that will be a great deal
of concern if you do not do so.
Also, using MongoDB tools to
test performance of MongoDB
is probably not a great idea.
If you're building your
application on top of the mongo
shell, for example, where
all requests of your code
invoke the mongo shell and
perform an operation, then yes.
Then that will be
the ideal scenario
to test the performance
using the mongo shell.
And by that we mean by testing
these sort of things where
you can run some sort of
cycle inside of mongo shell,
insert a bunch of
documents, and then you
get a response at the end saying
how much time did it execute.
If that's your use case, where
you invoke the mongo shell
from your application,
then go ahead.
That's a good way
of benchmarking.
But I'm not really sure that
that's exactly what you want.
Also, using mongoimports to test
write response of your MondoDB
installation is also
kind of dubious in terms
of what you are really
trying to achieve there.
Your laptop might be great.
I'm pretty sure
it's a nice machine
with a bunch of stickers
on it and all of that.
But assuming that any
performance testing
that you run from your laptop,
aside from any unit tests
or development testing that
you might be interested on,
might not be the
best way to assess
if MongoDB or any
database by that matter
actually performs accordingly
with your expectations.
Please use a purpose
server to run your tests.
And, finally, using MongoDB
out-of-the-box parameters
probably is not what you're
going to find in production.
That means that if you're
going to run your application
with MongoDB installed
on it and the only thing
that you do is download
the binary and boot it up,
that's great.
That's how MongoDB works.
But you might want to consider
things like authentication.
Now you may want
to consider, how
do you going to be dealing
with the high availability.
And testing, especially
benchmarking for performance
without those
conditions in place,
will be shooting
yourselves in the foot.
So be careful about that.
And that drives to the
benchmarking conditions.
Make sure you're fair,
you're fair in terms
of the comparisons
that you do concerning
the hardware that you're
utilizing the type of clients
and the type of operations
that you're doing,
and the kind of load that
you're going to be subjecting
your systems to.
Either different systems
or different versions
of the systems that
you are testing,
they should have a fair ground
in all those three dimensions.
Let's recap this lesson.
So, in this lesson, we talked
about the different types
of benchmarking that
you can do, either using
publicly-available data sets
and tools or building your own.
There's different types
like low-level, high-level,
distributed, load, a
bunch of different ones.
You can even do your own
specific benchmarking.
There's obviously
different public tools
available out there that
benchmark databases.
But make sure that you
are using the one that
is more suited to
the database that you
are interested in testing.
And don't forget about
the anti-patterns
of MongoDB benchmarking.
These are very, very
important to for you
to get a truthful view of
how the system is actually
going to be behaving.
And that's all we have
for basic benchmarking.