In this lesson, we are going
to talk about benchmarking.
Now we are not going to be
going through the full process
of benchmarking.
But basically just
highlighting some things
that you should take
in consideration if you
are going to benchmark MongoDB.
Once we start analyzing
a given software product
like a database, operating
system, or application server
we need to understand the
benefits that such component
brings to our application.
And for that we
use benchmarking.
Now there are different types
how to perform benchmarking.
Also, there's the other
concept of bench marketing.
Now there's a big difference
between benchmarking and bench
marketing.
Both have related value,
depending on the audience.
But we will be focusing
on the first one.
The one that allows us to
correlate with performance
indicators and
metrics that we can
use to assess if a given product
is actually good for our system
or not.
Benchmarking
assumes that you are
going to perform some
sort of comparison.
You can use publicly
available test suites,
and we're going to talk
about a bunch of those,
or you can also perform your
own private testing that
correlates better with your
use case or application.
Now there are different types
for each kind of performance
benchmarking that get more
specific or more broad
aspects of the benchmarking
that you might be trying to do.
So let's have a look
to a few of them.
We can perform low
level benchmarking.
Now what I mean by low level
benchmarking, our benchmarking
that are designed to
look into file I/O
performance, or
scheduler performance,
or even memory allocation
and transfer speeds.
There are benchmarking that
look into thread performance,
database server performance,
transaction isolation,
and multiple of
other parameters.
Tools like sysbench,
or even iibench
are good tools that allow you to
go very deep into the low level
benchmarking kind of testing.
Now there's also another
type of benchmarking,
which is the database
server benchmarking.
Now these tests are more
concerned about things
like data set load,
writes per second,
reads per second,
balanced workloads,
read and write ratios.
Things that will allow you to
understand how a database will
react with generic
data sets, but will
take into consideration
the output of a given node,
and look into
metrics to correlate
if there's been some sort
of advantage or disadvantage
of using a specific product.
Some tools like YCSB,
originally developed by Yahoo,
or even the TCP ones, which are
industry benchmarks in all it's
sorts and different
variations, are good test base
that you can submit
a database to.
Now do not forget that a
bunch of these tools that
do database server
benchmarking have been original
developed for
relational systems.
And if you are testing
those with MongoDB in mind,
some variations might
need to be applied
because a lot of the
different functionality you
might be expecting does
not behave in the same way.
So if you're looking
for YCSB, make
sure that you look
for a variation that
correlates better to
MongoDB, or does it perfect
what MongoDB does to actually
get some solid results?
And then we also
have distributed
systems benchmarking, which
for MongoDB is a big thing
because given that we are
a distributed database,
it is important not only to
look into a particular node,
but also how things react
under a distributed system.
Here, you want to do very, very
hard tests like linearization,
serialization, fault
tolerance, where
we will look into a bunch
of different perspectives
on how things occur over
time, how we can deal
with the serialization
of requests,
the linearization
of reads and writes.
And also, when we have
different DataNodes.
And if those nodes fail, how
does the overall system behave
under those conditions?
You can do that your
own set of testing
for distributed systems.
Now there are very good
data sets out there
like iBench, which is
more related to Hadoop
environments, and Jepsen,
which actually does
a very nice set of
reports on how different
databases react under a very
specific setting of conditions.
In this case, we
actually include
Jepsen tests in our MongoDB
build continuous integration
tooling.