In this lesson, we're going to
talk about building indexes.
Specifically, we're going
to spend some time talking
about the trade offs between
foreground and background
indexes.
We'll also talk about how we
can use background indexes,
and under what conditions
we would do so.
And finally, we're going to
look at currentOp and killOp,
and see how they relate
to building indexes.
Now we want to give some
special consideration
to the process of creating an
index for a few key reasons.
Most of what we'll cover
here is of primary concern
in production
MongoDB deployments,
because you'll want to
ensure minimal impact
on your application users.
MongoDB provides the
option of creating an index
in either the foreground
or the background.
Foreground indexes
are very fast,
but they block operations
to the database.
Specifically, an index
built in the foreground
will block all
incoming operations
to the database containing
the collection on which you're
building the index.
This means that
the database that
holds the collection is not
available to application
reads or writes until the
index build is complete.
This is unacceptable for
production MongoDB deployments,
except possibly during
a maintenance window.
As an alternative, MongoDB
provides the option
of a background index build.
The trade off is that, while
background indexes don't
block operations, they
take longer to complete.
How much longer is going
to depend on your read
write load in the foreground,
as well as other factors,
like whether the index will
fit entirely into memory.
Both background and
foreground indexes
are going to impose
load on your database.
Building an index
in the background
will still have some
impact on query performance
while the index is
being built. In a system
with sufficient resources,
a background index
is probably preferrable
if you don't want
to impose a maintenance window.
We're going to use
a new restaurants
dataset for this lesson.
You can import it here with
the mongoimport command.
We're going to pretend
that this dataset is
used for a production
application
where we need to
add a new feature.
This is going to give us an
example of the consideration
that you're going to want to
take into account when building
an index in production.
This new feature will require
us to build a new compound
index on this dataset.
Here I'm using MongoDB
Compass to take
a look at our new
restaurants collection.
Here's the schema
view, where I can
look at all of the
different fields
of a sampling of our documents.
I have the ability to
look at the cardinality
of the different fields,
as well as drill down
into different
embedded documents
and see what kind of
values these fields hold.
Briefly, let's take a look
at an example document
in the document view
inside of Compass.
Here, we can see that this
data set describes restaurants
in the United States.
Here is a restaurant
called Redhill Station
that serves Mediterranean
food, has 3.4 four stars,
and it's in North Carolina.
Suppose our new feature
is going to require
us to build a compound index
so that we can support queries
where we sort by name, where we
specify a particular cuisine,
and we specify a
range of zip codes.
Given the number of
documents in this collection,
we think that this is going to
take a decent amount of time
to create this index.
How long is going to depend on
the cardinality of the fields,
as well as how much
load is on the database
server from other operations.
Here's an overview
of the requirements
that we're going to have
for adding this new index.
We want to make sure that we
add a new compound index, which
we think is going to
take some time given
the number of documents
in our collection.
We really don't want to
schedule a maintenance window.
So we want to do this
with no downtime.
And we think that our new
index will fit into RAM.
A background index build
is a great option here.
Let's go ahead and do
it from the Mongo shell.
To create our index
in the background,
here's the command
that we'll issue.
You can see, here's the index
that we talked about building.
But I've also added
this special argument,
where I'm saying that
background is going to be true.
By default, background
is set to false,
so that's why we're
using the special option.
We can use this approach
to build indexes
in the background on
a standalone MongoDB,
or on the primary or
secondaries in our replica set.
Now, background index operations
run in the background,
so that other database
operations can run
while we're creating the index.
However, you'll see that
the Mongo shell is still
blocked until the index
build is complete.
We'll know that the index
build has completed, when
the connection is
no longer blocked
and we see an output
indicating the outcome of our
build operation.
To continue issuing
commands to the database,
we're going to open up
another mongo shell,
and we can do that right now.
So our build has been
running for a bit,
and you might be
wondering whether we
can check in on how our build
process is coming along.
And we absolutely can.
To see the status of
our build operation,
we can use the db.currentOp
command from the Mongo shell.
We can take this
command a bit further
and specify a filter to see
what specific current operations
we want to look at.
Here I'm using the OR
operator to look for commands
that are creating indexes, or
if we're inserting documents
into the system.indexes
collection.
And here you can
see the operation
for building our index.
Here we can see that
we're creating indexes
on the restaurants
collection, and here the keys
that specify the index
that we're creating.
Notice this field here, opid,
and this random looking number.
This is a unique identifier
for this specific operation.
And this is the ID that
we need if for some reason
we want to kill the index
build before it finishes.
We can do this using db.killOp.
And here's the kill up command.
It takes a single parameter
which is that op ID
number that we just looked at.
Here I'm just saying one,
two, three, four, five.
But in reality, if we wanted
to really kill an operation,
we would use that opid.
And this will kill
the operation.
We're going to take deeper
dives into currentOp and killOp
in other courses, so
please see those lessons
for more detail
on how to maximize
the value of these
methods for your purposes.
And here after a
little bit of waiting,
we can see that our
index creation completed.
We know this because
we got a response
indicating how many
indexes there were before,
and how many there are
now after our build.
Let's recap what we've learned.
So in this lesson, we
discussed the trade
offs between foreground and
background index builds.
We looked at under what
circumstances background
indexes are better over
foreground indexes.
We looked at under what
circumstances background index
builds are better than
foreground index builds.
And finally, we touched on the
currentoOp and killOp methods
as tools that you should
be aware of as you expand
your skills of
understanding performance
concerns for
MongoDB deployments,
and how to evaluate and
address performance problems.