In this lesson, we're going
to talk about query plans.
By the end of this
lesson, you should
be familiar with
what query plans are,
how the query optimizer
works with them,
and how they're cashed.
Let's go ahead and talk
about what a query plan is.
I think the best
way to illustrate
this is with an example.
When a query comes
into the database,
a query plan is formed.
Which is a series of stages
that feed into one another.
So in the case of this
query, for this given index,
we'd expect the query
plan to look like this.
Since we have an index
on zip code and cuisine,
we're able to fetch the record
IDs of the documents that
meet our query predicate.
From there, those record IDs are
passed up to the fetch stage.
This is where the
storage engine is
going to convert the
record IDs into documents.
And then those
documents are then
passed up to the sort stage,
where an in-memory sort will
be performed on them.
This is the only
reasonable query plan
for this query on this index.
But for a given query, we can
have many different query plans
based on what indexes
are available.
So if we have an index like
this, on a cuisine and stars,
this could prevent
an in-memory sort.
So we'd have a query
plan like this.
Here we'd do an index scan.
Where we fetch the record IDs
of our documents in store order.
We then pass this up
to the fetch stage
where they're converted into
documents and then returned.
So the available
indexes will determine
what possible query plans we
can use to satisfy our query.
Now that we know
what a query plan is,
let's talk a little bit
about how they're chosen.
When a fresh query
comes into the database
for the first
time, the server is
going to look at all
the available indexes
on the collection.
From there, it will
identify which indexes are
viable to satisfy the query.
We call these candidate indexes.
From these candidate
indexes, the query optimizer
can generate candidate plans.
Now MongoDB has what is
called an empirical query
planner, which means that
there is going to be a trial
period, where each of
the candidate plans
is executed over a
short period of time.
And the planner will then see
which plan performed best.
I don't want to get too
into the weeds here,
but best can be which plan
returned all the results first.
Or it might be, which returned
a certain number of documents
in store order fastest.
There's a lot of different
ways we can describe best,
and the query optimizer will
do it in different ways,
depending on the query.
And so for this run,
this is the winning plan.
If we were to run
explain and look
under the winning
plan field, this
is the plan it would
be talking about.
And so these other plans would
fall under the rejected plans
field.
Now, it wouldn't make
much sense to run a trial
run for every query that
came into the database.
We're going to have a
lot of the queries that
are going to have the same
shape and would benefit
from the same query plans.
Because of this, MongoDB
caches which plan it
should use for a
given query shape.
Now, over time,
our collection is
going to change in some
[INAUDIBLE] indexes.
What this means is, under
different conditions,
the plan cache
will evict a plan.
This can happen if the
server is restarted.
Or if the amount
of work performed
by the first
portion of the query
exceeds the amount of work
performed by the winning
plan by a factor of 10.
Plans are also evicted when
the indexes are rebuilt,
or if an index is
created or dropped.
And that should give you a
good overview of query plans.
Let's recap what we've learned.
We spent some time talking
about what query plans are.
We also discussed how the
query optimizer works,
and how it determines
which plan is best.
And we also discussed query
plan caching so that we're not
running trial periods
for every query that
comes into the database.