In this lesson, we're going
to discuss how we can force
indexes using the hint method.
And specifically,
we're going to discuss
how we can force a query
to use a particular index,
therefore overriding MongoDB's
default index selection
by using the hint method.
Throughout this
course, we spent a lot
of time discussing how to design
the optimal index for a given
query.
Unfortunately, for
one reason or another,
the query optimizer
might not always
choose the index that we'd like
to be chosen for a given query.
In this case, maybe this
query uses the name age index
instead of the name
zip code index,
like we would like it to.
Fortunately for
us though, MongoDB
provides an easy way to
override the query optimizer's
selection.
And this of course,
is done with hint.
In this example, I'm appending
the hint method to my query,
so that we're forcing
the usage of name
ascending zip code ascending.
And here, I am using
the indexes shape
to tell hint what
index we want to use.
Other than using the
shape, we can also
just pass the actual
name of the index
to hint, to let it know
what index we want to use.
And that's pretty
much how hint works.
I do want to point out that you
should use hint with caution.
MongoDB's query
optimizer generally
does a pretty good job of
selecting the correct index
for a given query.
The times when it does
fail to select the best
index for a given
query is generally
when there are a lot of
indexes on your collection.
And in those cases,
it's probably better
to look at index
utilization and determine
if you have superfluous indexes
that can be removed rather
than using the hint method.
So to quickly recap what
we learned in this lesson,
we discussed how we
can use the hint method
to override MongoDB's
default index
selection for our queries.