The most intensive resource
utilization by your indexes
will be RAM or memory.
Our deployments should
be sized in order
to accommodate our
indexes in RAM.
This means that we should have
enough space in our memory
to accommodate all
of our indexes.
That's a good role of
thumb in terms of sizing.
Now if we don't have
enough space in our memory
to accommodate our indexes,
a great deal of disk access
will be required to
traverse your index file.
If you have different
pages on the index,
they will be allocated
to your memory.
If you are traversing
that space,
it means that you will slide
your pages into positions that
are no longer in memory, so
allocating those into memory,
and flushing out
information to disk.
If you are constantly
traversing your index,
you will be doing a lot
of page in and page out.
Now the first assessment
that you should do
is make sure you understand
the capacity of the server.
In this case I'm using
a virtual machine,
and I have 4 gigabytes of RAM,
4 gigabytes of memory allocated
to this virtual machine.
And I'm already using 3.7.
I have 177 megabytes
of free memory.
Some of that is
going to be cached.
Now if I start my MongoD
with wiredTigerCacheSize
of 1 gigabyte, for example, I
know that the size of my memory
is larger than that.
But the amount of cache
size that I'm allocating
is only going to
be of 1 gigabyte.
So my indexes will be
placed within that cache
size of 1 gigabyte.
Now that we see that
we can have indexes,
and the indexes
can be quite large,
but also that those indexes
will occupy a significant amount
of memory, it will be nice to
know which percentage of that
index actually is
living in memory.
How can we know that?
How can we determine
how much of our index
is actually in memory or not?
If we go back to our shell and
connect to our londonbikes,
we have this
interesting command,
which is the collection stats.
Now with collection
stats, we can also
pass a flag saying that we are
interested in knowing the index
details.
If we run this, we
will see that we're
going to get a bunch
of information back.
So there's a lot of quite
nice information around how
are our indexes set up, apart
from the collection stats
that the command gives us.
So before cruising through
all this block of text,
lets do a little more
of an ingenious way
of dealing with this
information, which is basically
putting all of this
information into a variable.
And let's see about
a couple of indexes
that we are going
to be interested on.
Start by getting
the index details.
As you can see here,
there's a bunch
of index details for
each individual index.
And I'm mostly interested
on one of them, the one
that we just recently
created, our endstation_name.
Now if we look into this
particular set of information,
we can see some
interesting information
on this particular setup,
especially the cache object.
Inside the cache,
we are going to get
a clear view of how
much bytes are currently
in cache, how much bytes are
read into cache, for example,
or a bunch of other
criteria about, for example,
the number of pages
requested from the cache,
or pages read into cache.
So if you are interested
in determining
how much information is
currently allocated in RAM,
we most certainly can
get that information
by looking into the amount
of bytes currently in cache.
We can also determine the
hit and miss page ratios
by analyzing pages read into
cache and pages requested
from cache.
Currently we have zero.
But if we run our query, the
previous explain query here--
actually we don't even need
the explain command here.
We just need to run the query.
We get some results.
And then we can iterate
on them, and so forth.
If we send our command
stats back again,
if we rerun the rides
other stats again,
and if we look again into that
particular index and the cache
allocation values, we
will see that some pages
have been requested from cache.
That is great.
We did traverse the index and
we needed a couple of pages
from RAM.
We need to read pages into
cache, and the amount of data
of this index currently in
cache also [? erased, ?]
because we needed to allocate
more information than what
we previously added since
we had a clean restart
of this particular MongoD.
Now there's a bunch
of information
around this command.
And we are not going to go
deep into how to decipher
all of this information.
That is out of scope for
this particular course.
But do keep in mind that MongoDB
does allow you to understand
pretty well what goes into
cache, what is allocated
in RAM, and what isn't, using
MongoDB WiredTiger's storage
engine.