In this lesson, we're going
to look at the explain method.
And we're going to talk about
what kind of information
explain provides us, how it,
works what this output looks
like on sharded
cluster, and we'll also
see how to use explain
in MongoDB Compass.
Using explain on a
query is the best way
to analyze what happens
when the query is executed.
Explain can also
be used to tell us
what would happen without
the query being executed.
More on those modes of operation
a little later in the lesson.
Here's all the
different information
that explain can tell us.
It can tell us, is our
query using the index
that we expected?
Is our index
providing us a sort?
Can our index
provide a projection?
How selective is our index?
And it can also tell us,
what's the most expensive stage
in our query plan?
Running explain is as easy as
appending the explain method
to the end of our query.
However, that mode of operation
has a few limitations.
So if you have more
complex commands,
or if you need to
rerun several queries,
it's suggested that we
create an explainable object.
From this explainable object, we
can then run our query like so.
We can also run multiple
queries right off
of the same explainable
object, which is really handy.
For both of these
examples, the shell
would return what would
happen without actually
executing the query.
Now, this might
sound silly at first.
However, if you're dealing
with a server that's
under tremendous load, you might
want to validate your command
before executing it.
This is also the reason
why it's the default
mode of operation for explain.
Passing the parameter
query planner to explain
does the exact
same thing as if we
ran explain with no parameters.
This is the default behavior.
We can also pass executionStats
as an argument to explain.
This will execute
the query and then
return different
statistics about the query.
And finally, we have
allPlansExecution.
This is the most verbose way
that we can get explain output.
We generally run
this when we want
to look at the alternative
plans that were considered
by the query planner,
but got rejected
in favor of the winning plan.
But remember, both
of these commands
actually execute the queries,
whereas this command does not.
Let's go ahead and
jump into the shell
and look at some examples.
So go ahead and use
the m201 database,
and then we'll create our
regular explain object
on the people collection.
But we'll go ahead and create
another explainable object
for executionStats, and even
another for allPlansExecution.
And here we can go ahead
and execute our query
on the explainable
object, where we're going
to look at execution stats.
And so from this output we
can go up to the winning plan,
and see that the winning plan
is to do a collection scan.
And we can also see
some execution stats.
We can see that we had to
look at 50,000 documents
to return seven, and we
looked at 0 index keys.
And by this time, we
know that we don't
want to do collection scans.
We should probably
create an index instead.
So let's do that.
And here we're creating an
index on the family name.
And now we can rerun
that same query.
And now we can go up here.
Now we can see that
our winning plan
is to do an index scan
followed by a fetch.
And now under
execution stats, we're
only looking at
about 800 documents,
examining 800 keys to
return our seven documents.
Way better than
the 50,000 before.
It's important to point out that
for our most optimized queries,
we want the total documents
examined and the nReturned,
to be very close
to the same number.
Similarly, with
12 keys examined,
we also want this to be very
close the amount of documents
we actually return.
But we know this
is always possible.
So the general rule
of thumb is that you
want these numbers to be close
to each other for your queries
that are ran most frequently.
Now let's go and
create another index,
and see how this affects
our explain output.
So we'll rerun the same query.
And now when we do so,
there's a new field up here.
And this field is
called rejectedPlans.
So we still have our
winningPlan field,
which includes the fact that
we're doing an index scan,
followed by a fetch.
But now we also
have rejected plans,
which were the other plans
that were considered.
Before, we never had
this, because there
were no other indexes that
the query planner was even
considering.
Now, there are two indexes
for them to consider.
There's first the
state, last name index,
and then there's also
our original index,
which is on just last name.
And as we can see, we now
have a much better index
where we have a really, really
great ratio, and an even better
execution time.
We can also look at sorts.
Here I'm appending explain
to the end of our query,
so that we can store a variable
and access some of the fields
more easily.
In this case, I
can look directly
at the execution status field.
And in here, we can see that
we're doing an index scan.
But after our index scan,
we're doing a fetch.
And after that fetch, we're
doing sort key generator.
And this means that we're
doing an in memory sort.
And this is because we don't
have any indexes to support
our sorting.
So there's two things I
want to point out here.
First, there is
memory usage, which
is how much memory
was used by the sort.
Here, we are using about 2.8k.
And there's also
the memory limit.
And this is 32 megabytes.
And what this means
is, is if we ever
have a sort that uses
more than 32 megabytes,
then the server is going
to cancel that query.
And so we can do
some simple math.
We can say, OK, how many
documents are we returning?
What's the average
size of our documents?
And if we multiply those
two numbers together,
and that's bigger
than 32 megabytes,
then we can predict that
the sort is going to cancel.