So far we've seen that indexes
are important data structures.
They will help us optimize our
queries and, as a side effect,
reduce our response time.
If well designed, the usage
of an index supporting a given
query might reduce the response
time in a few orders magnitude.
Let's have a quick example.
I have a database
called London bikes.
And in this London
bikes database,
I have these
rides_other collection
where I'm going to just express
a query looking for all end
stations around the
MongoDB office in London,
and see how that behaves.
Now if I pull up
my explain command,
I can see that the execution
time in milliseconds
was quite alarming.
It took me 7,426
milliseconds to execute.
It did return a few
amount of results,
like almost 20,000 documents.
But still, it did a lot of work
just to find a few documents.
And by that, also inadvertently
got a lot of time to do that.
Now after we create an
index on that same field
that we expressed a query
on, and we write again
the same query,
and also expecting
to look into the execution
stats of our explain command,
we can see that we come from
7,000 milliseconds to only 337.
So the usage of a
single index did
reduce in an order of
magnitude the amount of time
that this query took to operate.
However, indexes are not
some sort of black magic.
They are data structures
that our databases use,
that will in turn require
resources to operate.
Therefore, it is quite important
to determine the index size,
and what kind of resources will
be involved in its allocation
and operation.
In some edge cases where
we might compromise or do
some compromising in
terms of what we need,
in terms of resources to operate
with those particular indexes.
Let's start by looking into how
can we determine an index size.
Using MongoDB Compass, we can
have a clear understanding
of the size of our indexes
for each one of our databases.
Once we select the
database, we can
look into the
different collections
and here, we will have the total
index size for each collection.
Now if we select, for
example, this one over here,
the collection we used before.
And if we look into
our indexes, we
can see we have a breakdown
between the different indexes
that support this
particular collection.
We have our _ID,
our primary key,
and obviously the one that we
recently created on endstation
name.
We can also, obviously,
get that information
from our MongoDB
command db.stats,
where we are going to
have the full index size.
And obviously,
per collection, we
can also see the index
size of a given collection,
and the different sizes for
the different in indexes
of this collection.
Now indexes need two basic
computational resources.
We are going to need disk to
store the index information,
and, obviously,
we are also going
to need memory so we can operate
with those data structures.
In index terms, disks are
generally not a big issue
or they are generally
not an issue at all.
If we don't have space in
our disk for our index file,
apart from having
larger problems,
the indexes would end up
not been created at all.
So if you are restrained
in terms of disk size,
if you ask the system to
create a particular index.
If we don't have space
for the indexed file,
then you don't have a
problem with the index,
you have other, slightly
more important problems.
After the indexes
have been created,
the disk space requirements
will be a function of your data.
Which means that
you will run out
of disk space for
collection data
before having issues with
space for your indexes.
That said, if you are using
different physical drives
in one dedicated
for your indexes,
you do need to make sure
we have enough resources
for our indexes in
that particular disk.
So regardless of
the amount of data
that you put for
your collections--
so let's say that you are
using this disk over here
for the index file.
If you have other disks
for your collection data,
you might not run out of disk
space on your collection data,
but you might end up having
issues allocating resources
for your indexes if you
don't pay close attention
to that physical drive.
Just keep an eye on this if you
have this type of architecture.