Our rule of thumb says
that we should always
have enough memory to
allocate our indexes.
But there are some edge cases--
like, for example,
the occasional reports
that our beyond
tools and reporting
mechanisms do perform, and
they might need an index
to support those queries.
And also situations
where we would
have a right-end-side
index increment.
Let's have a look
into both of these
and what kind of other
solutions we have
for these type of edge cases.
Apart from the obvious
situation where indexes are not
being utilized should
not be created or not
present in a production
environment anyway,
there are two edge
cases that do not
need to have the full extent
of the index size in RAM.
Most of our queries
are to support
operational functionality--
means they are recurrently
getting information and using
those indexes to support
operational workload.
That means, as well,
that any index that
supports a particular query
should be in RAM because we
know that that data will
be utilized to respond
to an operational query.
But let's imagine our reporting
or BI tool mechanisms.
If we do have indexes to support
those queries, which we should,
chances that you need this
information to be always
allocated in memory are very
small because the recurrency
by which these
tools operate is not
in the same amount or degree
that our operational workload.
One way of mitigating the
effect of these particular tools
is instead of running the
queries in our primaries
and having the indexes
created on those primaries,
we can have our secondaries be
replying to requests of our BI
tools, and therefore
having the indexes
that support those
queries been created only
on designated nodes.
Another situation where the
full amount of our indexes
does not necessarily requires
to be fully allocated in memory
is when we have indexes on
fields that grow monotonically,
like counters, dates,
and incremental IDs.
If you take in consideration
the index structures--
naively represented by this tree
over here, which is a petrie.
If we have monotonically
increasing data,
chances are that our
index will eventually
become unbalanced on the
right-hand side of that index.
Therefore, it will
grow accordingly
with the new data coming in.
So if you have an incremental
ID, you start with 0,
and you end up
with 100 every time
that you add a new
element to your data set.
You only grow positively.
That means that the
tree will always
grow in the right-hand side.
If we add to that
fact that we only
need to query on the
most recent data,
then the amount of index that
actually needs to be in RAM
is always going to be the
right-end side of your index.
So here, in terms
of memory allocation
for this particular
index, we only
need to care about
how much data--
from the recently added data--
how are we going to be needing
to access all the time?
This is a typical scenario
of IOT kind of use cases
where new data being
created in index
will be either time based or
incremental data that always
going to grow positively in our
right-hand side of our index.
Therefore, if your
total index size
is 10 gigabytes, but the
most recent access data--
the one that we are using
the index to query on--
is only 2 gigabytes
of information,
then that's the amount
of size that you
need to allocate a memory
to support those queries.
A typical case is,
for example, when
you have something
like a checkout,
that you have a
field, and an ISODate.
You create an index to
support queries on date.
And the queries that you
operate from the application
is looking to that
date, like doing
the exact same moment
in time now, and sorting
by date descending.
So you are getting always the
latest results on your query.
Therefore, it is admissible
that in these situations
you might not need to
allocate the full extent
of your supporting index.
To wrap it up, when thinking
about the resource allocation
for your indexes, and
when dealing with indexes,
we cannot forget about that
these data structures do
require a lot of resources.
They are part of your
database working sets,
and we need to take
them in consideration
in our original sizing
and maintenance practices.
And this is all you need
to know about resource
allocation for indexes.