Let's now discuss a powerful
feature of MongoDB--
Views.
MongoDB enables
non-materialized views,
meaning they are computed
every time a rate operation is
performed against that view.
There are a way to use
an aggregation pipeline
as a collection.
From the user perspective, views
are perceived as collections,
with some key differences we'll
go over later in the lesson.
So what might Views
be useful for?
Suppose we're a large financial
institution with customers
of different tiers.
We've just recently
launched a big promotion
and are conducting
a phone campaign.
We've hired a temporary
staffing agency
with several regional offices.
We'll assign a different
tier to each regional office.
This is a sample of one record
from our customers collection.
As we can see, there is
sensitive and potentially
biasing information that we do
not want to allow access to.
Views allow us to create
vertical and horizontal slices
of our collection.
What do we mean by a
horizontal and vertical slice?
Vertical slicing is performed
through the use of a project
stage, and other
similar stages that
change the shape of the
document being returned.
Here we've vertically
sliced our document
to only retain the
accountType field.
Vertical slices will change
the shape being returned,
but not the number of
documents being returned.
Horizontal slicing is
performed through the use
of match stages.
We select only a
subset of documents
based on some criteria.
Here, we horizontally
slice our collection
with the value of
the account type.
In fact, the documents
that are grayed out
would not be operated on at all
by the following project stage.
We could further slice
this data horizontally,
by only selecting accounts
that had a specified
minimum balance, and are
within a desired age range,
and, you get the idea.
It may even be necessary to use
an intermediary shaping stage
to calculate a value that we
wish to filter documents on.
Horizontal slices will affect
the number of documents
returned, not their shape.
Let's look at another
example of this,
with documents that have
the following schema.
I would like to vertically
slice the documents to remove
sensitive information, as well
as make the name and gender
information available,
but present it
in a more formal format for
the call center employees.
I would also like to
horizontally slice
our collection, by filtering
out documents that do not
have an account type of bronze.
Here's an example of
creating a view that
performs both horizontal
and vertical slicing.
To make data available
for the call center,
we're going to assign
bronze tier members.
We specify the name of the view,
the source collection, and then
the pipeline that will get
stored to compute this view.
Within the pipeline, we perform
our initial horizontal slice
with a match stage, selecting
only bronze tier members.
Then, within the
project stage, we
perform our vertical slicing,
retaining fields we want
and reassigning the name field
with a more formally formatted
name.
You can see this view
in action yourself.
Let's run the command to
get collection information
for the current database.
Here, we see information
about every collection.
I've already created
three views--
bronze banking, silver
banking, and gold banking.
We can see, they show up
just like collections,
except their type is view.
And then in the options we can
see the view that they are on,
and the pipeline
that funds them.
You won't be able
to create views
on the class atlas cluster.
If you'd like to see
these views in action
and how restrictive
they can be, along
with proper role-based
access control,
the login credentials
are contained
in the handout in this lesson.
If you'd like to learn more
about role-based access
control, refer to our
security course, which
is linked below this video.
Views can be created
in two different ways.
We have the shell helper
method, db.createView,
which we already saw, and the
createCollection method here.
A view consists in the
name, a source collection,
an aggregation pipeline, and if
required, a specific collation.
In essence, one
would call a view
and will be executing the
aggregation pipeline that
is used to define the view.
New meta information to
include the pipeline that
computes the view, is stored
in the system.views collection.
Let's look at this information.
Again, we can see
the same information
we saw before with the get
collection info command,
but now only for our views.
Hopefully, this illustrates
that the only information stored
about a view is the name,
the source collection,
the pipeline that defines it,
and optionally, the collation.
All collection read operations
are available as views.
And yes, we can perform
aggregations on views too.
Views do have some
restrictions--
no write operations.
Views are read-only and
computed when we issue
a rate operation against them.
They are a reflection of
the defined aggregation
on the source collection.
No index operations--
since the views
use the source collection
to get their data,
the index operations
need to be performed
on that source collection.
Views will use the source
collections indexes
during their creation.
No renaming-- view
names are immutable,
so they cannot be renamed.
That said, we can
always drop a view
and create it again,
with a new pipeline,
without affecting the
I/O of the server.
No dollar text-- the
text query operator
can only be used in the
first stage of an aggregation
pipeline.
And a view will execute
the defined pipeline first.
This query operator
cannot be used in a view.
No geoNear or the geoNear stage.
Same as with test,
junior is required
to be the first stage
of our pipeline.
Collation restrictions-- views
have collation restrictions,
such as views do not inherit the
default collation of the source
collection as specified.
There are other collations
specific concerns
which you can read
about by following
the link below this video.
Lastly, find operations with the
following projection operators
are not permitted.
Removing and retaining
fields is allowed,
but trying to use any of
these operators will fail.
View definitions are public.
Any role that can list
collections on a database
can see a view definition
as we saw earlier.
Avoid referring to
sensitive information
within the defining pipeline.
All right.
That sums up Views.
Here are a few
things to remember.
Views contain no
data themselves.
They are created on demand
and reflect the data
in the source collection.
Views are read-only.
Write operations to
Views will error.
Views have some restrictions.
They must abide by the rules
of the aggregation framework,
and cannot contain find
projection operators.
Horizontal slicing is
performed with the matched
stage, reducing the number of
documents that are returned.
Vertical slicing is
performed with a project
or other shaping stage,
modifying individual documents.