Let's learn about
one of the stages
in the aggregation
framework that
can help us protect information
from unauthorized access,
the redact stage.
The redact stage has
the following form.
The expression can be any
expression or combination
of expressions,
but must ultimately
resolve to one of three values,
descend, prune, and keep.
OK, at first these
seem pretty cryptic.
So let's examine what
each of them does.
First, let's look
at prune and keep.
Prune and keep are
inverse of each other.
Prune will exclude all fields
at the current document level
without further inspection,
while keep will retain
all fields at the
current document level
without further inspection.
So what do we mean by
further inspection?
Let's look at this
example document
from the employees collection.
Each colored square
represents a document level.
Specifying keep or prune
at any given document level
will perform the
associated action
and automatically
apply this action
to all levels of the document.
Let's look at this
example document
from the employees collection.
Each colored square
represents a document level.
Specifying keep or prune
at any given document level
will perform the
associated action
and automatically apply this
action to all document levels
below the level we specified.
OK, so let's look at descend.
Descend retains the field at
the current document level
being evaluated except
for subdocuments
and arrays of documents.
It will instead traverse
down, evaluating each level.
Let's visualize how
descend would operate over
this document, given this
conditional expression,
determining whether the
value of user access
is in the ACL array.
We start with the
entire document
and compare whether
management is in ACL.
Since it is, it descends
into the sub document
at employee compensation, here.
We now evaluate
whether management
is in ACL, which it is.
So we descend further.
At this level, upon
evaluation prune
is returned, because
the ACL at this level
does not include management.
This level and any subsequent
levels, if there were any,
would not be returned.
To the user, it's as if this
field doesn't exist at all.
Let's look at this in action.
We set up our user access
variable and then the pipeline,
ensuring we only have access
document levels we should.
Excellent.
We can see that we are
indeed only getting back
document levels where
management was in the ACL array.
The redact stage can be useful
for implementing access control
lists, though it
is not the only way
to limit access to
information, as we'll
learn later in the course.
Any user who has
access to a collection
to perform this
type of aggregation
can also perform
other read operations.
So the redact stage is not
sufficient for collection
and field level restrictions.
Lastly, if comparing to
a field in the document,
the field must be present at
every level of using descend,
or the expression must
account for and decide what
to do if the field is missing.
If we don't take any
of these precautions,
redact is likely to error.
Let's summarize some key points.
Keep and prune automatically
apply to all levels
below the evaluated level.
Descend retains
the current level
and evaluates the
next level down.
And redact is not for
restricting access
to a collection.
Remember, if a user has access
to perform an aggregation
on a collection, they have
access to read that collection.