Let's learn about a useful
stage for persisting
the results of an
aggregation, the $out stage.
The $out stage has
the following form.
We specify the name of the
output collection that we want.
The out stage must be the
last stage in the pipeline.
As such, it can't be
used within a facet.
MongoDB will create
the collection
with the name specified
if none exists.
Otherwise it will overwrite
an existing collection
if an existing collection
name is specified.
Now there's a few
things to know.
It will only create
the new collection
within the same database.
If an existing
collection is replaced,
any indexes that existed
on the original collection
will still be in place.
If the pipeline errors, it
will not create or overwrite
a collection.
This also means that the output
from out must honor index
restrictions, such
as unique indexes,
can include the _id field.
So this aggregation here
where we match every document,
perform some grouping
operation, unwind to create many
documents, and then try an
output to a new collection
would fail because it would
result in many documents with
the same _id value.
And that covers the $out stage.
This stage is very
useful for performing
an aggregation against existing
data to do a migration,
seed a collection
with useful data,
or distribute snapshots
of data for analysis.
Here are a few things to
remember about the $out stage.
It will create a new collection
or overwrite an existing
collection if specified.
It honors indexes on
existing collections.
It will not create or overwrite
data if pipeline errors.
And it creates collections in
the same database as the source
collection.