In this lesson, we're going
to discuss how failovers
and elections work in MongoDB.
The primary node
is the first point
of contact for any client
communicating to the database.
Even if secondaries
go down, the client
will continue communicating
with the node acting
as primary until the
primary is unavailable.
But what would cause a
primary to become unavailable?
A common reason is maintenance.
So let's say we're
doing a rolling upgrade
on a three-node replica set.
A rolling upgrade
just means we're
upgrading one server at a time,
starting with the secondaries.
And eventually, we'll
upgrade the primary.
Rolling upgrades are
great because they
allow us to perform updates
while maximizing availability
to any clients
using the database.
We'll start by stopping the
MongoDB process on a secondary,
and then bringing it back up
with the new database version.
And we can do the same thing
to upgrade our other secondary.
When all of our secondaries
have been upgraded,
it's time to
upgrade the primary.
But restarting the database
server on the primary would
trigger an election anyway, so
we're going to safely initiate
an election with rs.stepDown().
Once the election is complete,
the last database server
running the old database version
will be a secondary node.
So we can bring
it down, and then
bring it back up with
the new database server
without affecting
the availability
of the whole replica set.
Let's talk a little bit
about how elections work.
Elections take place whenever
there's a change in topology.
Reconfiguring a
replica set will always
trigger an election that may
or may not elect a new primary.
But you will definitely
see a new primary
elected in two cases--
anytime the current primary
node becomes unavailable,
or when the current primary node
steps down to be a secondary.
The method to figure out which
secondary will run for election
begins with priority, which
we'll discuss in a minute;
and whichever node has the
latest copy of the data.
So let's say every
node in our set
has the same priority, which
is the default unless we've
been setting priorities
for the nodes in our set.
And this node has the
latest copy of the data.
So it's going to
run for election,
and then automatically
vote for itself.
Then it's going to ask the other
two nodes for their support
in the election.
And they're going to
say, all right, you
have a pretty recent
copy of the data,
you seem like a
good candidate, then
they'll pledge their
support as well.
This node will be
elected primary.
There is also the
very slim possibility
that two nodes run for
election simultaneously.
But in a replica set with
an odd number of nodes,
this doesn't matter.
These two nodes are
both going to run,
which means they're both
going to vote for themselves.
And then this node is
going to essentially decide
which one of these
nodes becomes primary
by virtue of a tiebreaker.
This becomes a problem
when we have an even number
of voting members in a set.
If two secondaries are running
for election simultaneously
and there are an even number
of remaining nodes in the set,
there's a possibility
that they split the vote
and there's a tie.
Now a tie is not the
end of the world,
because the nodes will
just start over and hold
another election.
The problem with repeating
elections over and over
is that any applications
accessing the data
will have to pause
all activity and wait
until a primary is elected.
An even number of nodes
increases the chances
an election has to be
repeated, so we generally
try to keep an odd number
in our replica sets.
Another important
aspect of elections
is the priority assigned
to each node in a set.
Priority is essentially
the likelihood
that a node will become the
primary during an election.
The default primary
for a node is 1,
and any node with priority 1 or
higher can be elected primary.
We can increase the
priority of a node
if we want it to be more likely
at this node becomes primary.
But changing this value alone
does not guarantee that.
We can also set the
priority of node
to be 0 if we never want
that node to become primary.
A priority 0 node can
still vote in elections,
but it can't run for election.
Let's take a look at how to
change the priority of a node.
So here I'm just storing
a configuration document
in a variable.
So here I'm just setting
the priority of one
of our secondaries
to 0 so it can never
become the primary node.
And here, I'm just saving
the new configuration
in a replica set.
So now we've reconfigured
our replica set,
I'm going to run rs.isMaster()
through the new topology.
So in MongoDB, nodes that aren't
eligible to become the primary
are defined as passive nodes.
And we can see the node
that we reconfigured
to have priority 0 has appeared
in our list of passives.
The other two nodes are still
eligible to become the primary.
Something I want
to point out here.
When we call rs.stepDown(), it
always tries to choose a new
primary node.
But in this case, other
than the current primary,
there's only one node that's
eligible to become the primary.
Which means that if we were
to call an election right now,
this node would have to
become the primary node.
So incidentally, by
changing node priority,
we've rigged the election
in favor of this node.
So just to prove
our theory, we'll
call an election on
this replica set.
We just have to wait for
the election to complete.
All right, so it
finished, and I'm just
going to check what
the current primary is.
And we can see
that we were right.
This node became
the primary node
because it was the only eligible
primary in that election.
So one last thing to note.
If the current
primary can't reach
a majority of the
other nodes in the set,
then it will automatically step
down to become a secondary.
In a three-node replica set,
a majority is two nodes.
So if two nodes go down, even if
the primary is still available,
it will step down.
At this point, an election
cannot take place until enough
nodes come back up
to form a majority,
and the clients will be able
to connect to the whole set
because there is no primary.
So just to recap, we've covered
how availability is maintained
during elections, the effective
priority on elections,
and the behavior
of a replica set
when a majority of the
nodes aren't available.