All right, so in
this lesson, we're
going to initiate a
local replica set.
We're going to start by
independently launching three
mongod processes and
they won't actually
be able to communicate
with each other
until we connect
them, at which point
they'll be able to actually
replicate data for us.
So this is the configuration
file for standalone node.
We've called it node 1.
And these settings should
look fairly familiar to you
if you've been following
the previous lessons.
We don't actually need to
change any of these settings
in order to enable
replication, we just
need to add a few lines.
So this line enables
key file authentication
on our cluster, which mandates
that all members of the replica
set have to authenticate to each
other using a key file that we
create here.
And we'll create
this one in a minute.
This is in addition to
the client authentication
that we enabled in
the previous line.
So we create this key
file using OpenSSL,
and we place it in the
directory that we specified
in our configuration file.
But right now, our
mongod processes
can't actually use this
key file because they
don't have the permissions
to read from it.
So what we're going to
do is we going actually
change the permissions
using chmod
in order to allow them
to read from the file.
600 here just specifies
re-permissions.
So actually enabling key file
authentication here implicitly
enables the client
authentication
that we enabled in
the previous line,
but I'm going to leave both
here for the time being
just for clarity.
This is a reminder
that in addition
to authenticating
with the client,
our nodes are also
authenticating to each other.
So this is the last
line that we have
to add to our configuration file
in order to enable replication
on this node.
And all it does is
specify the name
of the replica set that this
node is going to be a part of.
Now all we need to do
is create the DB path
that we named up here.
And we can actually use
this file to start a mongod.
So here I'm just
creating my DB path,
and now I can start the mongod
using our configuration file.
And we have successfully
started our first node.
So right now we have
one node and we just
have two more to go.
So this command is
just copying the file
that we just made into a
new file called node2.conf
because the other two
nodes are going to have
very similar configurations.
We can basically copy this
one, change three lines,
and launch a brand new node.
Never underestimate the
power of copy and paste.
I'm just going to do the
same thing for our third node
here, and then edit
our second one.
So the three things that we
need to change in this file
are the DB path, the port
number, and the log path.
Once we do that, we're actually
good to start a new node.
So here I've just created
the path for node 2
and I'm starting
it up with mongod.
And we now have two
nodes in our set.
I'm just going to do the same
thing for our third config
file, and notice that all
three nodes in the replica
set reference the same key file.
Typically these
mongod instances would
be running on
different machines,
but because they're running
on the same machine,
they're all just going to
share the same key file
and use the same one to
authenticate with one another.
Typically this key
file would be copied on
to each machine where
each mongod was running.
So at this point we started
three mongod processes
that will eventually
make up a replica set.
But right now, they
can't replicate data.
And in fact, they
have no knowledge
that other nodes are out there.
They're blind to the
world around them.
We need to enable
communication between the nodes
so they can stay in sync.
So I'm just going to
connect to node one here.
So I use this
command rs.initiate
to initiate the replica set.
And we actually need to
run it on one of the nodes.
Because we ran it
here, we just have
to add the other two
nodes from this node.
However, we have client
authentication enabled,
so we can't actually add
other nodes to the set
until we create a user and
then connect as that user.
All right, so this command
created our m103 super user,
called m103-admin, that has
root access and authenticates
against the admin database.
Now I'm just going to
exit out of this mongod
and then log back
in as that user.
So this is the
command that we're
going to use to connect
to the replica set.
And in addition to
authenticating here
with a username
password, we have
to specify the name of the
replica set in the host name.
This will tell the mongo
shell to connect directly
to the replica set,
instead of just this one
node that we specify.
What the shell is
going to do is it's
going to use this
node to discover what
the current primary
is of the replica set
and then connect to
that node instead.
In this case, obviously there's
only one node in the set
and that node is the primary.
So that's the one that
the shell connected us to.
So this command,
rs.status is a useful way
to get a status report
on our replica set.
See, it gives us
the name of the set.
It gives us how
long the intervals
are between heartbeats.
By default, it's
2000 milliseconds,
which means the nodes are
talking to each other every two
seconds.
We can scroll down to get a
list of the members in the set.
In this case, it's
just one member,
which is the one that
we're connected to,
the current primary.
So this is the
command we use to add
new nodes to our
replica set, rs.add,
and all we have
to specify here is
the host name, which
is just the host
name of the vagrant
box and the port
that that node is running on.
Now that worked.
I'm just going to do the
same for our third node.
I'm just going to
check rs.isMaster.
And we can see that our replica
set now has three nodes in it.
So now that we've added those
two nodes to our replica set
and connected them, they
can replicate data from one
another.
One thing I want to
point out right now
is that the current primary
is running on port 27011.
And we could verify that from
the output of rs.isMaster,
where it says primary is in
fact the node running on 27011.
However, we can
force an election
so that a different
note becomes primary.
And the command we use to do
that is called rs.stepDown.
Now the step down
command is what
we use to safely step down the
current primary to a secondary
and force an election
to take place.
The error that
we're getting here
is because the shell is trying
to connect us to the primary,
but the secondaries are
still in the process
of electing a primary, so
there is no primary right now.
As soon as one is
elected, the shell
will connect us to
it, which it just did.
If we run rs.isMaster
again, we can
verify that now this node is
the current primary, as opposed
to 27011, which was
the primary before.
So just to recap, we've covered
how to initiate a replica set,
how you can add nodes
to the replica set,
and how to check the
status of the replica set.
We used rs.status and
rs.isMaster in this lesson,
and those commands
have different outputs
for different use cases.
And I would urge you to
explore those to figure out
which one fits your use case.