So in this lesson we're going to
take a look at reads and writes
in a replica set just to get
a sense of how the MongoDB
replication mechanism works.
So I'm just going
to use this command
to connect to our
three node replica
set called m103-example.
And to figure out which node
in this set is currently
the primary, I'm going to run
this command rs.isMaster().
And this output actually
gives us a lot of information.
It gives us the current
primary, which is
the node running on port 27011.
And it also gives us the
node that we're currently
connected to, me.
In this case, it's the
same as the primary,
because we're connected to the
replica set through the shell.
It also gives us the other
nodes in this replica set.
So I'm just going to create a
new database here called newDB.
And insert a new document
into a new collection
called new collection in newDB.
And I'm just going to
connect to a secondary
to make sure they receive
the write as well.
We can scroll up to
the rs.isMaster output
to figure out which of
these nodes is a secondary.
And we know this is
the primary, so we just
have to connect to one
of these two nodes.
So this is the
command we're going
to use to connect directly to
a secondary node in our replica
set.
Notice that we've changed
the node port that we've
selected in our host name.
And we also haven't specified
the name of the replica set.
Because if we were to specify
the name of the replica set,
the shell would automatically
direct us to the primary.
And in this case, we actually
want to connect directly
to a secondary.
And as we can see,
the shell prompt
is changed to reflect
that we're now
connected to a secondary node.
So we can to start running shell
commands on the secondary note,
right?
No, actually we can't.
When we're connected
to a secondary node,
we can only run read commands
after telling MongoDB
that we're sure that's
what we want to do.
This is because MongoDB errs
on the side of consistency.
Given that we want to
make sure you always
have a consistent
view of your data,
you need to explicitly
say otherwise
if you want to read
from the secondaries.
So this is the
command we're going
to run in order to
enable read operations
on the secondary node.
And now, our show DBs
command should actually work.
And it does.
And we can see that the
write command was replicated
to the secondary node.
So here I've tried to insert a
document into a secondary node.
And as expected, we can only
enable reads on this secondary.
We'll never be able to
write to a secondary node.
The purpose of this is to
enforce strong consistency
on our cluster.
The Mongo shell
lets us know that we
can't write to the secondary.
So far we've covered
how reads and writes
work in a replica set
when it's healthy.
In the interest of learning
how replica sets handle crisis,
we're going to
break a few things.
First, we're going to
shut this node off.
Now when we connect
back to the replica set,
we run rs.status() we can see
that the node we shut down is
no longer reachable
from the primary.
Now I'm just going to shut
down this other node here.
So now that we've shut
off two of the nodes
in our replica set,
there's only one left.
And one out of three
does not form a majority.
So we actually won't be able
to connect to the primary,
because the current primary,
which was running on this node,
has stepped down to
become a secondary.
So here I haven't specified
the name of the replica set,
because I want to connect
directly to this node.
And as we can see, that
node has stepped down
to be the secondary.
We can verify that by
running rs.isMaster().
So as we can see, we're
still connected the same node
as before.
But that node is now
a secondary node.
Even though the primary
node never went down,
we lost the last secondary
that gave us a majority.
If the replica set can no longer
reach a majority of the nodes,
all the remaining nodes in
the set become secondaries.
And because they're
secondaries, we
can't write anything
to the replica set,
because there is no primary.
This is just another
safe mechanism
used by the MongoDB replica
set to ensure data consistency.
So just to recap.
In this lesson, we covered
data being replicated
to a secondary, how reading
from secondary nodes works,
and how writing to a
replica set when a majority
isn't available-- which
is to say, we can't.