Read concern is a
companion to write concern,
an acknowledgment mechanism
for read operations
where developers can
direct their application
to perform read operations where
the returned documents meet
the requested
durability guarantee.
Consider a replica
set where applications
insert a document, which is
acknowledged by the primary.
Before the document can
replicate to the secondaries,
the application
reads that document.
Suddenly, the primary fails.
The document we have
read has not yet
replicated to the secondaries.
When the old primary
comes back online,
that data is going to
be rolled back as part
of the synchronization process.
While you can access the
rolled back data manually,
the application
effectively has a piece
of data that no longer
exists in the cluster.
This might cause problems
in the application,
depending on your architecture.
Read concern provides
a way of dealing
with the issue of
data durability
during a failover event.
Just like how write concern lets
you specify how durable write
operations should
be, read concern
lets your application specify
a durability guarantee
for documents written
by a read operation.
The read operation only
returns data acknowledged
as having been written to a
number of replica set members
specified in the read concern.
You can choose between
returning the most recent data
in a cluster or
the data received
by a majority of
members in the cluster.
One really important note.
A document that does not meet
the specified read concern
is not a document that
is guaranteed to be lost.
It just means that at
the time of the read,
the data had not
propagated to enough nodes
to meet the requested
durability guarantee.
There are four read
concern levels.
Local returns the most
recent data in the cluster.
Any data freshly written
to the primary qualifies
for local read concern.
There are no guarantees
that the data will be
safe during a failover event.
Local reads are the
default for read operations
against the primary.
Available read concerns the
same as local read concern
for replica set deployments.
Available read concern is the
default for read operations
against secondary members.
Secondary reads are an aspect of
MongoDB read preference, which
is covered in a later lesson.
The main difference between
local and available read
concern is in the context
of sharded clusters.
We're going to talk more
about sharded clusters later.
It's enough to know that
available read concern has
special behavior in
sharded clusters.
Majority read
concern only returns
data that has been
acknowledged as written
to a majority of
replica set members.
So here in our
three-member replica set,
our read operations
would only return
those documents written to both
the primary and the secondary.
The only way that documents
returned by a read concern
majority read
operation could be lost
is if a majority of replica
set members went down
and the documents were not
replicated to the remaining
replica set members, which
is a very unlikely situation,
depending on your
deployment architecture.
Majority read concern provides
the stronger guarantee compared
to local or available writes.
But the trade-off
is that you may not
get the freshest or latest
data in your cluster.
As a special note, the
MMAPv1 storage engine
does not support write
concern of majority.
Linearizeable read concern
was added in MongoDB 3.4,
and has special behavior.
Like read concern
majority, it also
only returns data that has
been majority committed.
Linearizeable goes beyond
that, and provides read
your own write functionality.
So when should you
use what read concern?
Really depends on your
application requirements.
Fast, safe, or the latest
data in your cluster.
Pick two.
That's the general idea.
If you want fast
reads of the latest
data, local or
available read concern
should suit you just fine.
But you are going to lose
your durability guarantee.
If you want fast reads
of the safest data,
then majority read concern
is a good middle ground.
But again, you may not be
getting the latest written
data to your cluster.
If you want safe
reads of the latest
data at the time of
the read operation,
then linearizeable
is a good choice,
but it's more
likely to be slower.
And it's single
document reads only.
One thing to be
really clear about,
read concern doesn't
prevent deleting
data using a CRUD
operation, such as delete.
We're only talking
about the durability
of data returned by a
read operation in context
of a failover event.
In a later lesson,
we're going to talk
about read preference, where you
can route your read operations
to secondary members.
Read preference for
secondaries does
allow you to specify local
or available read concern,
but you're going to lose the
guarantee of getting the most
recent data.
So just remember that
with secondary reads,
local and available read
concern is really just fast,
but not necessarily the latest.
To recap, read concern uses
an acknowledgment mechanism
for read operations
where applications
can request only that data which
meets the requested durability
guarantee.
There are four available
read concern options.
Local and available are
identical for replica sets.
Their behavior's more
distinct in sharded clusters.
Majority read concern
is your middle ground
between durability
and fast reads,
but it can return stale data.
Linearizeable has the strongest
durability guarantees,
and always returns
the freshest data
in context of a read
operation in exchange
for potentially slow
read operations as well
as the overall restrictions
and requirements for using it.
Finally, you can use read
concern in conjunction
with write concern to specify
durability guarantees on both
reads and writes.
Remember that the two
work together, but are not
dependent on each other.
You can use read concern
with write concern
or read concern
without write concern.