In this lesson, we are
going to take a quick peek
into a fundamental database and
the old replication process--
our dear, sweet Local DB.
The minute we start our MongoDB,
like I'm doing right now,
there's a standalone node.
And once I connect
to that node, we
can see two different
name spaces, or databases,
if you prefer.
We have admin, which comprises
all the Administration
Data and where most
of our administration
commands like db.shutdownServer,
for example, needs to be
executed, or will be executed.
And we have local.
So let's jump into
local for a second.
And we can see that,
in this instance,
a standalone, all
by itself, node.
The local DB has only one
collection-- startup.log.
Nothing extraordinary so far,
in that this startup_log only
holds the start up log
of this particular node,
as the saying kind of leads to.
So let's connect to
our replica set instead
and check out how
these local do once we
are in the replica set
land. Now that I'm
connected to a replica set--
and you can see here from the
prompt that I'm connected ta
replica M103 and to its primary.
If I use local and show
the collections-- so here
we have a little bit
more of information,
or at least a bit more of
collections in this scenario.
Great, but what are
these for anyway?
Most of these
collections, like me,
startup log, system replica
set, system rollback ID,
or replica set
election, and min val
are collections maintained
internally by the server.
They don't really
vary that much,
and the information they hold
are simple configuration data--
nothing too interesting there.
But where things get
really interesting
is with one collection
in particular-- oplog.rs.
oplog.rs is the central point
of our replication mechanism.
This is the oplog
collection that
will keep track of all
statements being replicated
in our replica set.
Every single piece of
information and operations
that need to be replicated will
be logged in this collection.
There are a few things about
the oplog.rs collection
that you should know about.
First of all, it's
a capped collection.
Capped collection means that
the size of this collection
is limited to a specific size.
If we collect the stats of our
oplog.rs collection into this
variable, there's a flag called
.capped that will tell us that
this collection
is, indeed, capped.
You can see the size
of this collection.
We can also see the max size
of the particular collection.
Now if you want to see the
stats into a megabyte unit,
you can see that this
collection in here
holds up to almost 2
gigabytes of data--
1.8 gigabytes.
By default, the
oplog.rs collection
will take 5% of your free disk.
In my case, I have nearly 36
gigabytes of available data.
So 1.8 gigabytes
gives me those 5%.
The size of our oplog will
determine our replication
window--
the amount of time that it will
take to fill in your oplog.
Now, we can also see
some of that information
from the printReplicationInfo,
where here,
giving the current
status of my oplog.
We are configured for
those 1,819 megabytes.
The log length starts to end is
around 362 seconds, 0.1 hours--
a very short one.
And it's calculated based on
the oplog first event time
and the oplog last event time.
Now as you can see, I
haven't done much so far.
And from now, where
we stand right now
at this moment in time, I
see that I have not done much
in this particular replica set.
So the calculated time to fill
in the oplog is relatively low.
But wait just a second.
I thought that the oplog
size was measured in size,
therefore it's megabytes, but
we are talking about hours?
Fear not, young Padawan.
What is happening here is
that MongoDB will let you know
how much time it will take--
given the current workload,
how much time will
it take to start overwriting
entries in your oplog.
In this case, I have
not been doing much,
therefore my workload
is quite low.
So it will only
take about 0.1 hours
to fill the oplog,
which is not really
predictable at this point.
We need more data to
actually calculate correctly
how much time does it
take to fill up our oplog.