Now that we've seen why
replication is important,
let's do a quick dive into
the details of replica sets.
Replica sets or groups
of mongods that share
copies of the same
information between them.
Replica set members can have
one of two different roles.
The either can be primary node
where all reads and all writes
are served by this node.
Or secondary node where the
responsibility of this node
is to replicate all
of the information,
and then serve as
a high availability
to node in case of
failure of the primary.
The secondaries will get
the data from the primary
through an asynchronous
replication mechanism.
Every time an application
writes some data
to the replica set, that right
is handled by the primary node.
And then data gets replicated
to the secondary nodes.
Now this replication
mechanism is based out
of a protocol that manages the
way that the secondaries should
read data from the primary.
In MongoDB this is synchronous
replication protocol
might have different versions.
We have PV1 and PV0.
The different versions of
the replication protocol
will vary slightly
on the way durability
and availability will be
forced throughout the set.
Currently Protocol Version 1,
or PV1, is the default version.
This protocol is based
out of the RAFT protocol.
If you are not familiar
with the RAFT protocol,
in the lecture notes
of this lesson,
you will find detailed
information about RAFT.
Just keep in mind for now
that prior versions of MongoDB
used the previous
protocol version PV0,
and that there might be
some configuration details
in between both protocols.
For now, we'll
just focus on PV1.
At the heart of this
replication mechanism
there's our operations
log, or oplog for short.
The oplog is a segment based
lock that keeps track of all
write operations acknowledged
by the replica sets.
Every time a write
is successfully
applied to the
primary node, it will
get recorded in the oplog
in its idempotent form.
We'll looking into the
idempotentcy details later.
But keep in mind that
an idempotent operation
can be applied multiple times.
And the end result
of that operation
will always results in the
same end result. More on this
up ahead.
Apart from a primary
or secondary role,
a replica set member can also
be configured as an arbiter.
An arbiter is a member
that holds no data.
It's mere existence is
to serve as a tiebreaker
between secondaries
in an election.
And obviously if it has no data,
it can never become primary.
Replica sets are
failure resilient.
That means that they have
a failover mechanism that
requires a majority of
nodes in a replica set
to be available for a
primary to be elected.
In this particular case, let's
assume that we lose access
to our primary.
If we don't have a primary
we will not be able to write,
and that's not good.
So we need to clear
between the remaining
nodes of the set, which one
could become the new primary?
That is through
an election, which
is embedded on the details
of the political version.
How a primary gets
elected or why this--
a particular node becomes
primary instead of another.
It's out of scope
for now, but keep
in mind the details
of these will
be related with the
protocol version
that your system may be having.
For now just keep in
mind that there is
a failover mechanism in place.
Important thing to note
is that you should always
have at least an odd number
of nodes in your replica set.
In case of even number
of nodes, do make sure
that the majority is
consistently available.
In this form of a
replica set, you
will need to have at least
three nodes to be available.
The list the replica set members
in their configuration options
defines the replica
set topology.
Any topology change will
trigger an election.
Adding members to the
set, failing members,
or changing any
of the replica set
configuration aspects
will be perceived
as it's topology change.
The topology of a replica set
is defined in the replica set
configuration.
The replica set configuration
is defined in one of the nodes
and then shared
between all members
through the
replication mechanism.
We will look into the
replication configuration
documents in detail later.
In this case, we
have four members
and I need to raise
your attention
to a specific situation.
This topology offers exactly
the same number of failures
as a three node replica sets.
can only afford to
lose one member.
In case of losing
two of them, we
will have no majority
available out of the sets.
Why?
Well the majority of 4 is 3.
Therefore the two
remaining nodes
will not be able to be electing
a primary in-between them.
Having that extra node will
not provide extra availability
of the service.
Just another redundant
copy of our data,
which is good, but
not necessarily
for availability reasons.
Now, replica sets can
go up to 50 members.
And this might be
useful, especially
for geographical
distribution of our data
where we want copies of our
data closer to our users
and applications, or
just multiple locations
for redundancy.
But only a maximum of
seven of those members
can be voting members.
More than seven members
may cause election rounds
to take too much time,
with little to none
benefit for availability
and consistency purposes.
So between those
seven nodes, one
of them will become the primary
and the remaining ones will
be electable as primaries if
in case its policy changes,
or in case a new
election gets triggered.
Now if for some reason
we can't or don't
want to have a
data bearing node,
but still be able to
failover between nodes,
we can add a replica set
member as an arbiter.
That said, arbiters do cause
significant consistency issues
in distributed data systems.
So we advise you
use them with care.
In my personal view,
the usage of arbiters
is a very sensitive
and potentially harmful
option in many deployments.
So I idly discourage
the usage of arbiters.
Withing secondary
nodes, these can also
be set to have specific or
special properties defined.
We can define hidden
nodes, for example.
The purpose of a hidden
node is to provide
specific read-only workloads,
or have copies over your data
which are hidden
from the application.
Hidden nodes can also
be set with a delay
in their replication process.
We call these delayed nodes.
The purpose of
having delayed nodes
is to allow resilience to
application level corruption,
without relying on
cold backup files
to recover from such an event.
If we have a node delayed,
let's say one hour,
and if your DBA accidentally
drops a collection,
we have one hour to recover all
the data from the delayed node
without needing to go
back to back up file
to recover to whatever the
time that backup was created.
Enabling us to have hot backups.
Let's recap what we just
learned in this lecture.
Replica sets are groups
of mongod processes
that share the same data between
all the members of the set.
They provide a high availability
and failover mechanism
to our application, making the
service in case of failure.
The failover is
supported by a majority
of nodes that elect
between them who
should be the new primary
node at each point in time.
Replica sets are
a dynamic system,
means that members may
have different roles
at different times,
and can be set
to address specific functional
purpose like addressing read
on workloads, or
set to be delayed
in time to allow hot back-ups.