In this lesson,
we're going to cover
some of the commands we
use to gather information
about a replica set.
You've probably
noticed that there
are a lot of different
ways to check
the status of a replica
set because each node emits
a lot of information.
Each replication command
gives a different subset
of this information.
The first one we're going
to cover is rs.status.
rs.status is used to report
on the general health
of each node in the set.
The data it gets
from the heartbeat
sent in-between
nodes in the set.
Because it relies on
heartbeats for this data,
it may actually be a
few seconds out of date.
This command gives us
the most information
for each specific node.
We can see that for a given node
we get the state of the node.
In this case, it's the primary.
We have the up time, which
is the number of seconds
this note has been running for.
And we have the optime, which is
the last time this node applied
an operation from its oplog.
There are heartbeat
stats for each node
as well but not for the node
that we ran this command on.
That's because the
heartbeat stats are all
relative to where
rs.status was run.
We know that it was run
from this because the self
flag in this node is true.
We can scroll down to
one of the other nodes
and see that we have some
heartbeats stats down here.
Because we know the
primary was where
this command was run from.
We know that last
heartbeat refers
to the last time this
node successfully received
a heartbeat from the primary.
Conversely, last
heartbeat received
refers to the last time the
primary successfully received
a heartbeat from this note.
We can see the actual frequency
of heartbeats in this set
through a heartbeat
interval millis.
In this case, this
set is running
with the default of
2,000 milliseconds, which
means that the nodes are
talking to each other about
every two seconds.
The next command we're going
to cover is rs.isMaster.
This one describes
the role of the node
where we ran this command from.
And it also gives
us some information
about the replica set itself.
The output is a lot easier
to read than rs.status
just because its output
is a lot shorter.
So as we can see,
the list of hosts
is a lot shorter
in this command,
and we can very easily verify
if this node is a secondary.
In this case, it's not
because secondary is false.
Or if this is the
primary-- and it's master
is true in this case.
It also gives us the name of
the primary node in the set
regardless of where we
ran this command from.
In this case, obviously,
we ran it from the primary,
so this primary
flag is just going
to say the same thing as me.
So I just want to
point out here when
we type this command with
parentheses afterward,
we're calling this method.
But we can remove
the parentheses
to see what's actually
being run in the background.
And we can see that
rs.isMaster is actually
just a wrapper around a
function called db.isMaster.
You're going to notice that a
lot of the rs.commands in Mongo
Shell are actually just
wrappers around db commands.
As a side note,
this is the command
that the drivers use to discover
each node's role in the replica
set.
For more on that, you
can follow the reference
in the lecture notes.
The next command
is db.serverStatus.
This command gives us a lot of
information about the Mongo D
process, but we're
just going to look
at the section called repl.
The output from this
command is going
to be very similar to the
output of rs.isMaster.
So as we can see, the
output of this command
is very similar to the output of
rs.isMaster with the exception
of one field here.
The rbid is not
included in rs.isMaster.
And all this does is count
the number of rollbacks that
have occurred on this node.
The last command
we're going to cover
is rs.printReplicationInfo.
This command only has
data about the oplog
and specifically only
the oplog for the node
we're currently connected to.
It'll give us exact time stamps
for the first and last events
that occurred in the
oplog for that node.
So this is a quick report on
the current length of the oplog
in time and in megabytes.
And remember that the
earliest event in the oplog
is subject to change because
the oplog is capped collection,
and it's periodically flush
to make room for new data.
In this lesson, we've
learned that there
are several different ways to
check the status of a replica
set, and each one is
important in its own right.