In this lesson, we are going
to dissect the replication
configuration.
In particular, we
will be looking
to which replica set
configuration options we have
and how those options are
reflected in the configuration
options document.
The replica set configuration
document is a simple BSON
document that we manage using
a JSON representation where
the configuration or our
replica sets is defined
and is shared across
all the nodes that
are configured in the sets.
We can manually set
changes to this document
to configure a
replica set according
with the expected topology and
overall replication options.
Although we can do this by
simply editing such documents
using the mongo.db shell, we can
also use a set of shell helpers
like rs.add, initiate,
remove, and so forth.
that will help us facilitate
the configuration and management
of this same configuration.
There is a fair amount of
different configuration options
at our disposal as you can see
from the baseline configuration
options document.
This might sound a bit
daunting, but in reality, it's
a pretty straightforward
set of options.
And for this lesson,
in particular,
we are going to be looking only
to a set of these configuration
options--
the basic and fundamental
ones and the ones
that we are going to be
using throughout the course.
All the other options are
out of scope for this course.
But let's start
with the _id field.
This field is sets with the
name of the replica set.
This is a string
value that matches
the server defined replica set.
Whenever we start our mongoD
and we provide a --replSet name
to our mongoD, meaning that this
mongoD will belong to the set,
or by setting that same name
in the configuration file--
for example, our
etc/mongodb.conf file,
we are setting a specific value
to be used as a replica set
name.
The same value must match the
_id field of our replica set
configuration document.
In case we have different values
from the configuration _id
and the defined
replica set name,
we end up with an error message.
We get an incorrect
replica set configuration,
stating that we are attempting
to initiate the replica set
with a different name
from which it
has been set as --replSet
or in the config file.
This is a safeguard against
incorrect configurations
or incorrect adding the server
to the incorrect replica sets.
The next field is version.
Now, a version is just
an integer that gets
incremented every time
the current configuration
of our replica set changes.
If, for example, we add
a node to our replica set
and if our version
used to be number 1,
we increment the value.
Every time we
changed a topology,
changed a replica set
configuration at all
or do something like
changing the number of votes
of a given host, that
will automatically
increment the version number.
The next field in
line is members.
And members is where the
topology of our replica set
is defined.
Each element of
the members array
is a sub-document that contains
the replica set node members.
Each has a host comprised
of the host name and port.
In this case, for example,
we have m103:27017.
Then we have a set of
flags that determine
the role of the nodes
within the replica set.
arbiterOnly is self-explanatory.
This means that the node
will not be holding any data,
and its contribution
to the set is
to ensure quorum in elections.
hidden-- it's another flag that
sets the node in hidden role.
An hidden node is not visible
to the application, which
means that every time we
emit something like an RS
is master command, this
node will not be listed.
Int nodes are useful
for situations
where we want a particular node
to support specific operations.
They are not related with
the operational nature
of your application.
For example, having a node that
handles all the reporting or BI
reads.
Both of these flags are
set to false by default.
Then we have
priority, and priority
is an integer value that
allows us to set a hierarchy
within the replica set.
We can set priorities
between 0 and 1,000.
Members with higher
priority tend
to be elected in
primaries more often.
A change in the
priority of a node
will trigger an election
because it will be
perceived as a topology change.
Setting priority
to 0 effectively
excludes that member from
ever becoming a primary.
In case, we are setting a
member to be arbiterOnly,
that implies that the
priority needs to be set to 0.
The same would apply for hidden.
The priority here also
needs to become 0.
If the note is
hidden, it can never
become primary because it will
not be seen by the application.
Failing to do that
will result in an error
where a new replica set
configuration is incompatible.
Priority must be 0 when
hidden equals true.
And finally, we have slaveDelay.
slaveDelay is an
integer value that
determines a replication
delay interval in seconds.
The default is 0.
This option will
enable delayed nodes.
These delayed members
maintain a copy
of data reflecting a state
in some point in the past,
applying that delay in seconds.
For example, if we have
our slaveDelay option
to 3,600 seconds,
which means 1 hour,
that will mean that such
member will be replicating data
from the other nodes in the
sets that occurred 1 hour ago.
By setting this
slave the option,
it also implies that
your node will be hidden,
and the priority
will be set to 0.
Oh yes, and I almost forgot.
We also have the _id
field within the members
sub-document.
This is just a unique identifier
of each element in the array.
It's a simple
integer field that is
set once we had a member
to the replica set.
Once set, this value
cannot be changed.
Now again, there is
a lot more that we
can configure within the replica
set configuration documents.
It feels like
settings where we can
define several different
replication protocol attributes
or things like the protocol
version and configsvr that will
be seen later in this course.
But the actual uses
of these options
for the basic administration
course are out of scope.
Let's recap.
Replication
configuration document
is used to configure
our replica sets.
This is where the properties of
our replica sets are defined,
and the document is shared
across all members of the set.
The members field
is where a bunch
of our basic configuration
is going to be determined--
which nodes are part of the
set, what roles do they have,
and what kind of topology
we want to define
is set on this field.
There is a vast amount of
other configuration options
that either deal with
internal replication
mechanisms or overall
configurations of the sets.
We are out of scope on
those, but keep in mind
that there's a lot more in
the replication configuration
document that you can set up.