In this lesson, we're
going to cover replication
and how it makes your
data more durable.
MongoDB uses asynchronous,
statement-based replication
because it's
platform independent
and allows more flexibility
within a replica set.
But first, let's just talk
about what replication is.
Replication is the
concept of maintaining
multiple copies of your data.
This is a really important
concept in MongoDB,
but really in any
database system.
The main reason why
replication is necessary
is because you can never
assume that all of your servers
will always be available.
Whether you have to
perform maintenance
on a data center or a disaster
wipes out your data entirely,
your servers will experience
downtime at some point.
The point of replication is
to make sure that in the event
your server goes down, you
can still access your data.
This concept is
called availability.
A database that does
not use replication
only has a single
database server,
and we refer to these
as standalone nodes.
In a standalone
setup, databases can
service reads and writes only
while that single node is
up and running.
But if the node goes down, we
lose all access to that data.
Our reads and writes
won't reach the server.
Now in a replicated
solution, we have
a couple extra nodes
on hand, and they
hold copies of our data.
In MongoDB, a group
of nodes that each
have copies of the same data
is called a replica set.
And in a replica set, all
data is handled by default
in one of the nodes, and
it's up to the remaining
nodes in the set
to sync up with it
and replicate any
new data that's
been written through an
asynchronous mechanism.
The node where data is sent
is called the primary node,
and all the other nodes are
referred to as secondary nodes.
The goal here is for all
nodes to stay consistent
with each other.
So if our application
is using the database,
and the primary node goes down,
one of the secondary nodes
can take its place as primary
in a process known as failover.
The nodes decide
specifically which
secondary will become the
primary through an election.
And this name is
not a coincidence.
The secondary nodes actually
vote for one another
to decide which secondary
will become the primary.
In a durable replica set,
failover can take place
quickly, so that
no data is lost,
and the applications
using the data
will continue communicating with
the replica set as if nothing
had ever happened.
And once the node comes
back up, and it's sure
that it can catch up and sync
on the latest copy of the data,
it will rejoin the
replica set automatically.
Availability and
redundancy of data
are typical properties of a
durable database solution.
Data replication can
take one of two forms.
There is binary replication and
statement-based replication.
We'll take a look at the
differences between these two
approaches, and we'll start
with binary replication.
So let's say we insert this
document into our database.
After the write completes,
we have a few bytes on disk
that were written to
contain some new data.
The way binary
replication works is
by examining the exact bytes
that changed in the data files
and recording those
changes in a binary log.
The secondary nodes then
receive a copy of the binary log
and write the
specified data that
changed to the exact byte
locations that are specified
on the binary log.
Replicating data this way is
pretty easy on the secondaries
because they get really
specific instructions
on what bytes to change
and what to change them to.
And in fact, the
secondaries aren't
even aware of the statements
that they're replicating.
This can be nice because there's
no context about the data
required to replicate a write.
However, using
binary replication
assumes that the
operating system
is consistent across
the entire replica set.
For example, if our primary
node is running Windows,
the secondaries can't
use the same binary log
if they run Linux.
And if they do have the
same operating system,
all machines in the replica set
must have the same instruction
set.
So either Windows x86 or
x64 and the same version
of the database server
running on each machine.
In other words, using
binary replication
requires a very
strict consistency
across every machine
running in a replica set.
Even forgetting to
update the database
server on one of the nodes
could result in corrupted data.
Statement-based
replication is pretty much
what it sounds like.
After a write is completed
on the primary node,
the write statement itself
is stored in the oplog,
and the secondaries
then sync their oplogs
with the primary's oplog and
replay any new statements
on their own data.
This approach works regardless
of the operating system
or instruction set of the
nodes in the replica set.
MongoDB uses
statement-based replication,
but the right commands actually
undergo a small transformation
before they're
stored in the oplog.
And the goal here of
the transformation
is to make sure that the
statements stored in the oplog
can be applied an
indefinite number of times
while still resulting
in the same data state.
This property is
called idempotency.
For example, let's
say that we had
a statement that incremented the
paid views on a website by 1.
The primary already applied
this statement to its data,
so it knows that after
incrementing page use by 1,
the total page views
went from 1,000 to 1,001.
It would actually
transform this statement
into a statement that
sets page views to 1,001
and then store that
statement in the oplog.
When statements are
replicated this way,
we can replay the
oplog as many times
as we want without worrying
about data consistency.
Now let's take a
look at the pros
and cons of binary and
statement-based replication.
The binary approach
requires less data
to be stored in the
binary log, which
means that less data is
passed from the primary
to the secondaries.
Binary replication
can be a lot faster
than statement-based replication
because less work is required
by the secondaries when
actually replicating
from the binary log.
The data that
needs to be changed
is written directly into
the log in that case.
On the other hand,
statement-based replication
in MongoDB writes actual
MongoDB commands into the oplog,
so the oplog is a little bigger.
However, statements
are not bound
to a specific
operating system or
any machine-level dependency.
So there are few
constraints on the machines
in a replica set in MongoDB.
This is valuable for any
cross-platform solution
that requires multiple operating
systems in the same replica
set.