All right, so until
this point, we've
covered basic replication
concepts and how
to deploy a replica set.
But in this lesson,
we're going to cover
how to reconfigure a replica
set while it's still running.
So let's say our replica
set containing our data
is up and running with a
primary and two secondary nodes.
Our supervisor tells us he
wants to add two more nodes, one
secondary and one arbiter.
This is going to be the
typology of our replica set
once we've added our two nodes.
And our supervisor wanted to
add a secondary and an arbiter
instead of just two secondaries,
because an arbiter is a much
cheaper node to maintain.
It doesn't need to copy or
replicate all of the data
from the primary, but
it still provides us
with an odd number of
voting numbers in the set.
So here I'm connected
to our replica set,
and I'm just going
to rs.isMaster to see
that typology really quickly.
And we can see that our
replica set currently
has three nodes in it.
So here I'm just going to launch
a mongod using a configuration
file for our fourth node.
And the config files for the
arbiter and the secondary
are going to be very similar to
the ones for our other nodes.
So I'm not going to
go over them here,
but you can find them attached
to the lecture as handouts.
So once we've started our
node4, we can start our arbiter.
And we now have the
two nodes we need.
And we just have to
add them to the set.
So here we're just adding
the fourth node to our set.
So here when we
add our arbiter, we
use a special command
called addArb.
And it looks like
this completed.
And I'm just going
to check rs.isMaster
to make sure of that.
And we can see that
our replica set now
has four nodes in
it and one arbiter.
So now our replica
set is running
with one primary, three
secondaries, and an arbiter
node.
But our head of
engineering just told us
we have to kill the
arbiter node because we
don't have the budget for it.
So here to the remove
command, we just
pass the port where our
arbiter was running.
And we've successfully
removed it.
However, right now our replica
is set only has four members.
We can verify that
from rs.isMaster.
Our list of hosts only
has four nodes in it.
So in order to
remedy this problem
of having an even number of
voting members in the set,
we don't have to remove
our secondary entirely.
We just have to revoke
its voting privileges
so that will leave us
with three voting members.
Our head of engineering
has also been
talking about using a hidden
node to store backups.
So we decide to be
a little clever.
In addition to being
nonvoting, this secondary
is also going to
be a hidden node.
So we can actually
reconfigure this node
to be hidden and
nonvoting without removing
it or restarting the node.
We use our rs.conf to retrieve
a replica set configuration.
So this gives us a
complete configuration
of the replica set,
including the host name
and port of each node, as
well as if the node is hidden
or an arbiter.
It also gives us the number
of votes that each node has.
So here I'm just storing the
configuration for the set
in a variable called cfg.
So members here is a section
of the config that has
a list of the nodes in the set.
And I've chosen the node at
index position 3 in that list.
And I've changed the number
of votes it has to 0.
This is going to leave
us with an odd number
of voting members in the set.
And here I'm setting the
hidden variable of that node
to true to hide this note
from any client applications.
And hidden nodes can
never become primary,
so in order to make
this a hidden node,
we have to set
the priority to 0.
So this is a new
command, rs.reconfig,
that we use to reconfigure
a running replica set.
We pass in our updated
configuration as an argument,
and we need to specify
this whole document.
That's why we took a copy of
the original configuration
and then modified
it as we needed.
Bear in mind that reconfig
might trigger an election
depending on what's in
the new configuration.
And it looked like this worked.
I'm just going to verify that
it worked with the rs.conf
to get the current configuration
of the replica set.
And it looks like this node now
has priority 0, it can't vote,
and it's hidden.
So now our replica set
still has four nodes in it,
which is an even number, but
only an odd number of them
can vote.
So just to recap,
in this lesson we
covered how to add arbiters
and new secondaries,
we said a little bit
about hidden nodes,
and we added one to our set.
And we also covered how to
reconfigure a replica set
while it's still running.