In general, the
core write commands
all support write concern.
Now, we've talked about this
all at a pretty high level.
Write concern makes
a lot more sense
when you watch it in action.
In an earlier
lesson, we showed you
how an application writes
"behave" during a failover
event.
Let's return to that example
now but to talk about
write concern.
We have our
three-member replica set
with an application inserting
data into the primary.
As you might remember, data
is replicated from the primary
to the secondaries.
The default write
concern is one.
So even though we don't set
the write concern explicitly,
the application
implicitly assigns
it a write concern of one.
At this point, we know
that our primary has
received the write operation.
We've received one
acknowledgment based
on our write concern of one.
Since that matches the
write concern we requested,
we're good to go.
But what would happen
if the primary failed
at this point of time before
it completes replicating
this write to the secondaries?
The secondaries
won't see the write.
While it was successful
on a single node,
we had no guarantee
that the write
had propagated to the
remaining replica set members.
Even though we got the
level of write concern
we asked for, the
guarantee level
was too low to
accommodate the scenario.
As far as our
application is concerned,
this was a successful write.
But when this primary
comes back online the right
would actually be rolled back.
Let's imagine the same scenario
but with a write concern
of majority.
That means we now would
need an acknowledgment
from two members of our
three-member replica set.
The application waits
until the primary reports
that at least one
of the secondaries
has also acknowledged the write.
With two acknowledgments
the application
can consider the
write a success.
Now if the primary
happens to go down,
we have a reasonable
guarantee that at least one
of the secondaries has
received the write operation.
If I set the write
concern to three,
the application would
require an acknowledgment
from all three members
before considering
the write successful.
At this point, you
might be thinking, well,
I want guarantees
of data durability.
So shouldn't I always
set my write concern
as high as possible?
Well, a stronger level
of durability guarantee
comes with the trade off.
Specifically, you have to
wait for the acknowledgments
to come in.
That means your write operations
may take longer than required
if you requested a lesser or
even no write acknowledgment.
As the number of replica
set nodes increase,
write operations may take even
longer to return as successful.
Alternatively, what happens
if one of your secondaries
are down?
Based on our write concern,
we need an acknowledgment
from three members
of the replica set.
This write now blocks
until the secondary
comes back online which may
take longer than is acceptable.
This is where the W timeout
option comes in handy.
You can set it to
a reasonable time
wherein the application
stops waiting
and moves forward throwing an
error related to write concern.
Remember, the timeout error does
not mean that the write failed.
We can see here that the primary
and at least one secondary
did acknowledge.
But because we timed out
waiting for the requested write
concern, as far as the
application is concerned,
it did not receive the level
of guarantee it requested.
Generally, setting
a W of majority
is a nice middle ground between
fast writes and durability
guarantees.
To recap, write concern
allows your applications
to request a certain
number of acknowledgments
for a write operation
for the MongoDB cluster.
These acknowledgments
represent increasing durability
guarantees for a given
write operations.
Write concern comes with a
trade off of write speed.
The higher guarantee you
need that a right is durable,
the more time the overall write
operation requires to complete.
MongoDB supports a write
concern on all deployment types.
That means standalone, replica
sets, and sharded clusters
all support write concern.