MongoDB write concern is
an acknowledgment mechanism
that developers can add
to write operations.
Higher levels of acknowledgment
produce a stronger durability
guarantee.
Durability means that
the write has propagated
to the number of
replica set member nodes
specified in the write concern.
The more replica
set members that
acknowledge the success of
a write, the more likely
that the write is durable
in the event of a failure.
Majority here is defined as a
simple majority of replica set
members.
So divide by two, and round up.
The trade-off with increased
durability is time.
More durability
requires more time
to achieve the
specified durability
guarantee since you have to
wait for those acknowledgments.
Let's go over the available
write concern levels.
A write concern of zero means
that the application doesn't
wait for any acknowledgments.
The write might succeed or fail.
The application
doesn't really care.
It only checks that it
can connect to the node
successfully.
Think of this like a
fire-and-forget strategy-- very
fast, but with no
safety checks in place.
The default write
concern is one.
That means the application
waits for an acknowledgment
from a single member
of the replica set,
specifically, the primary.
This is a baseline
guarantee of success.
Write concerns greater than
one increase the number
of acknowledgments to include
one or more secondary members.
Higher levels of write concern
correspond to a stronger
guarantee of write durability.
For example, I can set
a write concern of three
to require acknowledgment from
all three replica set members.
Majority is a keyword
that translates
to a majority of
replica set members.
It's a simple majority.
So divide the number of
members by two and round up.
So this three-member replica
set has a majority of two.
A five-member replica set would
have a majority of three--
so on and so forth.
The nice thing with
majority is that you
don't have to update your
write concern if you increase
the size of your replica set.
There's also a write concern
level for replica set tags.
That's a little advance
for this course series,
but you can check
out our documentation
on write concern for
more information.
We're just talking about
replica sets in this lesson.
But MongoDB supports
write concern
for both standalone
and sharded clusters.
For sharded clusters
in particular,
write concern is pushed
down to the shard level.
Finally, I want to
make it very clear
that no matter what write
concern you specify,
MongoDB always replicates data
to every data-bearing node
in the cluster.
Write concern is
just there for you
to have a way of tracking the
durability of inserted data.
There are two additional
write concern options
that MongoDB provides.
The first is wtimeout.
This lets you set a
maximum amount of time
the application waits before
marking an operation as failed.
An important note here--
hitting a wtimeout
error does not
mean that the write
operation itself has failed.
It only means that the
application did not
get the level of durability
that it requested.
The second is j, or journal.
This option requires that
each replica set member
to receive the write and
commit to the journal filed
for the write to be
considered acknowledged.
Starting with MongoDB 3.2.6,
a write concern of majority
actually implies j equals true.
The advantage of
setting j equals true
for any given write concern
is that you have a stronger
guarantee that not only
were the writes received,
they've been written
to an on-disk journal.
If you set j to false,
or if journaling
is disabled on the
mongod, the node
only needs to store
the data in memory
before reporting success.