After initiating our node and
adding the node to the replica
set, the oplog.rs
collection is created.
By default, as I
mentioned before,
we take 5% of the
available disk.
But this value can also
be set by configuring it
through the oplog size in
megabytes under the replication
section of our
configuration file.
As operations get
logged into the oplog,
like inserts or deletes
or create collection kind
of operations, the
oplog.rs collection
starts to accumulate the
operations and statements,
until it reaches the
oplog size limit.
Once that happens, the first
operations in our oplog
start to be overwritten
with newer operations.
The time it takes to
fill in fully our oplog
and start rewriting
the early statements
determines the
replication window.
The replication window
is important aspect
to monitor because we'll impact
how much time the replica
set can afford a node to
be down without requiring
any human intervention
to auto recover.
Every node in our replica
set has its own oplog.
As writes and operations
gets to the primary node,
these are captured in the oplog.
And then the secondary nodes
replicate that data and apply
it on their own oplog.
Now if for some reason
one of the nodes
gets disconnected,
either because they're
going some
maintenance, or there's
some sort of network
issues, or any server
downtime of any kind, and
the server keeps on working,
the replica set keeps on
accumulating new writes--
for the server to be able to
catch up with the remaining
nodes, you will
need to figure out
what's a common point
where everyone can
see what happened in the past.
Basically what will happen
is that a recovering node
will check for its
last oplog entry
and try to find it in one
of the available nodes.
Once he finds it, he will just
simply re-apply all operations
since that point and catch
up with the remaining
nodes of the sets.
However, if it is not able to
find the same common operation
in the remaining nodes' oplog
because of the oplog already
rotated and no sync source
point as the last operation,
the node will not be able to
automatically recover and sync
with the rest of the set,
being placed in recovery mode.
Now, not all nodes
need to be the same.
For example, sync sources might
have different oplog sizes.
However, if our oplog
size is larger and able
to accommodate more
changes in the system,
we can afford our nodes
to be down for longer
and still be able to reconnect
once they're being brought back
up again.
Therefore, the size of
our oplog.rs collection
is an important aspect
to keep in mind.
To sum up, the replication
window measured in hours
will be proportional to
the load of your system.
You should keep an eye on that.
The other good thing is that our
oplog.rs size can be changed.
And we have a fair amount of
good documentation telling you
how to do that as a
administration task.
Another aspect to know
about this collection
is that given the
idempotent nature
of the instructions,
one single update
may result in several different
operations in this collection.
Let me show you how this works.
I'm going to use
this database here--
M03.
I'm going to create a
collection called messages.
Once I create that, I can see
that collection there created.
Now if I jump into
my local database
and I look into our oplog.rs,
excluding any periodic noop
operations maintained
by the server,
I can find here the
instruction that creates
this collection in the oplog.
Cool, this is really good.
Now let's jump back to
our M103 collection.
And let's insert a few
documents just for fun.
There you go.
We inserted 100 documents
with the message, not yet.
If I go ahead and count them up,
I can see 100 documents there--
great.
If I jump back to
my local database
and look for those
messages, I can
see that I can find those
insert-- the operation there
is an insert.
And the object being inserted
is one of the 100 documents
inserted-- great.
But now let's do a simple
updateMany operation.
Let's say that I want to
make sure these messages here
have an author.
So I'm going to set a
new field called author
with the value called,
well, my own name--
Norberto.
Once I do this--
and keep in mind that this
is one single operation, one
UpdateOne, that
modified and matched
100 different documents.
If we jump back to local, and
if we look for more operations,
I can see that there
is an update operation,
or several update operations--
op equals u means an update--
for all the affected
documents in this collection.
So one single instruction--
an updateMany--
into our primary, produced
100 different operations
into our oplog.
Now this is the magic
of idempotence.
Be aware of this.
Sometimes is easy to dismiss
the fact that idempotency
might generate a
lot more operations
in our oplog than the number
of commands actually issued
from the client.
One last point that I want
to bring to your attention
is that, please don't change
any of this information present
on any of this collection.
Contrary to what MC
Hammer used to say,
you can, in fact,
touch this, given
the correct set of permissions.
But please don't.
This might affect
tremendously badly the way
that your replica works.
So try not to mess around too
much with this collection.
That said, and to prove you
that you can do some damage,
let's try to write to
this local database.
I'm going to go ahead and
in my local collection,
insert a message saying
that you cannot touch this.
And if we look for it in our
oplog.rs, we will not find it.
You should keep in
mind that this data
that I've just written into
this particular database--
there it is, my
local collection--
is written into
the local database.
That means it's local to
this particular instance.
Any data written
in this collection
will not be replicated.
Local database is like Vegas.
What happens in
local, stays in local.
No other node in the set
will ever see that data,
except obviously
for the oplog.rs,
which they are reading and
applying it on their own.
Anything else that you
might want to keep local,
you can write here.
But we do not recommend
you to do any of that
unless you really know
what you're doing.
Let's quickly sum up
what we just learned.
Local database holds very
important information
and should not be
messed up with.
Changing the data in your oplog
or any of the configuration
collections will
impact the settings
in the replication mechanism.
The oplog.rs is central to
our replication mechanism.
Everything that needs
to be replicated
will be stored and logged in
the oplog in an idempotent
way.
The size of our oplog will
impact the replication window
and should be closely monitored.
Any data written to local
database that is not
written to oplog.rs or
changing any of the system
configuration collections
will stay there
and will not be replicated.