Read preference allows
your applications
to route read operations to
specific members of a replica
set.
Read preference is principally
a driver side setting.
Make sure to check your
driver documentation
for complete instructions on
specifying a read preference
for your read operations.
Take this three member
replica set, for example.
By default, your applications
read and write data
on the primary.
With replica sets, data
is replicated to all data
bearing members.
So both of these
secondaries would eventually
have copies of the primary data.
What if we, instead, wanted
to have our application
prefer reading from
a secondary member?
With the read preference, we
can direct the application
to route its query to a
secondary member of the replica
set, instead of the primary.
There are five supported
read preference modes.
Primary read preference
routes all read operations
to the primary only.
This is the default
read preference.
PrimaryPreferred routes read
operations to the primary.
But if the primary
is unavailable,
such as during an election
or fail-over event,
the application can route
reads to an available secondary
member instead.
Secondary routes
read operations only
to the secondary members
in the replica set.
SecondaryPreferred
routes read operations
to the secondary members.
But if no secondary
members are available,
the operation then
routes to the primary.
Nearest routes read operations
to the replica set member
with the least network
latency to the host,
regardless of the members type.
This typically supports
geographically local read
operations.
With secondary reads,
always keep in mind
that depending on the
amount of replication
latency in a replica set,
you can receive stale data.
For example, let's say
this replica set receives
a write operation that
updates this document, where
name is Mongo 101, to have
a status of published.
At this time, the
secondary still
has the old version
of this document
where the status is pending.
If I issue a
secondary read, using
nearest read preference
selects the secondary member
to read from, I'm
going to get an older
version of this document.
This table gives you an idea
of some of the scenarios
where you'd use a
given read preference.
The big takeaway here, is
that secondary reads always
have a chance of
returning stale data.
How stale that data is, depends
entirely on how much of a delay
there is between your
primary and your secondaries.
Geographically
distributed replica sets
are more likely to suffer
from stale reads, for example,
than a replica set where
all the members are
in the same geographic region,
or even the same data center.
To summarize, read
preference lets
you choose what
replica set members
to route read operations to.
The big drawback of using a read
preference, other than primary,
is the potential for
stale read operations.
And the nearest
read preference is
most useful if you
want to support
geographically local reads.
Just remember that it can come
with the potential of reading
stale data.