Hi there, and welcome to
M042: New Features and Tools
in MongoDB 4.2.
One of our classics around
here at MongoDB University.
In this course, we'll be
looking to all the new features
that we have assembled for
you in the MongoDB 4.2 server
release and the tools
that are made available
around this release cycle.
And what do we have for
you this time around?
Well, a bunch of cool new stuff.
On the server side,
the main feature
we are going to be releasing
is sharded transactions.
Multi-document
transaction support
across sharded clusters.
You will get a deep
dive explanation
on how sharded transactions
work and the benefits regarding
the management of shard
keys, for example,
that come associated
with the support
of sharded transactions.
But there is more.
MongoDB 4.2 brings a
complete new index built
system and a new index type.
MongoDB 4.2 also introduces
a more expressive update
operator, the new dollar merge
aggregation pipeline stage
that allows for powerful
on-demand materialized view
mechanisms, and a set of
new aggregation pipeline
expressions.
On our tools front, we'll
be looking to improvements
and advances around Ops Manager
backup flows, each agent
support, new
organizations API access,
and the general availability
of our MongoDB enterprise
Kubernetes Operator for all of
you container people out there.
Regarding the cloud
offering, we'll
be introducing a
brand new product that
will enable the analysis of data
stored in S3 buckets or archive
data using the MongoDB query
language and the aggregation
framework.
Charts got a new set
of exciting features
like new geospatial charts
types and the ability
to embed charts directly
into your mobile application.
So a lot of new exciting
stuff to look for.
But let's talk logistics.
In this course we want
to focus your attention
on the new features and
products and remove away
any emphasis on completing
homework and assignments.
This means that we
are not going to have
you go through a final exam
or any graded assignments
in this course.
We still want you to follow
along with lecture material
and be able to experiment with
all the new server versions
and the new release tools.
Therefore, we will be making
available a virtual machine
supported by Vagrant
so you can play around
with all of those new
exciting features,
intellectual material in
an isolated environment
containing all the necessary
dependencies pre-installed.
That said, it is
completely optional.
You can, if you choose to,
install all the new features
and tools in your workstation.
In this lesson
lecture notes you will
find a full list of dependencies
and installation instructions
necessary for this course.
The VM is for your
convenience only.
The goal of this
course is for you
to have a clear understanding
of all these new features
introduced in MongoDB
4.2, have a view of how
these new tools help you
become more effective,
and expand the possible
usage of MongoDB
across a variety of
different use cases.
With all that
said, welcome, hope
you enjoy and get to
learn all the new features
and functionality
we prepared for you.
And I'll see you in class.