Hello.
My name is Matt.
And in this lesson,
we're going to look
at the virtual environment
for this course M042.
So throughout this
course, we're going
to show examples of the new
features in MongoDB 4.2.
And we want to give you a way
of testing out these features so
that you can feel
comfortable using them.
So one option is to spin
up a replica set locally
and then follow along lessons
on your local machine.
If you feel comfortable
doing this, you should do it.
But you should bear in mind
that in order for everything
to run locally you need to have
the dependencies installed as
well as the necessary
handout files to follow along
with the lesson.
This is all possible,
as we'll provide links
to download dependencies
and distribute the handouts.
But there is an easier solution.
Using the virtual machine
for this course, called
m042-vagrant-env, we can
download and provision
an environment that
already contains
the necessary dependencies
for this course
as well as any handout files.
In this case, we would call
the VM the guest machine.
And we refer to our local
machine as the host machine.
Once we provision the
VM, we can start up
a replica set without needing
to download anything else.
In addition, using the course VM
helps MongoDB university staff
such as myself diagnose
and debug potential issues,
because we're very familiar
with this environment,
and we may not be as familiar
with your local machine.
So without further ado, let's
take a look inside the VM.
So I'm just going to make a
new directory for this course
and then cd into it.
So I just downloaded
the VM from the handouts
on the university site, and now
it's in my Downloads folder.
So I'm just going to copy
it into my m042 folder here.
So now I'm inside the VM
folder m042-vagrant-env,
and there are only two
files in here to start out--
the Vagrantfile, which contains
some of the baseline hardware
configurations for the VM
and the provisioning file
as a shell script that downloads
all the necessary dependencies
and files for this course.
So using this command, I can
bring the VM up and then run
the provisioning file
in one fell swoop.
So we have to wait a
minute for this to run.
But when it's done, it
should read "Welcome
to M042 Vagrant Box."
If we see that
message, we'll know
that the machine was booted
up, and the provisioning script
ran successfully.
So now we can log into
the Vagrant machine
with SSH using the
command vagrant ssh.
And we can see the
shell prompt has
changed to reflect that we're
now logged in to the Vagrant
machine.
So remember, our provisioning
script already downloaded
MongoDB.
So we can spin up a
mongod process immediately
after logging into
the Vagrant machine
for the very first time.
I can connect to the
database I just started.
I'm just going to
shut down this server
so I can start up a new one.
So now I've just shut down
that database process,
and I've exited from
the Mongo shell,
so that I can start up a new
database process that's bound
to a different IP address.
So the guest VM
has been configured
to be accessed on the IP
address 192.168.42.100.
So if you want to access this
mongod server from your host
machine, you need to bind your
Mongo ID to that IP address.
So now that that's
started successfully,
I'm actually just going to
exit the Vagrant machine.
So now I'm connected
back to my host machine.
But the mongod process is still
running inside the guest VM.
I can connect to
that mongod process
using the IP address of the VM.
The --host flag allows us to
specify a network interface
where mongod is running.
And I started that process
in the default port,
so all I need to do is
specify a host here.
So one reason you might want
to connect to the guest VM
from your host machine
is if you wanted
to connect with Compass,
which was running on your host
machine, to a
mongod process that
was running inside the
guest machine or the VM.
So to do this, we can just
specify the same hostname here
and the connection
credentials on Compass.
And then we should
be able to connect.
I'm just going to
connect back to Vagrant
with SSH very quickly to
show you one more thing.
So when the home
directory of Vagrant,
which is the directory it'll
direct you to as you first
connect, there's this folder
in the home directory called
Shared.
Now, this folder is what we
call a synced folder, which
means that it's synced
to your host machine.
When you bring up
the Vagrant machine,
there are actually two Shared
folders that get created.
The first gets created
on your host machine,
and the second gets created
inside the Vagrant machine.
These two folders
are linked together.
So you can share documents
between your host
machine and your course VM.
If you place any file on one
of these folders or remove one,
that change will be reflected
in the other folder.
So be careful, because
you could accidentally
delete things from
your host machine
while you're still in the VM.
So that concludes our
lesson on Vagrant.
Just to recap, the
virtual environment
is used to mitigate the need
to download course dependencies
on your local machine.
The VM will come with
everything pre-installed.
If you want to share
files between your host
system and your VM, the Shared
folder will help you do that.
Lastly, Vagrant is
optional in this course,
as there is no homework.
So if you want to use
your local machine
to test out the new
features, please feel free.
But this approach is
most likely easier.