In this lesson, we'll cover
a few of the basic commands
necessary to interact
with the MongoDB cluster.
This won't be an
exhaustive list.
For that, take a look at
the reference documentation
included in the lecture notes.
We're actually going to focus
on the shell helpers first.
These are methods available
in the MongoDB shell
that wrap underlying
database commands.
The majority of your
interactions in this course
and likely in general
will use shell helpers.
First you have your
DB shell helpers.
These are methods that
wrap commands that interact
with the database.
You've already used a few of
these in previous lessons,
like db.createuser.
Next you have your
rs helper methods.
These methods wrap commands
that control replica
set deployment and management.
We're going to talk about
replication in week two.
Finally, you have your
sh helper methods.
These methods wrap commands
to control sharded cluster
deployment and management.
We will get to
sharding in week three.
Now the database shell helper
has one additional extension.
Remember that each
database can have
one or more collections in it.
And collections are where
your data is stored.
So Mongo shell provides shell
helpers for collection level
operations.
You specify the name
of the collection
here, essentially providing
a path to the collection
you want to interact with.
Let's go over some of the
most basic shell helpers
that you may find useful
during this course.
For user management, you've
got create user and drop user.
You've already used create
user in an earlier lesson.
Note that both of these are
acting on the database object.
That's because users are
created at the database level.
For collection management,
you can use rename collection
to change the name of
an existing collection.
You also have
collection.createindex
and collection.drop.
Both of these methods act on
the collection object, which
is why we have db.collection.
In the shell, you'd want
to change the collection
to the name of the collection.
This is just a placeholder.
For database management, you
can always use drop database
to drop the entire database.
This will destroy all
collections, indexes,
and users created
on that database,
so use this with caution.
db.createcollection lets
you create a collection
on your own.
In a previous lesson, we noted
that MongoDB creates databases
and collections implicitly
on a write operation,
but you may want to create
your collections first.
There are some additional
configuration options you have
when you use this method, such
as creating a capped collection
or setting language collation
support, both of which
are out of scope
for this lesson.
So look at the documentation
if you're curious.
Finally, when you want to see
how your database is doing,
you've got
db.serverstatus, which
returns statistics
on the database,
like the amount of storage
space you are using.
We're going to talk
more about replication
and sharding in later lessons.
And you'll see examples of the
rs and sh shell helpers then
I mentioned earlier
that shell helpers wrap
an underlying database command.
Let's look at the
db.collection.createindex
method, compared against the
underlying create indexes
command.
While they look sort of
similar, the database command
is a lot more
verbose in defining
the same level of work.
That's part of why MongoDB
provides helper methods
for wrapping these
database commands.
Depending on whether you're
using the MongoDB shell
or MongoDB driver, the exact
name and format of these helper
methods might differ,
but their purpose
is to provide a shortcut
for methods like this.
Running a database
command itself
is pretty straightforward.
The Mongo shell provides
the run command method
on the database object.
You pass in the command as
a parameter to this method.
DB here refers to
the active database.
Do you remember the use keyword?
We've used it a
few times already.
The run command always works
against the active database.
So make sure you set the
right database to active
before you use run command.
If you want information on how
a particular command works,
you can use the
db.commandhelp method
to retrieve any available
help information.
Now you might
wonder, why would I
ever want to use the
underlying database command?
Well, we've been talking
about the shell helpers.
They're only in the shell.
If you want to run a database
command from a driver,
then you're going to need to
execute the underlying database
command instead, assuming
that the driver doesn't
have some other
existing helper method.
You can actually introspect
a shell helper from the shell
by not including the open
and closing parentheses.
The shell helper will produce
the underlying code run.
In this case, we can see
that create index method
runs the create indexes command.
To recap, the database
commands provide the foundation
for interacting with MongoDB.
You can use db.run command to
run any given database command.
The Mongo shell
provides helper methods
for wrapping database commands
and simplifying usage.
For this course, you're going
to be using the helper methods,
but if you want to know more
about the underlying database
commands, check out
our documentation.