In this lesson, we will
cover the file structure
of a MongoDB standalone server.
This is a list of the
files you can expect
to find in a data directory of
a MongoDB server or standalone
process.
You typically never
need to interact
with the files in
this data folder
unless directed to by
MongoDB support personnel
or through a procedure
detailed in our documentation.
None of these files are
designed for user access
or modification,
and modifying them
can cause crashes or data loss.
If you want to explore,
please take time
to make sure you are
performing read functions only.
Let's take a look at a
real MongoDB deployment.
This group of files
here is related
to how the WiredTiger
storage engine keeps
track of information
like cluster
metadata and WiredTiger-specific
configuration options.
The WiredTiger.lock
file acts as a safety.
If you ran a second
simultaneous MongoDB process
and pointed at this
folder, the lock file
helps prevent that
second MongoDB process
from starting up.
If you experience an
unclean shutdown such,
as the host machine losing
power or a crash of some sort,
you may find that you cannot
start up the MongoD due to this
lock file.
You may be instructed
to delete lock files
before restarting the MongoD.
Remember that if
you are not guided
by MongoDB support or
a documented procedure,
do not interact with
any of these files.
This next group of files
ending in .wt are related
to collection and
index the data itself.
These are your collection data,
and these are your index data.
MongoDB WiredTiger
stores index data
as a separate structure
from collection data.
Each collection an
index gets its own file.
Even in a brand new
MongoDB deployment,
you typically have a few
databases and collections
by default, so you should always
see some collection in index
.wt files.
You can try to introspect
these data files
using a program like
Strings, but there's not
much human readable data here.
These files are designed
to be interacted
with through the MongoDB
server process, rather
than a third party tool.
Modifying these tools can
lead to data loss and crashes.
Now this diagnostic.data folder
looks pretty interesting.
Let's take a quick look.
This data contains diagnostic
data captured for specific use
by MongoDB support.
To be very clear, we
are not capturing any
of your actual private data.
The diagnostic data is captured
by our Full Time Data Capture,
or FTDC module.
FTDC collects data from
the following commands.
If you try to take a look at
the data produced by the FTDC
module using something
like Strings,
you'll find that it's
not human readable.
This data is only used
for diagnostic purposes
by MongoDB support engineers.
And they can only
look at that data
if you explicitly provide it.
Moving forward, let's take
a look at our journal files.
Each of these journal files
are part of the WiredTiger
journaling system.
Let's talk about
that just briefly.
With MongoDB WiredTiger,
write operations
are buffered in memory and
are flushed every 60 seconds,
creating a checkpoint of data.
WiredTiger also uses a
write ahead logging system
to an on disk journal file.
Journal entries are
first buffered in memory,
and then WiredTiger
syncs the journal
to disk every 50 milliseconds.
Each journal file is limited
to 100 megabytes of size.
WiredTiger uses a
file rotation method
for syncing data to disk.
In the event of a
failure, WiredTiger
can use the journal
to recover data that
occurred between checkpoints.
For example, during
normal operations,
WiredTiger flushes data
to disk every 60 seconds,
or when the journal file
has 2 gigabytes of data.
These flushes again create
a durable checkpoint.
If the MongoD crashes
between checkpoints,
there is a possibility
that data was not
safely and fully written.
When the MongoDB
gets back online,
WiredTiger can check if there
is any recovery to be made.
In case that there are
some incomplete writes,
WiredTiger looks at
the existing data
files to find the identifier
of the last checkpoint.
It then searches
the journal files
for the record that
matches the identifier
of the last checkpoint.
Finally, it applies operations
in the journal files
since the last checkpoint.
At the end, the MongoDB server
can resume normal execution.
Let's take a look at
the last group of files.
The mongod.lock file
has a similar function
to the WiredTiger.lock file.
If this file is
not empty, it means
that a MongoDB
process is currently
active in this directory.
Any other MongoDB
process attempting
to access this directory will
fail to startup in that event.
If this file is empty,
then everything is clear.
In some unusual situations,
like an unclean shutdown,
the mongod.lock
file won't be empty,
even though the MongoD
is no longer running.
You may need to delete
the mongod.lock file
if directed to by support
or our documentation.
These remaining two files are
more support and metadata files
for WiredTiger.
Remember, you should
never need to interact
with any of these files
and modifying them may
result in crashes or data loss.
In addition to the files held
here in the data directory,
there is also the log file.
We're going to be
going over logging
in more detail in
the later lesson.
But just to give you a quick
look, you can see in my log,
there's not a whole lot of
information in here right now.
That's because I'm not really
doing anything with my server.
As you use your MongoDB
server, the log file
will fill with
additional information.
These log files are vital
for post failure diagnostics
and should be treated
with care as well.
It's up to you if you
want to place your log
files in the same directory
as your data files.
It's not a bad idea to
keep them separate though.
There's one more file
that we should talk about,
but it's in neither
of the two directories
we've talked about so far.
This mongodb-27017.sock file is
a socket file used by MongoDB
to create a socket connection
at the specified port.
MongoDB needs to use sockets
for interprocess communications.
Without this file, the
MongoDB cannot function.
This file is created at startup
and lets the MongoDB server
own this port.
If there is a crash or
other unclean shutdown,
you might find an error on
startup related to this file.
You can safely delete it
if directed to by support
or our documentation
in that event.
Let's recap.
Some files, such as
diagnostic.data and your log
files, are used
by MongoDB support
for helping you resolve
problems with your database.
The rest are exclusively
used by the MongoDB server
process for normal
operations and should not
be modified without specific
direction from MongoDB support.
Defer to the MongoDB
support or our documentation
for instructions on interacting
with any of these files.