All right so in
this lesson, we're
going to discuss the
database profiler,
and how it can be used in
conjunction with the database
locks.
Servers generate a really
large number of events.
And a log file is great for
capturing this data, or subsets
of this data.
But the purpose of these logs
is to report on the health
of the database, as a whole.
The logs do store some
data on our commands,
but there's not
enough data in here
to start optimizing our queries.
The lines won't
contain any execution
stats, the direction of
an index used by a query,
rejected plans, or anything.
And even if we could place
that information in the logs,
we really shouldn't.
The log files are meant
to give administrators
operational information
about an instance or process,
so they can flag any
errors, warnings,
or interesting
informational messages.
For debugging slow
operations, we
need to be a bit more precise
in the information we capture.
So for that, we rely on
the database profiler.
We enable profilers
at the database level.
So the operations
on each database
are profiled separately.
When it's enabled,
the profile will
restore data for all
operations on a given database,
and a new collection
called system dot profile.
This collection will
hold profiling data
on CRUD operations, as
well as administrative and
configuration options.
It has three settings.
The default value is
zero, which just means
that the profiler's turned off.
One means the profiler
is on, but it's only
going to profile operations
that are considered slow.
By default, MongoDB
will consider
any operation that takes
longer than 100 milliseconds
to be slow.
But we can also define
what a slow query
is by setting the slow MS
value, as we'll see in a minute.
Two means that
the profiler's on,
and will profile all
operations on a database,
regardless of how
long they take.
This is a bit
dangerous because it
can result in a lot of rights
to the system dot profile
collection, and generate a
lot of load on the system.
This doesn't mean small
operations can't be blocking
other ones, but getting
data on those operations
requires more granularity.
All right, so now let's
take a look at the profiler.
This database doesn't
actually exist yet,
so the profiler by
default is set to level 0.
And we can verify that by
running db.getprofilinglevel.
And as you can see,
it gives us a zero.
We can change that to a one
with db.setprofilinglevel.
So this statement turned on the
profiler, profiling level 1.
If we run this
command, we can see
that MongoDB created a
new collection called
system dot profile.
But there's nothing
in it right now.
And because we haven't
specified a slow MS,
the profiler will
only store data
on queries that take longer
than 100 milliseconds.
All right so here, just to get a
sense of how the profiler works
and what the profiling
data looks like,
I'm just going to
set slow MS to zero,
so that everything gets
profiled in this database.
So I'm just going to insert
a small document here
into this new collection,
called new collection.
So now I'm just going
to look at what's
in the system dot
profile collection right
now, after we'd run
that query, and I'm
going to make the output
a little prettier so it's
more readable.
All right, so we can
see our rights statement
is recorded in the profiler.
It gives us the number
of documents inserted,
and inserted, and the
number of index keys
inserted by the
operation, keys inserted,
as well as how long the
operation took in milliseconds.
So we can also profile
read operations.
Here, we have a really
simple query predicate,
where we're only looking for
documents where A is one.
And we can see the profiler
recorded a little more
information about this query.
It tells us that we
exhausted the cursor
that we were using to
retrieve this data,
and it also has some
execution stats,
like the status that we
went through to get here.
In this case, it was
just a collection scan.
All right, so just
to recap, we've
covered the difference between
log data and profile data,
how to configure the
profiler on your database,
and how to interpret the
output from the profiler
depending on the operation.