The MongoDB configuration
file is a way
to organize the options you
need to run the MongoD or MongoS
process into an easy
to parse YAML file.
For the majority of use
cases outside of the most
basic of development
or evaluation,
you should be using
a configuration file
for storing your MongoD
or MongoS startup options.
Before we get into more detail
on the configuration file,
let's first start with
a MongoD option is.
If you've interacted with a
program in a terminal or shell
environment, you are likely
already familiar with how
the command line options work.
Typically you have
your main executable--
for example, the MongoD.
Then you chain in your
command line options.
Some of them like take a
value, like dbpath and logpath.
Others work like a flag
and don't require a value
to direct behavior, like fork.
In the end, you have
your full command
on the command line
with potentially dozens
of options and values.
This command is perfectly
valid and would work fine
in production environments.
But there are problems
with this approach.
We would have to type this whole
thing over again every time
we would like to launch a new
MongoD in a different server.
If we want to track
these settings,
we would need to grep the
existing services running
in the server or run a
command within MongoDB.
Finally, it's harder
to read and look
for individual options along
this very long command line
string.
Before we get into the
configuration file,
let's start with a few
common command line options.
You have your basic path
configuration options--
dbpath and logpath.
Starting with 3.6, you
need to set bind ip
to include a network adapter on
the host that provides access
to the network.
Otherwise, the MongoD can
only accept connections
on that same host.
Setting the replSet
and keyFile options
starts up the MongoD
in replication mode
with basic intercluster
auth security and user
authentication enabled.
These are very common
options, and chances are,
you'll see at least one of
these in any MongoDB deployment.
The SSL options are related to
tls ssl transport encryption.
You don't need to know much
about these options in detail
for this course.
Take a look at M3 10 here
on MongoDB University
for an in-depth course
on cluster security,
including tsl ssl.
Alternatively, take a
look at our documentation.
Finally, we have fork,
which just tells the MongoD
run as a daemon instead of
being tied to a terminal window.
So what are the configuration
file counterparts
to these command line options?
On the right, I
have the full path
to the configuration option.
That means each key in the
path to the final value
is the parent of the YAML file.
So the replSet name
configuration option
falls under the
replication parent key.
Configuration files to support
deeper nesting as well.
Take a look at
these two options--
sslPEMKey and sslCA file.
These are both under the
SSL parent, which themselves
are under the net parent.
The net parent also
captures a bind ip.
All three options are related
to the net parent, but as
a sslPEMKey and sslCAKey
are specific to net.ssl.
Now, how did I get
to these mappings?
This is where our fantastic
manual comes to the rescue.
All of our command line options
and our configuration file
options are well documented
in these two links.
I invite you to
give these a look
to find out about
which command line
options or configuration
file options are available
and how to map between the two.
Now let's take our list of
configuration file options
with the full path to the
option and translate that
into our configuration
YAML file.
YAML stands for Yet
Another Markup Language.
You have your key value pairs.
The top level key and a
MongoDB a configuration file
represents a logical
grouping of options.
Each nested element
under a top level key
represents an option related
to that top level key.
So here we see that dbPath
is a storage option.
Remember, previously this
was listed as storage.dbPath.
The command line option
was dash dash dbPath.
A key can have multiple
embedded key pair
values, each representing an
option related to the top level
key.
So here we have our
system log family
of options where I am
specifying the path to the log
file and the file type.
You'll notice that our one
option, log path, became two.
Sometimes a
configuration file option
will have one or more
required chained options.
The documentation will
always clearly state
these relationships.
It's also easier to see distinct
groupings of related options.
I can clearly distinguish
the storage options
from the system logging options
from the replication options.
I've even added a
comment to improve
readability and comprehension.
The configuration
file options have
the same effect as the
command line options,
but as you can see,
the YAML format
provides significant advantages.
These are all of the options
from our initial example.
The effect on the
MongoD is the same,
but the organization and
readability is vastly improved.
Now how do we use a
configuration file?
We are going to have to use
at least one command line
option for this to work.
Specify dash dash config
or dash f along with a path
to the configuration file.
For many Linux distributions,
when installing MongoDB through
a package manager, you'll find
a default configuration file
in etc/mongod.conf.
Feel free to modify this or
point to your own configuration
file.
You just need to
ensure that the MongoD
process can access the file
location and read the file.
You can find the complete list
of configuration file options
and how to use them on
our online documentation.
The documentation also includes
structural examples, as well as
a description of
how the options work
and what the
expected values are.
To recap, configuration
file options
provide the same functionality
as our command line options.
They improve the readability
of our configuration settings,
and you can use
the documentation
to facilitate mapping a command
line option to a configuration
file option.