MongoDB provides two
logging facilities
for tracking activities
on your database.
The process log
displays activity
on the MongoDB instance.
The process log
collects activity
into one of the
following components.
Each of these components has
an associated verbosity level.
You can use db.getLogComponents
in the Mongo shell
to review the currently
configured log
component verbosity.
Let's take a look.
I'm connected to the MongoDB
server using the mongo shell.
I can run db.getLogComponents
to retrieve the log components
from my current database.
So what does all of this mean?
Starting at the top,
the verbosity field
is the default verbosity
level for the MongoDB server.
Any of the other components
can inherit from this field.
See how all of these other
components have negative 1
as their verbosity?
Negative 1 means
inherit from parent.
You can see I have a verbosity
of 1, so all of my components
are inheriting from that.
Log levels 1 through 5 just
increase the verbosity level
to include debug messages.
The higher the number,
the more verbose
your debug messages are.
Let's just recap
that very briefly.
Negative 1 means that
the log component
inherits its verbosity
level from its parent.
By default, your
verbosity is typically 0.
That means informational
messages only.
I had set my
verbosity level to 1
so I could see more
debug messages.
A higher verbosity level means
more detailed and more frequent
debug messages.
If you're not trying to actively
identify and resolve an issue,
you can leave the verbosity at 0
for a base level of monitoring.
You'll notice that for some
of these log components
there are actually
subcomponents as well.
Remember, there were
three different components
for replication.
You had your standard
replication component,
and then you had a heartbeats
and a rollback component.
You can see all three of them
here under the replication
parent.
Each one is inheriting.
Heartbeats and
rollback both inherit
from replication,
which itself inherits
from my top-level
verbosity field.
Now, how does all this work?
There are two ways that
we can look at the logs.
The first is by using the
getLogs database command here
in the mongo shell.
The other is to use a
utility, like tail -f,
to follow the end of the log.
Let's start with
the getLogs command.
I'm using db.adminCommand
because getLog
has to be run against
the admin database.
I'm specifying global to
tell getLog to give me
all of the log activity.
This is going to return
the entire log up
to the point we
ran this command.
You can see that I have
a lot of index activity.
There are several
commands in here,
including the command I
ran when I ran db.getLog.
Looking at this, I actually
have a little bit too much index
activity.
I don't really need
this level of detail.
Let's change the log verbosity
for the index component
back down to 0.
I'm specifying the
verbosity level
that I want to change
the component to
with db.setLogLevel.
The output here is what the
log level configuration was.
I can rerun
db.getLogComponents to see
my updated value of index.
We can see here that
I've successfully
set the verbosity level of the
index logging component to 0.
Let's take another look at the
log, this time using tail -f.
I'm specifying the path to my
log file to the tail utility.
And I'm specifying the
-f flag to direct tail
to follow this log.
That means that
I will constantly
get updates as there is new
activity posted to this file.
Depending on your
operating system,
there may be different utilities
from tail available to you
that perform the
same basic function.
Let's specifically take a look
at this COMMAND logging event.
So this is the
command that I just
identified in the log file.
Let's start with the time stamp.
This lets us know when
the event occurred.
Next, I have the severity
level of the message.
Briefly, there are five
types of severity levels.
You have Fatal, Error,
Warning, Informational--
which is related to
verbosity level 0--
and Debug, which is related to
verbosity level 1 through 5.
This component has a
verbosity level of I,
which means that this is
an Informational message.
Next, we have the
actual log component
that the operation falls under.
In this case, the
operation is a command.
We can also see the connection
that the event occurred on.
Connections are
incremented and unique,
so any events initiated
by a specific connection
are likely from the same client.
We have more specific
information on the event.
We have a command
action that was
executed on the admin database.
The $cmd indicates that
this was a database command.
The full list of possible
events and descriptors
are out of scope.
But in general, you can
expect that what immediately
follows the connection
to be the operation that
triggered the event.
AppName indicates what client
initiated the operation--
in this case, the mongo shell.
Now we can dig into
the command itself.
The entire document
is the skeleton
of the command executed.
Under the hood, we have
a set parameter command
that sets the log component
verbosity of the index log
component on the admin database.
The command was
spawned by me using
the db.setLogLevel method.
Finally, we have
some metadata related
to how the operation performed.
The last data point is
of particular interest.
It's how long this
operation took to complete.
We will talk in another
lesson about slow operations
and how to identify them.
Looking back at my log, we can
see that the index events have
reduced in frequency since
we're just back to Informational
messages for that log component.
Let's see what happens
when we issue a write.
I'm going to update a document
in our products collection.
This is a simple
update command where
I'm setting the sale price
of this particular product.
Now let's take a
look at our logs.
Both of these log events are
related to the single update
command that I issued.
Now, you might be
thinking, I thought we
just updated one document.
Well, an update operation is
essentially two components.
One is the command,
and the other
is the write
operation that occurs
as a result of that command.
Let's recap.
The MongoDB review process log
supports multiple components
for controlling granularity
of events captured.
You can retrieve the
log from the mongo shell
or by using command line
utilities like tail.
Finally, you can change the
verbosity of any log component
using the mongo shell.