Now the first thing
I'm going to do
is basically connect
with an existing user
that we've previously created--
our root level user.
Once I'm connected
and authenticated,
the first thing I'm going to do
is create my security officer,
which enables user admin role.
In this case, I'm creating
it on the admin database.
Now, this is the first user
you should always create.
And why is that?
Well the main reason for this
is that this particular role
allows the user to do all
operations around user
management.
But in themself is not
able to do anything
related with data management
or data modifications.
Cannot create or write,
cannot list databases,
cannot do anything around
database administration aside
from creating and updating
or reviewing database users.
This is quite
important if you want
to ensure that there
are specific users
in your organization that are
not allowed to do anything
with data in your system--
just managing other users that
themselves can create the data.
So the command for doing that
is the create user, as always.
We'll create a user we are
calling here security officer,
passing a password, the roles
where it's going to be created.
And the command gets
successfully created.
Now next, I'm going
to create a user that
is allowed to actually
administer the database.
Yep, you got it.
It's our dbAdmin role--
a user that is created
using this role.
Now the list of privileges that
this particular role enables
is quite long.
But it can get a feeling
of what it can actually do.
All the statistical data,
kill cursors, lists indexes,
list databases and
collections, get
collect statistics
on the collections,
do collection modifications,
convert to capped.
There's a variety of
different operations
that this built in role
allows the user to operate.
But again, similar to
the user admin role,
this role does not
have the ability
to read any user data at all
or write data for that fact.
Everything that is related
with DDL, data definition
language, this user
will be able to perform.
Everything that is related
with the DML, data modification
language operations, he
will not be able to do.
This is to prevent the dba
to go in and modify data
inadvertently.
Does not stop him from
dropping collections
though because that's
a DDL operation.
But it cannot remove specific
fields from a document or even
create new documents
in a collection.
Let's go ahead and do that.
So here I have my dba user
with some password and the role
that I've given him on the
database m103 is role dbAdmin.
Now if you look closely
to this operation,
I'm doing something
quite tricky.
I'm using the database admin
to create a user on admin,
but granting a role of
dbAdmin on M103 database.
Although this might sound
a little bit strange,
this is actually a
recommended approach.
All users should be
created on the database
admin for simplicity reasons.
That means that
the database admin
will be used to authenticate
the users that we create.
That said, it might
not be needing
to access the database
admin at all for doing
what it's supposed to do.
So if he wants to be
administrator on M103,
the roles of dbAdmin should
only be granted to M103.
Roles can also vary
between databases.
I can have a given user with
different roles on a per
database basis.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Let's do that to
this database user.
Now to do that, I can just
simply use this grant roles
to user, when I select the user,
which is my dba that I recently
created.
I'm going to give it a
database playground where
this particular user
will be the dbOwner.
Once I do this, the role
dbOwner is the database owner.
And therefore, it can do
any administrative action
on the database.
That also means that
this role combines
all privileges of read write,
dbAdmin, and user admin roles.
That said, any user which is
granted dbOwner over a database
can actually do pretty
much anything he wants.
You can read write,
it can dbAdmin,
and it can even user admin
on that same database.
So you can interpret this
dbOwner role as a meta role--
one that combines several
other built in roles
that MongoDB provides.
And we can see that by
running this command--
rolesInfo where you want
to know what dbOwner
is on the db playground.
We can also say to
show the privileges
of this particular role.
Once we do that, we can have the
list of all different actions
and resources, meaning
the privileges,
of each role that this
particular role inherits
for himself.
Let's recap.
We've looked into the
structure of the roles
and how they are defined.
We've seen the list of
built in roles and how they
are logically grouped together.
And finally, we've seen how
to create and grant roles
to users using the
built in roles.