All right.
So in this lesson, we're
going to discuss the mongod.
You'll learn what the mongod
is how works at a high level
and what a daemon is, the
availability of mongod,
and the options you can
use to configure it.
Mongod is the main daemon
process for MongoDB.
It's the core unit of the
database, handling connections,
requests, and the most
important part of it,
persisting your data--
or writing your data at a disk.
So what's a daemon?
A daemon is a program a
process that's meant to be run
and not interacted with
in a direct manner.
By convention, daemons
have a d appended
to the end of their name,
hence the name mongod.
When we run. mongod, we don't
interact with it directly.
Instead, our application
utilizes a driver
to communicate with the mongod.
The user interaction is
at the application level.
And the driver handles all
the nitty gritty details
of communication
with the mongod.
MongoDB is available on
numerous 64-bit architectures,
including popular ones, such
as Ubuntu, Windows, and others.
For development
and demo purposes,
you can also install
it on a Mac OS.
All right.
So now we have an
idea of what mongod
is, let's discuss its usage.
Mongod is most easily started
by running the command mongod.
We see a bunch of output
here, but the most important
information is at the very
top and the very bottom.
All right.
Now, so we can see
here, mongod has
told us the process ID of
this mongod process, 5838,
the port that it's running
on, 27017, the dbpath.
And these are both
defaults, that's
because we didn't
specify anything else.
It also gives us the hostname
of the vagrant box, m103.
And we can see, at
the bottom here,
that it's listening for
connections on port 27017.
Notice that our terminal
is no longer interacted.
For example, if we
type, nothing happens.
The terminal just
feeds us a new line.
We have to open up a different
window and terminal in order
to connect to mongo here.
So we're just going to open up
a second terminal window here
and type the mongo command
to connect to mongo.
This will connect on the
default port, which is 27017.
And we're connected.
Now, let's run the
command show dbs
from the shell to get
a list of databases.
We see admin and local.
And there were do.
Keep in mind that if you've been
using MongoDB locally already,
you might see more
databases than this.
So looking back at the
terminal output from mongod,
we can see exactly
when we connected.
The lines with the information
"connection accepted"
can tell us exactly when
a connection happened
and where it came from.
In this case it was just us
connecting through the mongo
shell.
OK, we're done with
this mongod for now,
so we're going to
shut down the server
and exit the mongo shell.
To do so, we'll switch back
to the terminal with the mongo
shell, use the admin
database, and then run
the shutdown command.
Finally, we'll exit the mongo
shell with the exit command.
So I'm just going to use
the admin database here,
and then I'm going to run the
command db.shutdownServer.
This is going to close
the mongod process.
And if we look at
the mongod output,
we can see that it's shutdown.
To exit the mongo shell,
we simply had to type exit.
We can see the output from
mongod, that as it shut down,
it removed any socket
files, and, in general,
just cleaned up
after itself, just
to be a good process
on our computer
and not take up too much
space while it's not running.
All right.
So now let's talk about how
to configure the mongod.
The mongod takes
a myriad of flags,
and we can see all of them
by typing the command mongod
--help.
That's a lot of flex.
For right now, the ones
we're going to cover
are port, dbpath,
logpath, and fork.
--port is the argument
used to tell mongod
which port to listen on.
If this isn't specified, mongod
will listen on port 27017
by default.
The --dbpath is
where mongod creates
the files that will store
information for our databases
and collections.
--Logpath is one that we
didn't specify just now,
but it's where mongod will
log informational messages.
We saw this early
when we ran mongod.
But in that case, it printed
it right to standard out,
or to the terminal.
Instead, we could
specify a destination
with a logpath and mongod will
output the information in that
file instead.
--Fork is an argument used
to tell mongod to start
as a background process.
We can use this so
that mongod doesn't
block the current terminal
window as it just did.
All right.
So let's give some of
these options a try.
I'd like to start
MongoDB on port 30,000
with a dbpath to a local
directory called first_mongod
and forth the process so
it doesn't block my shell.
So first, in order to
specify a different db path,
we have to create the
directory beforehand.
Mongod won't do that for us.
So in this command, we're
just creating the directory
first_mongod.
So now, if we run this, it's
going to give us an error.
I forgot to mention that if
we specify the fork flag,
you must also specify a logpath.
So let's set the logpath
to a file called mongod.log
in the first mongod directory.
All right.
So now that we've specified
our logpath, this should work.
And it does.
It forked the process, it gives
us the name of the process ID--
6114, and tells
us that the child
process starts succesfully.
So because we
forked this process,
we actually have
access to the shell
even after starting mongod.
So we can connect to
mongo in the same shell.
However, this isn't
going to work,
because it's trying to
connect on port 27017,
but we've started our
process on port 30,000.
If we specify that
to the mongo command.
It should connect us
to the right port.
And it does.
We can just run a quick
show dbs to make sure
that our databases are expected.
And again, we have
the admin database
and the local database.
So now I'm going to
shut this one down
just like we did last time.
So we shut down our server
from the admin database,
and then we exit out
of the mongo shell.
All right.
So just as recap.
In this lesson we learned
that mongod is the main daemon
process for MongoDB.
We interact with mongod
through a driver, not directly.
Mongod is available on
many 64-bit systems.
And we learned about some
of the basic command-line
configuration options.