Have you ever thought about
the process required for you
to withdraw cash from an ATM?
How does the ATM
figure out who you are,
and what accounts you have
access to, and what you can do?
The ATM starts with a challenge.
Who are you?
Depending on your
response, the ATM
can validate you as who you
say you are and grant access
to the system.
This process of challenge,
response, and validation
is authentication.
Now, there is a second
step that takes place.
We know who you are, but how
do we know what you can do?
The ATM first asks a question.
What does this user
have access to?
The answer here are the
resources you have access to
and the privileges
or actions you
can execute on these resources.
The process of verifying
the privileges and resource
access of an authenticated
user is authorization.
In this case, the ATM
authorizes you to only access
your own accounts.
Now, you're logged in
and you can withdraw cash
because you authenticated,
using your debit card and pin,
and were authorized to only
access your own accounts.
MongoDB Security is built around
the process of authentication
and authorization.
When you enable authentication
on a MongoDB cluster,
every client must provide valid
credentials for authentication.
MongoDB then authorizes the
user with certain resources
and privilege access.
Let's start with authentication.
MongoDB supports four
different client authentication
mechanisms.
SCRAM is the default
and most basic form
of client authentication
MongoDB provides
when you deploy in MongoD or
MongoS with security enabled.
The SCRAM prefix stands for
Salted Challenge Response
Authentication Mechanism.
The key here is
challenge response.
Basically the MongoDB
server presents a question
or challenge to the client who
must provide a valid answer
or response for authentication.
This is basically
password security.
You don't need to know the
exact workings of the SCRAM
authentication mechanism.
Just remember that scram is
basic security for your MongoDB
cluster.
Every MongoDB cluster should
have authentication enabled
and at least SCRAM in place.
With the community
version of MongoDB,
you also have the option of
configuring X.509 security.
This form of security
uses an X.509 certificate
for authentication.
This is a more secure,
albeit more complex,
authentication mechanism that
is also available to you.
MongoDB Enterprise includes
two additional authentication
mechanisms designed for
enterprise environments.
The first is the Lightweight
Directory Access Protocol,
or LDAP for short.
If you haven't
heard of LDAP, you
might have heard of Microsoft
Active Directory, which
is built on the LDAP protocol.
MongoDB you can use an Active
Directory or other LDAP
service as the authority
on authentication
or authorization of users.
Finally, we have
Kerberos authentication.
The bright folks at the
Massachusetts Institute
of Technology designed Kerberos
as a powerful authentication
mechanism.
Since this is a basic
security course,
we're sticking to SCRAM.
Now, we're not quite done
with authentication yet.
We've only talked about
client authentication.
MongoDB also supports intra
cluster authentication,
the mechanism by which nodes
in a cluster authenticate
to each other.
Think of this like
a secret handshake.
If you don't know the handshake,
you can't join the cluster.
We'll talk more about intra
cluster auth in a later lesson.
For now, just
remember that MongoDB
provides both cluster
and client authentication
for complete security.
To recap MongoDB provides
four client authentication
mechanisms, in addition
to cluster authentication.
All editions of MongoDB
get SCRAM and X.509
for client authentication.
Enterprise editions of MongoDB
also get LDAP and Kerberos
authentication.
At the very minimum, you should
always configure your MongoDB
deployments with
SCRAM where there
is a single administrative
user protected
by a very strong password.
We'll be sticking to the
basics in this course.
Take a look at M310 or
our MongoDB documentation
for guidance on implementing
other available authentication
mechanisms.
Now, we've covered
the who are you.
What about the what
are you allowed to do?
MongoDB uses role
based access control
for authorizing an
authenticated user.
Each MongoDB user has one or
more roles associated to it.
Each role has one
or more privileges.
These privileges
represent a group
of actions and the resources
that those actions apply to.
Role based access
control allows you
to ensure a high level of
responsibility isolation
among individual users.
That means a user can be
granted the exact roles required
for that user to execute
its expected workload.
Users exist per database, so you
can isolate user privilege down
to the database or
even the collection
that the user should
have access to.
For the most basic
security possible,
create a user on
the Admin database
with one of our built in
administrative super user
roles, such as root.
We're going to cover
roles in detail later on.