All right, so in
this lesson, we're
going to take a look at the
tools you get when you download
the MongoDB package.
You should already be familiar
with a couple of them,
such as mongod, the core
database process, and Mongo,
which is the interactive
MongoDB shell
that you use to
connect to mongod.
In this lesson,
we're going to cover
some of the other
important tools
you get when you
download MongoDB.
So in order to get a full
list of the Mongo tools
that we get when we
download MongoDB,
we can use a find
command in Unix.
To the find command,
we pass a search term--
in this case, mongo*--
which just looks for anything
that begins with the word
"mongo" in this
directory-- /usr/bin/.
So this is a lot of stuff.
Specifically in
this lesson, we're
going to cover mongostat,
mongodump, mongorestore,
mongoexport, and mongoimport.
mongostat is a utility designed
to give quick statistics
on a running mongod
or mongos process.
All right, so I'm just going to
launch an example mongod, here,
on port 30000, and I'm going to
fork the process so I can still
use this terminal window.
In order to connect
to this mongod
and get Mongo stats
from it, I have
to specify the port
in the mongostat call.
And here I've specified my port.
And if I enter
this command, it's
going to return Mongo
stats to me every second--
indefinitely, because
I haven't specified
when I want it to stop
or how often to report.
So I'm just going
to cancel this so we
can take a look at the output.
These first six fields
represent the number
of specific operations
per second--
such as inserts, deletes,
and just overall commands.
The next seven fields represent
lower-level memory statistics,
such as dirty, which is the
percentage of dirty bytes
in the cache, used,
which is the percentage
of currently-used
bytes in the cache,
vsize, which is the total
amount of virtual memory used
by the process,
and res, which is
the total amount of resonant
memory used by the process.
Net_in and net_out are used to
measure the amount of network
traffic that's being
received and sent out
by the mongod or mongos process.
All right, so we're going to
discuss the next four Mongo
server tools and pairs.
The first pair is
mongorestore and mongodump,
which are used to import and
export dump files from MongoDB
collections.
These dump files are in
BSON, or Binary JSON format.
These tools are very quick,
because the data in MongoDB
is already in BSON format,
and mongodump simply
needs to make a copy to export.
So we can see the full options
that we can pass to Mongo, now,
by passing the help flag here.
The only one we're going
to use right now is port.
All right, so in
order to use mongodump
with access control enabled,
you must authenticate
through the mongodump command.
So in addition to
specifying a port here,
we also specify a username,
password, and authentication
database-- in this case, admin.
All right, so
running this command
without specifying a directory
creates a folder called dump.
We take a look inside
dump and then take
a look inside the database
that we dump from,
we can see two files.
One of them is a BSON file.
This file is the actual
data from the collection,
but it's not very readable,
because it's a BSON.
The JSON file here is metadata
about the collection that
was dumped, and we can
take a look at it with cat
and see it's very short.
It has a list of the indexes,
which right now is just the one
on _id that comes by default,
and then the namespace
of the collection that we
dumped-- exampleDB.students.
So this is a
mongorestore command,
which is the inverse of
the mongodump command.
It takes a BSON dump file and
creates a MongoDB collection
from it.
This drop flag will drop
the current collection--
exampleDB.students--
and then replace it with
what's in the dump file.
And now we're done.
All we needed to pass
was the dump directory,
because that had the metadata
in JSON format, which
told it about any indexes--
in this case, there
were no indexes--
and the namespace--
exampleDB.students.
So mongodump and
mongorestore output and input
BSON, which are binary files.
The next couple commands
we're going to go over--
mongoexport and mongoimport--
deal with JSON instead.
We can see the full list
of options for mongoexport
by passing the help flag, here.
And we see there
are a lot of them.
The ones we're going to use are
the authentication options--
username, password, and
authenticationDatabase--
and port.
All right, so now we get to
see mongoexport in action.
We still have to authenticate
and specify a port,
but notice that this time,
we didn't specify a file name
for our output.
And unlike mongodump,
mongoexport
will not create a
directory for us.
Instead, it'll send the
output to standard out.
This is a lot of information,
and it's not so useful
when it's just printed
in the terminal.
So this is the same
exact command as before,
except this time
we've passed this -o
flag, which is for the output.
We specified a new file
called students.json
to store all that output that
was printed at the terminal
before.
All right, so now we have a
new file called students.json,
and I'm just going to
tail the file so we can
take a look at what's in it.
So as we can see, this
is a JSON representation
of the MongoDB collection.
These are just
documents and arrays.
All right, so this is a
mongoimport statement,
which is the inverse
operation of mongoexport.
This is pretty similar to its
BSON counterpart, mongorestore.
In this command,
I'm going to use
mongoimport to import the data
set that we just exported.
So as we can see here,
we didn't specify
a database or a collection for
this mongoimport statement.
Because there's no metadata
in the JSON export,
mongoimport has to figure out
a place to put all this data.
It defaults to use
test as the database,
and the name of the
JSON files-- students--
as the name of the collection.
So just to recap,
in this lesson we
covered mongostat, which
gives quick statistics
on a running mongod
or mongos process.
We covered mongodump, which
outputs BSON representations
of MongoDB, and
mongorestore, which
restores BSON
representation in MongoDB
into MongoDB collections.
We covered mongoexport,
which outputs JSON or CSV
representations of
MongoDB collections,
and mongoimport, which takes the
JSON or the CSV representations
and creates a MongoDB
collection from it.