Time for us to talk a
little bit about roles,
in particular, about
built-in roles in MongoDB,
and how the role-based
access control system works.
Now, there is a fair
amount to say about roles.
But by now, you should be aware
that MongoDB role-based access
control system is in place,
and that database users will
be granted roles to perform
operations of MongoDB.
So we're not going to
cover that in this lesson.
Roles can be of two types.
It can be either custom roles,
which are tailored roles
to attend specific needs of
specific users, which we are
also not going to
cover in this lecture,
and built-in roles, which are
prepackaged MongoDB roles.
Now, saying that we are not
going to cover custom roles,
doesn't mean you cannot
learn about them.
And we have a specific
course, MongoDB Security,
for you to learn everything
related with security,
including the custom roles.
So I do recommend
you to take that,
if you want to learn a
lot more about custom
roles in other security
aspects of MongoDB.
But before we go into the
list of built-in roles,
the MongoDB packages, let's
talk about the role structure,
how can we define roles, or how
roles are defined internally.
A role is composed
by the following.
There is a set of privileges
that the role enables.
If a new user is
granted a given role,
all privileges that
that role defines
will be made
available to the user.
And a privilege defines
the action, or actions,
that can be performed
over a resource.
A resource on its
own can be defined
by either being a set
of specific database
and specific collection, any
database in any collection,
any database in a
set of collections,
or a specific database
in all collections
within that database.
And finally, we also have
the cluster level resource
that applies to operations
regarding the replica
sets or shard clusters.
A privilege is
defined by a resource
and the actions allowed
over that same resource.
So for example,
here, we would have
the system allowing the
shut down of a full cluster.
By that, we define the
resource cluster equals true,
and the action to be shutdown.
A role with such
a privilege will
be allowed to shut down
any member of the cluster.
But apart of having
a list of privileges,
a role can also inherit
from other roles, either one
or several of them, making
this a potentially quite
elaborate architecture
of permission
and privileges across
several different roles.
And finally, we can also
define network authentication
restrictions at the role level.
This basically allows us to
define that a given role is
allowed to connect
from a clientSource,
or to a serverAddress, by
specifying the set of list
of clientSource
and serverAddress
in the network restrictions.
OK.
So now that we've seen how
the roles are organized,
or defined, let's look into this
set of different built-in roles
that MongoDB provides.
So the built-in
roles are organized
by four different sets of
groups, plus this super user
role type.
We have database
level users, which can
either be read and readWrite.
These are the
application users that
should be allowed to
read or read and write.
We have database administration
roles, like userAdmin, dbAdmin,
and dbOwner.
We have cluster level
administration roles,
which are clusterAdmin,
clusterManager, clusterMonitor,
and hostManager.
We have specific roles
for backup and restore.
And obviously, we also
have our super user root
role that should be granted
only in specific situations.
All the roles defined here
are purely database level
for each user.
That means that I can
grant different roles,
to different users, on
different databases.
But there are also
built-in roles
that are all database level.
That means they apply to
any database in the system.
For the database users, we
have readAnyDatabase or read
and write any database.
For database administration,
we have dbAdminAnyDatabase,
or userAdminAnyDatabase.
And obviously, this
super user nature of root
is, in fact, a whole
database level role, as well.
But these are a lot of them.
So I want to focus your
attention on the ones
that we're going to need
throughout this course--
userAdmin, dbOwner, and dbAdmin.