Right now, we're actually going
to create our first MongoDB
superuser.
First, let's take a look
at our MongoDB server.
Let's look at the configuration
file for my MongoD.
Notice this line here?
This configuration file
option does two things.
First, it enables role-based
access control or authorization
on my cluster.
Second, it implicitly enables
authentication as well.
You cannot have one
without the other.
Now I need to connect
to my cluster,
but this cluster has no
existing users configured,
even though auth is enabled.
Since by default MongoDB
doesn't give you any users,
you have to create
them yourself.
Since my server does not yet
have any configured users,
there is no way for me
to authenticate myself
to the server, nor can I be
authorized to do any work.
Instead, I must use
the localhost exception
to connect to the
server, meaning
I must connect to
the Mongo shell
from the same host that is
running the MongoDB server
process.
Remember, once you have
created your first user,
the localhost exception closes.
So always create a user
with the administrative role
first so you can create other
users after the localhost
exception has closed.
So here I am running
my Mongo shell,
and I'm going to connect to
the server from the same host.
In this case, the Vagrant
box for this course.
Notice here that I'm using
the localhost address.
This is also a way for
you to just double check
that you are
specifically connecting
over the localhost interface.
Now I'm connected.
Let me try to run a
few commands here.
Well, I am connected,
but I'm not authenticated
nor authorized to do anything
on the MongoDB server.
When using the
localhost exceptions,
your privileges on the
system are very restricted.
Now I do have access, so I
can create my first user.
I'm going to create this
user on the admin database,
because this is going to be
an administrative superuser,
and I'm going to use
the root built-in role.
I'm using the
DB.create user method
to create a user on
the admin database.
I've specified the
username and the password,
as well as the role I want to
be associated to this user.
The username and password are
used for the authentication
steps.
And this array of roles
is used for authorization.
I've specified the
built-in role, root,
which provides the highest
level of privileged action
across all database resources.
I do want to note MongoDB
3.6 adds some additional user
authentication restrictions in
the form of an IP whitelist,
meaning that the roles
granted to a user
depend on what IP
they connect from.
It's a little advanced
for this course.
But if you want to
learn more, make
sure to check our
documentation on db.createuser
or the Create User command.
We can see here that I've
successfully added my new user.
Now I have to authenticate
as my root user to continue.
The localhost exception at this
point in time is exhausted,
and I cannot create any
additional users without
authenticating first.
Remember, I'm currently using
an unauthenticated session
that I was only
able to open because
of the localhost exception.
Now there is a shell
command db.auth
that lets me authenticate
from this particular session.
But let's do this
via the Mongo shell
to simulate how a client
would normally connect.
I've specified my username,
root, and password, root.
Remember, using
scram so there is
a challenge-response
mechanism here.
The authentication
database parameter
tells the MongoDB server which
database contains my user
credentials.
Remember, users
are per database.
That means if I have two
users, Bob at inventory
and Bob at sales, those
are two different users.
The authentication
database dictates
which user I authenticate as
and what privileges I get.
I created this user
on the admin database,
so that's where I'm connecting.
So now I'm connected,
and I have the privileges
associated with root.
Remember, earlier, I could
not run this command.
Now I am authenticated
and authorized
as a user who has
access to this.
So now I'm connected,
and I have the privileges
associated with root.
Again, this is the most basic
implementation of security.
You will have to create
additional users as necessary
to fulfill specific
operational tasks.
You don't want everyone
using this system
to have root access.
This is a lot of information
so read through carefully.
Let's recap.
MongoDB user security
is an authentication
and authorization
model, so users
must provide who they
are to the server, which
decides what they can do based
on the user they authenticated
as.
MongoDB supports multiple
authentication mechanisms,
SCRAM and X.509 are the
community authentication
mechanisms.
These are also available on the
enterprise versions of MongoDB.
LDAP and KERBEROS our enterprise
only authentication mechanisms.
Each user that you create
has one or more roles that
define their authorized access.
And at the very minimum,
you should always
configure SCRAM-SHA-1 with
a single administrative user
protected by a strong password.