Welcome to the
chapter on indexes.
In this chapter,
we're going to cover
some of the different
indexes supported by MongoDB
and we'll also discuss
the different properties
that those indexes have.
In this first video, we're going
to examine what indexes are,
and how they work.
And to answer this
first question,
I think it's helpful
to ask the question.
What problem do
indexes try to solve?
And that is, slow queries.
Let's use a quick
analogy to illustrate
what I'm talking about.
Let's say we're looking for
some content on bedspreads
in a book about interior design.
One way that I can
find this information
is if I went through
the book page
by page looking for
information on bedspreads.
But this would not be very fast.
I could find this
information much more quickly
if I went to the back of
the book to the index,
where I can quickly search
for the word bedspread
because the index is
ordered alphabetically.
I'll then find what page
talks about bedspreads,
and I can go directly
to that page.
And this is essentially
how database indexes work.
Working off the book analogy,
a book, in the context MongoDB,
would be a collection.
If you don't use an index
when we query our collection,
then the database will have to
look at every single document.
Creatively we call
this a collection scan,
which means that as our
collection grows in size,
we will have to search through
more and more documents
to satisfy our query.
In computer science we call
this an order of N operation,
commonly referred
to as big O of N,
or having a linear running time.
And that's because the
running time of our query
is linearly proportional to
the number of documents--
N-- that we have
in our collection.
But we can do much better
if we have an index.
Like in the book analogy,
we can use an index
to limit our search space.
Rather than searching
through every document,
we can search through
the ordered index first.
The MongoDB index
keeps a reference
to every document
in our collection.
Think of this index as a
list of key value pairs,
where the key is the
value of the field
that we've indexed on,
and the value of the key
is the actual document itself.
I like to point out that this
means an index is associated
with one or more fields.
This means when we
create our index,
we have to specify which
fields on the documents
in our collection
we want to index on.
For example, _id field is
automatically indexed for us.
But if I were to write a query
that didn't use the _id field,
I wouldn't be able search
the _id index and find
the reference to my documents.
And it is possible to have many
indexes on the same collection.
I might create multiple
indexes on different fields
if I find that I have different
queries for different fields.
Like the index at
the back of a book,
the index keys are
stored in an order.
Because of this, we don't have
to look at every single index
entry in or to find it.
MongoDB uses a data
structure called a b-tree
to store its indexes.
B-trees can be used
to find target values
with very few comparisons.
With a collection scan,
each new insertion
creates an extra comparison.
But with a b-tree,
each new insertion
doesn't necessarily mean
an extra comparison.
For example, if I was
searching for the value of 15,
my search wouldn't change if
I inserted the value of 5.
We can plot a chart
to get an idea
of how many fewer
documents we need
to examine when using an index.
You can see that when
we don't have an index,
we have a very linear function
of number of comparisons.
But when we do have
an index, we need
to examine far fewer documents.
Before I finish
this video, I would
to discuss one last topic,
which is index overhead.
The awesome query performance
gain that we get with indexes
doesn't come for free.
With each additional index,
we decrease our write speed
for a collection.
Every time there's a
new document inserted
into collection, a
collections indexes
might need to be updated.
Similarly, if a
document were to change,
or if it was completely removed,
one or more of our b-trees
might need to be balanced.
This means that we need to be
careful when creating indexes.
We don't want to have too
many unnecessary indexes
in a collection because
there would then
be an unnecessary loss in
insert, update, and delete
performance.
You should have a good
idea of what indexes are,
their pros and cons,
and how they work.