In this lesson, we're going
to talk about text indexes.
And specifically,
we're to discuss
how we can create inquiry
with text indexes.
What kind of implications text
indexes have on the number
index keys that are generated.
And finally, we're
going to discuss
some of the costs that are
associated with text searches
and text indexes.
Oftentimes, we store
text in our documents.
And for certain
use cases, it can
be useful to search
for documents
based on the words that are
a part of those text fields.
For example, here
I have a document
with English words
describing this product
as a long sleeved t-shirt.
Now using MongoDB's
default query engine,
I can specify a string
that exactly matches
the string specified
in this document
if I wanted to
find this document.
Now there are
obvious limitations
to querying in this way.
Users of our application
are unlikely to know
the exact string to input
to return this document.
One possible solution
to this problem
would be to take
advantage of MongoDB's
built-in regular
expression support.
While this would work, there
are performance disadvantages.
As you'll learn
in another lesson,
regular expressions don't
have the best performance.
And this is even true
when they use indexes.
And this is where text
indexes come into play.
Rather than specifying
that we want our indexes
to be ascending or
descending, rather, we
pass a special text
keyword to createIndex.
This allows us to create
a special text index.
By doing this, were able to
leverage MongoDB's full text
search capabilities, while
avoiding collection scans.
Under the hood, this works very
similarly to multi-key indexes.
The server is going to
process this text field
and create an index key
for every unique word
in the string.
So in this case, MongoDB
would create five index keys
for this document.
This is because Unicode
considers both spaces
and hyphens as text delimiters.
The five index keys would
be mongodb, long, sleeve, t,
and shirt.
You'll notice that each of
these tokens are also lowercase.
That's because, by default, text
indexes are case insensitive.
With regards to performance,
like multi-key indexes,
we want to be aware that the
bigger our text fields are,
the more index keys per
document we'll be producing.
This will affect the
number of index keys
that the query engine
needs to examine
as well as the overall
size of our index.
You'll want to watch very
closely how big our index is
getting to make sure that
it fits entirely in RAM.
You'll also want to
be aware that this
means that it's going to take
longer than normal to build
this kind of index, than
a traditional index.
And of course, since we're
generating more index keys,
we'll also see a more
significant decrease
in write performance,
than with a typical index.
One strategy for reducing
the number of index keys
that need to be examined, would
be to create a compound text
index.
Here I'm creating
a compound index
on category and product name.
And this allows us to limit
the number of text keys
that need to be inspected
by limiting on the clothing
category.
We'll only need to
examine index keys that
fit the clothing
category, rather
than looking at all index keys.
Let's go ahead and try out
some of the other features
of text indexes from the shell.
First, let's connect
to the m201 database.
From here, we can go ahead and
insert some example documents.
Here, I have inserted
two documents.
One that says that "MongoDB is
the best," another that says
that "MongoDB is the worst."
More on this in a second.
And of course, I can go ahead
and now create a text index
on the statement field.
And now when I search for
the special $text and $search
operators for the
phrase "MongoDB best,"
you'll see that the first
document returned says,
"MongoDB is the worst."
And the second
document it returns
says, "MongoDB is the best."
So what exactly happened here?
Why was worst before best.
And why did worst
even appear at all?
Well, first of all, it's
important to understand
that text queries logically
"or" each delimited word.
So in this case, when
we say that we're
searching for
"MongoDB best," we're
searching for any
documents that include
MongoDB or any documents
that include the word best.
To address this issue, we can
project the special textScore
value to our returned results.
The $text operator assigns
a score to each document,
based on the relevance of that
document for a given search
query.
And now that we've
projected this field,
we can go ahead and sort by
the same projected field.
Now the documents that
best match our search
query are at the
top of our results.
Let's go ahead and recap
what we've learned.
We discussed how to create
inquiry with text indexes.
We also discussed some
of the implications
of having so many
text keys being
generated by text indexes.
And finally, we talked about
some of the associated costs
with tech searches in general.