In this video, I'd
like to discuss
how we can utilize
indexes to sort
the documents in our queries.
We already know that any
query can also be sorted.
Now there are two ways that
these documents can be sorted.
They can be sorted in
memory or by using an index.
Let's talk about the first case,
when sorting happens in memory.
The documents in
our collections are
stored on disk in
an unknown order,
therefore, when we query
the server our documents are
going to be returned
in the same order
that the server finds them.
If we happen to want
them in the same order
that the server finds
them, great, but that's
not very likely to happen.
This means that
when we add a sort,
the server is going have to
read the documents from disk
into RAM.
And then in RAM, it
will perform some kind
of sorting algorithm on them.
Depending on how many
documents you have,
this might take a long time.
Moreover, because sorting
a large amount of documents
in memory might be an
expensive operation,
the server is going to
abort sorting in memory
when 32 megabytes of
memory is being used.
This leads nicely in how
we can sort with indexes.
In an index, the
keys are ordered
according to the field
specified during index creation.
The server can take
advantage of this via sort.
If a query is using
an index scan,
the order of the
documents returned
is guaranteed to be
sorted by the index keys.
This means that there is no
need to reform an explicit sort,
as the documents will be
fetched from the server
in the sorted order.
Now it's important to point out
that these documents are only
going to be ordered according
to the fields that make up
the index.
If we have an ascending
index on last name,
then the documents will be
ordered according to last name.
If there's an index
on first name,
then the documents
will be ordered
according to first name.
It's important to note that the
query planner considers indexes
that can be helpful to
either the query predicate
or to the requested sort.
Let's dig a little bit deeper
into sorting functionality
with single field indexes
by looking at the shell.
For this lesson, we're
going to continue
using the people.json
data set that we have been
using in the previous lessons.
If you haven't got it, you
can go ahead and import it
with Mongo import.
If you can, go ahead
and skip this step.
Let's go ahead and
find all the documents
in our collection sorted
by social security number.
Here are the first 20 documents.
You can see that we're
finding everyone,
and we're sorting by the
social security number.
Let's go ahead and create
our explainable object
and use it to explain our query.
If we go to
executionStats, you can
see that we had to look
at 50,000 documents
to return our 50,000
documents, which makes sense.
But you also notice that
we used 50,000 index keys
and that's because we
still did an index scan.
Well, why did we do an
index scan if we needed
to return all the documents?
Well that's because
the index wasn't
used for filtering
documents, but was rather
used for sorting.
If I instead sort on first name,
which we don't have an index
for.
If we scroll up
to executionStats,
you'll see that we still
examined 50,000 documents
because we returned
50,000 documents.
But this time we looked
at no index keys,
and that's because we
did in memory SORT.
So we effectively did
a collection scan, read
all the documents
into memory, and then
once they are in memory, we
were able to do an in memory
SORT on the unsorted documents
for the first name field.
In our previous
index sorted example,
we sorted by security
number ascending.
This time let's sort
by it descending.
And then we look at
our output, you'll
see that we're still
doing an index scan.
This is because this
time we're able to walk
our index backwards instead
of walking it forwards.
When we're sorting with
a single field index,
we can always do that.
I can sort my documents either
ascending or descending,
regardless of the physical
ordering of the index keys.
I can both filter and
sort in the same query.
Here I'm finding everyone whose
social security number starts
with 555.
And then we look at
the explain output,
you can see that we
did an index scan.
And this index scan was used
both for filtering and sorting
the documents because
we can see that we only
had to look at 49 documents,
which were the same 49 that we
were returned.
Just to verify
things, let's see what
would happen if we built
descending index keys.
We'll first drop
our old indexes.
And now we'll
create another index
on social security number, but
this time descending instead of
ascending.
And so now, when I search
for social security numbers
beginning with 555, and I
sort them the descending,
we're now walking
the index forward
because it is a
descending index.
Whereas before, we were
walking it backwards
because it was an
ascending index.
This may seem
unimportant, but it
will become more
important later when
we discuss compound indexes.
Let's recap what we've learned.
In this lesson you learned
how to use indexes to sort.
And how to create
indexes that both match
and sort on a single query.
And you also learned
how to create
indexes that can be used
for ascending and descending
sort orders.