In this video, I want to take
her understanding of sorting
with indexes to the next level.
In our first lesson we discuss
how we can use single field
indexes to sort on queries.
Since then we've learned
about compound indexes.
In this video we'll discuss
how we can use compound indexes
to sort our queries.
Let's continue using
the people data set
and we'll continue using the
index from our compound index
lesson.
The most simple way we can use
compound indexes for sorting
is to use the index key
pattern as our sort predicate.
When we run this query and
look at the explain output,
we can see that we're
doing an index scan.
Which shouldn't be
surprising since we're
matching the same
index keys in the order
they were specified
during index creation.
This is very similar to how we
work with single key indexes.
We don't have to use
all of our index keys
in our sort predicate
to prevent and in-memory
sort by doing an index scan.
Here's another query.
This time I'm only using the
first two fields of our index.
But when I run it you'll
notice that I'm still
doing an index scan.
And this is because I'm using
an index prefix for our index.
If you look at our query
we did job: 1, employer: 1,
which is a prefix for
our keyPattern "job" : 1,
"employer" : 1.
Let's try another query
and see if we're still
able to use the
index for sorting.
Instead of sorting by job
and then employer, this time
we're going to sort by
employer and then by job.
And if we look at
our winning plan,
you'll see that we
did a collection scan
followed by an in-memory sort.
And unsurprisingly,
this is because we
did it using index prefix.
Last time we the job
comma employer, this time
we did employer comma job.
This means that all of
these following sort queries
would use an index instead
of an in-memory sort
because all of their sort
predicates are index prefixes.
And it doesn't matter what
the query predicates are.
The server really doesn't
like doing in-memory sorts.
So in the following
example it's still
going to use an index to
fetch the documents because we
have an index prefix
in our sort predicate.
So even though we're only
returning one document,
we still have to look
at all 50,000 documents.
Because the index scan was used
for sorting not for filtering.
The server was going to
have to look at those 50,000
documents either way.
It didn't know that
there was only going
to be one document returned.
But an index can be used to
both filter and sort documents
if the query includes
equality conditions
on all of the prefix keys
that precede the sort keys.
Let's look at this example.
This was a very fast
query because we
were able to use indexes for
both filtering and for sorting.
And this is because these
keys are an index prefix.
The first keys, "job,
employer" are an index prefix.
But continuing onward,
last_name would
complete another index prefix.
I've modified this
query slightly
so I can no longer be able
to use the index for sorting.
Job is still an index
prefix, so we'll still
be able to filter
documents using the index.
But since job comma last_name
is not an index prefix,
we'll no longer be able to use
the index for both filtering
and sorting, as we'll see now.
So we were able to use
the index for filtering
we only had to examine 99
documents for the 99 returned,
but we still had to
do an in-memory sort.
The next was first
useful filtering
and then those
filtered documents
were then sorted in-memory.
The last topic I want to
talk about in this video
is about sort direction when
sorting on multiple fields.
In the single key
index sorting lesson,
we saw that we were able
to walk our index backwards
by inverting the key
in our sort predicate.
You might be wondering
how is this going
to work with compound indexes.
Well, it's actually
surprisingly simple
to determine if your
sort key pattern will
be able to walk the
index backwards.
If I was to create
the following index,
we know that the
following sort predicate
would walk the index forward.
In order to walk the index
backwards all we need to do
is invert each key.
All of the following
sort queries
would use the index for sorting.
The first two would
walk the index forward
because they're index prefixes.
The last two would walk
the index backwards
because they're the
inverse of these prefixes.
We can look at an example
with our people collection.
Here I'm sorting on job
descending, employer
descending, which job
ascending, employer ascending
would be an index prefix.
So here I'm just inverting
the ascending version.
And when we look at
the explain output
you can see that
I use the index,
and rather than walking
the index forward,
we're walking it backwards.
But if I were to change
one of these keys
we would then have to do a
collection scan, followed
by an in-memory sort.
Let's recap what we've learned.
We learned how to sort our
queries by using index prefixes
in our sort predicates.
We also learned how to both
filter and sort our queries
by splitting up our index prefix
between our query and sort
predicates.
Important to remember
that our query part has
to precede the sort part and
that these have to be equality
matches.
And finally we learned
how to sort our documents
with an index if our sort
predicate inverts our index
keys or their prefixes.