Collations allow users to
specify language specific rules
for string comparison, such
as rules for letter, case,
and accent marks.
A collation is
defined in MongoDB
by the following options.
Locale determines the
ICU supported locale
for such a collation.
And then we have caseLevel,
caseFirst, strength,
numericOrdering, alternate,
maxVariable, and backwards.
These specific options
and what they represent
are out of scope.
However, you should
be aware that there
are multiple different
settings that collations allow.
Now, collations can be defined
at several different levels.
We can define a collation
for a collection, which
means that all queries
and indexes created
in such collection will be
using that particular collation.
In this case, we
have a collation
for the Portuguese language
on foreign_text collection.
I'm going to insert
this documents
on my recently created
collection using the Portuguese
collation for that effect.
Once I insert the
document, I can [INAUDIBLE]
find on that
particular collection.
After it executes the
explain plan on this query,
I can see that the collation
used for this particular query
will be the
Portuguese collation.
We'll have a
winningPlan, where we
will use a indexed query using
that collation for the results.
We can use collations
for specific requests,
like queries and
aggregations, for example,
where we're defining a different
collation than the one used
and defined for the particular
collection that supports those
find requests or aggregates.
That is totally
possible, and we can even
specify different
collations for our indexes.
This way, we can
create an index or name
that overrides the default
collation or any collection
level defined collations.
So in this case, we
have foreign_text
being defined as the
collation of Portuguese,
but we are creating the
index using a collation
using the Italian language.
If we execute a query using
that particular field,
you might expect that we'll
be using this particular index
here.
Now, there's a small caveat.
First, we enable the use of this
index on this particular query.
So we have an index
on name, and we are
querying on that same field.
First, to use that
index, the query
must match the collation of
the index, which in this case
is Italian.
That means that if we run
this query without specifying
or overriding the underlying
defined collection collation,
we will not be using this
index, because it will not
match the required collation.
If you run this query, we
will see that, first of all,
we are using a
collection scan, meaning
that we are not using the
index that we recently created.
And the collation used
to satisfy this query
is the underlying collation
of our collection.
First, to use that
index, our query
should specify the matching
collation for that index.
If we do so, once
we run the query,
we can see that we are, in
fact, having an index scan
that matches the index pattern
that we want using the index
that we specified, since the
collation matches the index
collation.
Being able to correctly
match and sort
text space on a given locale is
mandatory for many use cases.
So collations allow
that correctness
in terms of sorting and
matching on different locales.
Now, we're testing collations
offer a marginal performance
impact and should
most definitely be
used for correctness.
Another benefit of
introducing collations
is the ability to support
case insensitive indexes.
To enable these, we can
simply define a collection
with a given locale
on our collation
and setting the strength
of that collation
to 1, which offers primary
level of comparison,
ignoring case and diacritics.
If we do so, and if we insert
a few documents that only vary
on the case, for example,
if we express a sort query,
ascending on name,
we will see that we
have a particular ordering.
If we execute the same
query but by changing
the order of our
sort, now descending,
we will get the exact
same set of results.
This means that regardless
of the accent, case,
or even diacritics, this
particular collation defined
for this collection
will allow us
to have case insensitive
queries, and therefore,
indexes as well.
And that's how collations
work in MongoDB.