Databases tend to have
this nice feature that
allows data to be persisted
using the server's file system.
But how do they do it?
Which files do they
write information to?
How these files are organized?
How do databases
collections, indexes, get
to get organized within the data
structures and storage engines
that support the persistency
layer of your database?
These are the topics we're
going to discuss in this lesson.
The way that MongoDB
stores data will
differ between the
different storage engines
that MongoDB supports.
The particular details of how
each storage engine organize
data in detail are out of
scope, but let's review
at a high level how
the different storage
engines organize data.
Now, MongoDB allows us to create
a few data management objects.
We have databases, which are
logical groups of collections,
collections, which
are operational units
that group documents together.
We're going to have
indexes on collections
over [INAUDIBLE]
presence on documents.
And obviously,
we're going to have
documents, atomic
units of information
used by applications.
But before we jump into
the overview of the data
structures, let's have a
peek into the dbpath content
of our MongoDB directory.
Here, I'm going to
start my mongod,
pointing my dbpath to data/db.
Now, this is the default
MongoDB data path.
But I just want to
reinforce the fact
that you can change it to
another alternative dbpath
if you wish to do so.
All right.
I started the process.
And this is going to be a
very short lived instruction,
because I'm going to shut
down the server again.
If we ls that data/db
folder, we can
see that immediately
MongoDB stores and starts
writing a bunch of different
documents in some directories.
For each collection, or index,
the WiredTiger storage engine
will write an individual file.
We start with a MDB
catalog file that
contains the catalog of
all different collections
and indexes that this
particular mongod contains.
But we can have a little
bit more elaborate file
system in data structures than
this plain flat organization.
Let's go ahead and remove
that data/db folder,
remove all its content.
Let's recreate the folder again.
And now let's launch the mongod
with a little with more flavor.
I'm going to use the same
dbpath, the same logpath as
well, the same file for logging.
I'm also going to
fork the process.
And I'm going to add this
directoryperdb instruction.
Once I do that, I'm also going
to write a single document
on a particular
new collection that
doesn't exist at
the moment, hello,
and inserting it
on collection a.
And then, I'm just going to go
ahead and shut down the server.
If I look into the
folder, my dbpath again,
I can see that now I have a
slightly different organization
of data.
I'm going to have these three
new folders, admin, local,
and hello.
Admin and local are default
databases that MongoDB creates.
Hello is the newly
created database
that we've created on
the previous instruction.
By specifying dash
dash directoryperdb,
we'll get slightly different
organization in the way
that we are going to have a
folder for each single database
that this mongod raised.
If we look into the
subfolder inside
of our dbpath for our
newly created database,
we will see that we are going
to have one collection and one
index file.
Collection for our a database
collection, and obviously you
will always have an
underscore there's ID index.
So this is the file
that we have created.
But we can go a little
bit step forward
in terms of organization of our
data, especially on WiredTiger.
I repeated exactly
the same process.
I created, again,
our hello database.
And here, I've shut
down our mongod again.
If we look into our
database folder, our dbpath,
we can see that
we're still creating
one single folder for each
database that our mongod holds.
But if we're looking at
the hello database now,
we're going to have a
different organization.
We're going to have a single
directory for collections
and one for all index files.
So that sounds cool
and all, but what
does this have to do
with performance anyway?
Well, if you have several
disks in your server,
this will enable a great
deal of I/O paralyzation.
To do this, we create
symbolic links to mount points
on different physical drives.
Every time you write or
read from our database,
we will most likely
be using the two data
structures, the collections
and the indexes that
support our queries, or
when we need to be updated,
we will write the
data to the collection
and to the indexes too.
Paralyzation of I/O can
improve the overall throughput
of our persistency layer, and
therefore, positively impacting
the performance of operations.
Mongod also offers compression
while storing information
on disc.
We instruct our storage
engine to store data
on disk using a
compression algorithm.
This has a direct
impact on performance
by performing smaller
I/O operations, which
means that smaller
data is faster
I/O, at the cost of CPU cycles.
Before writing
data to disk, data
will be allocated in memory.
Without getting ourselves
too overwhelmed in details
of memory allocation, all data
is eventually written to this,
for persistency reasons.
This process will be triggered
by two main ways, user side,
by specifying a
particular writeConcorn,
or forcing an [INAUDIBLE] sync
operation within administration
command, or by the periodical
internal process that
regulates how data needs
to be flushed and synced
into the data file.
This is defined by sync periods.
Journaling is as well
an essential component
of our persistency mechanism.
The journal file
acts as a safeguard
against data corruption caused
by incomplete data file writes.
The system suffers a shut
down and expected data stored
in the journal will
be used to recover
into a consistent correct state.
Now, journal has its
own file structure
that include individual
write operations.
To minimize the performance
impact of journal,
the journal flushes our
performed using group commits
in a compressed format.
All writes to the
journal file are atomic,
ensuring consistency of
on this journal files.
From the application
perspective,
and taking performance
of operations in mind,
we can also force data
to be synced to journal
before acknowledging a write.
This is using j equals
true in our writeConcern.
That said, keep
in mind that these
will have some impact
in the performance
of your application.
We will wait till the
sync is done to disk,
and then confirm back that the
write has been acknowledged.
And this is how data
is stored on disk.