In this lesson, we're going
to talk about partial indexes.
Sometimes, it makes sense
for us to only index
a portion of the
documents in a collection.
When we index on a
subset of our documents,
we can have lower
storage requirements
and reduce the performance cost
of creating and maintaining
indexes.
To achieve this, MongoDB
supports the creation
of partial indexes.
Let's look at an example.
Take, for instance, a collection
of restaurant information.
Maybe there are lots
of queries for finding
a particular cuisine
in a particular city,
but of all these queries
that the server receives,
90% of them are for restaurants
with 3.5 and above stars.
So instead of creating
a compound index on city
and cuisine, or city
cuisine and stars,
instead we can create
a partial index
where we index on
city and cuisine
only if the restaurant
has 3.5 or more stars.
We're effectively reducing
the number of index keys
that we need to store, and
therefore reducing our space
requirements for our index.
This can be useful if
our index has grown
too large to fit into memory.
Partial indexes can also be
useful with multi key indexes.
As we know, with
multi key indexes,
keys are created for
each array entry.
If our documents have
particularly large arrays,
then the server will be
creating lots of index keys.
This could cause issues with
fitting the index into memory.
We can mitigate
these kinds of issues
by creating a partial index.
I'd also like to point out
that sparse indexes are
a special case of
partial indexes.
With a sparse
index, we only index
documents where the
field exists that we're
indexing on, rather
than creating an index
key with a null value.
We can achieve the same effect
by creating a partial index
where the filter expression
checks for the existence
of the field were indexing on.
It might be somewhat
obvious, but I'd
like to point out that
partial indexes are much more
expressive than sparse indexes.
With partial indexes we can
define a filter expression
that checks for the existence
of fields other than the ones
we're indexing on.
Therefore, we suggest that
you use partial indexes
over sparse indexes.
Let's head over to the shell so
that we can see partial indexes
in practice.
We can go ahead and switch
over to the M201 database
that we've been using.
And from here, we can go
ahead and insert a document
similar to our example.
And let's go ahead and run a
find query on our document,
matching on city and cuisine.
And of course, we find the
document we just inserted.
And now we can go ahead and
create our explainable objects
and rerun our query.
Now, I would expect
this to be a collection
scan because we have not
created any indexes yet.
And indeed, the winning plan
was to do a collection scan.
Let's go ahead and create the
partial index from our example.
Now, if we run the
same query again,
we'd expect it to use
the index because we're
querying on the keys
of our compound index
and our document has
greater than 3.5 stars.
And when we scroll
up, we see that whoa,
we're doing a collection scan.
I did this because I wanted
to point out an important part
of partial indexes.
In order to use a
partial index, the query
must be guaranteed
to match a subset
of the documents, specified
by the filter expression.
This is because the server
could miss results in the case
where matching documents
are not indexed.
In order for us to
trigger an index scan,
we need to include the stars
predicate in our query that
matches our filter expression.
And now when want
to explain output,
we can see that we're
indeed doing an index scan.
Just remember that
your query predicate
must be guaranteed to match a
subset of the documents that
will match our
filter expression.
This property will hold,
regardless of which documents
happen to be in the collection.
Let's take a moment to discuss
some of the restrictions
of partial indexes.
So we cannot specify both
a partialFilterExpression
and the sparse option, and
that's OK because we can
actually make a sparse query
with a filter expression.
We also can't make
our _ID index partial,
and that's because every
document has to have an indexed
_ID field.
And finally, we cannot have our
shared key be a partial index.
Let's recap what we've learned.
So we've learned how to create
and use partial indexes,
we've also learned about
some of the advantages
and disadvantages
of partial indexes.
We've learned how to predict
when a query will ignore
the existence of
a partial index,
and we've learned how to
emulate a sparse index
with a partial index.
And that should give you a good
overview of partial indexes.