In this video, let's continue
talking about single field
indexes.
In the last video,
we saw how we can
create an index
on a single field
to query on a single
value or to use
dot notation to query
on a single value
inside of a subdocument.
In this video, let's talk about
using single field indexes
to query on ranges of
values and querying
on several distinct values.
Earlier, we saw
how to use an index
to get just one value for
a social security number.
Here, we're going
to try to match
for a range of social
security numbers.
And if we look at our explain
output, as we would expect,
we're able to do an index scan.
And by doing this
index scan, when
we look at execution
stats, we can
see that we only had
to examine 49 documents
to return 49 documents.
So we didn't have to look at
any superfluous documents, which
is really, really
awesome, because we were
able to use our 49 index
keys to directly get those 49
documents.
Rather than using
a range, what if I
wanted to query on a set
of social security numbers?
Well, as you'll see, we're
still able to do an index scan
as our winning plan.
And you'll see, if we
look under executionStats,
we only had to examine
three documents
to find the three documents
that matched our set.
We did have to look at
six index keys, which
is more than we would
probably expect,
which is a little less
efficient than it could be.
But it's still much better
than doing a collections scan.
These extra index keys are due
to the algorithm the system
used, which can
involve overshooting
the values we're looking for.
I also want to note
that I can specify
multiple fields in my query.
We can still use an index,
even if we're only touching
one of the multiple fields.
So when we look
our explain output,
we can see what's going on here.
And we can see here, by
looking at our winningPlan,
that what we're
doing is, as we're
doing an index scan on the
social security number,
to filter down to the three
documents that match our query.
And then from those
three documents,
we're then filtering
on which of those three
match our last name predicate.
So if a query is
matching documents
on two or more fields,
but the database only
has a single field index
for one of them, what
will happen is the database
will filter using the index
and then it will then
look at those documents
and fetch only the ones that
match the other predicates.
Later, you'll see how we can
use compound indexes to get even
more efficiency in our queries.
But this is the behavior you
should expect from single field
indexes.
So let's recap
what we've learned.
In these last two
videos, we've learned
that we can use a
single field index
to query on a single value or
to query on a range of values.
We can also use it
for dot notation
when using subdocuments.
And finally, we've
seen that we can use it
for several distinct values,
as I have a single query.
And that's what you need to
know about single field indexes.