In this video, I want to talk
about single field indexes.
The single field index
is the simplest index
that MongoDB has to offer.
It will form the foundation
for all later indexes
that we'll discuss.
And we'll be describing
all of those in contrast
with the based on behaviors
that we'll learn about here.
A single field index is
exactly what it sounds like.
It's an index that captures
just the keys on a single field,
and it has the
following key features.
The keys are from
only one field.
We can find a single value
for that indexed field.
We can find a range of values.
We can use dot notation to index
the fields in our subdocuments.
And we can use it to find
several distinct values
with a single query.
By the end of this
section you should
be able to create
single field indexes,
and use them in each of
the cases listed here.
Let's go ahead and see what
this looks like in the shell.
First, let's go ahead
and import some data
by using the Mongo
import command
and, we're going to import
the people.json on file.
Let's go ahead and use
the Mongo import command.
Import the people.json file.
Now, let's fire up
the shell, and run a
find query on our new
people collection.
So here's the query
we're going to run.
We're going to try to find
all the documents that
have a SSN, which is a social
security number, of this value.
And you'll notice I've appended
this "explain" function of pass
and this execution
stats parameter.
And this is so that we can
get some extra information
about our query.
Now, there's a lot
of output here.
In other lessons, we'll dig into
this output much more deeply,
but for now there's just a
few fields we care about.
If I scroll up here, you can
see that the query planner says
that we're doing a
collection scan, which
means that we're looking at
every document in the database.
And if we scroll down here, we
can look at execution stats,
and see that we had to
examine 50,000 documents.
Which makes sense
because there's
50,000 documents
in this collection,
and since we had
a collection scan
we had to look at
all 50,000 documents.
We had to look at
50,000 documents,
even though we only
returned one document.
So this is a very bad ratio.
Even though we only had
to return one document,
we had look at 50,000.
It's not very efficient.
You'll also notice that we
looked at zero index keys,
and that's because we
did a collection scan.
We didn't use an index
because we haven't
created any indexes yet.
Let's go ahead and do that now.
Here I'm creating an
index on the SSN field,
and I'm saying one
to specify that it's
going to be an ascending index.
Now, that I've ran this command,
MongoDB built the index.
And by doing that, MongoDB had
a look at every single document
in the collection.
And then it pulls
out the SSN field.
If the SSN field is not
present on a document,
then that key entry is
going to have a null value.
Let's go ahead and
run our query again.
I want to show you a cool trick.
Here I'm going to create an
explainable object, where
instead of putting
explain after the find,
I'm going to put it
directly on a collection.
Now, I can just run "find"
on my explainable object.
So I'm running the same
query as I did before.
Now, this time when we
look at the explain output,
we'll notice that the winning
plan is now an index scan.
So we're not doing a
collection scan anymore.
And if we scroll down
to execution stats,
we'll see that we returned the
same document we did before.
We return one document.
But rather than looking
at 50,000 documents,
we only had to look
at one document.
We only have to look at the
one document that we returned,
which is awesome.
And that's because
we're able to use index
keys to find our document.
In this case we had
to use one index key.
We immediately
found the index key
that had the value of our
query, and that index key
pointed directly to the document
that we wanted to return.
This is much more efficient than
scanning the entire collection,
which is what we do if
we don't have an index
to use on our query.
Now, if the query
predicate of my query
doesn't use a field
that is indexed on,
you'll see from
the explain output
that we weren't able
to use that index.
We had do a collection scan.
So that means that
because we didn't
use the SSN field, the
field that we indexed on,
we still had to look
at 50,000 documents
to return the 10
documents that we wanted.
Now, we know that
MongoDB allows us
to use dot notation to query
inside of a subdocument.
But you can also
use dot notation
when specifying indexes.
Let's use a simple example
to illustrate this.
Here, I'm going to insert a
document into the examples
collection.
This document will
have a field that
has a subdocument as its value.
And the subdocument
has two keys,
One called index field and
one called other field.
And I'll go ahead
and also insert
another document that
has similar fields,
but with different values.
And like I was saying,
we can specify an index
that uses dot notation
to index on the fields
of our embedded document.
And this way, when we use
dot notation in our queries,
we'll still be able
to use an index,
as illustrated by our
explain output, right here.
By the way, I want to point
out that we should never
index on the field that points
to a subdocument, because doing
so we'd have to query on
the entire subdocument.
It's much better
to use dot notation
when querying because we
can just query on the fields
that we care about
in our subdocuments.
If you do need to index
on more than one field,
you can use a compound
index, which we'll
learn about in another lesson.