In this lesson, we're going to
talk about multikey indexes.
Because of MongoDB's
flexible data model,
we're able to embed
arrays into our documents.
And when we index on a
field that is an array,
this is what we call
a multikey index.
It's called this because
for each entry in the array,
the server will create
a separate index key.
For example, in
this document, if we
were to create
index on categories,
then the server would
create index keys
for t-shirts,
clothing, and apparel.
With multikey
indexes, we can not
only index on scalar values,
like strings and numbers,
but we can also index
on nested documents.
For instance, we
might want to be
able to create an index on the
quantity field of our stock
sub-documents so
that we can sort all
these documents by quantity.
This would work the same
way as with scalar values.
In this case, the server would
create three index keys, one
for each of the sub-documents.
For each index document, we can
have at most one index field
whose value is an array.
In the case of our example,
we can create an index
on product name
and stock quantity,
but we couldn't create an index
on both categories and stock
quantity.
If we were to create
a compound index
on both categories
and stock, then we'd
be creating index keys
for the Cartesian product
between the length of the
category and stock arrays.
We'd be generating a huge
amount of index keys, which
would affect the
performance of our queries.
And this brings up a good point.
We want to be careful with
creating multikey indexes
because we want to make
sure that our arrays don't
grow too large.
Because in doing so, we'd
affect how large our index is,
potentially causing problems
with fitting the index
into memory, pushing our
data out, and vice versa.
Another important
caveat to point out
is that multikey indexes
don't support covered queries.
So if you're inclined
to use covered queries
to prevent the reading
of your documents,
then you'll want to
keep that in mind.
Let's go ahead and look at
how multikey indexes work
from the shell.
We can go ahead and switch
over to the m201 database
that we've been using.
And from here, let's go
ahead and insert a document
similar to our example.
Now we can run a FIND query and
look at the document we just
inserted.
You'll notice that
this document is
slightly different than
the one from our example.
In the example,
stock was an array.
Here, it's an embed document.
You'll see why I did
this in a second.
Let's go ahead and create
an index on stock.quantity
like we did in the example.
And like always, we
can go ahead and create
our explainable object.
You'll notice that I'm not
specifying execution stats
because we're just going
to look at the stages.
And now we can run
a FIND on this query
and look at the explain output.
And you'll see that we're able
to successfully use our index.
But you'll notice that
is multikey is false.
And this should make sense
because we haven't yet
indexed on our array field.
We modified our
document slightly so
that stock was an embedded
document rather than our array.
And so now we can actually
insert the document
from our example where the
stock field is an array.
And now, if we run our
first query, which would not
match the document
we just inserted,
it should only match
our first document,
you'll note that the
output has changed.
We're still doing an index
scan, but now multikey is true.
So MongoDB only recognizes
that an index is multikey
when a document
is inserted where
that field is in an array.
And like I said
earlier, if we try
to create an index where
both fields are arrays,
then this should fail.
And it does.
However, we can still create
compound multikey index using
product name and stock.quantity
because the stock field is only
an array.
So it should be fine for
me to insert this document
where product name is an
array, but stock is not.
Also, I should
point out this isn't
a particularly good schema
to use so I wouldn't
use this in production.
And the document
inserted just fine.
However, if both product
name and stock were arrays,
like in this document,
then we'll get an error.
I hope this gives you a good
overview of multikey indexes.
By now, you should be familiar
with how to create and use
multikey indexes,
the implications
of multikey indexes
on your index size,
and some of the limitations
that are associated
with multikey indexes.