Let's take a look
at compound indexes.
A compound index is an
index on two or more fields,
and it can support queries
based on those fields.
By the end of this
lesson, you should
be able to identify and
create compound indexes.
Let's talk for a moment
about the structure
of a compound index.
Now, in MongoDB,
indexes are b-trees
and they have an ordering,
and that ordering is flat.
So if you have two
fields, you might somehow
think that your indexes are
two-dimensional in some way,
but they're not.
They're actually
one-dimensional.
You can actually think of
index keys as an ordered list.
Looking at this diagram,
this is an index
on last name comma first name.
If I wanted to find a
document for Adam Bailey,
I'd go to the Baley
comma Adam index
key, which then points to
the Adam Bailey document.
I checked this one
index key and it
tells me to go in our
collection of documents.
There's no checking
of two things.
Even though there are
really two fields, the index
itself is still one-dimensional.
Let's make an analogy.
When working with
an index that's
ordered last name ascending
comma first name ascending,
you may not realize it
yet, but you're probably
already familiar with
the physical index
that works this exact same way--
a phone book.
Like an index, a phone book has,
as its keys, an ordered list
of names.
There is last name ascending,
first name ascending.
If I want to find
Chris Bailey, I'd
go to the Baley section
of the phone book
and go down through
and find Chris.
And then I would then
find his phone number.
But in the case of MongoDB,
it's going to be a document.
So if I wanted to find everyone
with a particular last name,
it'd be very easy.
They're all grouped together.
However, if I wanted to find
somebody with the name James,
I'd have to go through
every single key
or every single document in
order to find that person.
As we'll see the field
or fields that come first
are in some ways more
useful than the fields
that come later.
For this lesson, we'll be using
the same people.gif on file
that we've used in
previous lessons.
If you don't already
have this imported,
go ahead and import it now.
Now that we have these documents
imported, let's go ahead
and fire up Compass so we
can look at our indexes
and look at some queries.
And now that we're in Compass,
we can see our M201 database.
Go ahead and click
it and we're going
to see our people collection.
Go ahead and click that.
Now that we're in
here, we can go ahead
and click the Explain Plan
Area and then paste into Query.
In this case, we're
going to query
for last name Fraizer and first
name Jasmine and click Apply.
And when I do this, we get
the Explain Plan output.
So you can get this
exact same output
if you wanted via
the Mongo shell,
and it would look something
like this raw JSON.
You'd see a bunch of
great information--
literally all the information
you could ever want.
For now, we're going to
stick to the visual tree
and this query
performance summary.
So we can immediately see
that this query first of all
is on one document.
And to find that one document,
it took 24 milliseconds.
And you see that we used
zero index keys, which means
that we did not use an index.
Which is also
stated right here--
and that we had to look
at 50,000 documents
to find this one document.
And that's really important.
What really matters
here is this ratio.
We had to look at
50,000 documents,
even though we only
wanted one document.
So now let's go ahead and
build a single key index
to see how this will
affect our performance.
So I'll go out and
click Create Index.
We'll give it a name.
We'll say last name, and then
we'll use the field last name
and we'll make it
an ascending index,
and we'll go ahead
and create it.
Now, let's go ahead
and run it again.
Now, when we run again, we can
see our performance summary,
and we've still got the one
document that we wanted.
And we can see the 31
documents that we then examined
to find that one document.
So this is a much better ratio--
one to 31 rather
than one to 50,000.
And as such, you can
see that our query time
is much, much slower.
It actually says
zero milliseconds.
There's some rounding
going on here.
It obviously took some
time, but 0 is way faster
than what we had before.
And you cam see that it
even states the index
that we were able to
use-- the last name index.
And so this is also
exemplified by the 31 keys
that we had to examine to go
and find those 31 documents,
and to see whether or not
the first name matched.
Because basically
these 31 documents--
they all match the
last name Frazier,
but there's only
one document that
matches those 31 that also
has the first name of Jasmine.
And we can see this
visually over here.
We can see that we
had a fetch stage.
We had to find
that one document,
and then in our
index scan, we were
able to find all the people
who matched last name Frazier.
But let's actually
make a compound index
and see if we can
make this even better.
So we go and create
another index.
I'm going name this one
last name first name.
We'll click the last
name field, ascending.
We're going to add
another field--
first name, ascending,
and we'll click Create.
Now, the order does matter here.
The order, as we'll talk
about later in this video
or in another video, the order
here really matters a lot.
So we'll click Create, and
as you can see here now,
we're now able to use
our compound index--
last name first name--
took zero seconds, so
again it's very, very fast.
We found our one document, but
this time instead of looking
at 31 documents and
examining 31 keys,
we only had to
examine one document--
the document we
actually care about--
and that document's key.
So the ratio is one to one.
So the ratio of one is
basically the best ratio
that we could have.
And if we look down
here, we'll see
that we were doing an
index scan and able
to use the compound index
that we just created.
Much like single
field indexes, we
can also use compound indexes
to find a range of values.
So now, let's modify
our query slightly.
So now instead of saying
Jasmine, we'll say greater than
or equal to capital
L. When we run this,
you'll see that we had
examined 16 documents,
we had examined 16 keys, and
we returned 16 documents.
So a ratio of 16
to 16 is still one.
So it's a very, very good ratio.
We don't have to look at any
superfluous or unnecessary
documents.
And as such, we are able to
have a very, very fast query
because we are able to
use this compound index.
And the reason that we only
had to examine documents
that were returned is because
the first name field are all
ordered.
We're saying greater
than or equal to L--
so everything that's greater
than the capital letter L.
So it's just like our phone
book example and it's just
like how the index
keys are stored.
All the first name fields
with the last name of Frazier
are all in ascending order.
So we just go to the L section
and then go straight down.
That's exactly what
MongoDB is able to do.
And now you know how to create
compound indexes using MongoDB.
You've seen how it's done
through MongoDB Compass.
All of these features
I've shown you--
the explain outputs and the
ability to create indexes--
are also available obviously
by the Mongo Shell.