In this lesson, I want
to further discuss
about querying with
compound indexes.
And specifically, I want to
talk about index prefixes
and how they're
used when we query.
By the end of this lesson,
you should be able to--
for a query that has
multiple fields that
overlap with an index--
you should be able to identify
which fields the query can
use the index for.
The way you're going
to learn how to do
that is through index prefixes.
An index prefix is a continuous
subset of our compound index
that starts to the left.
The easiest way to illustrate
it is to look at examples.
So here's our compound index.
We have a compound index on
item, location and stock,
and they're all ascending.
And so our index prefixes
for this compound index
would be the following--
item, or item location,
because we always
start on the left-hand side
and it has to be continuous.
We couldn't have an index
prefix of location stock,
or just stock by itself,
or location by itself.
And obviously we can't
have anything out of order,
like stock item,
or even item stock.
It's always from the
left and continuous.
So the only two prefixes
for this compound index
would be item and item
location, both ascending.
And so just like
with the phone book,
I can use an index prefix
just like a regular index.
The query planner will ignore
the other parts of the index,
and will use the prefix to
find your documents that you
care about.
Let's look at a simple case.
So we already have this compound
index of last name, first name.
And so an index prefix for
this would be last name.
So if I have a query where
I query on last name--
last name is a index prefix
for our compound index--
when we run this query,
we get our 22 documents.
And if we look at
the explain output,
and so we can see that we
only had to exam 22 documents,
which is really good
because we ended up
returning 22 documents.
So again, a very good ratio.
A ratio of 1.
And we also had to look
at 22 index keys, which
is also very, very good.
We didn't have to look at
any superfluous index keys,
and as such, we have a execution
time of 0 milliseconds.
But what if we were to
query on first name instead
of last name?
Well then, we would still
get our eight documents
that we wanted.
But now when we
look at the explain,
you'll see that we had to
examine 50,000 documents,
whereas only eight
were returned,
and we didn't look at
any index keys at all.
So this is a terrible ratio.
We looked at no index keys,
and it took a long time.
And that's because if we
look at the explain output,
we can see that we had
to do a collection scan.
And that's because we
weren't able to use
an index for this
query, and that's
because we didn't
use an index prefix.
So it's really helpful
to remember this image.
As you can see,
the first names can
be anywhere in the index,
whereas the last names have
an ordering.
And the first names have
an ordering relative
to the last name.
But the first name by itself, if
that's what we're querying on,
they could be anywhere.
So the index is
really no use to us.
We're just going to have
to go through and look
at every single document.
We're going to have to
do a collection scan.
And so this is one of
the interesting features
of compound indexes.
If we have a compound
index, it can
serve as query use
for both the compound
and any of its prefixes, but
it won't use an index when
we're not querying on a prefix.
So this is something
you should consider
when building your indexes.
If your application has two
queries and one uses fields
that are a subset
of the other, you
should build an
index where one query
uses the index
prefix and the other
uses all fields of the index.
There's no point in building
two indexes when you can have
everything with just one index.
Let's look at a better
example of this.
Let's go ahead and delete
this compound index
that we have right
now, and we'll
create a new, larger index.
So here is our
new, larger index.
We're going to call it
job, employer, last name,
first name.
And naturally, those are the
same fields that we'll have.
And here's the
name of our index--
it's job, employer,
last name, first name.
And our indexes are going to
be job, employer, last name,
first name, all ascending.
And go ahead and create it.
And now it's been created.
Let's go ahead and run a query.
You can see here,
our query reported
on both job and employer, and
these make up an index prefix.
So when we run the query,
we get our five documents.
And when we look
at explain, we can
see that we only had to examine
five documents, which were
the five that were returned.
So again a very good ratio.
We only had to
examine five keys,
and we had great execution time.
And you can see that we're
able to use the index.
So if we look at
this, we can see
that we are able
to do an index scan
using our compound
index, which is larger
than our query parameters,
but our query parameters
are an index prefix
for our given index.
What if we were to also
filter on last name?
We know that one of our
documents is for Sara Cook,
and so we can just add this
last name predicate for Cook.
So when we run this, we
find our Sara Cook document.
And when we look
at explain, you can
see that we only had to examine
one document for the exact one
document that we
returned, and we only
had to look at
that one index key.
So of course, it was
really, really fast,
because we were doing an index
scan, because again, we're
using the index prefix.
Let's do the same thing
again, but this time,
instead of querying
on last name,
we'll query on first name.
So we'll use Sara's first name.
And when we run the
query, we get the document
that we would expect.
But when we looked
at explain, you
can see that even
though we only had
to look at one document,
which was the same one that we
returned, we still had to
look at six index keys.
So we had to look at basically
five unnecessary index keys.
So even though our
query was very fast,
and we were able to
use an index scan,
we still had to spend
some time looking at keys
that we really didn't need to.
So we were still able to
use an index prefix of job
and employer, but we
weren't able to use an index
prefix that had three fields.
We were only able to use
two of the four fields
that make up our compound index.
We can take this a step
further by looking at job,
first name and last name.
We still get the one
document that we wanted,
but now we're examining way more
keys than what we were before.
So we still only have to look
at one document, the same one
that we returned, but now we're
looking at a bunch of keys
that we don't need to.
Just to be clear, there are
some performance considerations
that we'll be getting
into in other lessons.
We haven't yet dealt with
sorting with compound indexes,
but these are the basics.
And everything that we talked
about in single key indexes
also still apply to
compound indexes.
So now you know how
to use index prefixes
to determine for a given query
that overlaps the index which
fields in the
query will actually
be able to use the index.