We also have our count stage.
The count stage counts
all incoming documents.
The argument to count
is the field name
on which we are going to
collect that count value.
In a document of the results.
In this case, I'm going
to filter our collection
so we only look
at documents that
are in terrestrial planets.
Here we are
specifying that match
where the type of the
document will have the value
terrestrial planet.
Then, from there results from
match which are then dispatched
to the project stage,
I'm going to filter
only name and number
of moons, removing
ID, as we've done before.
And from all of the documents
coming from the pipeline
I'm then going to count them.
The count will give me
back a result document,
which has a field
that I specified
here, terrestrial
planets, which contains
the value of number
of documents that are
of type terrestrial planets.
Now for this particular
pipeline here,
where the end result
is going to be
the count of the number
of documents, which
have a type of
terrestrial planet,
the project stage here is a
little bit of an annoyance.
It doesn't really interfere with
the end result of the pipeline.
So if we would just remove
it, and we just have a match
and then count,
we can see that I
get exactly the same execution
in exactly the same results,
having or not a project
in between the match
and the count.
Lastly, let's look at the sort.
Sort needs to be supplied with
the field we want to sort on.
In this case, if I'm going
a project, name, and number
of moons, I can
sort on the fields
that I'm collecting from
the incoming pipeline.
So in this case, if I want to
sort on the number of moons
descending, I'll get
the results as expected,
where I get the planet
which has more moons first,
and on that order to till ones
that have absolutely no moons--
like sun, Mercury, and Venus--
poor guys.
An important aspect
to refer to here
is that the sort
stage is not limited
to just one single field.
You will operate on
multiple different fields
in combination, as we
would do in normal queries
and find operations, if you
want to sort first on one field
and then on another,
that is totally
possible in the aggregation
pipeline stage as well.
So let's say here,
for example, that I
have this different
project where
I'm going to project
as well, apart
from name and number of moons,
the field has magnetic field,
which is a pulling field.
In the third stage,
I can specify
that I want to sort on as
magnetic field, descending,
and number of moons descending.
By executing this
specific query,
we get a very similar
result as before,
where are we going to have
Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and so
on.
The only difference
is that, for example,
sun and Mercury will
come before Mars.
So how is that possible?
Well, the result is being
sorted first on the field
as magnetic field
equals true, and then
on the number of moons.
So first I'm going to
have all the ones that
has magnetic field
is equal to true.
And then after that I'm going
to search on the number of moons
for the results.
Now if sort is near the
beginning of our pipeline,
in place before a project, and
unwinds in the group stage,
it can take
advantage of indexes.
Otherwise, this sort stage will
perform an in-memory sort, ,
which will greatly increase
the memory consumption
of our server.
Sort operations within
that vision pipeline
are limited to 100
megabytes of RAM by default.
To allow handling
larger data sets,
we need to allow DiskUse, which
is an aggregation pipeline
option that we can provide
to the aggregate function.
By doing so, we
will be performing
the excess of 100
megabytes of memory
required to do a sort using
disk to help us sort out
the results.
So in short, $sort,
$skip, $limits, and $count
are functionally equivalent
to the similar named cursor
methods.
So we can take
advantage of indexes
if it's near the
beginning of our pipeline,
and before a project
group or unwind stages.
By default, the $source
will only take up
to 100 megabytes of RAM.
For more than that, we
will need to provide
the allowDiskUse option as
equal true to our pipeline.
If we do not do
so, the operation
will be terminated
on the server.
And that's all we have for
you in cursor-like stages
of the hour
aggregation pipeline.