Let's now discuss another
transformative stage,
$addFields.
$addFields is extremely
similar to $project, with
one key difference.
As the name applies, $addFields
adds fields to a document.
While with $project, we
can selectively remove and
retain fields,
$addFields only allows
you to modify the
incoming pipeline
documents with new
computed fields
or to modify existing fields.
Oftentimes, we will want
to derive a new field
or change existing fields,
and the requirement
in $project that once we perform
a transformation or retain
a field then we must specify
all fields we wish to retain
can become tedious.
Let's look at an example.
First, we'll look at $project.
Let's just extract the data
from the gravity.value field
and reassign it to the
top level, gravity field.
As expected, we can get the
results back with the _id field
and the gravity field
we just calculated.
Now let's remove the _id
field and add the name field
for easier reference.
All right, this is pretty good.
But what if we also want to keep
the temperature, density, mass,
radius, and SMA fields?
As we can see, in order to
keep the information we want,
we had to be
explicit, specifying
which fields to retain
along with performing
our transformations.
As said, this can
become tedious.
In comes $addFields.
If we substitute $addFields
for $project and execute
the following pipeline, we can
see that we indeed performed
the desired transformations.
However, we do not
remove any fields
from the original document.
Instead, we append new
transformation fields
to the document.
OK.
One last example.
By combining $project
with $addFields, we
remove the annoyance
of explicitly needing
to remove or retain fields.
In this example,
with $project, we
are selecting the fields
that we wish to retain,
and in $addFields, we are
performing our transformation
on those pre-selected fields.
There is no need
to go one by one
and remove or retain
fields while performing
our transformations.
This is a style
choice and can prevent
having to repeatedly
specify which
fields to retain
in larger pipelines
when performing many
various calculations.
Let's see it in action.
As we can see, we will
retain the specified fields
and perform the
specified transformation.