Another very useful
utility stage is $sample.
$sample will select a
set of random documents
from a collection
in one of two ways.
The first method is if the
size that we are specifying,
the N number of documents
that we want our sample to be
looking like, if
it's less than 5%
of the number of documents
in our source collection,
and the source collection
has more than 100 documents,
and $sample is the first stage,
then a pseudo-random cursor
will select the specific number
of documents to be passed on.
If all other
conditions, and let's
recap them very quickly,
if N is more than 5%
or the source collection
has less than 100 documents,
or if sample is not
the first stage, if any
of these conditions does
not apply, then what is done
is a in-memory random
sort and select
the specific number of documents
that we specify as the size.
Now this sort will be subjected
to the same memory restrictions
as the sort stage of our
aggregation pipeline.
So let's see some
of this in action.
In my database, I will have
a NYC facilities collection.
This collection contains
more than 100 documents.
The sample size
is greater than 5%
of the total amount
of documents.
And the sample stage is
the first of my pipeline.
Therefore, the pseudo-random
operation will apply.
When I run this
pipeline, we can see
that we got randomly selected
documents from our collection.
Now $sample is very useful when
working with large collections.
And we only want a limited
amount of documents
to operate with.
They can be useful to
do an initial analysis
or to do some sampling on
the result set that we might
be interested to work with.
It can be used to
fetch documents
in a random fashion for
features such as random user
search in a
collection, or when we
want to seed some random
object for some computation,
or when we want aleatory
data for our data set.
And this is all we have
for you on $sample.