Let's take a break from
transformation for a moment
and discuss a
useful utility stage
if we work would GeoJSON data--
$geoNear.
$geoNear is the aggregation
framework solution
to performing geoqueries within
the aggregation pipeline.
Within a pipeline,
$geoNear must be
the first stage in a pipeline.
Also of note, we cannot use the
$near predicate in the query
field, though it wouldn't
really make much sense to do so.
So if we already
have $near operator
available for find
operations, why
do we need an aggregation
stage like $geoNear?
$geoNear can be used
on charted collections,
whereas $near can't.
Additionally, any query using
$near cannot use other special
indexes, like
$text, for example.
One last thing,
$geoNear requires
that the collection we're
performing our aggregations
on to have one and
only one geoindex.
Here is the structuring
arguments for $geoNear.
As we can see, it can
take a lot of arguments,
though only if you're required.
Required arguments are near,
distanceField, and spherical.
Near is the point we'd
like to search near.
Results will be
ordered from closest
to furthest from this location.
distanceField is the
argument we supply
that will be inserted
into returned documents,
giving us the distance from
location to the location
we specified in near.
Spherical is the last
required argument.
Specify true if the index is
a 2dsphere, otherwise false.
During this lesson, we'll
be using a 2dsphere index.
Let's go ahead and execute
a $geoNear aggregation.
I'm going to search for
locations near the MongoDB
headquarters in New York City.
Here I've specified my
three required arguments--
near, distanceField,
and spherical.
Well, we got a ton of results,
so we can see it works.
However, it's not very
useful in its current state.
Let's look at those optional
arguments in greater detail
to learn how to make this
aggregation much more targeted.
minDistance and
maxDistance specify
the closest and furthest
results we want.
Query allows us to
specify conditions
that each document
must meet, and uses
the same query operator
syntax as match.
includeLocs would
allow us to show
what location was
used in the document
if it has more
than one location.
For our dataset,
this isn't necessary,
as each document only
has one location.
And remember, $geoNear
requires that we
have exactly one 2dsphere
index in the collection.
Limit and num are
functionally identical
and are used to limit the
number of documents returned.
Lastly,
distanceMultiplier is used
to convert distance results
from radians into whatever unit
we need, should we be using
legacy geospatial data.
So let's clean up
our aggregation
and fetch useful results.
I'd like to find the
five nearest hospitals
to the MongoDB headquarters.
Here I've added the
optional query field
and specified that it
should be type "Hospital."
And here I've added the
optional limit field
and specified it as 5.
Much better.
We got the five nearest
places that matched hospital.
And we could see that our
distance is in meters.
And that's it for $geoNear.
There's just a few
things to remember.
The collection can have one
and only one 2dsphere index.
If using 2dsphere, the
distance is returned in meters.
If using legacy
coordinates, the distance
is returned in radians.
And $geoNear must
be the first stage
in an aggregation pipeline.