It is time we discuss some
useful utility stages, what
we call cursor-like stages.
These stages are sort,
skip, limit, and counts.
And they have an equivalent in
our query language as a cursor
method.
Let's have a look.
After connecting to my
aggregations database,
I can express this simple
query on solar system
where I am going to
find all my documents.
This is a full collection scan.
and only projecting out
the name, number of Moons,
and keeping out the _id.
If I do this, I can see all
the results of my collection,
only exposing the
name, number of Moons
per each one of the documents.
Sweet, this works well.
The other thing I can do
is basically call count.
Now this will count the
full amount of documents
returned by the query.
Here, I can see that I have on
my solar system nine documents.
Another thing that I can do is
basically skip five documents.
And if execute this
query, I can see that a
skipped a few first documents.
Now if you are wondering
why did I get this order,
why did I skip those previous
five documents and not
others, if I do not specify a
sorting operation or a sorting
of my cursor, I will
get from MongoDB
the order by which the
documents are inserted
in the collection, what
we call the natural order
of the collection.
So in this case,
I'm going to skip
the five first
elements that have been
inserted into this collection.
The following method
will be limit,
where I can specify
the number of documents
that I'm going to return.
And again, following the
exactly same sorting order,
which in this case is going to
be my natural insert sorting
order on our solar
system collection,
I'll get the Sun, Mercury,
Venus, Earth, and Mars,
which are the five first
documents of my collection.
And lastly, I can
also specify a sort
for the result set
of my collection.
Here, I'm going to
find everything.
But instead of
giving back the order
by which documents are
inserted in the collection,
I'm going to sort the result
set based on the number of Moons
that each one of these
documents contain.
Minus 1 specifies the order.
And in this case, it
will be descending.
So as we can see, we
are going to get, first,
the ones that have more Moons to
the ones that have less Moons.
Now we've seen the
cursor methods,
but we also have stages that
execute exactly the same kind
of functionality.
We have $limit, $skip,
$count, and $sort.
They will vary a little bit
on the syntax, where limit
will take an integer,
skip will take also
an integer, specifying the
number of limit documents
and the number of
skip documents.
Count, on the
other hand, we will
need to specify a
field where we want
to collect the count value.
And sort, we need to specify
the keys and the order
by which we want our result sets
of the pipeline to be sorted.
Let's see some of
this in action.
Now to mimic exactly the same
operation as before in our find
command, I'm going to execute
the project of name and number
of Moons, excluding _id, exactly
the same operation as before.
And in this case, given the
pipeline that I'm executing
and given the documents that
this aggregation pipeline will
provide, I will add a limit
stage to my pipe, saying,
I only want the
first five documents
coming from this project stage.
And as expected, I
get the same results
as I would if I would
limit on a find operation.
The following
stage will be skip.
And again, given the results
incoming from the project
stage, I will skip only one.
In this case, I'm
going to skip the Sun.
So how do I know that I'm
going to skip the Sun?
Well basically,
the order by which
I'm going to get the
results into the project
is the natural order,
exactly in the same way
as we've seen before.
The project will filter
out only the fields
that I'm interested on and pass
along that to the skip stage.
Skip, by skipping up one, I'm
going to be skipping the Sun.
As you can see here, all
different celestial bodies
will be reported
back in my results,
except for the Sun, which is the
first element, the one that I'm
skipping in the pipeline.