Now that we understand
how data lake works,
let's see how we can use it.
So we'll start by creating a
data lake called Atlas Data
Lake.
To do this we're going
to select the Data Lake
option on the left-hand
side in the Atlas UI,
and then we're going to
click Configure A Data Lake
and follow the
onscreen commands.
As we've mentioned in
the previous lesson,
our data lake tutorial steps
you through this process.
This is what our data looks
like inside our s3 bucket.
We have a JSON folder with
six sub-directories containing
JSON files.
For this example we're using
uncompressed JSON files.
We've added the link to the s3
bucket in the lecture notes.
For this example, we're going
to configure the databases
and collection for a data
lake through the Mongo shell.
We configure our JSON data
files with the storage
set config command.
Remember we need a MongoDB
database user with Atlas admin
privileges to configure
our s3 files into databases
and collections.
The stores object
defines each data store
associated with the data lake.
In this example we've defined
an s3 bucket as the data store,
we've named a single data store
and we've call it s3 store,
we've provided the
name of the AWS region
where the s3 bucket is located.
We've also defined our
database name as sampleDB,
and here we're using the
star wildcard operator
for the collection name.
And the reason we're doing
that is because we're
using the collection
name function
to define our
collection names here.
What this means is that
the data lake will actually
generate the collection names
from all some directories
underneath this JSON directory.
What this gives us
is a database called
sampleDB and six collections
within that database.
So let's have a look at
what we've done so far.
We've created a data
lake, we've configured it
by the Mongo shell, and
we've configured our database
and collections.
Now we're ready to go and
run some analytic queries
against our raw s3 data.
Let's start by searching the
sample airbnb collection, which
contains property reviews
for short-term rentals
in a range of cities.
Now, let's say we want to find
properties in New York which
got a high rating from guests.
To make it meaningful, we're
going to exclude any properties
with less than five reviews.
You may notice that the syntax
here is the same standard Mongo
query language.
We can run queries
and aggregations
just as we would run them
against a standard MongoDB
replica set or shard or cluster.
The find command should
return output in this format.
Note that this s3 bucket holds
the same data as our Atlas load
sample data.
More details on that
data can be found
in our docs page, which we've
linked in the lecture notes.
So let's recap what we've done.
We built a data lake
in the Atlas UI.
As part of the process,
we created a new IAM role
and we gave this role read-only
access to our s3 bucket.
We configured our data
stores from our s3 data
through the Mongo shell
using the new storage set
config command.
And then when our data
is stored and configured,
we can run queries
and aggregations
as normal through the shell,
compass, or a MongoDB driver.