Welcome back.
In this lesson, we're
going to discuss
a new feature an Atlas
called the data lake, which
allows us to query archived data
stored in as S3 buckets MongoDB
query language.
So keeping all of your data
available in' database clusters
may not be financially
responsible.
So customers archive
data from time to time.
Having that data
in archive format
does not mean we won't ever
need it again because you still
may need to access this data
for data analytics or compliance
purposes.
However, now you could
also use the Atlas data
lake to query the data that
you've archived in S3 buckets.
So you create a data lake
through the Atlas UI,
similar to creating
an Atlas cluster.
Your data lakes appear in
the UI at the same level
as your Atlas clusters.
And once you've
created your data lake,
you can configure the data
stored in your S3 buckets
to be exposed as MongoDB
databases or collections.
Then you can build
and run queries
through the Mongo
Shell, MongoDB Compass,
or through your driver.
So operations can be run
using the MongoDB query
language, or MQL, which
includes most but not
all standard server commands.
In particular, the data
lake is a read-only service,
though we will be adding support
for the dollar out aggregation
stage sometime in the future.
MQL operations can
be run in parallel
to enhance performance for
large and complex queries.
However, the data lake is meant
for analytics-type workloads
and is not intended for
day-to-day operational
workloads.
The data lake supports many
different file formats,
such as JSON, BSON, CSV,
TSV, Avro, and Parquet.
You can specify the
file format, or it
will be detected automatically.
An AWS IAM role is required
to access the S3 data.
This rule is created
using the AWS command line
interface or the AWS console.
You can then assign
a role policy
to this role that gives Atlas
data lake read-only access
to your S3 buckets.
Using this approach, you
control what buckets are
exposed to the Atlas data lake.
Also, should you decide
to terminate access
to the archived data, you
can remove or restrict
a configured AWS role
whenever you want.
Instructions are
provided in the Atlas UI
during the data lake setup
to help you create this role.
You can find more detail on IAM
role management in the AWS User
Guide.
And we'll attach a link to
that in the lecture notes.
So a few things to consider
about using the Atlas data
lake, as this is a
very new feature.
Currently, the maximum
cursor size is 1 gigabyte.
So if the query returns more
than 1 gigabyte of data,
the result set will be
truncated down to 1 gigabyte
and then returned.
So as we mentioned before,
the Atlas data lake
does not currently
support dollar out.
There are a few other
aggregation pipeline
stages that are not supported
by the data lake at this time.
Those stages are collection
stats, geoNear, graphLookup,
indexStats, and listSessions.
In particular, the
collection stats command
omits some fields, as
they are either not
applicable to the data
lake, or they would
be too expensive to compute.
And lastly, the Atlas
data lake supports
all of Parquet's base types,
except the deprecated INT96
type.
So now let's recap.
The Atlas data lake
allows you to run queries
against data stored in S3
buckets through the Mongo
Shell, your driver, or
through MongoDB Compass.
The data lake is integrated
with MongoDB Atlas,
so you can build data
lakes through the Atlas
UI, similar to building
an Atlas cluster.
There's no
infrastructure required.
You just need an AWS IAM
user with read-only access
to the S3 bucket.
The stored configuration
allows you to flexibly define
how your S3 data is mapped
to databases and collections.
Our Atlas data lake tutorial
guides you through the data
lake setup process.
There are steps in the procedure
on how to set up a data lake,
and it'll provide access
to a public S3 bucket
with sample commands to
help you create named spaces
and run MQL queries.
We'll also provide a link
to this documentation page,
as well as some other helpful
ones in the lecture notes.