With MongoDB 4.2,
we're releasing
our very own sync-and-source
connectors for Apache Kafka.
Although slightly outside of
the scope of this lesson, let's
talk about what
Kafka is and why we'd
want to connect MongoDB to it.
At a very high level,
Kafka is a high-performance
distributed messaging system.
It was first
developed by LinkedIn
to handle their internal logs.
A simple way to think of Kafka
is as a router for messages.
So you can configure
Kafka to route messages
to and from different source and
consumer systems, both of which
can be a MongoDB closer.
Kafka organizes data
into messages and topics.
Messages can be a
line of a log file
or a document in a
MongoDB collection.
A topic is just a
category or message.
So use cases for this would
be a user adding an item
to a shopping cart
or a tweet being
sent to a specific hashtag.
We could have a
topic per hashtag.
Or another example would
be a financial application
which could pull NYC
stock trades from one
topic and company
financial announcements
from another in order to look
for trading opportunities.
So any system that
publishes messages to Kafka
is called a "source," and
anything that receives
input is called a "sync."
A source connector
ingests entire databases
and streams table
updates to Kafka topics.
It can also collect metrics from
all of your application servers
into Kafka topics, making
the data available for stream
processing low latency.
A sync connector delivers
data from Kafka topics
into secondary applications or
data storers such as MongoDB.
And the Kafka servers
which process the messages
are called "brokers."
We can have multiple
brokers in a Kafka closer.
So now that we have an
idea of what Kafka is
and how MongoDB fits into
the Kafka architecture,
let's have a look
at this in action.
We've pre-configured a
Kafka instance and MongoDB
as a Kafka source in the VM
provided to you in this course,
so feel free to follow along.
First let's look into Kafka
UI and see what we have.
If you look into the UI, you
see that we have a Mongo dot
test dot sync topic.
And if we look at
the Data tab here,
you should see something
familiar to you
in the messages.
We've got MongoDB
documents embedded.
And not just
documents, but change
stream events which are
streaming from our MongoDB
instance.
That is because we've
configured our MongoDB
to send change stream
events to Kafka.
And that means that if
we add or we update data
in the sync collection
in a test DB,
it will show up as change
messages in the Mongo dot test
dot sync topic.
So let's test that out
by opening up to shell,
inserting a document
into the test
dot sync collection
on the MongoDB.
You can see here
that we are inserting
a document into the test
DB in the sync collection.
So our document's inserted.
Let's jump back to
the UI and see if we
can see it in our Kafka stream.
As you can see, our
document has shown up
as a message in
our Kafka stream.
With the MongoDB
Kafka Connector,
we can also use
MongoDB as a sync.
And what this basically means
is that we can insert documents
into MongoDB from a topic
or multiple topics in Kafka.
Remember, a topic is simply a
logical partition of messages.
The Kafka messages are converted
into BSON documents, which
are in turn inserted in the
corresponding MongoDB target
collection.
According to the chosen Roi
model strategy in the connector
config, you can use
either a replaceOne model
or an UpdateOne model.
Either model will
perform an upsert
if the data does not
exist in the collection.
One thing to remember is
the data coming into Kafka
may not necessarily
be in JSON format.
We can get around this
by enforcing schema
using Apache Avro.
Avro is a message serialization
system from Apache
that allows you to enforce
strict schema on data
coming from Kafka.
You can see an example
of an Avro schema here
we're defining with the fields,
their names and data types,
which will be enforced
on the Kafka side
before being inserted
into MongoDB.
MongoDB also offers rich schema
validation using JSON schema
so that you can ensure that
documents inserted from Kafka
follow your schema design.
While this isn't a
schema design lesson,
it's important to remember that
MongoDB is schema-free, not
schema-less.
Schema has a big impact
on performance in MongoDB
and definitely
should be considered.
So let's recap.
MongoDB now provides
source and sync connectors
for Apache Kafka.
You can enforce schema on
both the Kafka and MongoDB
side, using Avro
on the Kafka side,
and JSON schema validation
on the MongoDB side.