Hi, there.
In MongoDB Atlas, you can
now easily embed charts
in your website or web app.
MongoDB Charts has
been designed to make
it very easy to create
compelling visualizations
of data stored in MongoDB.
Up to now, you could only
share your visualizations
with users who had access
to your Atlas project.
MongoDB now provides a
quick and easy way for you
to embed visualizations of
data in your web application.
So that's enough
talking about it.
Let's get our hands
dirty and embed a chart
in our very own website.
So we've loaded sample
data into our cluster
using the Load Sample Data
feature in MongoDB Atlas.
We are going to jump into
Charts and create a chart.
So that we can use the
data that's in our cluster,
we need to create
a new data source.
So let's select our cluster
here, which is Cluster0.
We'll connect charts
to the cluster
and just wait a minute
for it to connect.
So now the chart is
connected to our cluster,
we're going to
select the collection
that we want to work with.
And that is our
ListingsAndReviews collection
inside the airbnb data set.
So next we need to
set permissions.
There are three different
permission levels
that we can set here.
Viewers can access data
from the data source
by viewing existing charts
and creating new charts
with that data source.
Managers can point to
another data source
by changing the connection
string or alias.
And, finally, owners-- in
addition to manager privileges,
owners can manage permissions
on the data source
and delete the data
source as well.
Great.
So now we've got our
data source created.
And our cluster is
linked to charts.
So now we can make a
dashboard and start
making some nice visualizations
to embed in our website.
Now that our dashboard has been
created, let's add a chart.
So we've selected Geospatial
from the drop-down menu.
And we're going to
create a heat map.
So let's grab the location
field from the address document
and put that onto
the coordinates.
And then we're going
to grab the price field
and put that onto our
intensity option in the map.
Great.
So you can see here that we've
got some pretty interesting
detail on the map.
We can zoom in and out.
And we can see where the
most expensive properties
in our data set are.
But let's try and embed
this now in our website.
So, first, we're going
to click on the ellipses
and click Embed Chart.
There are two options
available to us
to grant access when
embedding a chart.
We can either use an embedding
key, which is a shared secret
to grant access to the chart,
or we can use no authentication.
This means that our chart
is visible to anyone
in the outside world
who has the URL.
For the purposes
of this tutorial,
we're going to use an unverified
payload, which allows anyone
to see the chart.
It's worth noting, however,
that Charts provides
the functionality
for you to ensure
your data remains secure by
passing a shared secret key.
It's also worth noting
that the verified signature
functionality requires
additional coding.
Copying and pasting the HTML
snippet will not suffice.
If you want to use
authenticated embedding,
you can read more
about that in our docs,
which will be linked the
notes for this lesson.
Now let's grab the iframe code
and paste it into our HTML file
so we can see how it looks
embedded in our website.
I'm going to paste the iframe
in between these two div tags,
save the file.
And let's have a
look at our website.
Great.
Our chart's embedded
in our site.
It looks pretty cool.
But what if our data
changes over time?
We have you covered.
The beauty of Charts is
that it's linked directly
to your Atlas cluster.
So we can set how often we
want the chart to refresh
from the chart's UI so
that, when people land
on our website, they'll
see a visualization that's
representative of the current
state of the source data.
MongoDB Charts provides options
to both manually refresh data
and configure the dashboard
to automatically refresh
within a specified interval.
These options allow
you to control
how current the data displayed
on your dashboard is.
And, as analytical queries can
be long-running and expensive,
we also allow you to specify
a read preference for Charts
to use when creating
your cluster,
so that the primary server
won't become impacted
by long-running queries.
The default read
preference is secondary,
which you can also specify an
analytical node for workload
isolation.
So let's recap.
Charts allows you to create
real-time visualizations
of data in your Atlas cluster.
You can use authentication to
control who sees your chart.
And you can also
specify a read concern
to allow charts about
read from secondaries
or an analytical node
to isolate workload away
from your primary.
You can also now embed charts
in your website or web app.