In this lesson,
we're going to look
at the new geospatial chart
types available in MongoDB
Charts.
So these charts are
a great way for you
to gain quick and visual
insights into your data stored
inside MongoDB.
MongoDB documents have a
rich set of data types,
such as dates, subdocuments,
arrays, Decimal128, and others
to provide data precision
and data affinity with what
that information represents
and how the application works
with that same data.
One of those rich data
types is the ability
to store geolocation
data, and there
are several different
types of analysis
that one can do using
geospatial fields.
Charts is built to
natively support and work
with the MongoDB document
model, and it connects directly
to your MongoDB cluster.
This means that we do not need
to go through ETL operations
to convert or
format data, or use
different connectors to
integrate with other BI tools.
Let's jump into the Charts UI
and have a look at the three
different type of
geospatial charts
we've added in this
latest release of Charts.
So from the Atlas UI,
let's jump into Charts
and create a geospatial chart.
So we have our m042 dashboard.
Let's open that up
and add a chart.
And as we're going to be looking
at our geospatial charts,
we're going to create
a geospatial chart
from the dropdown
and select Heatmap.
So we need to select our
data source from the top,
and we're going to use our
sample_airbnb data set.
And we're interested
in the address field.
So let's drag our location
onto the coordinates plane.
And for intensity, we're
going to use the price.
And we're going to
select the mean price.
That's a lot of
information, so let's say
we wanted to filter down
by a suburb in New York.
Let's have a look at
how we can do that.
So we add a filter, go back up
to our address, subdocument,
and select suburb.
Let's drag suburb
onto the Filter field.
And you can see, we have quite a
few suburbs all over the world.
So we'll deselect
all the suburbs
and let's have a
look at Brooklyn.
Great.
Here you can see we've
got a heatmap of all
the most expensive Airbnb
listings in Brooklyn
in New York.
It's pretty impressive, right?
Let's have a look at
the other chart types
and see what we can do.
So as we said, our heatmap
shows the most expensive areas
to rent an Airbnb in Brooklyn.
That's really nice,
but what if we
want to get more detail
on what type of rentals
we have in this data
and their price?
For that, we can
use a scatter chart.
So let's add a new chart.
Again, we're going
to select Geospatial.
And this time, we're going
to use a Scatter chart.
We need to select our
data set, which is
our Airbnb.listingsAndReviews.
and again, we're interested
in the address field.
So we're going to drag the
location onto Coordinates.
And we want our color to
indicate the number of bedrooms
in a listing.
So let's drag the number
of bedrooms onto Color.
And we want the size
to indicate the price,
so let's drag the price
field onto the Size.
OK, so we've got a wide
range of documents here,
and you might
notice that we have
a little message of
the top that says,
The maximum query
response is 1,000.
So let's go again and
filter by address.
So we'll drag
suburb onto Filter.
And again, we can see we've
got suburbs all over the world.
So if we deselect them
and select Brooklyn,
so now we've got
a map which shows
all the listings in
Brooklyn, and their price
is indicated by the size of
the circle on the scatter plot.
You may notice that we
only have properties here
listed with zero bedrooms.
So that's not quite right.
So let's turn the BINNING off.
And there you can see
that we have a list
from 0 to 4 for bedrooms, and
the size of all these circles
indicates the price.
And when we hover over
each individual listing,
charts will pop up and
give us more detail
on that actual listing or that
actual geopoint in our data.
That's pretty cool.
So this is really
useful information.
We can very clearly see the
amount of rooms and properties
available on the map.
There are a lot of properties
on Airbnb globally.
What if we wanted to see where
all of those properties were
and how many properties
were in each country?
Let's use the sample
data set in Atlas again.
And this time, we're going to
see how many properties are
in each region of the world.
To do this, we're going to
use the choropleth map, which
is basically a fancy
way of saying that we're
going to color countries.
So let's go back out
to our dashboard.
So this time, we're going
to create a choropleth.
So again, select
Geospatial, Choropleth.
We're going to select
our Airbnb data source
and all the fields
will load in the left.
So we're going to use the
address.county country field
and drag that onto Location.
And we're going to use
the _id value for Color.
We're going to use a
count of that value.
We're sure the _id is
unique in every collection,
so we can reliably use this as
a count for all the properties
listed around the world.
There are obviously a lot of
listings on Airbnb globally,
but from this map, we only have
a subset of those listings.
We can see that if we
hover over each country,
we will be given a map
of the amount of Airbnb
listings in that country.
That's really cool.
But this is just
a sample of what
you can do with the new
geospatial maps in Charts.
You can see that
these visualizations
can be very powerful for
insights into your data.
And best of all, it's
very easy and quick
to generate these charts.
This is just an example
of the information
you can easily
visualize from your data
in MongoDB using charts.
There's a lot more functionality
for you to explore.
The great news is that
you can experiment
with Charts for free on your
free tier Atlas cluster.
So let's recap.
Charts now allows you to
create three new chart types--
heat map, scatter,
and choropleth.
And best of all, you can
explore this in Atlas
using your free tier cluster and
the sample data sets provided.