The next stage we'll
learn about is $project.
$project, like $match,
is a vital stage
to thoroughly understand, to be
successful with the aggregation
framework.
Please don't think
of $project like the
projection functionality
available with the find query
operator.
While it is true, $project
is much, much more.
Not only can we selectively
remove and retain fields,
we can reassign
existing field values
and derive entirely new fields.
A common method or function
available in many programming
languages is $map.
It is a higher
order function that
applies some transformation
among a collection.
If $match is like a filter
method, $project is like $map.
Here is the basic
syntax for $project.
We've appended a
dollar sign to signify
that it is an
aggregation operator,
then open up with a curly brace
and close with a curly brace.
Between these two
braces is where
we use aggregation expressions
and perform field logic.
More on that soon.
Here is how we'd specify
values to remove and retain,
just like the projection
functionality available
with the find query operator.
This specifies that we wish
to remove the _id and retain
the name field.
Notice that since we have
specified a value to retain,
we must specify each
value we wish to retain.
Let's also keep
the gravity field
so we can see some
difference in real data.
And of course, an exception.
Here we can say we're getting
the name and the gravity field,
but we're also
getting the _id field.
The _id field is the only field
that we must explicitly remove.
All others will be
removed when we specify
at least one field to retain.
Also, it looks like whoever
put this data together
used the international
system of units, so let's
also just get the value.
An error.
One thing to keep in mind, once
we start diving into documents
selecting on subfields, we
must surround our arguments
with quotes.
There, the data we wanted.
$project is already showing
to be pretty useful,
but so far, it appears to
be identical to projection
available with the
find query operator.
Let's started exploring what
makes $project so powerful.
Instead of returning a
subdocument with just the value
field, let's directly assign
the value to the gravity field.
Here we can see that we are
indeed reassigning the gravity
field to now contain
the information that
was available at gravity.value.
We're prepending gravity.value
with a dollar sign.
This is one of the many
aggregation expressions,
and we're directing the
aggregation framework
to look for and
fetch the information
in the document
at gravity.value,
or a field path expression.
As discussed in the aggregation
structure and syntax lesson,
this is one of the
ways we reference
documents for information.
We can also create a new
field called surfaceGravity.
This isn't just renaming
the gravity field.
It's creating an
entirely new field.
Very powerful.
And we'll be using this
functionality a lot
through the course.
Let's have a bit of fun and
use the aggregation framework
to calculate a value.
I'd like to see
what my weight would
be on each main body
in the solar system.
I'm going to have to use an
expression to accomplish this.
We'll cover expressions in
much greater detail shortly,
but I'm going to break
this down since this
is our first time seeing
it, and the syntax
can catch people off guard.
I weigh about 86 kilograms.
Looking at our
previous results, it
looks like if I divide
the gravity of a body
by the gravity of Earth and
then multiply that value
by my weight, I can
find out how much I'd
weigh on every main body.
I'm going to have to use an
expression to accomplish this.
The first expression
I'm going to use
is the $multiply
arithmetic expression.
$multiply takes
an array of values
and multiplies them together.
So I know I need to
multiply my weight
times the ratio of a specific
planet's gravity divided
by the Earth's gravity.
That will look
something like this.
I know my weight is
about 86 kilograms,
so I can just hard
code that for now.
To calculate the
gravity ratio, I'll
need to use the $divide
arithmetic expression.
$divide takes an
array of two values
and divides the
first by the second.
Within $divide, I'll need
to reference the information
at the value subfield
within gravity.
Let's see what this
will look like.
Here we're using a
field path expression
to refer to information
within the document,
specifically the information
found at the value field
within the gravity field.
I know the gravity of Earth is
around 9.8 meters per second
per second, so I'll
just hard code that in.
So putting it all together,
we have the following.
All of this is
assigned to a new field
we create called myWeight.
Awesome.
We can see I'd weigh about
32.5 kilograms on Mars
and 2,404 kilograms on the Sun.
We're beginning to see
the power of $project.
$project is a powerful stage
of the aggregation framework.
Not only can we remove
and retain fields,
we can derive new fields and
reassign existing fields.
$project may be
used as many times
as desired within an
aggregation pipeline,
and it should be
used aggressively
to trim data out
of documents that
isn't required in order to
keep our pipelines performant.
Some key things to remember.
Once we specify one
field to retain,
we must specify all
fields we want to retain.
The _id field is the
only exception to this.
Beyond simply removing
and retaining fields,
$project let's add new fields.
$project can be
used as many times
as required with an
aggregation pipeline.
And finally,
$project can be used
to reassign values to
existing field names
and to derive
entirely new fields.