Now that we've discussed the
concept of what pipelines are,
and have given you an
overview of aggregation,
and structure, and syntax,
it's time we learn about one
of the most important
stages, $match.
The $match state is vital to
a successful and performing
pipeline.
He should come as
early as possible.
And you were free to use as
many $match changes as necessary
in your pipeline.
Here is a basic
syntax for $match.
Since it is an
aggregation operator,
we prepend a dollar
sign to the name.
Again, $match may be
used multiple times.
And virtually every
other stage can
be used after it, with a
few exceptions that we'll
cover later in the course.
Instrumental in understanding
$match and the context
of an aggregation
pipeline, I invite
you to think of $match as a
filter, rather than a find.
We configure the filters
in our $match stage.
And as documents flow in, only
those that meet our criteria
are passed further
in the pipeline.
Here, our $match stage will only
let circles and stars through.
$match uses standard MongoDB
read operation query syntax.
We can perform matches based
on comparison, logic, arrays,
and much more.
The only limitations are, we
can't use the $where operator.
And if we want to
use a $test operator,
the $match stage must be the
first stage in a pipeline.
If $match is the
first stage, it can
take advantage of
indexes, which increases
the speed of our queries.
Again, $match should come
early in our pipelines.
As a reminder and
for reference, you
can find a link to this
page just below the video.
We encourage you to bookmark
this page for future reference.
Here's an example
of $match in use.
If I ask you the following
aggregation, which
filters the solar
system collection,
allowing only documents with
types that don't equal star
through, I can see that I
get the results I expected.
To show that $match uses
the MongoDB query syntax,
let's use find to see if
we get identical results.
The same results.
Let's observe this another way.
First, let's count the
number of documents
with types that
don't equal star.
It should be eight, now let's
see how many documents make it
through our $match stage.
I'm going to use the utility
station this example called
count, that you'll
learn about later.
Here, we can see
that eight documents
pass through our aggregation.
Sorry, Pluto.
Lastly, $match does not have
any mechanism for projection.
With find, we can do
something like this
if we want to project out
the undescribed field.
Although this may seem
like a limitation,
we will soon learn about a
powerful stage that allows us
to do this and much, much more.
And that's it for $match.
Again, we encourage
you to think of $match
as more of a filter than a find.
Once documents are in
an aggregation pipeline,
and we're shaping them with
new fields and new data,
we'll be using $match heavily
to keep filtering documents out.
Some key things to remember.
A $match stage may contain
a $text query operator,
but it must be the first
stage in the pipeline.
$match come early in an
aggregation pipeline,
you cannot use
$where with match,
and $match uses the same
query syntax as find.