Ah, the many-to-many
relationship.
Here's the most
complicated relationship.
Or is it?
It can trick us, but
don't worry too much.
We can also trick it.
The many-to-many
relationship is identified
by documents on the first
side being associated
with many documents
on the second side,
and documents on the
second side being
associated with many
documents on the first side.
Looking at products
sold in our stores,
we can see that the given
store sells many items,
and each item is
sold in many stores.
This relationship can
trick you into thinking
it is a one-to-many
relationship, if you only
consider one side
of the relationship.
So ensure you ask the
question of associativity
from both directions, and
that you review your model
the few times, especially
for these less apparent
relationships.
In a normalized
relational model,
you can't actually link
two tables as many-to-many.
However, some design tools
can do the extra work for you.
Under the hood, an
additional relationship table
needs to be created to define
this relationship, sometimes
referred as a jump table.
It [? result ?] in breaking up
the many-to-many relationship
into two one-to-many
relationships
linked together by
our extra third table.
For example, keeping track of
the many-to-many relationship
between actors and movies
requires this table
in between our
actors and movies.
Misidentifying these
types of relations
means creating new tables and
incurring data migration costs.
This type of modification,
it's just not fun
with traditional databases.
MongoDB's flexible
schema easily allows
for this type of
schema modification,
and is more forgiving, as
scatter field can easily
be transformed into
an array field.
Let's take another example--
people and phone numbers.
Someone may have a
few phone numbers.
Some of these phone numbers are
exclusive, and some are not.
A family's shares the
home phone number.
So a person can have
many phone numbers,
and the phone number may
be owned by many people,
resulting in a
many-to-many relationship.
Well, not so fast.
We said we could also
trick this relationship.
We can treat the phone
number for a home
as uniquely owned by
each member of the family
by making copies of it.
Now, we have a one-to-many
relationship instead,
which removes complexity.
[INAUDIBLE] of this duplication,
if the family moves,
we must modify each family's
members phone numbers
separately.
Performing the same update
multiple times may not
sound like the right
design, however,
considered the
previous design, where
we store only one telephone
number value in the database.
If someone moves-- like
the child, for example--
and updates their phone
number, the update
will apply to all the
members of the family.
We don't get the
option to choose
between doing multiple updates
or one update that applies
to all [? records. ?]
Duplication is better,
in some occasions, especially
when you want to keep control
of [INAUDIBLE] data and when
you want to avoid joining data.
What are the different
ways in which we can model
this many-to-many relationship?
Similarly to the
other relationships,
we can embed the data
from the other collection,
or we can reference
the other collection.
Embedding in one side [? or ?]
[? the ?] [? other ?] is
a symmetric operation.
Usually we embed documents of
the last queried collection
inside documents of the
more queried collection.
Let's use the carts and items
from our product catalog
example.
The main entity is
the cart in which
we want to find the
items, not the reverse.
We embed the items in the cart,
because we always retrieve
this information together.
Having copies of items
in the carts period
is usually fine,
because they represent
the state of those
items at the time
they were added to the cart.
The same applies to
addresses and orders.
The address used for that
order at the time of the order
creation should be duplicated.
Observe that we need to keep
a collection for the items.
Even [INAUDIBLE] we embed
the items in the carts,
these items require [? a ?]
[? collection ?] to hold
their definition
for several reasons.
There will be several
other access patterns
in your application that utilize
items without [? carrying ?]
or needing the information on
orders they have been added to.
Item documents have different
life cycle than cart documents.
An item may exist without being
in any carts, like an actor may
be listed before
being in a movie.
This requirement of
keeping a source of input
applies only to this
specific representation
in the many-to-many
relationship.
In a one-to-many
relationship, if a user
is deleted with
their phone numbers,
we don't care about not
having this phone number
in any other document,
because the phone number only
belonged to this deleted user.
Instead of embedding, we
can also use references.
Let's start with
a representation
that keeps the references
on the side that
is the most often queried.
When a document is
retrieved, we will
get the list of all
the associated object's
unique identifiers.
Those are expressed in
[INAUDIBLE] [? field. ?] If we
need to add the
information on these,
we can use a second query, like
the [INAUDIBLE] [? IDs. ?] Or
we can use the [? dollar ?]
[? lookup ?] operator
to effectively do a join
between the object ID for stores
and the corresponding documents
in the stores collection.
This is very similar to join
operations in the SQL language.
The second representation of the
many-to-many relationship that
uses references is the
one where we keep--
as we may have
guessed-- the reference
in another collection.
Because this representation
[INAUDIBLE] [? arrays ?]
of references, they
are very similar.
However, there are
few differences.
Here, each store has a
field called item sold
that carries a
list of references
to the items sold
in the given store.
When we retrieve
an item, we still
don't know where it is sold.
We need a second query to
get this information, which
was another case in the
previous representation.
A query like the
following will return
to stores in which the item with
an ID of 10 or green MongoDB
T-shirt has sold.
So which of those two
representation that [? use ?]
[? references ?] should we use?
The representation that fits
[? our ?] queries and also
works well with the way we have
the documents in our system.
When we add an item, which
happens more often than adding
a store, is it better to add
the list of store in which it
is sold or to
individually update
all stores to add the item?
How we answer this
question will help us
pick the right representation.
To recap this lesson, ask the
right questions to ensure it
is a many-to-many relationship
that should not be simplified.
A many-to-many
relationship can be
replaced by two
one-to-many relationship,
but does not have to
with the document model.
Prefer embedding on
the most queried side,
prefer embedding for
information that is primarily
static over time and may
profit from duplication,
prefer referencing
over embedding
to avoid managing duplication.