The most interesting
type of relationship
is the one-to-many relationship.
First, because if
all our data is only
composed of one-to-one
relationships,
a spreadsheet application
like Excel could do the job,
at least for a small data set.
As for the many-to-many
relationships, most of them
can be expressed as two
one-to-many relationships.
We will describe
this in more detail
in the many-to-many
relationship lesson.
A one-to-many relationship means
that an object of a given type
is associated with n
objects of a second type,
while the relationship
in the opposite direction
means that each of the
objects of the second type
can only be associated with
one object on the one side.
As an example of
this relationship,
we use a person and
their credit cards,
or a blog entry
and its comments.
A person has n credit cards,
but each of these credit cards
belongs to one and
only one person.
Using MongoDB and
its document model,
give us a few ways to represent
this kind of relationship.
We can embed each document
from the many side
into the document
on the one side.
Or vise versa, we can embed
the document from the one side
into each document
on the many side.
Instead of using a
single collection
and embedding the
information in it,
we keep the documents in
two separate collections
and reference documents from
one collection in documents
of the other collection.
Using our product
catalog use case,
let's have a look at all
of these representation
of the one-to-many relationship.
The first representation
embeds the end documents
as an array of sub documents.
In our product catalog,
we keep the top reviews
of an item within
the item itself
because we want to display
these reviews once the item gets
retrieved from the database.
In other words, items are
the main objects we access.
And when we do so, we want to
bring in all the associated top
reviews with them.
For simple applications
where the number
of embedded documents
is small,, this
is the most common
representation.
The information that is needed
together stays together.
As for quartering on the many
side, which is now embedded,
we use multi key indexes,
which are designed for indexing
values in array fields.
The second representation
of one-to-many relationships
is to embed the document
from the one side
in each of the
documents associated
with it from the many side.
Let's use an as the
count of document
associated to our
document on the one side.
A good example will be an
address and the order's
delivery to the address.
Over time, because many
orders were delivered
to the same address, we have
a one-to-many relationship
between address and orders.
Application are more
likely to handle orders
than trying to figure out
everything shipped to a given
location.
The access pattern's focus
is on orders, not addresses.
As a result, it makes
more sense for us
to store the address, the
one side of the relationship,
on every order, the many
sides of the relationship,
rather than the
other way around.
This representation
is less often used.
The main disadvantage
of this representation
is that the embedded
object must be
duplicated in many locations.
However, the nature of
the embedded information
is static--
hardly ever changes-- such
as the shipping address
of the order.
It is, in fact,
better to store it
in the order document itself.
If the address for a given
customer changes in the future,
it does not that affect
all the previous orders
and where they got delivered.
The third representation
is to have two collections.
From the one side, we
reference the many side.
To do so, we need an
array of references.
In our zips collection,
which contain our zip codes,
we create an array of stores
where each element in the array
is a store ID value that
identifies documents
in the store's collection.
The referencing
representations are great.
If we can't or don't need to
embed the remaining entity
information, we get to know
all the references, the stores,
without making a second query
on the store's collection.
If the entries in the array
are descriptive enough,
we are saving
ourselves some queries.
However, in this
representation, we
need to keep in sync the area
references and their reference
documents.
If we need the
reference document,
we must also delete the
reference to this document.
MongoDB does not currently
support foreign keys or cascade
deletes, therefore there is
no way for all references
to automatically be removed
on document deletion.
The application must
perform all of this sort
of data management.
More commonly,
references are stored
in the documents on
the many side of a one
to many relationship.
For example, we may
have a collection
of zip codes, each
zip code adding
possibly many stores in it.
By adding a single
field called zip
in each of my
stores documents, I
can reference the document
in the zips collection.
Compared to the
previous representation,
if we delete a store, there
is no additional reference
to remove because the
reference is inside
the document we are removing.
To recap this lesson, when
representing one-to-many
relationships, there
is a lot of choices--
embed or reference and choose
the side between one and many.
Duplication may occur when
embedding on the many side.
However, it may be OK
or even preferable.
Prefer embedding over
referencing for simplicity,
or when there is a small
number of reference documents,
as all related information
is kept together.
Embed on the side of the
most queried collection.
Prefer referencing when the
associated documents are not
always needed with the most
often queried documents.