In previous lessons, we used the
word zillions, and introduced
a graphical notation
for representing
the one-to-zillions
relationships.
We extended the
crow's foot notation
by adding fingers the foot
in order to easily see
those zillions sides.
We should also use
the notation used
in this course
for cardinalities.
One thing is to identify
a relationship as one
to zillions, but better
still if you can quantify
that same relationship.
What is the minimum number
of associated document?
The most likely number
and the maximum number.
The maximum number is
what we care the most
about this relationship.
Zillions means something is
humongous, out of proportion,
so watch out for it.
The one-to-zillions
relationship is not
that different
relationship, per se.
It is a subcase of the
one-to-many relationship.
If we have a one to
many relationship
and the many's identified
as 10,000 or more,
we call that relationship
one to zillion.
This means we need to be
mindful of this relationship
every place we use
it in the code.
The last thing you want
the application to do
is to retrieve a document
and its zillions associated
documents, then process
the complete results set,
unless this you like
long coffee breaks.
So comment those sections
of the code with directives
on how to handle or reduce the
result set that comes back.
Given the cardinality
of these relationships
and the pressure on
computational resources
to process them, you
need to be on the lookout
for very large arrays
of subdocuments
or unbound arrays of references.
Looking back at
the representation
for the one-to-many
relationships,
we have a single one left--
the representation where
we referenced the document
on the one side of
the relationship
from the many or zillion side.
As you model this relationship,
make an effort to quantify it.
This will become
important, so that you
can understand the impact
of the maximum value
on your resources.
To recap the one-to-zillions
relationship,
it is a particular case of
the one-to-many relationship.
The only available
representation
is to reference a
document on the one
side of the relationship
from the zillion side.
And finally, pay extra
attention to queries and code
that handles zillions
of documents.