Commonly, a one-to-one
relationship
is represented by a single
table in a tabular database.
In general, the same
applies to MongoDB.
For example a
person's name, date
of birth, and email address
would be kept together
in the same document.
All these fields have a
one-to-one relationship
with each other.
A user in the system has
one and only one name,
has one and only
one date of birth,
and is associated with one
and only one email address.
When we group information
together, that
is in two different
entities, we refer
to this action as embedding.
This is in contrast to
grouping fields together
in a given entity.
We refer to those fields as
attributes of the entities.
The group fields can appear
side by side in the document.
Or we can use the
document model ability
to add sub-documents to create
logical groups of information.
This capability also allows us
to embed the document or entity
inside another one.
Alternatively to
embedding the information,
we can divide the fields
into many documents,
usually in separate collections
and reference one document
from another one.
Using our product
catalog use case,
let's have a look at all
these representations
of our one-to-one relationship.
The most common way to represent
a one-to-one relationship
between pieces of data
is to put the fields
with their values in the
document as described earlier.
Using the user's
collection as an example,
I would keep track
of a given user,
the address we use for billing,
and the default shipping
address if different.
A user as only one street
address, city, and zip
code for billing and
only one street address,
city, and zip code used as
the default shipping address.
This address information
may profit from a little bit
more organization.
Using the power of
the document model,
regroup each set of address
information into a subgroup.
Now, we still have a one-to-one
relationship, however,
we can't describe it as a
user having one and only
one billing address,
and having one and only
one shipping address.
The document is now more clear
and easier to understand.
This is the recommended
representation
of a one-to-one relationship.
Now let's say there is
a lot of information
about a given object
in our product
catalog like our stores.
In this example, the
list of staff employees
is kept within the
store document.
If most of the time
we create the stores,
we don't care about
the staff information,
we could separate out
this set of information,
placing it in a
second collection.
Consequently this adds some
complexity to our model.
So we should only do it for
schema optimization reasons.
Once we have retrieved
a given store,
we would find
additional information
like the manager and staff
by querying the store details
collection using the link to
the corresponding document,
as we do for any relation
expressed by a reference.
In the case of a
one-to-one relationship,
it is easy to simply
use the same value, here
our store ID in both documents.
We also want to prevent
this one-to-one relationship
from becoming a one-to-many
relationship for subdocuments.
In order to do so,
we need to ensure
that the values in
our store ID field
are unique for both collections.
To recap this lesson, for
one-to-one relationships,
prefer embedding over
referencing for simplicity.
Use subdocuments to
organize the fields.
Use a reference for
optimization purposes.