In this lesson, we'll examine
the type and cardinality
of relationships.
Most of the relationships
between units of information
can be classified as
one-to-one, one-to-many,
or as many-to-many.
The relation between a customer
name and their customer_id
is an example of a
one-to-one relationship.
A customer has one name, which
is associated with only one
customer_id, and
this customer_id
can only be used to identify
one customer's name.
The one-to-one
relations are often
represented by grouping
the two pieces of data
in the same entity or document.
Invoices associated
with the customer
are an example of a
one-to-many relationship.
A customer has many invoices,
and each of these invoices
is only associated
with one customer.
Finally, an invoice may
contain many products,
and each of these
products is likely
present in more invoices
than just the one
that we were looking at.
This is called a
many-to-many relationship.
However, is this the
best and complete
way to describe data
relationships, especially when
dealing with Big Data?
Let's say we look
at the relationship
between a mother and the
children she gave birth to.
Well, she may not have
children, have one, have two,
ten, however, the maximum
is pretty limited.
Very often there are
two children per family.
A different example
is Twitter users.
Some people just
started their account
and may have zero
or one follower,
while others may have 20,
100, or up to 100 million
if they are a celebrity.
In this case, many-to-many
is a very poor way
to characterize a relationship.
And this might be true for an
increasing number of examples
in the world of Big Data.
We could embed the
information about the children
in the document
representing the mother,
but it would not make sense
to embed 100 million followers
into one document.
What we need is a
more expressive way
to represent the one-to-many
relationship so that we know
that we are dealing
with large numbers
and avoid mistakes associated
with that distinction.
Looking at earlier examples, we
are missing some information.
The fact that the relationship
can be a large number
isn't reflected clearly with
the one-to-many description,
the value for the maximum
of many is not clear.
The most likely many value for
a given one-to-many relationship
is also missing.
Let's introduce this additional
symbol for the crow foot
notation, and call it zillions.
It is based on the many symbol,
however, with additional lines.
This relationship would read
as from one to zero to zillion.
Or in short, one-to-zillions.
This new symbol addresses
the identification
of large numbers.
And if we go to the trouble of
identifying the maximum number,
why not preserve this
information in the model?
For this we use a tuple
of one to three values,
with the following meaning.
Minimum, usually zero or
one, most likely value,
or the median, and the maximum.
If you have two
values they represent
the minimum and the maximum.
When a single value is used
it means the relationship
is fixed to that number.
We will use this
notation to describe
either arrays or reference
between collections
in our models.
For example, in this
diagram, a movie
has a minimum of zero actors
and the maximum of 1,000.
The movie has exactly two sets
of financial results, likely
the forecast and the actuals.
And the movie can receive
zero to 100 reviews,
with a median of 30.
Let's recap this lesson
one-to-one, one-to-many,
and many-to-many are
the usual cardinalities
found in design for tabular
or relational databases.
However, these are not enough
when dealing with Big Data,
so we add the notion
of one-to-zillions.
With the use of maximum
and most likely values
in the tuple form, minimum,
most likely, and maximum,
you can identify relationships
in a more precise way.