In this chapter, we will cover
auto express relationships
with MongoDB.
even if MongoDB is classified
as a document database,
the pieces of information
stored in the database
still have relationships
between them.
Old style databases
are often referred
to as relational databases.
However, NoSQL databases
are also relational,
so a better name for
those legacy databases
is Tabular, which highlights a
notion of columns and tables.
Understanding how to
represent relationships,
and deciding between embedding
and linking relationship
information, is crucial.
We have seen customers
embedding large arrays
where they should not have.
Other customers creating
too many collections
or too few collections.
Many of these customers
with subpar designs
ended up having huge
performance issues.
As we said in the
introduction of this course,
having a good model is the
single most important thing
you can do to ensure you
get good performance.
The face of identifying
and modeling relationships
correctly is a step that is not
optional in the methodology.
This chapter will
give you the knowledge
you need to do it right.
What are relationships
in the data model?
If you look at any schema
implementation in MongoDB,
or any other database,
you can observe objects,
referred to as entities.
The relationships
represent all the entities
and the other piece
of information
are related to each other.
For example, a customer
name and its customer ID
have a one to one relationship.
We often group this
type of relationship
in a single entity.
The relationship between a
customer and the invoice sent
to them is a one to
many relationship,
as one customer
has many invoice,
but each invoice only
belong to one customer.
And the invoices
and their products
have a many to
many relationship,
as the invoice referred
to many products,
and a product is likely
listed in many invoices.
If any of this is
confusing, don't worry.
We'll cover it all in great
detail in the following
lessons.
In this chapter, we will go
over these different type
of relationships and their
implementation in MongoDB.
We will start with the different
types and cardinalities that
describe our
relationships, then we
will answer one of the
essential question when
modeling unit of
information for MongoDB.
Should the information be
embedded or referenced?
If you are still feeling a
little uncomfortable with some
of the terminology
and parallels we
make between tabular
databases and MongoDB,
it is a great time to review
the lists of prerequisites
and references we presented at
the beginning of this course.
By the end of this chapter,
you will have all the knowledge
necessary to design
basic MongoDB models,
and you should
understand why people
say that MongoDB is the best
database for representing
relationships between
units of information.