Great.
What if we want to
make more complex rules
for some of our edge cases?
What if a represents a score,
and if a person doesn't
have a score yet,
what if we want
to start them with
20 instead of zero,
like what happens by default?
So if they get one point,
but they didn't have a score
before, they should now get 21.
We can now use the conditional
expression in aggregation that
says, if a was missing,
type of a missing,
then we give 21, otherwise, we
just add the value of a and 21.
Notice that that will also
cause that same 21 to show up
in an upsert case because an
upsert is a document where
the existing value
of a was missing,
and what if we wanted to
add another rule that says,
you can't get a score
higher than 100.
We want to cap everybody at 100.
Well, all we have to do is
wrap this conditional inside
of a minimum
expression, and says,
you get the lower of 100
or your calculated score,
so when we add 100
and one we get 101.
100 is less than that, so
your score's still 100.
Now, when you get something
other than a number,
you might want to
check for it, right?
The aggregation expressions let
you access the type of a field,
or you can even converted using
type conversion expressions,
or you can just let the
default behavior of some take
care of it, but then you might
want to save the current value
in another field.
So you could just set previous
a to current value of a and this
is what you will get then.
Pretty powerful.
Let's look at another example.
Here, I have a very
simple collection,
where across all
the documents, they
have fields like a, b, and
c, but not every document
has every one of those fields.
I could do a monthly update that
says, if a or b are missing,
they're numeric so
set them to zero.
If c is missing, set
it to the string unset,
and it would look
something like this.
We apply to all
documents multi true,
and we're going to
replace the document
with a merge of two objects.
Root is second, because
remember merge objects,
the latest value always
wins, and the first document
that's being merged is the
one with default values.
a zero, b zero, c onset.
So if root has any
of these fields set,
they will override
the default values,
otherwise, we are left
with default values,
and you can see that's
exactly what happens.
a is zero, b is zero
here, c is unset there.
That's pretty cool.
Let's look at the
most complex example.
Here, we have some
kind of, I don't know,
maybe internet of things
document, where for each,
let's say device id,
and date combination.
We have an array of
hours that specifies hour
and the value for
some particular thing
that we happen to be
collecting, and now,
if I receive for id X, day
Y, hour Z, some value, VAL.
How would I construct an update
that if the document doesn't
exist, it would
create it, meaning
I'd need to specify
upsert, but if it exists,
it would check the hour's array,
and if this hour didn't exist,
it would add it to the array,
so like an upsert for an array.
But if it did exist,
it would add the value
to the already existing value.
Sounds pretty complex.
So we probably need more space.
It's going to be an update
where the condition is dx--
oh, sorry, that should
be id X and day Y. Now,
we have some kind of
a pipeline, and we're
going to specify upsert true.
Now this pipeline,
as you imagine,
needs to check whether
or not the hour we
have is already in this array.
So here it is.
If Z, our hour, is
in the h.hour array,
now I wrap this in
if no so that we
use an empty array if the
document does not exist at all.
So if it's in the array, then
we're going to map or iterate
over the array h, and if
hour is not our value,
then just pass it through.
If it is the value, then
we're going to compute.
Our Z value is going
to be a sum of what's
already there, plus VAL.
Now, that's if Z already
was in the array.
If it wasn't, then we want
to concatenate the existing
array with our Z value, VAL.
Upsert true means the
record will be inserted
if it doesn't already exist.
It sounds pretty
simple and it is.
So let's recap.
Updates can be specified
either the old way
or with an aggregation
pipeline that
lets you transform
the existing document,
as all the fields from
the existing document
can be accessed to
compute new values.
Now, because it's doing
more complex computation,
it will be slightly slower,
but it is a lot more powerful.