Welcome back.
In this lesson, we are going
to talk about Z standard,
or ZSTD for short.
This is a fast, loose,
loose compression algorithm
that we added support
to on MongoDB 4.2.
Allowing options to compress
WiredTiger collections
and to compress the journal.
It was intended to target real
time compression scenarios.
But at a better compression
ratio than zlib.
The Z standard algorithm
did compress faster
than any of the currently
available algorithm
within the similar or
better compression ratio.
It defers from snappy
algorithm, as z
standard trades compression
speed for stronger compression
ratios.
These results show
that Z standard
is the best for
compression ratio,
and performs very well for both
compression and decompression.
The figure shows that disc size
of our Atlas sample data set--
a mix of data sets used for our
various courses and tutorials
in our documentation pages--
using various
different compression
algorithms available in MongoDB.
In MongoDB 4.2, snappy's
still the default compressor.
With Z standard zlib
being alternative options.
Z standard provides
the best compression
in this small data set of
five databases with 456,000
documents.
And internal testing for
MongoDB 4.2 Z standard
shows to give the best
compression ratio compared
to snappy or zlib whilst
only using a little bit more
of overhead than snappy.
There are two
options to configure
the use of Z
standard compression
for WiredTiger journal
and the collections.
The config file
option for collections
will only apply to new
collections created after Z
standard is set as an option.
We are very excited
about Z standard,
as it offers a great new
addition to compressing
your data in MongoDB--
balancing speed of
compression, decompression
vs. compression ratio.
But remember snappy is
still enabled by default.
Zlib and Z standard
are optional algorithms
that you can use for both your
journal and your collections.