Hi there.
In this lesson, we're going
to look at the new traffic
recorder feature which we've
introduced in MongoDB 4.2.
The traffic recorder
feature allows
you to inspect and record
commands sent to a MongoDB
instance and then replay
those commands back
onto another host
at a later time.
So why would you want to
do this, I hear you ask?
And that's a great question.
Replaying operations
can help you preview
how your MongoDB deployments
will perform on a production
workload in a brand
new environment,
such as with a hardware
migration, a new storage
engine, or a system
reconfiguration.
To explain why we made
this change in 4.2,
let's have a look at what we had
available in previous releases
to capture network traffic.
There are obviously tools we
can use like Wireshark and TCP
Dump, however, those did
not capture network traffic
specific to MongoDB.
And it don't provide
us with the ability
to replay the MongoDB
commands at a later date.
Prior to 4.2, if users
wished to capture
network traffic between a
client and a MongoDB instance,
they needed to use mongoreplay.
This worked well, but if you
were following best practices
and had your network
traffic secured
over the wire using
TLS, mongoreplay
could not capture this traffic.
So by moving the traffic
capture functionality
to the mongod itself,
we can capture traffic,
whether it's encrypted or not.
The new traffic recorder
writes to a traffic recorder
log which can then be
leveraged by mongoreplay which
takes the traffic
recorder log and replays
the operations on a mongod.
In order to capture traffic
on the mongod process,
the mongod needs to be started
with the traffic recording
directory parameter.
If you don't set this
parameter, the command
to start to traffic recorder
from the shell will fail.
Once the mongod is
started with this option,
we can start capturing
traffic directly
from the mongo shell with
the start recording traffic
command.
So once you issue the
command, the traffic recorder
will record all incoming network
traffic on the mongod side.
This network traffic is all
written to the traffic recorder
log which can then be
leveraged by the latest
version of mongoreplay to
be replayed on a mongod.
So let's recap.
Replaying traffic is
useful for testing.
You can replay traffic to
simulate production workloads,
to test a new environment, or
to inspect database operations.
Previous releases didn't support
the capture of network traffic
which was encrypted
over the wire.
The traffic recorder captures
traffic on the mongod side
to allow you to capture
any unencrypted traffic.
And that's a brief introduction
to our new traffic recorder
feature in MongoDB 4.2.