Hello.
I'm [? Astiya ?] Comski.
I'm going to talk about
updates using aggregation
pipeline, which is new in 4.2.
MongoDB 4.2 added
a powerful ability
to use aggregation
pipeline in both update
and find and modify commands.
Let's quickly review what
an update statement is.
And update operation
identifies the document
that should be modified and
specifies the modification
to be performed on it.
The filter or query
is the part that
specifies which document
should be updated.
This update portion
specifies how the documents
should be transformed.
And then you have access
to a number of options
to specify whether an
upsert should be performed
or whether it should be a
multi-update, et cetera.
The big change in 4.2 is
just to the update section.
So query and options
are unchanged.
Now, remember, update takes
the form of a document,
and you can have
two different types.
One is where the top level
fields are modifiers.
Those can be things like
set, ink, unset, push, add
to set, et cetera.
Those indicate
which fields should
be transformed in what ways.
A second type of
update is one where
you specify the
full document that's
going to replace the
existing document,
and that's called the
replacement type update.
One of the shortcomings
is that there is no way
to reference fields that
are currently available
in the existing document,
other than in a limited way
such as ink, which lets you
increment an existing value
and you get to
specify by how much
or push to an existing
array, et cetera.
The big change in 4.2 is now you
will be able to specify either
a document for the update
portion, in which case,
the behavior will be completely
unchanged from 4.0 or earlier,
or you can specify an array.
And that's new.
The aggregation pipeline will
specify what transformation
should be applied to the
existing document that's
being updated.
This means that you
will have full access
to the current values of all
the fields in the document,
and to all aggregation
expressions and operators
to manipulate the document
into the result you want.
Now, I said you can only
apply transformations
to the document being updated,
so you don't have access
to all of the aggregation
stages, only the ones that
take as input a single document
and output a single document.
So that would be
$addFields, which
adds new fields to
the existing document,
or if you specify a field
name that already exists,
it will overwrite
that one field.
Project an exclusion
mode, right?
Project will take the names
of fields followed by zero
or false to exclude, or unset,
from a current document,
and replace route,
which takes new route in
and then a specification
for the new full document.
We created aliases for these
three, which functionally
are exactly the same, but maybe
seem more similar to operations
that already exist in update.
$set is just like
$addFields, unset
takes an array of fields
you want to unset,
that's just like
exclusion project,
and $replaceWith
takes the document
that will be the
replacement document,
the complete specification
of it, for the new update.
Let's look at a
specific example.
First, let's consider
how an example we already
performed in
regular syntax might
look like when we switch
to new pipeline syntax.
Here, we have an update.
We're specifying
document with _id:1.
We're specifying that we
should increment field a by 1,
then we're specifying
upsert true, which
means if the document doesn't
exist, it will be created.
Let's see what effect that
has on some basic document
examples.
If the document exist
without field a,
a will be set to 1 as if
it existed would value 0.
If it was some number like 10
becomes 11, 100 becomes 101.
If the document didn't exist,
it will get created with _id:1
and a will be set to 1, just
like in the example where
a didn't exist.
And if the document exists,
but a is not a number,
you will get an error
because we cannot increment
the non-numeric
value by a number.
Now, let's write this using
the aggregation pipeline.
Most importantly, you can
see that these brackets
in the second argument
indicate that this
is an array,
therefore, a pipeline.
And now we do a $set, which
is, remember, just $addFields.
We said a to be the sum of
current value of a and 1.
The upsert option is still that.
We now expect to see
pretty much the same thing.
This is because sum, if a field
doesn't exist, just ignores it.
If it was 10 then we
get 11, 100 we get 101.
If the document didn't exist,
again, it's just like a being
missing.
The only difference
is when a was not
a number, because
in aggregation $sum
ignores non-numeric fields,
we will actually get a 1 here.
If we wanted to use
aggregation, but preserved
the behavior of non-numeric
fields giving an error,
we would use add instead
of sum, and then we'll
get an error that says that $add
only supports numeric things
or date types.
Things that can be
added, not strings.