In this lesson, we're going to
be talking about replicas set
nodes with different indexes.
Now I need to know
right from the start
that an architecture that
relies on secondary nodes
with specific indexes
is not very usual,
and is only useful for
a handful of use cases,
things like specific
analytics on secondary nodes,
or reporting on delayed
consistency data, or even
text search.
Those are a few of the
examples of use cases
that will benefit from
having specific indexes
on secondary nodes alone.
But again, this should
not be a common practice.
Once you have identified
a favorable scenario,
you also need to consider the
requirements for this setup.
These nodes should
not be allowed
to become primary nodes.
So we should configure them
either with priority 0,
becoming hidden nodes, or pure
simply delayed secondary nodes.
This is because if a
primary were to step down,
then your main
application could then
begin communicating
with replica set
members whose indexes are not
designed to serve its queries.
This will be a very
bad performance
scenario for your application.
Let's see this in
practice using an example.
Let's start by
creating a replica set.
I'm going to start by
creating the folders or DB
paths for each one of
my replicas set members.
I'm going to have our
data r 0, 1, and 2.
With the handouts
for this lesson,
you'll find a set of
configuration files
that I'll be using to
launch my replica set.
As you can see here, there
are three different files,
r0, r1, and r2, one for each
of the instances of my replica
set.
The next step is to launch
all of these instances.
But before that, let's see
in on which ports are we
running this particular
set of instances.
So my r0 will be listening
on port 27000, r1 on 27001,
and r2 on 27002.
So now that we've seen on
which ports my instances
are going to be
listening on, I can
go ahead and launch them all.
So I'm going to launch my r0,
my r1, and obviously my r2.
If
I look for the grep of all
[? MongoD's ?] running,
I can see that all my
instances are up and running
and very well,
thank you so much.
The configured replica set is
called M201 very originally.
Once all instances
up and running,
we can go ahead and configure
this particular replica set.
We are going to have one
primary and two secondaries.
One of the secondaries will
be configured with priority 0,
preventing it from
becoming a primary node.
So it can then select them to
create a specific index that
is going to be only
accessible if we run queries
through this particular node.
So let's go ahead and connect
to one of the members.
In this case, I'm
going to use 27000.
And I'm going to set this
particular configuration.
The ID [INAUDIBLE] the
replica set name, M201.
And here on hots 2, or ID 2,
and running on port 27002,
I will set this
member as priority 0.
This will be the selected node
to hold those specific indexes
that will be different from the
remaining nodes of my replica
set.
Once I have the
configuration in place,
I can now go ahead
and initiate it.
Once the configuration
is up and running,
I'll see that I will have my
hosts and one passive node,
here my priority 0 node.