In this lesson, we're going
to talk about the aggregation
pipeline on a sharded cluster.
Specifically we're
going to discuss
how it works, where
operations are completed,
and we'll also look
into how pipelines
are optimized to perform
well on sharded clusters.
Let's go ahead and talk
about how aggregation
works in a sharded cluster.
When we run aggregation queries
on a replica set or standalone
MongoDB, it's much
easier for the server
to reason about because all the
data is located in one place.
In a sharded cluster, since
our data is partitioned
across different shards, this
become slightly more difficult.
Fortunately, MongoDB has some
good tricks up its sleeve
to address these issues.
For example, here we have
the simple aggregation query
where I'm using match to find
all the restaurants in New York
state.
I'm then using group
to group by each state
and then average the amount
of stars for that given state.
Since my shard key
is on state, all
of the restaurants
in New York are
going to be on the same shard.
This means that the server
is able to simply route
the aggregate query
to that shard, where
it can run the
aggregation and return
the results back to the Mongo
S and then back to the client.
Very straightforward.
Now look at this example.
I've changed the query
slightly so we're no longer
using the match stage.
So now we're talking
about all documents
in our sharded collection.
Now since these documents are
spread across multiple shards,
we're going to need to do
some computing on each shard,
but then we'll also
need to somehow get
all of those results
to one place,
where we can merge
the results together.
In this case, our pipeline
needs to be split.
The server will
determine which stages
need to be executed
on each shard,
and then what stages
need to be executed
on a single shard where the
results from the other shards
will be merged together.
Generally, merging will
happen on a random shard,
but there are
certain circumstances
where this is not the case.
This isn't the case when
we use $out or $facet
or $lookup or $graphLookup.
For these queries,
the primary shard
will do the work of
merging our results.
And this is important
to understand
because if we're running these
operations very frequently,
then one of our shards,
the primary shard,
will be under a lot more load
than the rest of our cluster,
degrading the benefits of
our horizontal scaling.
Under these specific
circumstances,
you can mitigate this
issue by using a machine
with more resources
for your primary shard.
There are also some
cool optimizations
that the server
will try to perform
that you should be aware of.
Most of these will also apply
when you're not sharding,
but are still helpful to know.
Take this example.
Here we have a sort
followed by a match.
Now the query optimizer
will move the match
in front of the sort to
reduce the number of documents
that need to be sorted.
This is particularly
useful in sharded clusters
when we have a split
in our pipeline
and when you want to
reduce the amount of data
being transferred over the
wire to our merging shard.
Similarly, we can reduce
the number of documents
that we need to examine
by moving the limit
after a skip in front of it.
Notice that the query planner
updates the values accordingly
to support this optimization.
Other than moving stages
around, the server
is also able to combine
certain stages together.
Here we're going
to see where we're
combining two limits into one.
Same thing with skip.
And finally, we're seeing
the same thing with match.
Now all these optimizations
will automatically
be attempted by the
query optimizer.
That being said, I think
it's important to point out
these optimizations so that
you can more carefully consider
your own aggregation
pipelines and the performance
implications.
And that should give you a good
overview of the aggregation
pipeline on a sharded cluster.
Let's recap what we learned.
We discussed how the
aggregation pipeline
works on a sharded environment.
And specifically we looked at
where the different operations
happen when we're
using sharding.
And finally, we looked
at some optimizations
that the server
will try to do when
running aggregation queries.