So now that we have
our configuration
set up and running, it's time
for us to load some data.
I'm going to connect
to my replica set,
passing along the seed list.
And on database
M201, very original
again, and in
collection restaurants,
I'm going to load
my restaurants.json,
our famous file that
we've been working
with throughout this course.
After we inserted all documents
into are brand new replica set,
it's then time to
run some queries.
Once my 1 million documents of
restaurants is all loaded up,
I'll go ahead and connect
to my replica set.
I'm going to pass on the
replica set I'd name,
all the seed lists.
Once I'm connected
to the primary,
I'm going to just go ahead
and use my M201 database.
And I can see here that I have
my collections, or my recently
created restaurants collection.
Great.
And as you are already
familiar with it,
I'll have my
restaurants document,
where I have a name, a cuisine,
stars, address, and so on.
Let's say that our
application wants
to be able to query on
the restaurant name.
That's the main purpose
of our application.
A very lame application,
I have to say,
but the only thing
that he needs to do
is actually find elements in
this restaurants collection
based on the name.
This will be our operational
workload going forward.
To do that, we will probably,
as you've probably figured out
already, need to create
an index to support
such a query so it's optimized.
In this case, we only need name.
So let's go ahead and create
an index to do just that.
Once the index is
created, we will
see that this index is not only
available in the primary node,
but also on secondary nodes.
So by running this
particular query, where we're
looking for one of the
restaurants available
and explaining
the output, we can
see that this query
is actually supported
by our recently created index.
That's all good, but
let's connect to one
of the secondaries-- in
this case, the secondary,
which is a passive secondary
right now, priority 0--
and see if the same
behavior is present.
So once I'm connected to now
the secondary node, as you
can see here I'm
connected to 27002,
I will need to enable
reads from secondaries.
To do that, I need to express
the sets label k command.
Otherwise, as you
all know, MongoDB
does not allow you to do
secondary reads by default. You
need to explicitly enable that.
Once I do this and
run exactly the same
explain command on
the exact same query,
I can see that the same winning
plan and execution stats apply.
So the same index has
been used, and pretty much
the same winning plan.
So once I create
something on the primary,
it will be reflected
on the secondary nodes