In this lesson,
we're going to talk
about reading from
secondaries as it relates
to performance in MongoDB.
We're going to spend some
time talking about when
reading from secondaries
is a good idea,
and we're also discuss
when it's a bad idea.
Before we talk about
when it's a bad idea
to read from a secondary,
let's first talk
about read preference.
When we read data
out of MongoDB,
there's always an
associated read preference.
By default, this is
set to a primary,
meaning that all of our
reads will go to the primary.
There are several other read
preferences available to us,
but discussing what
each of these do,
and when you'd use them, is out
of the scope for this lesson.
For now, we're just going
discuss the read preferences
relevant to performance.
Like I said, by default,
mongoDB's read preference is
primary, meaning that
all reads and writes
are going to go in to
your primary server.
If you change the read
preference to secondary, then
all your reads will be routed
to one of the secondaries.
When your read preferences is
set to secondary preferred,
then that means your
reads will be preferred
to go to a secondary, but if
there aren't any available
then your reads will be
routed to the primary.
And finally, we
have nearest, where
we will read from the member
that has the lowest network
latency.
Now, it's super
important for you
to understand that whenever
we read from a secondary,
that there's the
chance that we're
going to be reading stale data.
Since all writes come
into our primary, when
we read from the primary,
we are guaranteed
to be reading the latest
state of our data.
This is called
strong consistency.
On the other hand, when we
read from the secondaries,
we're not guaranteed to be
reading the most up to date
copy of our data.
This is because our data
is being asynchronously
replicated to our secondaries
as writes occur on the primary.
This is called
eventual consistency.
So anytime that
our read preference
isn't set to
primary, the default,
we need to make sure that
our application or client is
OK with reading stale data.
Now that we understand
how we can change the way
we read our data,
let's discuss it
when it's a good idea to do so.
The two most common
performance scenarios
for reading from secondaries
is for offloading work,
and for doing local reads.
Let's talk about offloading
work onto secondaries.
A great example of
this is that you
might need to run an
analytics or reporting
job against your data.
This is a great example
because the queries required
to do analytics are generally
resource intensive and long
running.
We don't want to execute
these queries on our primary,
because the reads and writes
coming from our application
would be affected.
So with this set up, we get
the best of both worlds.
Our application continues
to read the most up
to date copy of our information,
just like it always has.
And we're also able to run
these long running and resource
intensive queries made
by our analytics job.
Now, I want to point out
that this is possible
because our analytics job is
OK with reading still data.
This is typically true
for batch operations,
since they don't expect to
be ran on the latest data.
Another great use case for
reading from secondaries
is for local reads in
geographically distributed
replica sets.
In this case, we have
two application servers,
one on the west coast
of the United States,
and the other on the east coast.
In this hypothetical
scenario, one of our members
is located on one coast, and
the remaining two members
are located on the other coast.
This is favorable when
application clients
need to have low latency, but
are OK with reading stale data.
We've discussed the two most
common best practice use cases
for reading from secondaries.
Now let's discuss why it's a bad
idea to read from secondaries.
First of all, it's not
generally a great idea to rad
from secondaries.
Secondaries exist to
provide high availability
to our database, not to
provide increased performance.
Sharding increases the
read and write capacity
by distributing read
and write operations
across a group of machines.
And this is often a better
strategy for adding capacity.
Two commonly
encountered bad ideas,
is to increase your
overall read throughput
by reading from secondaries,
and to read from secondaries
in sharded clusters.
Some people have
the false notion
that if their primary is
overworked by writes, then
they can offload their
reads to secondaries.
This is not the case, because
as writes come into our primary,
they're replicated
to the secondaries.
This means all members
of a replica set
have roughly about the same
amount of write traffic.
On the other hand, if a
primary is overworked by reads,
and you're OK with stale
data, then it's totally fine
to read from secondaries.
Now a really terrible idea is
to read from the secondaries
in a sharded cluster.
In general, it's a
very bad idea to ever
connect directly to a shard
to read or write data.
When we query the secondary
of a sharded collection,
we may return stale results
with missing or duplicated data
because of incomplete or
terminated chunk migrations.
So we should never do this.
We should never read
directly from a shard,
whether it's a primary
or a secondary.
But secondaries are
definitely worse.
And this should give
you a good overview
of reading from secondaries.
We discussed some different
good ideas with regards
to reading from
secondaries, but then we
also discussed some
bad ideas with regards
to reading from secondaries.