In this lesson, we
are going to talk
about some important
considerations regarding
Performance in a
Distributed System.
A distributed system in MongoDB
includes both replica sets--
or Replica Clusters--
for a high availability
solution, and Shard Clusters.
Shard Clusters are our mechanism
to allow horizontal scalability
of our data.
When working with a
distributed system,
we need to acknowledge
a few things.
When more than one machine
talks to each other,
latency will be involved.
So we need to consider latency.
Data is generally spread
across different notes.
It's either copies of the
data or different sets
of data in different charts.
There will be read
implications, so things
will be performing
in a different pace,
and obviously, also,
write implications.
Now, regarding
your replica sets,
let me reinforce a
message around this.
Please do use them in
production environments.
High availability is key to
guarantee that your service is
not affected by any potential,
and probable, system failure.
Having a replica set in place
is super, super important.
Apart from the main purpose of
providing high availability,
in case of failure of
a node, we will still
have availability of a service
provided by the remaining
nodes, but replica sets can also
provide a few other functions,
like offloading ventral
consistency data
to secondaries,
privileging your primary
for operational
workload, or having
specific workload
with target indexes
configuration on
secondary nodes.
More on this topic to be
covered in upcoming lessons.
The other side of distributed
systems in MongoDB,
with a purpose of
horizontal scalability,
is our Shard Cluster.
In our Shard Cluster, we
will have our Mongo assets,
responsible for routing
our client application
requests to designated nodes.
We're going to have
config servers.
These nodes are
responsible for holding
the mapping of our Shard
Cluster, where data sits
at each point in time, but
also the general configuration
of our Shard Cluster in its own.
And finally, we have
our Shard Nodes.
Shard Nodes are responsible for
holding the application data.
Databases,
collections, indexes--
these will reside
in these members,
and it will be here that
all major workload will
be performed.
Shard Nodes are in
themselves replica sets.
This is important since if a
Shard Note will be configured
as a replica set, therefore
with no high visibility
for that node, we could
eventually lose access
in case of failure for
a significant portion
of our application data,
and that's not cool.
A Shard Cluster does
require a few steps
to be properly configured,
but these are out
of scope for this
particular lesson.
But we will be
looking to what you
need to know before you can
figure your Shard Cluster.
Sharding is our horizontal
scalability solution,
which is great scaling strategy
for very large data sets.
You'll eventually reach the
limits of your vertical scaling
either in terms of cost
per performance gains.
But before you jump
into charting bandwagon,
you need to consider if you're
already reached those limits.
If buying another box
would not give you
that gain in terms of
performance and cost
that you are expecting.
Another important
thing is that you
need to understand
how your data grows,
and how your data is accessed.
Since Sharding works by
defining a key base ranges,
knowing how your data grows,
and knowing how your data is
being constantly
accessed allows you
to get into a good shard key.
And that's a very,
very important exercise
that you need to do.
Before doing any
sharding at all,
is defining what will be a good
shad key for your data sets.