In this lesson,
we're going to talk
about increasing your write
performance with sharding.
First, we're going to
discuss the differences
between horizontal
and vertical scaling.
After that, we'll
talk about rules
for picking a good shard key.
And finally, we'll spend
some time talking about bulk
write operations in
a sharded cluster.
So there are going to be times
when you have too much data
or too much throughput for
your database to handle.
And this problem is
solved by scaling.
And there are two
schools of thought
when it comes to scaling.
There's vertical scaling, and
there's horizontal scaling.
With vertical scaling.
The idea is that your current
server has too few resources
and is being overworked.
And to fix that
issue, you're just
going to buy a bigger, faster
machine with more CPU, RAM,
and disk.
This approach will
eventually reach a limit.
There's a ceiling to
how much CPU, RAM,
and disk one single
physical machine can have.
Moreover, the cost to scale
your machine vertically
is not linear.
When we buy a machine that
is twice as fast and powerful
as our current server,
our cost doesn't double,
it normally quadruples
or even worse.
With horizontal scaling,
on the other hand,
instead of increasing the
resources of your server
you just increase the
total number of servers,
effectively splitting
the workload
between many different machines.
When we reach the limit
of our current setup,
we just add more machines.
This is nice because we can
use commodity machines, where
we're simply buying more
of the same machine.
When we do this, our costs
scale nice and linearly
with our performance
requirements.
Now, it's important
to understand
that with a sharded cluster,
all of our reads and writes
are going to go into a mongos.
This is important to realize
because this mongos needs
to be able to determine where
to send the reads and writes.
This is achieved
with a shard key.
The shard key defines how
our data is partitioned
across different machines.
The shard key is either an
index field or an index compound
of fields that exist in every
document in the collection.
Now it's very important that
we evenly distribute our data
across these shards
so that we can evenly
distribute their load.
This is why picking
a good shard key
is the most important
part of sharding.
With a shard key, our
data is divided up
into bite size
pieces called chunks.
Each chunk has an inclusive
lower bound and exclusive
upper bound.
In this hypothetical example,
we defined a shard key
on last name and we
created three chunks.
The first chunk has a
lower bound of Abbott
and has an upper bound Fisher.
Now in reality,
with sharding, we'd
have far more chunks than this.
By default, a chunk's
maximum size is 64 megabytes.
Chunks will grow
close to this value,
and then they will be split.
So there are many
chunks existing on each
of the shards in a cluster.
Now in order for
our write throughput
to truly scale linearly
as we add shards,
we need to ensure that
these chunks are evenly
distributed across each shard.
To achieve this, there
are three key things
to keep in mind when
designing a shard key.
There is carnality,
frequency, and rate of change.
Let's take a look
at each of these.
With cardinality,
we're referring
to the number of distinct
values for a given shard key.
We want high cardinality.
The cardinality of our shard key
determines the maximum number
of chunks that can
exist in our cluster.
If, for instance, we were
to build an application that
was used only by people
who live in New York City,
and we were sharding
on state, then we
could have a maximum
of one chunk,
because both the upper and
lower bound of this chunk
would be New York.
And since we only
have one chunk,
this means we can
only have one shard.
So we want to ensure that our
shard key has high cardinality.
If you can't use a field
that has higher cardinality,
you can increase the
cardinality of your shard key
by creating a
compound shard key.
Now instead of having the
range of values just on state,
we have a range of values
for every state and last name
combination.