Next, let's talk
about frequency.
Not only is it
important that we have
a large number of different
values for our shard key,
but we also want to
make sure that there's
an even distribution
for each value.
If certain values come into our
system more often than others,
then we won't have an
even amount of load
across our cluster.
This limits the
effectiveness of our ability
to scale the handling of
incoming reads and writes.
If for example, we
built an application
where the majority of
the people using it
had the last name Brown,
then the throughput
of our application would
be constrained by the shard
containing those values.
We define this as a hot shard.
Furthermore, the
chunks containing our
frequently appearing values
would grow larger and larger.
Typically, when a chunk gets
close to its maximum size,
MongoDB will then split
it into two chunks.
However, if a chunk
is created where
the lower and upper
bounds are the same,
then that chunk is no longer
eligible for splitting.
We call these jumbo chunks.
These reduce the effectiveness
of horizontal scaling,
because we won't be able to move
these chunks between shards.
The issue of uneven
frequency can
be mitigated if we create
a good compound shard key.
You want to make
sure that the fields
at the beginning
of your shard key
still have high cardinality.
But by compounding
the key, we're
able to effectively
distribute the frequency
of popular values.
And finally, we
have rate of change.
Here, we're going
to talk about how
our values change over time.
The key here is that we want to
avoid monotonically increasing
or decreasing values
in our shard key.
Monotonically means in a
way that either is always
increasing or always decreasing.
The classic example
of this is obectID.
Because of the way that
objectID is designed,
new object IDs will
always increase in value.
Keep this in mind
if you're using
underscore IDs default
data type, objectID,
as your shard key.
As you can see, when we have
a monotonically increasing
shard key, all of
our writes are going
to the same shard, the shard
that contains the chunk where
the upper bound is max key.
As you can see, when we have
a monotonically increasing
shard key, all of our writes
are going to the same shard.
This is the shard that
contains the upper bound
of max key, which is often
referred to as the last shard.
If we were to have a
monotonically decreasing
value, then all of
our writes would
be coming in to this
shard, the shard
where the lower bound is set
to min key, our first shard.
Now, its OK to have
a monotonically
increasing value in your
shard key, as long as it's
not the first field.
Adding a monotonically
increasing value
to the end of our shard key
actually is a great idea,
because it increases the total
cardinality of our shard key
since it's guaranteed
to always be unique.
Now let's spend some
time talking about bulk
writes in a shard cluster.
When we make bulk
writes into MongoDB,
we have to specify whether
we want those writes
to be ordered or unordered.
With an ordered bulk
write, the server
is going to execute these
operations one after another,
waiting for the last
response to succeed
before executing the next.
If an operation
fails, we immediately
stop the bulk insertion and
report back to the client.
With an unordered
bulk write, the server
can execute all these
operations in parallel.
Now, with a sharded
cluster, ordered
bulk writes can be an
issue because we have
to wait for the last
operation to complete
before we can execute the next.
While both replica
sets and sharded
clusters would both
work in this way,
the difference between the
two is that in a replica set,
these operations will
be processed entirely
in one machine, the primary.
While in a sharded
cluster, we are
bound to the response
time of each shard.
So with a sharded
cluster, the latency
in between executing an
operation and it's response
is increased, since the
write is being performed
on a different machine.
On the other hand, with
an unordered bulk write,
we can execute all
of our operations
in parallel, maintaining
the distributed benefits
that we get with
a sharded cluster.
It's important to note
that with a bulk write
in a sharded cluster,
the Mongos is
going to need to deserialize
these write operations
into the corresponding nodes.
This means that the
mongos will have
to send each write operation
to each individual shard.
And that should give you a
good overview of increasing
your performance with sharding.
Let's recap what we've learned.
We talked about the differences
between horizontal and vertical
scaling.
We also discussed
some important rules
to keep in mind when you're
designing a shard key,
as it's the most important
part of sharding.
And then finally, we discussed
bulk inserts and some
of the differences
that you'll see
when doing bulk inserts
on a sharded cluster.