What would actually
be interesting to do
is allow our system to
run special analytics
queries on this node alone.
Queries that do not
serve any operation
workload therefore never going
to be run on the primary node.
We can do this by
creating such an index
on a particular secondary.
For that, what we will do is
just shut down our server.
Once the server is down, we'll
bring it up as a standalone.
To do that, I need to reflect
the exact same DB path.
The port could
potentially be different,
but let's keep some
consistency here.
But the important thing is
that we are loading a MongoD
using the same
previously set up r2 DB
path to load this machine
without a replica set
configuration in place.
So bringing it up as
a standalone node.
Once I do that, and I connect
to the nodes on port 27002,
I can confirm that this
instance is no longer running
on replica set enabled mode.
Not running with --replSet.
Also telling me no replication
enabled, which is great.
This is exactly what we wanted.
So let's create a
specific index to support
our analytical query.
In this case, we want to be
able to index the full address
information and the
restaurant's type of cuisine.
So for that, we're going to we
creating an index on cuisine
and all members of our address
sub documents, street, city,
state, and zip code.
Once we do that, and
as you can imagine,
this is going to be a large
beefy index, that is only
going to serve a set
of specific queries
from the analytical workload.
If we then run our
query, that looks
for example for
cuisine that starts
with medi for Mediterranean,
and in a given address zip code
range, which all zip codes
start with the digit 6.
If we explain this
query, we will
see that our recently
created index is, in fact,
supporting our query,
and therefore being
used to optimize
search types of queries
like this one, where we are
using a regex for the zip code
and another regex for cuisine.
So apparently we've
done our job here.
So let's go ahead and shut
down the server once again.
Once we shut down the server,
we can then relaunch our MongoD
by just basically relaunching
with the configuration file
that it previously sets.
Once we have that
up and running,
we can then connect
again to our replica
set by passing along the set
list and the replica set name.
Once connected to the primary,
let's use our designated
database, which is M201.
And if we run the previous
analytical query that
looks for cuisine and zip
code in a range using regex
as we've seen before
on the primary node,
we will see that we are
no longer using the index.
So what happened?
Did our index just
run away scared?
No, not at all.
Our brave index will
only be utilized
if we run this query on the
designated secondary node.
So let's do just that.
Let's go ahead and connect
again to our 27002 priority 0
passive node.
Once we connect it, we need
again to enable reading from
secondaries with
sets labelled k.
And if we run the query again
now under a replica set,
no longer in a
standalone mode, we
can see that our index
is being used to support
this particular query.
Let's recap what
we learned today.
Again, let's reinforce
that it is not a usual set
up for our indexes.
The main purpose
of our replica set
is to enable high availability.
Therefore, all nodes should
be configured homogeneously.
It is a very useful set up
for attending analytical,
reporting, and text-based
search kind of workloads
on secondary nodes alone.
You should prevent
your secondaries
that hold those indexes
to ever become primaries.
If they do, given the nature
of the indexes, the expected
performance of your
system, especially
in what right
workload is concerned,
will be considerably impacted.
So be careful about that.
But then again, great
for analyticals.
Not very usual, but awesome.
And that's what we learned
today on replica set
nodes with different indexes.