Now as you can see
from this diagram,
once you have a shard
cluster in hand,
there will be a bunch
of different nodes
that you need to consider.
And with those nodes will
come some communication,
and therefore latency.
The client application
will talk to our MongoSes.
The MongoSes themselves
will establish connections
with config servers to fetch
all the configuration of all
your shards, and obviously
with the shard nodes
to retrieve the information
requested by the application.
So there's a lot
of communication
between all different elements
of this topology for a given
shard cluster.
Now, all of this communication
and the fact that the nodes can
be spread apart from
each other, latency
will have an impact in your
application performance.
As you can imagine, not
only the fact that you're
going to have different
nodes talking to each other,
but also within the
replica sets themselves,
there will be some entropy
caused into the network
by the replication mechanism.
As you can imagine, having to
talk to a single replica set,
or with a different
set of shard nodes,
will have its
latency consequences.
There are architectures
that try to minimize
the impact of latency in
your application given
a shard cluster.
Things like co-locating a
MongoS within the same server
as your application server to
minimize the number of network
hoops required to
access the shard nodes
are some of the strategies
enforced to minimize
the impact of latency.
And if the nodes are
correctly connected
without passing through
very slow or latent or even
low-bandwidth network
segments, then the effect
of latency in your overall
performance of a distributed
system will be marginal.
However, the speed of
light limit is still there.
And if your application
server sits in Barcelona,
tries to reach a shard node that
is placed, for example, in Palo
Alto, then this will not
be done without paying
the latency toll.
And this drives us to
another important aspect
of working with
distributed systems,
especially in how
reads are concerned.
In MongoDB, there are two
types of reads that we
can perform in a shard cluster.
Scattered gathered,
where are we ping
all nodes of our shard
cluster for the information
corresponding to a
given query, or routed
queries, where we ask one single
shard node or a small amount
of shard nodes for the data that
your application is requesting.
These two different types
of reads, routed queries
and scattered gathered will
have two different performance
profiles.
With scattered gather,
we will pay the price
for asking everyone
for the information
that we need to reply
for a single query,
while in routed
queries, we only need
to ask one or a very
small set of the elements
for all the data that we need.
The difference will be based on
if we are using the shard key
on our queries or not.
If we are not using
the shard key,
we will be performing scattered
gathered queries, where
the system is not
able to determine
with exact precision
which of the nodes
contains the information that
you need to satisfy your client
request, while in
routed queries, that's
completely different,
by using the shard key,
our MongoSes can
pinpoint exactly which
shards contain the information
relevant for our client query.
Sorting in a sharded cluster
involves a few hurdles.
From the application
perspective,
this is totally transparent.
It works exactly in the same way
as a single node replica set.
You do not need to change a
single comma in your code.
But from within
the shard cluster,
things change a little bit.
After you [INAUDIBLE] the
query that contains the sort,
the MongoS will then
drive the request
to the designated shards
and locally a sort
will be performed.
Once that local
sort is performed,
then a final sort
merge will need
to occur in the primary
shards of our database.
Once that sort
merge is performed,
then we return back the
information to our clients.
The same set of
operations and logic
will be applied with the
skip or even with the limit.
The application will send
their query to MongoS.
MongoS will select
the designated shards,
and local skip and
limit will be performed.
And once those results
are done, a final merge
of that result set is
performed on the primary shard.
And then the result is
sent back to our clients
through the MongoS.
As you can see, there's
a few more steps
in the overall chain
of requests that
need to be attended
by the shard cluster
before providing back a correct
answer in terms of limit
and skip, but also
in terms of sorting.
Let's recap what
we've learned today.
There are a few things that you
need to know before sharding.
Have you reached the vertical
scaling limit of your cluster?
Have you considered how
your data is growing,
how it is accessed, and
determined a good shard key.
Latency will be involved
in a distributed system.
There's no way to avoid it.
It might be minimized with
good architectures to do so,
but it will still be something
that you need to consider
from a performance perspective.
Scattered gathered
and routed queries
are two completely
different profiles in terms
of read response in
a distributed system,
so pay close attention to that.
Sorting, limit,
and skip will also
have its hurdles within
a given distributed
system for correctness and
to reflect the exact request
that our clients are asking for.
And this is all we have on
performance considerations
for distributed systems.