In this lesson, we're going to
be looking at different ways
to add an index to a collection.
When you get to
building indexes,
you're already pretty
deep into the process.
You've done a good
job of figuring out
that an index is missing.
And now it's time
to fix the problem.
However, before we
start, there is something
we have to remind ourselves.
Building an index means
doing a collection scan
on the collection you're
adding the index to.
As we all know,
collection scans are evil
and can have a severe impact on
your performance in production.
We're going to try
to minimize that.
First, we could build an index
on the Primary from the shell.
Building on the Primary
in the foreground is easy.
You simply build the
index and the creation
will automatically propagate
to all other members
of the cluster
through the oplog.
The index will build in
the foreground, which
will have the
drawback of locking
your collection for rights.
The alternative method is to
build in the background, which
is a non-blocking
operation for the rights,
but it takes a little longer.
It's usually
preferred to building
in the foreground for
a production system,
all else being equal.
Do note that the default is
to build in the foreground.
So you have to explicitly
say, build in the background.
If you don't want
to use the shell,
you can use Compass to do
either of the first two methods.
The fourth option is
to build the index
on each member separately
using a rolling upgrade method
that we'll see.
And the fifth and final
option, and by far my favorite,
is to do the previous
rolling upgrade
procedure without
getting our hands dirty
using Cloud or Ops Manager.
If you have a managed
cluster or replica set,
meaning a set of machines
controlled by automation
under a Cloud Manager
or Ops Manager,
you can let those systems
add the index for you.