OK, sometimes you'll
be going along,
your database is looking great,
and then all of a sudden things
get slow.
Queries are taking forever
and you're not sure why.
In this lesson we'll look into
some of the common reasons
why this might have happened.
We're going to look
into long running
queries and some possible
explanations, index builds,
and write contention.
So the first thing you're
going to want to look at
is, to check to
see if you're doing
a lot of collection scans.
Maybe your application has
just deployed a new query
that doesn't use an index.
Or maybe that new DBA
just dropped an index.
How do you check
this hypothesis?
You have a few places to look.
So the server logs should
show any long running queries.
Db.currentOp will show
whatever is going on right now,
including long running queries.
And, of course, you can
always turn on the profiler.
But if the issue is
performance, that
may not be a great
idea because it's
going to slow down your
system even further.
Now once you know it's
a collection scan,
you can simply
build a new index.
But it's also
possible that you've
got a new query
that uses an index,
but it's not using it well.
For example, maybe
your database is
doing regex queries
that are not anchored
at the beginning
of a string field,
so it has to do a full
index scan with every query.
This can actually be
fixed, if you anchor it
to the beginning of the
string, so that it only
has to search a
subset of the index.
It's also possible that you're
looking at inefficient index
usage.
This is where you're
using an index,
but maybe not
using it very well.
This can be harder to
find because if logs
capture these queries, they
still show index usage.
In this case, you may need
to go through and explain
the queries, to see
how efficiently you're
returning them.
So that summarizes how
to find and respond
to long running queries.
Again, if you see a
sudden performance drop,
it's probably because
your application
is fielding a new query
or because someone
dropped an index.
If you want more details,
you can find them
in M-201, the MongoDB
performance course.