Another issue that can come
up is write contention.
This is a complicated issue.
So let's draw it out.
When a document is updated in
the WiredTiger storage engine,
it uses a
copy-on-write approach.
First, a new version of
the document is prepared.
During this process, only
the original document
is visible to any applications.
Then the update is committed
by switching a pointer
in a single CPU operation.
And suddenly, the old
version of the document
is no longer available,
but the new version is.
This is how things work when
everything's going smoothly.
And it's how you
can simultaneously
both read from and write to the
same document at the same time.
You simply read
from the old version
while the new version
is being prepared.
And once the new
version is in place,
queries will read from that.
This method, known as
multiversion concurrency
control, is also how
the storage engine
is able to achieve
so much throughput.
However, an issue
occurs when you
have multiple writers all trying
to update the same document
at the same time.
In this case, the writers
don't realize that other writes
are updating the document.
There aren't any locks.
It just uses optimistic
concurrency protocols.
So what happens?
Here, I'm drawing
what would happen
if three writers were trying
to simultaneously update
the same document.
Each of them would begin
preparing a new document
on its own.
They all devote system
resources to the update,
including CPU cycles
and allocation of RAM.
But only one update can happen.
Maybe in this
example, it's v2-3.
The pointer is flipped
and these versions fail.
But those writes
still need to occur.
So if they're valid, they'll
write to this version
of the document.
Now, in this example, two
writes had to be repeated.
But you can imagine a scenario
where you have 20 writes
and 19 of them have
to be repeated.