Talking about getting
our hands dirty,
let's do that right
now by looking
at those different methods
of creating an index.
First, I'm going to
prepare my system.
Let's prepare this setup.
We're going to want a
three-member replica
set that starts on port
30,000 of localhost.
And we'll prepare a
collection with some data
that we can build indexes on.
We'll also build one
index just to make
it feel like a regular
production system.
Great.
And let's see what
our data looks like.
In this example,
we'll want to add
an index on the Social Security
number to our collection.
First, let's look at
the existing indexes.
Great.
We can see that there's no index
on Social Security numbers.
So let's create it.
The index has been created.
And the command reports
the number of indexes
before and after the
index creation process.
This looks good.
The index, by the way, is also
building on the secondaries.
I can connect to one
of those and confirm.
I'm going I want to
give myself permission
to read from a secondary.
I can connect to one
of those and confirm.
I'll give myself permission
to read from a secondary.
And here's my index on
Social Security number.
Next, let's go back to the
primary, drop the index,
and create it in the background.
It looks pretty much the same
as the previous operation.
So how can we tell
that the index
was built in the background?
One way to find out is
to look into the log.
I'm going to let bash
do the work for me.
And there's our log file.
Let's look at the index options.
And here, the index got built in
the background with background
true.
I can also see this if I look
at the command components.
And here, once again, is
our createIndex command
with background true.
Interestingly, in
the commands, I
can also see my
dropIndex command.
A difference between the
background and foreground
builds is that this command
will yield the collection
locks more often, letting
other [? rights ?] happen.
Again, for that
reason, you would
prefer building an
index in the background
instead of building it in the
foreground on a production
system.