In this lesson, we will look
into a common issue regarding
applications.
Response time degradation.
What we mean is that
the application response
time, measured generally
in milliseconds,
will become higher
as time goes by.
And there's a couple
of factors that
will drive you to get into
a situation like this.
So in this lesson,
we will look into how
to determine the culprits,
how to fix them, and more
importantly, how to avoid them.
There are a few scenarios
that may lead to response time
degradation.
There are a few culprits that
we might have to look into.
Those scenarios can
be, the working set
exceeding RAM, queries taking
longer as the data set grows,
growing pool of clients,
unbounded array growth, or even
excessive number of indexes.
We're going to be looking
to a couple of those--
working set exceeding
RAM and queries taking
longer as the data set grows.
Those are the two
more common ones
that we see coming in
to our support queue.
When are working sets,
which compromises
the data set that is most
often accessed by our client
application, requires more RAM
than the server has available,
or configured, one of
the possible symptoms
is that the application
becomes slower over time
and the response time
of incoming requests
takes longer and longer.
Let's see an example.
Let's start by creating our
folder our dbpath, which
is going to be our rtd.
I'm using our vacant
box to do this,
so I recommend you
guys if you want
to follow along to do the same.
So in this dbpath we are going
to be launching a new MongoD.
Now, within the
handouts of this lesson
you will find this
file, which should
be placed under
the shared folder,
and it's called rtd.cfg.
And you can see there are
some instructions on how
to run our MongoD.
Now, as you all know by
now, what we need to do
is, basically, call
our MongoD, pass along
the file, which
should be on shared,
and it should be
named rtd-config file.
There we go.
Once this is up
and running we will
be able to see that we have
a clear MongoD up and running
in our system.
And there it is.
Now, if you look closely
into this rtd config file,
you will see that
we are setting are
wiredTiger size to a
very small value, only
0.25% of a gigabyte.
Roughly, or exactly, 256
megabytes of cache size.
Now what we are trying
to simulate here
is when you do not have enough
resources for your MongoD.
And we will be loading
some large data
set that will be requiring
a little bit more
than this to operate correctly.
Now that we have our MongoD
up and running, let's go ahead
and import a data set.
The londonbikes data set.
You should also have
access to that data
set through the
handouts of this lesson.
Once I put it up
and running, you'll
see that I'll start
restoring that data.
Since we configured
this instance
to run only on 256
megabytes of cache size,
this may take longer
than expected.
In normal conditions,
with a bit more memory
to allow us to
operate correctly,
this process should take a
very, very small amount of time.
Or not such a big
amount of time.
But given the fact that we
are using a very tiny amount
of memory, the minimum
that MongoD requires,
this will take a
little bit longer.
How can we detect that into
a production environment?
Let's go into a different tab
and let's connect to this box.
Now, if we connect to this
machine using our mongostat
we will see some interesting
data coming along.
There's a bunch of
information here
that I might not be
so much interested in,
but I'm starting to see that
my used memory is pretty
high, in my dirty memory,
the amount which is currently
used, pretty low.
And this might be
an indicator that we
don't have enough
space for accommodating
all the data set that we need.
But let's make this a
little bit more streamlined.
With this instruction
over here we
are trimming out only the
fields in the output that we
are really interested in.
We are going to be looking to
the time, the amount of memory
which is dirty--
or the amount of memory which
is currently being used--
the number of inserts,
the queues for
reads and writes, and then the
active readers and writers.
Once we do this we can see that
we have more sane information
in front of our eyes.
And we can see here that our
dirty amount of information
and our used amount
of information
is quite off balance.
Generally, what we see is
that this value of used memory
is quite smaller than it
is showing right here.
And it's much more
balanced with the amount
of dirty information.
Dirty means, all the pages,
or memory allocation,
that is constantly being used.
So if we are doing a bunch
of inserts, around 8,000
or between 8,000 and 7,000,
and we are only dirtying up,
let's say, this small
amount, but we're still
using a quite significant
amount allocated--
meaning that we are using this
amount of information in RAM--
there's probably,
or more likely,
the indicator is that our
total data set is exceeding
the amount of memory available.
We know this because we are
simulating that situation.
But in a production
environment if you would not
know exactly what was
going on and if we just
see a spike in the response
time per application
that will probably be the cause.
If we don't have enough memory
to allocate all of our data
sets this will imply
that we are paging out
a lot of information.
So the actual amount of
dirty pages coming in
is not being able
to be allocated
on our total amount of
memory, and therefore, we
will need to page a
bunch of information
out to be able to accommodate
new incoming data.
We can also see that from
our queues and active readers
and writers if we don't
have a lot of pending jobs
to do it means that our
system is actually quite idle.
It just processes
everything that it needs
to process, no big problem.
The problem here is that
the response time taken back
to the client and say, OK,
I got that and I read it,
or I wrote it.
It's taking a lot
more time because we
need to make space in our
memory to actually allocate
the memory, or the data, which
is incoming to the server.
Now, if we go back and shut down
the server in a controlled way
by emitting the shut
down server command
and we edit our
shared config file,
and raise the level of this
cache size to two gigabytes,
and we run again, or
relaunch back our MongoD,
and try to reload the
information that we
got before--
the same exact data sets, we
are actually going to say,
we are going to
drop it so we don't
have any errors of, for
example, unique key violations--
And if we look back into
our mongostat again,
we start seeing a completely
different scenario
where the amount of used data
and the amount of dirty data
are pretty much aligned.
And also as you can see from
this table here indicating
amount of inserts per second
that we might be getting,
which we already
finished for example,
it's a clear indicator
that things went way,
way faster than before.