If we run a exact
same query again,
looking for all of
my Barcelona friends
and iterating a few times over
the result set, as I can see,
I getting a lot of
this information.
So if we look into
the data again
and we only look for the queries
that we are running with,
we might be again
[? led ?] to believe
that our total amount of time
that the application needed
to wait for a response was
actually 0 milliseconds again.
Now, a way to avoid
any confusion--
and let's stop our
profiling for a second.
Let's put it back to 0.
And let's say it's back into the
100 milliseconds default level.
Once we are in this
situation and if we
want to fully understand
how much time is
our queries actually
taking, we need
to call our explain command.
Once we run this, saying that
we want to execute our query,
we will see exactly
the statistics
needed to determine if our
query is actually taking
the appropriate amount of time.
Now, in this case
here, what we can see
is that we're returning
roughly 167,000 documents.
And the total amount of
documents is 1,001,010.
And the actual execution time
in milliseconds is quite high--
is around 356 milliseconds.
If you all know, MongoDB will
log this as a slow query.
So we can see that there's
been a progression in terms
of the response time taken by
this operation as time goes by
and as we add more
data to our system
because frankly, this
is not optimized at all.
It's a collection scan.
So we could do way
better than this.
We can also get this
information from our mongo logs.
If we run our Mongo logvis
against our MongoDB log,
say no-browser, and specifying
this output as the file
that we want to analyze,
if we open our rtd.html
from our local box,
we will be able to see
that that exact operation
are captured in our mlogvis.
As you can see here, this
operation here alone,
the one that is a command that
does a find and the filter
equals our city of Barcelona--
it's actually taking
a huge amount of time.
To complete, it took
around 235 milliseconds--
so a quite significant
amount of time
to complete a single operation.
Now, to solve this
operation, we will need
to connect back to our mongod.
And once in our mongod in this
particular collection, where
we have my friends, I will
need to create an index
over that field,
which is my city.
And once I have
this index created,
if I run my query
again with the explain,
I would see a dramatic change
in terms of the execution stats.
The total amount of time
taken for the execution time
is now a third of
the previous one.
And I have a much
more optimized query.
Now, obviously, we should
not sit tight only on this.
We probably could do way better.
Let's say, for example,
that what I'm showing
is not at all
relevant to my system.
What I only need is
the name of my friends.
And I don't even need
their underscore ID field
because I'm not going
to treat it at all.
I can filter that out.
So if I execute again the
query with my execution stats,
I'll see that there's
even more benefit there.
I'll be sending back a
smaller amount of information.
The same number of
documents has been returned.
But the total payload
of those documents
will be much, much smaller.
We could even go further
and say that we only
want an index on city and name.
And if we run the
query again specifying
that we want to filter on the
city and only show the name,
I'll even go a few
steps further in terms
of the actual optimization
[? my ?] query
and reduce even further
the amount of time
taken to execute this query.
So to recap what we
learn in this lesson,
make sure your working
data set fits RAM.
Make sure to
optimize your queries
by using indexes and filter
responses and [INAUDIBLE]
pagination of those responses.
Smaller documents are
better documents in general.
So take that into consideration.
Mongostat, Mongo logvis, and
profiler are here to help.
Make sure you use profiler
only on development.
And don't get tricked
by the partial results
that profiler might give you.