In this lesson, we'll
see how Mtools can help
us to identify slow queries.
We'll dive deep into
three tools to help
you identify those slow
queries, mloginfo, mplotqueries,
and mlogvis.
Mloginfo can be used to
create a quick summary
of the query shapes.
Mplotqueries gives you a plot to
show all the queries over time.
And mlogvis is similar
to mplotqueries,
but will make use of
your internet browser
instead of using the
graphical libraries needed
by mplotqueries.
Let's take a look.
First I'll ssh into
my Vagrant box.
Great.
Next I'll go into
my shared folder.
OK, all of these tools need log
files and I've got one here.
This is actual data from
one of our customers,
but the databases,
collections, and field names
have been replaced
by animal names,
while the text values are
replaced by random strings.
Let's start with
the simplest tool.
Mloginfo can be used
for a lot of things.
The most common is to
get the envelope of log,
basically figuring out the
period of time it covers
and from which host it comes.
We've redacted some of
the information, which
is why it's unknown.
However, there is also a
mode with minus minus queries
where it reports all
the queries by shape
ordered by the total amount
of time that it took.
That means if a query took
two seconds, on average,
and appears one million
times in the log,
then the total amount of time
will be 2 million seconds.
By ordering the
queries that way,
we can easily see the
most expensive query shape
at the top and decide if
it should be optimized.
I'm afraid the text is wrapping.
I had to do that in order to
keep it big enough to read.
We can see at the
top of the queries
that there is an update
that has a count of 1203.
The update may have been
run more often than this,
but this is the number of
times it appears in the log,
because all those log entries
were for updates that exceeded
the threshold of a
slow query, which
by default is 100 milliseconds.
This update takes an
average of 599 milliseconds,
as you can see from
this mean value column.
And obviously, for
all these queries,
we see those are
not great numbers.
And we'd like to look at them.
It could be that there is
no index on hamster.wallaby.
And adding the index could
improve the performance a lot.
Not just for this update, but
also improving the performance
of the overall system.
The following two lines show
another query and an update
that should also be optimized.
The following
queries and updates
are only a fraction
of the time of those,
so they have less of an impact.
That's why we care about
this total time taken.