Now that we've done
all the heavy work,
let's have a look at the
preferred method, the rolling
upgrade.
This time, we're going to
leverage the MongoDB management
tools to do this.
Using Cloud Manager, we're
going to build a new index
in a rolling upgrade
fashion, just
like we covered a moment ago.
If you have Ops
Manager, this feature
is also available to you.
From this page, you want to
click on the Modify button
on the replica set line and
scroll down to the Index
Configuration section.
We'll click Add
and add our index.
Will put it in the
m312.people namespace.
We'll put it on the
address.city, address.zip
fields.
We click Apply, Review &
Deploy, Confirm & Deploy,
and that's it.
I just have to wait
for Cloud Manager
to do a rolling upgrade for me.
If this isn't a
production system,
building on the primary in the
foreground should do just fine.
If you have your cluster managed
under Ops Manager or Cloud
Manager, use that to
build your indexes.
If you don't have those systems
and you have a window of time
where performance
isn't at its peak,
you can use that time to build
the index in the background.
And if you have a
primary under stress
and can't afford to
add any load to it,
use the manual rolling
upgrade procedure.
And those are your options
for building indexes.