Our queries taking
longer as data set grows.
And obviously, this is
the read response time
that gets affected.
And we need to understand
why if our data set grows--
why does our
queries take longer?
Now, just to be clear,
all queries are like that.
But we should not have a
response time that is linear.
When this occurs, we're going
to have a situation where
we have big O notation of
N, which basically means
that as your data size grows,
so does grow the response
time in terms of
milliseconds of any query
that you do to the database.
And now that's
pretty bad because it
will mean that as more
successful you are in terms
of the data you are
including into your database,
the longer it will take for
you to query on that data.
And that just means that there's
no benefit in actually growing
the data size.
And as we all know, that's
not particularly right.
What we are mostly looking
for is something like big O
notation of logarithm
of N, log of N.
And this is a much
more saner situation,
where as your data size
grows, your response time
doesn't grow that much.
It keeps it in a very
consistent, stable way in terms
of what you can expect.
No matter how much
data you get, you're
always going to get
a good response time.
This only happens if you have
in place the proper indexes
to respond to your queries.
And this situation
over here, where
you have big O
notation of N, you
will get this when you
do not have indexes
that support your queries.
Let's see this in action.
I'm going to simulate the
constant growth of data
by importing a
slightly larger set
and running the same
query after each import.
Now, the first data set
that I'm going to import
is into our MondoDB
database m312,
and the one that
we've been using
for this course, a collection
called norberto_friends.
I have a lot of friends.
But let's start with
my 10 first friends.
Once my 10 friends
are imported, I
can go and have a
look to those friends.
In this friends data set,
if I use my m312 database
and if I show my
collections here,
I'll see my
norberto_friends there.
I can query that to see what
kind of friends do I have--
all good friends,
I can assure you.
But this is the
information I can get--
an ID, a name, a
created at, a city--
my lovely city of Porto--
an ID which is incremental,
an email, age, phone number,
and so on.
For me to show you that
sometimes we [INAUDIBLE] some
parts of our development phase,
let's say that I want to find
all my friends that I made--
let's say a city like Barcelona.
If you never visit Barcelona,
you are missing out.
So if I run this query,
easily I can get immediately
all the results corresponding
to all my friends
which live in Barcelona.
If we want to understand
while in development phase
how well does this
query perform,
we can enable the profiler and
test execution of this query.
Here I'm going to set
the profiler to 2, which
means it captures every single
operation in the system,
and setting the threshold
of my slow operations
milliseconds value to 0.
Anything that is higher
than 0 will be captured
in the profiler collection.
So let's do just that.
Once we have that done,
let's run again our query,
exactly the same query.
And let's look into our profiler
and look for that query.
Now, some of the queries, since
we are capturing everything,
will be collected here.
But the important thing that
we are collecting is this one
here, where we are
querying on this namespace,
m312.norberto_friends.
This is the filter--
and tells me how
many keys examine,
how many docsExamined, and
some other information,
like the amount of time it
took, which in this case
is 0 milliseconds.
Now, doing a naive
interpretation of this data,
we might be bound to
say that this data is
looking pretty good.
It's not going
through a lot of data.
It actually returns in
less than 0 milliseconds.
So we can't go faster
than that, right?
Well, let's see how this
story develops when we
add more data to the data set.
Let's get out of the shell.
And let's import now
instead of 10 friends--
since I'm very popular, I have
lots and lots of friends--
let's import my 1,000
friends data set.
So import that.
This is pretty quick.
MondoDB is pretty
awesome on this.
So let's go and connect again.
Now let's go and jump
directly to our m312 database.
Once we are in, we can
run the same query again.
If we run the same
query, will we--
having grown our data set--
so the number of
results that we get.
But also, that will be reflected
on the total time taken
by the application to actual
return the result set.
So let's do that.
As we can see, we
get more results.
That's fine.
But if we go to our
system profile again,
we can see that some
things have changed.
Now, this query, the
same query as before
with a different
cursor ID, obviously,
has examined 629 documents.
This is because we
didn't fully iterate it
for the full amount
of documents.
But it did reply in a very small
amount of time, 0 milliseconds.
So again, if we are
looking into this data
crudely without analyzing the
planSummary or execution stats,
we might be led into error to
think that this is pretty good.
This is pretty, pretty awesome.
We taking 0 seconds to reply.
This is fantastic.
Well, not so fast, young
grasshopper, because there's
more to this story.
To show you exactly that,
let's import a little bit more
of data--
instead of 1,000, a
million of my friends.
I can guarantee you I am
a very popular person.
So once all this data
is back into our mongod,
and obviously, a million
is quite larger amount
of information than 1,000--
once this is done,
we will be looking
into running the
exact same query again
and see how does this translate
in terms of the response time--
can go back.