So in my system here,
I can see that there's
been a normal flow
of connections,
then a spike in this place here,
and then another spike here.
Now, connection
spikes are generally
correlated with something
that the application is doing.
New connections
being established
means that you might have
new clients or new threads
of those clients establishing
connections to do some work.
There are a couple of
things that also can provoke
this which are not that good.
Well, exhausting
connection pools
is probably an indicator
and a direct correlation
between how your
driver's configured
and how connections have you
been enabling your system
to work with.
The drivers will try to reuse
as many connections as possible
by maintaining a
connection pool.
If those connections
pools are exhausted,
they will have
specific configuration
to allow you to establish
new connections.
But once the connection
pool is exhausted,
it will try to connect
more and more and more.
So seeing exactly why
there's some exhaustion
of your connection pools
might be a good indicator
from debugging
perspective to see
if your application is actually
doing what it should be doing.
There can also be occasional
incorrect connections
to your production environment.
Let's say, for
example, that we are
running a long-lasting tests
that inadvertently connects
to your production environment.
Those can also be identified
in terms of connection
spikes in your system.
And obviously, there's the
analytical workload load
and reporting tools.
If they are supposed
to connect your system,
you eventually see the
spikes in the numbers
of connections and some
specific operations
that those tools will do.
Now, if your connections
keep increasing but not
a lot of work or workload is
associated with that increase,
that might be provoked by
two different situations,
either stale operations
or incorrect credentials
used by the application.
In this case in
particular, for us
to analyze exactly what happened
in terms of number of workload,
we need to see if the number
of connections, especially
in these two setups
here, [? did ?]
actually correlated with
more operations per second.
We can see that there's
a small spike in number
of operations per second
here, especially commands.
There are some queries going
on, not a lot of get mores.
So there's something
going on here.
And there's some document
metrics as well--
some operations that are
related with return documents
per queries.
But the connections
keeping increasing
at a completely different
pace than the number of
returned documents
and the number
of operations per second.
That might not be
a very good sign.
Actually, it's not at all
a extremely good sign.
For us to understand
exactly what's going on,
we also need to see the
number of cursors open.
Now, if I need more cursors--
and here, I can totally
see that there's
been an increase once we jumped
the first level of number
of connections in the
number of cursors open.
But once I increase it
again a second time,
no more curses were
needed to be opened.
So that means that the
database is actually
being able to fulfill
the number of requests
that these new connections
are establishing
with the same number of cursors.
Now, this can be correlated with
a particular situation where
we have very, very,
very bad queries.
And for that, we need to analyze
this particular metric here,
which is query targeting.
Query targeting will
allow us to identify
long-lasting
non-indexed queries,
which as you all know
from this chapter,
that's a very bad thing.
So identifying them--
it's our mission.
Here, I can tell you
right now that this is not
an ideal scenario for
a couple of reasons.
Let's look in more detail.
The query targeting metric
allows us to see two different
ratios, the number of scans
per returned documents--
so number of scan
entries in an index--
and the number of
returned documents
consecutive to that
number of scans.
As you can see here, it's
pretty much flat to almost 0--
so very little index
scanning going on here.
The other ratio is the scanned
objects per returned documents.
This gives us the information
on how many documents
we are scanning divided by the
number of documents returned.
Now, as you can see here,
this is looking pretty bad.
Why?
Well, we are scanning a
lot of different documents
and returning a
very small amount
of those documents in return.
This is basically
clear indication
that the queries
that our clients are
doing in this
particular stage here
are all non-indexed queries.
Once you target such a
thing and correlate it back
with the number of
connections being
increasing constantly and
not a lot of document metrics
being returned, for
example, and not
a lot of different
operations per second,
you might want to go back
to your developers and ask,
why do we need so many
clients, or why are we
launching so many
requests to our system
if the total amount
of work in our system
is actually pretty
much not significant?
Now, once you have clearly
identified the situations,
apart from going back
to your developer team
and start doing some
questions about why did we
launch at this point and this
point and again at this point
so many different
connections, you
should also analyze the
logs of these machines
to pinpoint what
kind of queries are
being done by these clients.
So you'll have much
more clear information
of what kind of queries
are our system doing.
And for that, we will
need tools like mlogvis
or just analyzing the logs
of your mongod instance.
So just to recap what
we've learned, keeping
an historical monitoring data--
it's quite important to
analyze how the system is doing
and how we can predict the
system application will
be doing in the future.
Watching out for spikes
in connections or spikes
in the number of operations
per second, cursors,
and so on will allow us to
correlate values between them.
And if they out
of sync, you need
to come back to your developers
and ask educated questions.
Make sure you use
mlogvis and other tools
to understand exactly what
those connections are doing,
what those clients are doing.
Do not forget that some spikes
might skew out your data.
So make sure you know
what you're looking for.
And obviously,
don't forget to spot
long-lasting queries
or non-indexed queries
to understand how those can
affect your overall performance
of the system and get to
the bottom of why they exist
and why they are present.
Now, changes, if
notified and controlled,
will still be observed
by the monitoring tools.
Make sure you keep an eye on a
change log of your application.
Ask your team to keep you
up-to-date on incoming changes.
If they don't, given that
you have all this information
and the detailed
information of mlogvis,
the profiler, the
explain commands,
you'll be able to go back
with a great deal of detail
and help them solve
some potential issues.