Now at the other extreme,
the opposite event
can also cause sudden problems,
an unexpected index build.
If you're building an
index, your storage engine
needs to create a
lot of index entries.
This will be a
blocking operation.
And depending on the size of
the index, it could take time.
Your server won't take
rights while the index
is getting built.
We'll create an index.
Then we'll go to the log.
Here you can see
the index build.
And if you look at the
start and stop times,
you can figure out
how long it took.
Obviously, it didn't
take long here,
since I just spun up my replica
set and everything was empty.
If you can catch an
index build in action,
you can also find it
with db.currentOp.
But once an index
build is in progress,
you've already got a problem.
And by the time
you connect, it's
probably going to be done with.
But maybe you really
need to build an index.
And maybe you can't afford
to take the performance hit
while an index is getting built.
What are your alternatives?
They basically all
come down to planning.
We'll cover this in detail in
our lesson on building indexes.