Now let's use mplotqueries.
To do this, I'm going to have to
get out of the virtual machine.
I've set it up on my laptop.
And it'll show us
what we want to see.
First, I'm going to go
to a tab of my terminal
that's not in the Vagrant box.
I'll go into the Shared folder.
And we'll look at the
help documentation.
This is a very rich tool and
there are a lot of options.
It may look overwhelming.
But you can run the tool
with all the defaults,
and it's likely to
do what you want.
Once you become more
accustomed to it,
you can do things
like change the y-axis
to a logarithmic scale
so outliers aren't
as distorting to your view.
You can create different
types of graphs,
for example, looking
at connections
instead of slow queries.
And you can overlay
a few of those graphs
together to correlate events.
Let's go ahead and run it by
passing the log file to it.
This tool goes deeper.
And it doesn't just give you
aggregates per query shape.
It plots every single slow
query as a dot in the picture.
You may want to
keep that in mind
if you try to plot
millions of slow queries.
Reducing the scope of
your log ahead of time
may save you some processing
time for the mplotqueries tool.
Our x-axis is the
timeline, while the y-axis
is the value in milliseconds
each query takes.
And every dot in this picture
is one of those slow queries.
The first thing you
probably want to do here
is to narrow down the graph to
a time frame that interests you.
Again, if you know
that period in advance,
use mlogfilter to
do it beforehand.
Let's say you want
to pay attention
to the beginning of when we get
a lot of those slow queries.
Just click on the Zoom
icon and draw a rectangle
with your mouse.
The graph is a little
less crowded now.
You can also get out of
Zoom Mode when you're done.
There seems to be a lot of
green dots, which correspond
to the hamster.wallaby
namespace,
as indicated by our
legend on the left,
though it may be a bit
small for you to read.
My apologies to those of
you who are colorblind.
I know there is a lot to parse.
If I wanted to omit
this namespace,
I could simply click on
the dot in the legend.
However, I think I want
to keep those right now.
Let's look at one of those early
green dots and click on it.
The corresponding query
from the mongod log
is printed into the console
where I started the tool.
At this point, I
can take this query
and figure out if
there is something
wrong with the
indexes or conclude
that it's slow because
of another issue,
like an overloaded system,
an underprovisioned system,
et cetera.
We'll go through some of
those in a more complete way
in other exercises.
For right now, we just
want to easily identify
the slow queries.