Let's go back into our VM.
And let's look at our
last tool, mlogvis.
This tool is very
similar to mplotqueries.
But the tool was created
later and doesn't
require the graphical
libraries used by mplotqueries.
Instead, it produces an HTML
file in your local directory
and points your browser to it.
If the tool is unable
to open the default
browser in your system, you
can open the file yourself
from the browser.
I'm in the VM in
the shared folder.
So I can switch out
of the VM and open it
on my desktop machine if I like.
The nice thing
about this behavior
is that you can create the
output file from one system
with the minus minus
no-browser option
and move it to another
one for analysis
or send it to someone who
doesn't have mtools installed
at all because this HTML file
doesn't require anything, just
a browser.
Similar to the
other tools, we'll
simply call mlogvis by passing
it our mongod.log file.
And now I've got this HTML file.
I'll go to this on my host
machine and open it up.
Just like before, we can
zoom in on the graph.
First, we select Zoom
and then draw a rectangle
on the area of interest.
And like our
previous tool, I can
toggle the collections
I'm looking at
and look at individual
slow queries
by clicking on the event.
When you do so, you can
see the corresponding query
in the status box at the bottom.
The UI is simple and intuitive.
So feel free to play with it.
In summary, these
tools are particularly
helpful for identifying and
visualizing slow queries.