In this lesson, we'll
be looking into ways
that you, wearing the system
administrator or DB hat,
has to identify potential impact
of client application changes.
We'll be looking into keeping
track of historical monitoring
data, why is that important.
We'll be looking to a couple
of different spikes in terms
of graphical information
that we should look into,
like watching out for spikes
and connections and spikes
in ops per seconds and
some other few indicators
for a couple of
different examples
that we have prepared for
you, and obviously, spotting
long-lasting
non-indexed question.
This is specifically interesting
from a slow query or slowness
analysis of our system.
But you, if you're wearing the
DB hats or system administrator
hats, you might
say, why do I need
to care about what
developers are doing?
Well, let's face it.
Any of this information
will allow us as DBAs
to sleep better at nights.
That new super-hot
feature that will
generate thousands of
instructions per second
and make everyone happy
needs to be well-tested
with the expected
load, well-configured
in terms of schema design
and indexes to support it.
So you as a DBA need to
make the necessary steps
to keep your system in
shipshape and Bristol fashion.
Let's start with the basics.
If we want to be able to
pinpoint changes in your code
from our system
infrastructure, we
will need context
and historical data.
Let's see this in action
using MongoDB Atlas.
It will look similar from
Cloud and Ops Manager.
In this account of Atlas, I
have the best of two worlds.
We can deploy machines
with the click
of a button, which is great--
can select our infrastructure
engines and Confirm and Deploy.
But once we deploy it,
we would immediately
get our system monitored.
In this particular
example here, I already
have preloaded a
instance, or in this case,
a replica set called Cluster0.
And from there, I
can go immediately
into the dashboard
of historical data,
of monitored
historical data, and I
can start analyzing what
happened with my system.
Once we have a nice set
of historical information
on the behavior of
our application,
we can start to track
down any changes that
might affect our back end.
And this includes watching
out for spikes, spikes
in connections, spikes in
[INAUDIBLE] per second,
and a few other types of
spikes in our dashboard.
Now, in this example, I have
a few client applications
mimicking the constant
flow of requests.
You can see it from the
number of connections
and a bunch of different metrics
that I'm collecting here.
Just analyzing the
number of connections,
I can see here that
a few things happen.
I had a jump here in
terms of my connections,
and then another
jump on this one.
And then they fall back again.
But if we cross-checked
with the number of documents
and the number of
app counters, well,
looks like the spikes did not
affect that much our system,
or did they?
Well, the question
here is that we need
to analyze all types of spikes.
In this case here, I'm
going to zoom in a region
where I can have information
on all different spikes that
happened here.
In this one here, my up counters
and document metrics, as well,
is skewing up a
little bit my data.
I know exactly
what happened here.
But if you don't, you as
a DBA should immediately
be asking your developers,
what went wrong
on this particular
point in time?
What that is saying,
not what was wrong,
but what did you guys
do at this point?
Now, if I want to correlate that
with the number of connections
established, I need
to select just those--
still getting a little
bit of skewed data.
Let's just remove
that from our view.
And once we do that, we can
see a total different figure.
Raising the number of
connections in my system--
this correlates with a bunch
more work in my application
that was being skewed out
by other spikes in my graph.
So make sure you understand
that not always what we see
is what actually is going on.
So you need to be
careful about that.