I've written an example script
so that you can try this.
What this script
does is it spawns
a bunch of parallel
processes, 20 by default,
and they all try to
write the same document.
Let's create a replica set.
And I'm going to
show a few things to.
So I'm going to open up a few
tabs to do things in parallel.
First, I'm going to start
here with the mongo shell.
I want to capture
some information
about what I'm going to do.
So let's take a snapshot of
the current server status.
Next, let's set up
mongostat in another tab.
I'll connect to just the
server on port 30,000.
And I just want a few fields
to make it look pretty.
Right now, I've got a
few connections just
from the replica set, the
mongo shell, and now mongostat.
And now we're in
a third tab, where
we're going to run our script.
Let's go to mongostat.
First, you'll notice that it
says there are 20 inserts.
It did get 20 insert commands.
But most of them failed with
the duplicate key error.
Next, you can see that we've
got a bunch of updates going on.
And you can see that I'm
dirtying a lot of my cache
quickly all just to update
that one single document.
You can also see that I've
added more than one connection
per process.
There are 20 processes.
And we created 40 connections,
even though each is just
one mongo client.
Each mongo client actually
maintains a connection pool
to the server,
though that's outside
of the scope of this course
to discuss that in detail.
I've added a link to the
[INAUDIBLE] mongo FAQ in case
you're interested in
reading a bit more.
You can also see
that we're doing
a ton of updates, basically
as fast as our system can
handle them.
And once it's finished,
no more writes.
And our connections
are back down.
Going to the mongo shell,
there's our document.
And if I scroll up, we
had 200,000 updates,
10,000 per process.
Also, while we saw that we
were getting a relatively high
throughput if we
looked at mongostat,
we still have some seriously
long-running operations,
which we'll see in the logs.
I can also check the
current server status
to see how many
operations I've done.
There are my 200,000 updates.
There are my 20
attempted inserts.
And there is my one
insert that succeeded.
Let's check out those logs.
Here is my log path--
copy that.
Let's jump to the bottom.
So most recently, I
can see my 20 processes
closing their connections.
But if I scroll
up, here I can see
a bunch of pairs of write
and command entries.
Note that each pair is
for the same connection--
in this case, connection 71.
They're both saying
the same thing.
I've got queries
that took too long.
You can see we've had
41 write conflicts,
and it yielded 41 times.
That's the source
of the problem.
Typically in
circumstances where you
see a lot of write
conflicts, you probably
would want to
revise your schema.
If all those processes were
working on different documents,
things would improve
dramatically.
With that then, let's go back
to our shell and run our script.
I've set this docPerProcess
flag to avoid contention.
And when we go to mongostat,
here we have our inserts--
looks like it
miscounted a little.
We've got our connections.
We've got our updates happening.
Let's wait for this to finish.
Once again, we'll
look at our logs.
Here, if we start
at the top, we've
got our initial log entries.
Following that,
we can see a bunch
of our connections spinning up.
Then we see a bunch of
our connections closing,
and that's it.
We don't see any of those
long-running queries
we saw before.
We've eliminated
the write conflicts
by simulating a change
in our schema from one
with a lot of write
conflicts to one without.
What have we seen?
We've looked into
how you can have
sudden drops in throughput.
We've looked at long-running
queries, index builds,
and server write
contention, all of which
does happen in production.
We've seen how to
investigate the causes--
typically, using the
server logs, but also
with currentOp, the profiler.
And we've talked a bit about
how to fix these issues when
they're identified.