So your application is
taking its first baby steps.
You start getting some decent
load, and with that you start
to understand if the choices
that you've made, in terms
of hardware provisioning, schema
design, and overall system
configuration, meet
the expected load.
One of the first obvious aspects
will be the response time
of your system.
If we have a web
application, a role of thumb
is that any end-to-end
Application Request should
be under 200 milliseconds.
After that, operations
become noticeably slow
by the end user and impact
the perceived performance
of your application.
This does not apply
to all operations.
There are several
operations that are expected
to take longer response times.
Especially if you rely
on external services
to accomplish a task.
Like a payment service,
or a booking service,
and other similar services.
However, if we are building
an application that
relies on intermediary
API, like a REST API.
Or just simple, ordinary HTP
request, the 200 milliseconds
mark is something to consider.
Keeping this in mind,
any operation that
takes over 100 milliseconds,
in regards to MongoDB,
is considered slow
by default. This
means that if
requests to database,
which tends to be where the
significant amount of the work
ends up happening.
Having 100
milliseconds threshold
allows you to
understand, very quickly,
that some operation might
be taking longer than
originally expected.
Regardless of your SLA's.
Your service level agreement.
For these reasons,
you can in fact
set the threshold value
to something different.
This small command
here that I am showing
does the trick
for us in MongoDB.
If you are in the
financial trading business,
or your use case requires
high speed processing,
your SLA's will probably be
a few orders magnitude lower.
Therefore, you can set up that
threshold to what you need.
The notion of slow queries,
or operations for that matter,
in an application will be
affected by your SLA's.
Any external dependency to
services that you do not make
part of your stack, and
therefore you cannot control.
The workload your
application is subjected to,
and the infrastructure
that you set in place.
All of these need
to be considered.
When using [INAUDIBLE],
we will look
into this topic from three
different perspectives.
How much time does it take
to read from the database?
Where should we be looking
to resolve any issues
with the read response time?
How much time does it take
to write the database?
Which components will affect
the write performance?
And what indicators will we
follow to deal with them?
Lastly, the end-to-end
response analysis.
This is the
cumulative time taken
to provide the response
back to the client, when
multiple different
operations in the database
need to be packaged together.
Not the response time of
a single query or write
operation.
In this chapter, we will
use sample application,
and analyze scenarios where we
have to detect slow queries.
Situations where the response
time degrades over time.
Or when a single
operation impacts
expected load, and some
other similar situations.
We will use the previously
introduced tools
so we can diagnose
these scenarios.
But in essence, this chapter
is all about slowness.
How to identify, measure,
and correct its occurrence.