OK.
So these first three are
all ways to create indexes.
But as I said, creating an
index does a collection scan,
and that may be an
issue, especially
with the system under a load.
So next, we're going
to create the index
on the replica set using what
we call a rolling upgrade.
Let's go back into our
VM and go to the primary.
And we'll connect
to our primary.
From that primary, let's drop
the social security number
index.
Great.
Now I'm creating a connection
object to this secondary
and running the shutdown
server command on it
directly from my primary.
Perfect.
Let's check our status.
And as I can see,
we're no longer
able to reach this
secondary, because we've
killed the process.
Now I can check to see that
I'm down to only two servers.
Good.
Definitely just the two.
Next, I want to restart
the MongoDB process
in standalone mode, meaning I am
omitting the --repl set option
and using a different port.
This change of port is to
avoid any traffic trying
to connect to that instance
while I build the index out
of the replica set.
First, I want to know
what command I used.
I shut down the server on
RS3, so it's not appearing
in the list of processes.
I'm going to start with one
of these processes I see here.
I'm going to change its
port, change its directory,
and drop the --repl
set argument.
You can do this
yourself manually,
but I wrote a little
script to do it for me.
You're welcome to use it.
But if you do, then use
it at your own risk.
Also, if you see a more
elegant way to do this,
please don't judge me.
Connecting with the Mongo shell,
I now can create the index.
This time, there's no reason
to build in the background.
Foreground is better.
It's not a part of
the replica set.
It's a standalone.
And foreground builds
tend to be faster.
Let's make sure we're
in the right place.
And yes.
We're in the M312 database, and
there's the people collection.
Perfect.
Let's shut down this instance.
And I can restart
the MongoD server
and verify that it's
back in the replica
set with another script that's
similar to the previous one,
just a little different.
Now let's go back to
the primary and check up
on our replica set.
Secondary, secondary, primary.
Great.
Our server is back up,
and it's the secondary.
In real life, there's a
chance that the index build
would take a really long time.
If that had happened, I would
then want this re-added member
to catch up on its oplog
before doing the same work
on the other secondaries.
But this is a class demo, and
I haven't done any writes,
so I'll just shrink
down my other secondary
and do the same work on it.
And that member is down.
So we'll go through a
similar set of steps,
just like we did before.
Now our second server
is up as a standalone.
We're in the right place.
We've created our
index, so we want
to shut down and restart it.
Let's go back to the
primary and confirm.
Secondary, secondary, primary.
Great.
All three of my
members are up again.
And once I've
re-added this member,
my two secondaries
both have the index,
and we're left doing
the work on the primary.
Let's step down the primary
and then shut it down
and do the same procedure.
So now we're no
longer the primary.
This server on port
30002 is the primary,
and we're just a secondary.
OK.
Let's go through and
repeat all of our steps.
First, I'll shut down
my server, then exit.
Next, I'll spin it back
up as a standalone.
And let's jump to it.
Once again, a sanity check.
We'll create our index,
and we'll shut down.
OK.
Let's restart it and confirm.
Server on port 30002
is still primary.
Secondary.
And here we are.
Once I'm done with updating
my last replica set member,
I'm good to go.
There are a few things to note.
First, the role of primary
was exchanged between hosts.
This server on port 30000
used to be the primary.
Now it's a secondary.
And this server on port
30002 is now primary.
By the way, which server
steps up to be primary
may vary on your system.
It doesn't matter.
The important thing
is that another server
is going to have to step up.
Also, it's up to me to
build the same index
with the exact same
parameters on all hosts.
There is no check
from the system
to tell me that
the indexes aren't
the same across all the nodes.
Even if you're not going
to build indexes this way,
this is a powerful
procedure that you
should master in order to do
any kind of upgrade on MongoDB.
Use this process anytime
you change your MongoDB
version or your server's
operating system
or upgrade your hardware.
You can do all of this by
leveraging the replication
feature of MongoDB.