Let's see how we can do
the same with Compass.
There isn't a Compass for
Linux as of this recording.
And we're running a
headless VM, anyway.
So I'll exit and run
this on my host machine.
First, I'll need to connect.
I've got my system setup to
forward ports 30,000 30,001,
and 30,002 from my VM
onto my host machine.
So I'm going to be
looking at the same data
here that I have in
the virtual machine.
Great.
We're connected.
Now let's go to m312.people.
And we'll click on
the Indexes tab.
Great.
This page is presenting
me with a view--
well, a much prettier view--
of my current indexes,
but with a lot of
cool additional stats.
For purposes of this lesson,
what we're interested in
is this green
button, Create Index.
The first thing that
we see is that we
don't have to remember all the
options when creating indexes.
They're right there
in front of us,
including the Build Index
and the Background option.
If you want to name
the index, go ahead.
Otherwise, you'll get the
default name constructed
by the field names and types.
Note that you can also name
your index in the shell,
but I rarely do that.
Let's add the field
address.city of type Ascending.
We'll create it
in the background.
And we click Create.
That's it.
We can see the new
index in the list.
This is obviously much
easier than the command line
interface.