Many of these cases
require the ability
to manipulate,
inspect, and analyze,
data across multiple dimensions.
Apart from this,
these use cases often
required that this data
categorization meets
strict application as well
SLAs, service level agreements,
to enable responsive
Interfaces In MongoDB 3.4,
we are introducing support
for facet navigation enabling
developers to quickly
create an interface that
characterizes query results
across multiple dimensions
or facets.
Application users can then
narrow their query results
by selecting a facet value as
a subsequent filter providing
an intuitive interface
to exploring a data set.
Facetf navigation is heavily
used for browsing data catalogs
and grouping the data
in analytics use cases.
Combining facet navigation
with the functionality
of the MongoDB
aggregation framework
provides a powerful way to
manipulate data and analyze it.
Extending MongoDB usage to a
wider range of applications
with minimum overhead.
What is faceting?
Faceting is a popular
analytics capability
that allows users
to explore data
by applying multiple filters
and characterizations.
Using this approach
an application
classifies each
information element
along multiple
explicit dimensions,
called facets, enabling the
classifications to be accessed
in order in multiple ways.
For example, let's
consider a user catalog
for a popular
social media-- sites
like LinkedIn in
this example let's
do a search on the catalog.
This search is looking for
users with the term MongoDB
somewhere in their profile.
Initial results set return
is roughly 200k users.
The location and
current company facets
can be used to further narrow
down the results set according
to certain criteria.
For example, if a user chooses
to limit the result's sets
to only users in
the United States,
then the result set will
narrow down to near 62k users.
Facets in MongoDB
are implemented
using the aggregation
framework and comprehend
a few different stages.
We will be covering
single facet queries,
manual, automatic bucketing,
and rendering multiple facets.
Well let's get ourselves
busy working with facets.