So now let's have a look into
buckets, or better saying,
looking to bucketing strategies.
Now bucketing is a very common
operation associated facets,
where we group data
by a range of values,
as opposed for
individual values.
So basically, we group
sorts of documents
based on some specific
brackets or boundaries where
our documents will fit in
based on a particular value
comprehended on those ranges.
In our example, we might
want to bucket companies
based on the size
of their workforce,
the number of employees.
Now to do that, if we
look into for example,
the range of values that
we have in our data sets,
we can see that we go from
the very large workforce
for companies to
companies that don't even
have number of employees
set or are set to 0.
And this will give us the
ranges and an opportunity
to establish boundaries
for those buckets,
if we want to group the
different companies based
on the number of
employees that they have.
But then again, not individual
values, but ranges of values.
So to put this in place,
let's use a simple aggregation
example.
So in my particular
case, for this example,
we're going to have the
companies founded after 1980.
And we are going to have
on the same data set
only companies that have a
number of employees value sets.
Basically, not no.
And then we are going to
bucket those results using
a new stage of the
aggregation pipeline
called buckets,
where are we going
to be using a group
by in boundary fields
to define exactly how our
buckets are going to be looking
like, and which
field we are going
to be using for our
grouping, which in this case,
is number of employees.
Once we run this, we can see
that we are going to have
a result which contains an _id
field pointing to the bucket
name or bucket
value in this case,
where we can see a count of the
number of companies that fall
into that bucket.
For the following
bucket, which is 20,
we see a different count, 1,172.
Now the boundaries
define the brackets
where the lower bound in this
case, here 0, is inclusive,
and upper bound, 20,
will be exclusive.
So meaning that there
are 5,447 companies that
have been founded after
1980, which have either
0 up to 19 employees.
In the case of from 20 to
50, we have 1,172, 50 to 100,
we have 652, and so forth.
Now an important
aspect to keep in mind
is that if we have
documents with the field
number of employees in this
case, which we are grouping
by our boundaries array
here, these field types
need to be the same.
Meaning that if we have a number
of employees that doesn't have
in this case, a numerical
value, here infinity
is a double value that
we are using to define,
or even if they fall
outside the buckets,
we will have an error generated.
Let's see an example of that.
So let's say that we have
this particular document
on this call collection
where x equals a string of a.
If we run this
aggregation pipeline
on this particular
collection where
we bucket grouping by x, and
with the boundaries of 0,
50, and 100, we will
get back an error saying
that the switch will not find
a matching branch for an input,
and no default was specified.
Basically what it's
trying to say here
is that our boundaries do not
have a place for our documents.
Since our document is
defined with a value x equals
a, and our boundaries are
from 0 to 50, 50 to 100,
we do not have a place to
put this particular document.
Therefore, we error out saying
that we cannot find a place
to put it inside the buckets
that we are asking for.
To avoid these
scenarios, bucket stage
contains a default option
where we can define field,
or in this case, the name
of a bucket, which doesn't
fit the described boundaries.
So in our match
query, you are going
to change it slightly
to include again,
all founded
companies after 1980.
But now let's remove
the restriction
on having our nots the no values
for the number of employees.
So basically what it is
saying is if a company does
not that field particular set,
and since we wouldn't find
a bucket, a manual bucket to
place that particular field,
we will be placing it in other.
Once we run this, we can
see that the normal buckets,
with it's previously
provided number
of documents that fit those
buckets, are correctly placed.
And for all other
field values that
are not contained
within this range
or have a different
data type, we
will place it on other and
with its [INAUDIBLE] count.
Another important
aspect of bucket stage
and in regard to boundaries
defined manually,
is that all values
inside the array that
defines our boundaries need
to have the same data type.
In case that we do
not do so, we'll
get an error back saying that
all values in the boundaries
option to bucket must
have the same type.
And in our case, it
found conflicting types
between string and double.
So young padawans, be
careful about that.
Once defining our manual
boundaries for our buckets,
make sure that our boundary's
array only contains
values of the same data type.
The output result
of the bucket stage
will be this plain
simple document,
where we're going to have the
underscore ID and accounts.
That's pretty much
straightforward.
But let's say that we would
like to have something
a little bit more elaborate.
Now the other option
that bucket stage
allows us to set is
our output field,
or how the output
would be looking like.
The shape of our output
result for this facet.
In our case, let's assume that
we don't want just a total.
That's fine.
And with sum 1, that's OK.
But we also want to get
back the average value
of the number of employees, or
even a set of all categories
that match that
particular bucket.
That can be set through this
optional field output, where
we define exactly that.
In this case, the
aggregate operators that
will give me that
particular grouping.
Once we run this particular
aggregation pipeline,
in a pretty fashion we will
see that we will get the list,
or in this case, a
set of all categories
that match the other bucket
with a total of 4,522.
An average of no, because
averaging no by no gives me no.
That's pretty OK.
But in the case of the
bucket for companies
above 1,000 employees,
we have the total of 137.
The average being a
little bit above 13,000
in all sorts of different
categories for those companies.
Same thing for the
500 buckets and so on.
So to recap, we have
a new operator stage
or new mongodb aggregation
stage called dollar bucket
that we need to set the group
by elements specifying the field
that we want to group by.
We need to specify
the boundaries, which
tells us the brackets in
which our documents will
be grouping by.
Don't forget they need
to be the same data type.
We can specify a default bucket
for all documents that do not
fit the boundaries or
the buckets defined
by the boundaries that
we are specifying.
They are all going to be
placed under the default
with the appropriate
value associated to it.
And also we can define a
different document shape
for our output by specifying
different operators
that we might find useful,
given the bucketing
that we are doing.