$sortByCount takes one
argument, an expression
to group documents on.
It works just like a group
stage, followed immediately
by a sort and
descending direction.
Here, we're using a group stage,
grouping on the $imdb.rating,
getting a count,
and then sorting
on that count in
descending direction.
Here we're using the
$sortByCount stage,
simply specifying what value we
would like to sort by count on.
The exact same results.
We've covered a
lot of information.
But let's recap a
few important things.
In $bucket, we must always
specify at least two values
to boundaries.
Boundaries must be all
of the same general type,
either numeric, or string,
or Boolean, you get the idea.
And count is inserted by
default with no output,
but removed when
output is specified.
In $bucketAuto, cardinality
of the group by expression
may impact even distribution
and number of buckets.
Specifying a granularity
requires the expression
to groupBy to resolve
to a numeric value.
And lastly, $sortByCount is
equivalent to a group stage
to count occurrence, and then
sorting in descending order.