So far in facets, what we've
been seeing in terms of buckets
is the manual creation
of these buckets.
We have a bucket we
group by a field,
and then we specify the
boundaries for those fields,
and respectively
to those buckets.
Now, with MongoDB, we can
also generate automatically
those buckets.
So let's have a look
how to set that up.
So with MongoDB 3.4, we
also have $bucketAuto.
$bucketAuto is another
aggregation pipeline stage
which is very similar to the
previous $bucket operator.
We also have here the
groupBy specifying the field
on this data set that
we want to group on.
But instead of defining
the boundaries, what
we are expected to
set is the number
of buckets-- in this case, five.
It is very similar to
the previous $bucket,
but we reversed the order by
which we specify our options.
Instead of defining
boundaries, we
define the number of buckets.
So we run this.
You can see that
the output is very
similar to the
previous $bucket one
where we, again, have an ID.
Instead of having now _id
pointing to a value of one
of the boundaries--
the inclusive one--
what we're going to have
is basically a subdocument
defining at the min and
max value of our bucket,
and obviously, the count-- the
number of documents that match
or fall into this bucket.
Same thing for all different--
five different buckets.
The way that the auto
bucket generates our buckets
is to try to evenly balance
the number of documents
that will be distributed across
those different five buckets.
Similar to $bucket, we can
also define a different output
by defining our fields
and the accumulators that
will calculate those particular
fields on our output documents.
Once we run it, you
can see that we still
have the same exact boundaries.
But instead of having
only one field,
we're going to have
the fields that we
defined in our output
option-- total and average,
in this case.
Apart from those
particular options,
$bucketAuto also has the
option of defining granularity.
And granularity is basically
a numerical series-- one
that we might prefer from
these different options
that we have
supported in 3.4 where
the boundaries of
our buckets will
adhere to that specific
numerical series.
Now, we have several
different ones.
We have the Renard series.
We have the E series,
the 1-2-5 series,
and powers of two series,
all of them well-specified
on this particular
page with all the
supported values for the
granularity-- R5 to R20,
1-2-5, E6 to E192,
and powers of two.
To better see this in action,
what we can do is generate
a series collection where we're
going to have _id values from 1
to 1,000.
Once we generate
that collection,
I can just generate
my auto buckets--
so calling my stage for auto
bucketing-- grouping by _id,
and generating five buckets.
This is the default behavior
of our bucketAuto stage.
And with this, we
again see that I evenly
get buckets from 1 to 201
divided, and having around 200,
or 200 in this case because
it's an easy match, of 200
documents per bucket.
And defining the
option granularity here
to using the Renard series
R20, which basically
takes the 20th root of 10.
We will have a slightly
different set of boundaries
where the boundaries'
values will adhere
to that particular
series, but it still
tried to distribute accordingly
with the number of buckets
that we requested the
number of documents
across those different buckets.
And this is how
$bucketAuto works.