So let's get started
working with facets
and explore this
new functionality
that [INAUDIBLE] brings.
Now, to get a better picture
of what we are going to do,
let's imagine the
following scenario.
Let's imagine that we
have an application that
has some sort of
search bar where
we can look for things
like MongoDB, for example.
Once we press the
Enter button looking
for this particular
keyword or term,
we are generally prompt
with some list of results.
We might have some
attributes, some indication
of things related with this
term given the catalog that we
are searching on.
But we also might have some sort
of filters or characterization
for this search
term in combination
with several
different dimensions
that this information
that we are
storing in the catalog of
this application might have.
So to explain this
very well, we're
going to be using a very
dear data set to you guys
that we've been exploring
throughout the course.
The data set that we're
going to be looking into
is the Companies
data set that you can
find on our startups database.
With this, we're
going to be exploring
this data set as a
catalog of companies,
and how we can organize, search,
and find information and get
facets out of the data stored
in that particular collection.
So let's get started by looking
through one single document
inside this Companies data set.
As usual, you can find
a bunch of information
from external links to awards
and milestones and acquisitions
and a bunch of other information
related to one single company
listed on this data set.
Now, what we might
have is the need for us
to search on a bunch of
different dimensions.
And for that-- going to be using
a very straightforward search
terms, like for example on
description and overview
for companies which are in some
way related with networking.
To express such a
query, we're going
to be creating a text index
on description and overview.
And if you want to
find the companies that
have the keyword
"networking" in their field--
either in description
or overview--
we can use it by simply issuing
the query where Companies
can aggregate and match on tags
searching for term "network."
Once we do this, we
get a list of results.
Now, let's assume
that the application
of our building-- our corporate
catalog-- not only wants
to give the end user
the result set, but also
to render a facet describing
the category code.
Now, this is a field
that will tell us
the type of company or sector
on which this particular company
is operating.
So basically, for that
particular functionality,
we now can use SortByCounts.
SortByCount will allow us to
create the facet by category
on the list of results that
the previous stage, match, will
provide.
So for all the companies that
will include "network" keyword
on their description
or overview,
those will be piped
into a SortByCount
where we're going to be
grouping the category code.
Once we run this, we have a
full list with their count
and sorted of the
sectors of activity
where we can find companies.
In this case,
we're going to have
web with 788 companies
listed, software with 463,
and so forth.
So SortByCount groups incoming
documents coming from our match
query based on their
specified expression, "search
for network," and then computes
the count of the documents
in which distinct group.
And sort by its count.
Each group is a document
with two fields--
an _id specifying the value
by which we are grouping,
and accounts-- determining the
number of documents that match
that group.
If we want the same
result, but let's
say with instead of having
the breakdown per category,
we want it for office
location, city-- something
like that-- we could run the--
an aggregation pipeline that's
a little more elaborate
than this simple one.
Let's say, for
example, what we want
is still search for
all companies that
have "network" keyword on
their description or overview,
but then given that offices is
an array of different locations
that we might have, we want to
unwind that particular array
and then match the offices
which do have a city.
So they have this city
value different than empty.
For all that, let's SortByCount
on the different offices.city
values that we find.
So there we go.
We now have a list of
documents specifying
the value of the office
city-- in this case,
for example, San Francisco
with a count of 245.
New York will have 218--
London, Los Angeles, Palo Alto,
and so on.
So this is also to
demonstrate that we
can have elaborate
pipelines that
would filter project,
match, group, determine
the list of documents that
then can use to sort by
and count given one
of the attributes
that is coming
with the result set
to this last stage
of the pipeline.
In essence, with this
aggregation inquiry,
we can have the breakdown
of companies per city
that match networking,
or in this case,
"network," in their
description overview.