Let's learn about some
other powerful data analysis
and groupings stages within
the aggregation framework.
In this lesson, we'll learn
about bucket, bucketAuto,
and sortByCount.
We'll discuss bucket first.
bucket has the following form.
And as we can see, it takes
a few different arguments.
So let's go over each one.
As we go along and
cover each field, let's
also incrementally build
a real aggregation.
groupBy groups documents
on evaluated expression,
just like the _ID argument
to the group stage.
One catch-- we can only
specify one value to match on.
We could use an expression
that evaluates two field paths,
but it must ultimately
resolve to one value.
Let's specify a field
path to $imdb.rating,
grouping documents together
based on their rating.
All right, boundaries--
this is where buckets
begin to become very powerful.
In boundaries, we specify
an array of values.
Each value is a lower bound of
the group the documents will
be placed in.
And successive values are
the exclusive upper bound
of the previous group.
A few things to be aware
of about boundaries--
the values that we
specify in boundaries
must all be of the same
type, with the exception
being number values.
Different types of
number can be mixed.
Also, we must specify
at least two boundaries.
Here, I'm specifying
an array of 0, 5, 8,
and infinity to boundaries.
That means that documents
with an $imdb.rating
from 0 inclusive to 5 exclusive
will be placed in the 0 group.
Documents with an IMDB
rating between 5 and 8
will be placed in the
5 group, and documents
with an IMDB rating
between 8 and infinity
will be placed in the 8 group.
We call these groups buckets,
hence the name of the stage.
The default field is
optional but important.
If we don't specify
it, the expression
we specified to
groupBy must resolve
to a value that can fall within
one of the buckets specified
in boundaries.
Otherwise we'll get an Error
The default value we specify
can be of the same type
as the boundary values,
but it must either be less than
the minimum boundary specified
or greater than the
maximum boundary.
Since we know that not all
documents have an $imdb.rating,
we'll specify not
rated to default.
This will catch all
of the documents.
Before we go over the
last argument, let's
test out bucket to
get a feel for it.
Here, we're specifying
the argument to groupBy,
hence setting our boundaries.
We know this will error
because not all documents
have a value for $imdb.rating.
But let's run it anyway to
see what that looks like.
This is the error we'll get.
Now that we know
what it looks like,
if we encounter
it in the future,
we'll know where to look
to fix our pipeline.
Let's include that
default argument.
Here we included the default
and specified not rated.
Now let's see it in action.
We can see a few
different things.
The $bucket stage
automatically gives us
a count field
within each bucket,
counting how many documents
were put into that bucket.
We can see that there were
4,992 documents in the 0 to 5,
35,516 documents in
the 5 to 8 bucket,
and 2,284 documents in the
8 to infinity document.
We can also see there were 1,705
documents that aren't rated,
meaning they did not have
a value that we could group
on in the $imdb.rating field.
This is pretty cool.
We can see the vast
majority of IMDB ratings
fall between 5 and 8.
This alone, however,
may not be enough.
The bucket stage fundamentally
transformed the resulting
documents.
What if we wanted to find the
average rating per bucket?
This is where the last
field, output, comes in.
output is much like the
additional fields we
can specify in the group stage.
We can give the
fields almost any name
we like and use familiar
accumulator expressions
to calculate their values.
Let's get the average
rating per bucket.
Here I've specified
the same arguments as
before with the addition
of an output field
and the average per bucket key.
Awesome.
We can see that we get the
average for documents that fall
within our defined buckets.
But we're missing
the count field now.
The reason for this
is because count
is the default accumulator
for the bucket stage.
If no output is defined, MongoDB
inserts the count for us.
If we specify an output
and also want the count,
we must specify that as
well using the same method
we do in the group stage.
Here, everything is identical
with the addition of the count
field.
Now we're seeing we get the
same average ratings as before
per bucket along with the
count that we expected.