Until this point, we've
been looking to how
to determine individual facets.
But as you probably
already realized,
when building
applications, we might
need multiple different facets
to achieve the kind of filters
that we want to provide
to our end users.
An initial example.
I've shown you that apart from
the list of results that's
given from a
particular search term
or query that we might
do against a catalog,
we might have different filters
to help us trim down, narrow
down the search results that
we might be more interested on,
depending on the
dimensions that are
suited for what we want to do.
And we've been
exploring some of those
throughout the previous lessons.
When building applications,
we might want to group
our data and their
orthogonal properties.
In running all
this individually,
we might take too many
round trips to the database.
With MongoDB 3.4,
faceting support
can compute several different
facets in one single command.
Due to this, we
have a new operator
called facet that allows
us to do exactly that.
So let's basically take
all the different facets
that we've been building
throughout the course
individually.
Let's say the Categories, the
Employees, the Workforce facet,
and the Founded year that
company's have been created.
And let's start
grouping all of this
into one single command in
our aggregation pipeline.
So let's start by matching all
documents that have databases
on their description or
overview by specifying a text
search query.
Pass along that list of
results to our facet stage.
And then generating
the different facets
that we've been
looking into before
by the Categories,
Employees, or Founded
dates to provide back that
set of different facets
that we've been
exploring so far.
So in essence,
with this command,
we are collecting back
all different facets
with their matching conditions
and output variations,
bringing in documents from
the database all at once.
Once I run it, I'll get all
sorts of different facets,
facet for Founded, the
facets for Employees,
and the facet for Categories
that my initial match
search provided.
Each sub pipeline within facet
is passed the exact same set
of input documents that this
match stage here generates.
And they are completely
independent from one another.
The output of one's sub pipeline
cannot be used by the following
ones within the
same facet command.
This means that we can
interpret this as sub pipelining
inside of our aggregation
framework pipeline
provided via the
dollar facet stage.
And this is how we can
generate facets navigation
using MongoDB 3.4.