OK, let's move on to
the $bucketAuto stage.
$bucketAuto has
the following form.
As we can see, it looks
similar to $bucket
with a few key differences.
GroupBy works exactly the
same as the bucket state.
Instead of defining
boundaries, we just
let MongoDB figure
those out by specifying
how many buckets we want.
$$bucketAuto will attempt to
evenly distribute the documents
into the specified
number of buckets,
calculating the
boundaries for us.
Here, we must
specify four buckets,
and $bucketAuto
will try to give us
four buckets with roughly
equal number of documents.
Keep in mind that we may
not get as many buckets
back as we specify,
especially if we specified
a number of buckets greater than
the number of input documents
or the number of unique values
in the groupBy expression.
Output works the same as it
does in the bucket stage.
Before we cover the
field, granularity,
let's see $bucketAuto in action.
OK, we're specifying that
we'd like to groupBy the IMDB
rating, we want four
buckets, and as output we'd
like the average per
bucket and account.
Let's run it.
This is pretty neat.
We got back four buckets.
And we can see the
count per bucket
and the average per bucket.
The documents don't look
evenly distributed, though.
And our boundaries
are a bit strange.
This is because
some documents are
missing an $imdb.rating value.
Let's clean this up
with a match stage
so we only get documents
with an IMDB rating.
Here, we'll just
filter documents out
they don't have an IMDB
rating value greater than
or equal to 0.
Documents with
the missing values
won't be messing up our results.
Pretty interesting.
We can see the $bucketAuto
did nearly the same thing as
before.
While it attempts
to evenly distribute
the documents among the
specified number of buckets,
it isn't guaranteed to do so.
Here, because the
cardinality of $imdb.ratings
isn't very unique, it's
impossible to evenly distribute
documents among buckets and
maintain contiguous ranges.
Let's groupBy title
instead to see
a much more even distribution.
And here we see a much more
even distribution of documents.
OK, the last thing to talk
about with $bucketAuto
is granularity.
It's an optional argument,
and specifying it
will attempt to place
bucket boundaries
along the given
preferred number series.
What's a preferred
number series?
They are commonly used
in industrial design
to standardize
product dimensions.
For R, E, and 1-2-5
series, it's a way
to subdivide 10 according
to a standard specification.
POWERSOF2 attempts to create
boundaries along powers of 2.
Keep in mind that
specifying a granularity
requires us to specify
a numeric value
in the groupBy expression.
It may produce less
buckets than specified
if the granularity
specified has less intervals
or is not fine enough to
evenly distribute documents.
Let's look at a quick example.
OK, first I'm going
to open a local Mongo
shell in my computer
to test this out.
I'll disconnect from
the Class Atlas Cluster
and connect to a local
running instance of Mongo.
OK, now that we have a Mongo
shell to a local instance,
let's use a small
JavaScript function
to generate some values for us.
I'm going to use a database
[? neo-space ?] called Agg fort
this example.
So here, we use a four loop
to generate some random values
that should map nicely to
powers of 2 and the Renard
and E-series distribution.
We insert those numbers
into a collection
called granularity test.
We run our function,
and then verify
that the function
worked by calling count
on our collection.
OK, let's look at the
powers of 2 granularity
and leave the R and
E-series for self-testing.
Here we specifying
that we'd like to group
by the powers of 2 field.
We want 10 buckets,
and the granularity
should fall on the
preferred number
series called powers of 2.
And there we go.
We can see that our
bucket boundaries
were placed along powers of 2.