I'd like to spend
some time to talk
about KMIP, which is the
Key Management Communication
Protocol.
MongoDB Enterprise supports
secure transfer of key files
with a compatible key
management appliance.
Using a key manager
allows for the keys
to be stored in the
key manager instead of
in some random place.
By using a KMIP key
management solution,
it will make it very easy for
you to rotate your master keys,
and thus fortify your
MongoDB deployment.
It's important to note
that using a key manager
meets regulatory key management
guidelines such as HIPPA, PCI,
and FERPA.
And this is why it's recommended
over local key management.
Enabling the encrypted storage
engine with a KMIP server
is arguably more straightforward
than using a key file.
For the sake of
this demonstration,
I'm willing to assume
you already have
a KMIP server up and running.
In my case, I'm using
pi KMIP and running it
on my local machine.
So you can see right here I
have the certificates that I'll
be using to talk from
MongoD to this KMIP server.
And this is a pretty
simple KMIP server.
We're using the py KMIP library.
And then I'm just specifying
my server, key files,
the port I'm running on, the
version of SSL I'm using,
my CA file.
And I'm pretty much just
starting up the server.
So I can just go ahead and
run Python pyKMIP server.
And now my KMIP server
is up and running.
And now we can go ahead
and start our MongoD
and have it connect
to this KMIP server.
So to start MongoDB with storage
encryption turned on and using
KMIP, we're just gonna pass
the dash dash enable encryption
flag, the dash dash
KMIP server option,
passing in the
local host argument
because I'm running the
KMIP server on this machine.
Then gonna pass our CA
file that we're using,
and our Client Certificate.
And it really is
as simple as that.
You can see our server is
up and running and waiting
for connections.