Now that we have our
sysadmin Ben all set up,
it's time for us to try and
see if this role authorization
model is actually
working properly.
Let's go ahead and
authenticate with Ben's user.
First we'll need to switch
to the admin database
and log in with
Ben's credentials.
Great.
Now we're authenticated.
Let's try to create one
of our remaining users.
There's still Carol,
our superstar DBA
that introduced us to the
magical world of MongoDB.
Let's create an account for her.
Carol's our DBA, so
it makes sense for us
to give her the dbAdmin role.
And as you can see, our role
based authorization model
is working as expected.
Could not add user.
Not authorized on admin to
execute command create user.
Now in the example, we
specified a document
that said w majority
and w timeout 300.
These are here to
define the write concern
that we're applying to
execute this command.
In particular, we
want to make sure
that this is a state
change that is propagated
across all members,
or in this case
the majority of the
members in our replica set.
And we also don't want to wait
longer than 300 milliseconds
to obtain a response.
Now, it's important that Ben
leave operations like this
to Alice, who is after all
responsible for these sorts
of tasks.
Let's go ahead and
authenticate with Alice
and create this user.
Great.
Now we want to make
sure that we understand
what Carol needs
to be able to do
and what she shouldn't
be able to do.
As a DBA, it's important that
Carol can check the database
statistics, kill long running
operations with kill op,
and then be able to
also create collections,
indexes, et cetera.
However, we don't
want Carol to be
able to write any data to any
collection, manager the cluster
in any way, or to be able
to create any new users.
As you saw when Ben tried
to run this command,
we gave Carol the
dbAdmin role, which
makes the most sense for the
reasons we just discussed.
Let's go ahead and
create this user.
Awesome.
It successfully added Carol.
Let's go ahead and
authenticate with Carol
and make sure she can do the
things she needs to be able to.
We should be able to list the
admin database collections.
Awesome.
And we can see this special
system dot users and system dot
version collections.
But if we try to list all the
databases we'll get in error.
What?
How does Carol not
have the privilege
to list all the databases?
Well, this happens
because we didn't
create Carol as a global
database administrator.
We only gave Carol
the ability to dbAdmin
on the admin database.