Now it's time to create an
account for Dan, our intern.
Dan will be working
on the NASA database.
So he's going to need to be
able to query the NASA database.
But since he's an
intern, he doesn't need
to be able do anything else.
He shouldn't be able to write
or change data in any way.
Let's go ahead and log in with
Alice on the admin database
and create this user.
Great.
Now we're logged in.
First we're gonna need to get an
instance of the NASA database.
That's because Dan
is only allowed
to read on the NASA database.
Great.
Now we can go ahead and
create the user using the NASA
database.
And here we go.
On the NASA
database, we're going
to run createUser with
the user name of intern,
a password of slacker, and give
Dan the read role on the NASA
database.
Awesome.
Our user has been
successfully added.
So if we now want to
make sure that everything
is up and running correctly,
let's go ahead and authenticate
against this new user.
Wait.
What?
Why can't we authenticate
with this user?
Well, that's because we created
the user on the NASA database,
not on the admin database.
That means that this account
needs to authenticate
against the NASA database.
Here we go.
We've now successfully
switched the NASA database.
And by running this command,
we should successfully
authenticate.
Awesome.
At this point, we have
a database called NASA.
And it has one user-- intern.
And this intern
user can only read.
Now this is a problem,
since we don't
have any data in the database.
To make sure the intern
can actually do some reads,
we need to create a user
that is capable of importing
a data set to this database.
Let's create a user
called bot loader that
has the capabilities of
writing on the admin database.
Here we go.
Here we're creating a
user called botLoader,
whose password is bolts.
And we're going to give them
the read role on the admin
database, and the readWrite
role on the NASA database.
And then we're also going
to give write majority
in a write time amount of 300.
Awesome.
Our user has been
successfully added.
Let's go ahead and load our
NASA meteorites.JSON file
into the NASA database.
Here I'm using the
mongoimport command,
specifying our username of
botLoader, password of bolts,
saying that the collection
will be called meteorites
on the NASA database.
And then I have our NASA
meteorites.JSON file
that's provided as a handout.
Wait.
What?
Why isn't this working?
Did we not create
our user correctly?
Well, no.
Unfortunately, what
is happening is
that we're trying to
insert data into a database
for a user that's created
on another database.
For these situations
we need to specify
the dash dash
authentication database
option in providing the
name of the database
that we want to
authenticate with.
Now when we run
this, it should work.
Connected to localhost.
Awesome.
We can see that we've
imported 45,000 documents.
And our intern should be
able to run his queries.