In MongoDB, roles are updatable.
Well, some of them at least.
Not surprisingly, if we try
to update a built-in role,
we're not going to get too far.
User defined roles,
however, can be updated.
There are three ways
to update a given role.
We can go ahead and
use db.getRole to get
a role like the intern role,
and then store it in a variable
called role.
From here it's not hard to make
changes to this object just
using JavaScript.
As you can see here,
we now have a variable
called updatedPrivileges,
which currently contains
all of the old privileges
on this role, which
is just the ability
to update meteorites
on the NASA database.
And it's not hard to
just use JavaScript
to push a insert action onto the
actions array of the privileges
array.
Now if you look at
updated privileges,
we'll see that insert
is also in action.
I'm not going to
run this command,
because I don't actually want
to update the intern role.
But the db.updateRole allows
us to pass on a role, and then
any updates you want
to make to that role.
In this case, I'm just going
to update all the privileges
with this new privilege
array that we have to find.
Another way to update
roles in MongoDB
is to use the
grantPrivilegesToRole function.
With this command we pass in the
name of the role that we want.
And then we pass an array of
all of the privileged documents
that we want to
add to this role.
Drawing from the last
example, if I just
want to add the
ability to insert
on the meteorites collection
in the NASA database
on the internRole, we just
pass in a privileged document
with a resource
document like so.
And adding an action like so.
Again, I'm not going
to run this command,
because I don't actually
want to add this privilege
to the intern role.
The last way that we can
add privileges to a role
is by granting roles to a role.
And by "roles," I mean the
roles that a role inherits from.
So in this case,
grantRolesToRole
takes in the name
of the role we want
to add inherited roles to,
and then just an array of all
the inherited roles
we want to add.
In this example I am adding
the readWriteAnyDatabase role
to the internRole, which of
course we don't want to do.
So I'm not going to run it.