By now you should have
a pretty good high level
understanding of how transport
encryption works in MongoDB.
We're now ready to look at
a concrete example of how
to enable TLS/SSL between
a client and a server.
The best part
about this exercise
is that you've already
done it before.
If you recall from when
we used X509 certificates
for authentication with
MongoDB that it requires an SSL
connection.
So this is a very
similar command
to what we've run before.
You'll see some similar things.
We're requiring SSL.
And then we're providing
a server certificate
for SSL connections.
So this command will force all
clients to connect via TLS/SSL,
meaning that connection between
the client and the server
is completely encrypted.
Awesome.
Transfer encryption.
We've done it.
But wait a second.
If you take another
look, you'll notice
that it differs slightly
from similar commands
that we've issued before.
Take a look at this command.
This is even more
similar to what we
used for X509 authentication.
The difference between this
command and this command,
obviously, is the
dash dash sslCAFile
and the passing of the
certificate authorities
certificate.
So what is the difference
between these two commands?
Well, both commands will enable
encryption between the client
and server, meaning that
the attacker can't simply
sniff the traffic in between.
The second command,
however, will
verify the identity of clients
connecting to the server,
and make sure that they are
connecting with the certificate
signed by the same CA.
This command is not checking
the client's identity,
which means that clients
connecting to our server would
be susceptible to a
man-in-the-middle attack.
An attacker could act
like a MongoDB client
and connect to the server.
If we don't provide
the SSL CA file,
the certificate
authorities certificate,
that means that
would be susceptible
to a man-in-the-middle attack,
which means an attacker can sit
right here in between the
client and the server,
acting like a server
to the client,
and acting like a
client to the server,
and therefore intercepting all
the traffic in between the two.
So while the connection
will be encrypted
between the client and
the man in the middle,
and the traffic
will be encrypted
between the man in the
middle and the server,
the man in the middle can
look at all the traffic
in plaintext, because it's
using the man in the middle's
private key and
public key to encrypt
all the traffic in
between the client
and in between the server.