So let's say our
intern now needs
to log all of his operations
that he is running into one
specific collection, but
independent of the database
that collection is on.
Well, we can update his
role to do just that.
Here I'm going to run the
db.grantPrivilegesToRole
command where I'm gonna specify
that I want on the intern role
I want to add this
array of privileges.
In this case it's just
one privileged document
where I'm saying any database
that has the intern log
collection, I want this role
to be able to insert and update
on this collection.
And it looks like
it ran successfully.
And here I can go ahead
and run db.getRole.
And I can specify
the intern role.
And I say I want to
show all the privileges.
And as you can see,
here are the privileges
that we saw before--
the ability to update
the meteorites collection
on the NASA database.
We now also have
a new privilege,
which is the ability
to insert or update
a collection on any database.