Now that we
understand what roles
are and know what built-in
roles come with MongoDB,
we can now talk about
user-defined roles.
The built-in roles
that come with MongoDB
should cover the majority of
the different types of people
who need to use our database.
That said, sometimes we
have specific requirements
that do not exactly
fit a particular user.
Let's talk about the
different parts that
make up a user-defined role.
When we create a
role, we create it
on a specific database, so
the role name and the database
that it was created on
define a unique role.
After giving the role
a name, we specify
what other roles we'd like
to inherit privileges from.
It's important to note that
for any given role created
on a specific database, we
can only include resources
and inherit roles defined
on the same database.
For example, if we define a
role on the Products database,
we can't inherit that role
on the Orders database.
If we would like to
share user-defined roles
across databases, then we
need to define a global role.
To define a global
role, roles that
have privileges on
several databases,
we need to create such
roles on the admin database.
Cluster-wide
resources can also be
created on the admin
database and then inherited
by other databases.
Coming back to our definition
of a user-defined role,
recall that we create
a name for a role,
and we create the
role with regards
to a particular database,
and that will uniquely
identify the role.
After that, we add
any other roles
that we would like to
inherit privileges from.
And then finally, we list all
of the additional privileges
we'd like this role to have.
Recall that a privilege
is just an action
acting on a particular resource.
And this is the definition of
a user-defined role in MongoDB.
We'll walk through
an example of how
to create a user-defined role
in the shell in a later video.