Encryption plays
an important part
in any security infrastructure.
In this series of
videos, we're going
to discuss the
different corruption
options that MongoDB supports.
There are two discrete
categories of encryption
with regards to MongoDB.
Be There's Transfer
Encryption, and then there's
also Encryption at Rest.
Transfer Encryption,
as the name implies,
refers to encrypting
information over network traffic
between the client
and the server.
Encryption at Rest concerns
actually encrypting the data
that we store on disk.
There are two broad classes of
approaches to encrypting data
at rest with MongoDB.
There's storage level
encryption, and application
level encryption.
We'll take a deep dive into
each of these topics later
in this course.