While transport encryption
between client and server
is very important,
it's equally important
that the members
of our replica set
are also using TLS or
SSL to communicate.
Remember, a security
system is only
as strong as its weakest link.
Setting up TLS
within a replica set
is a relatively
straightforward process.
At a high level,
we're essentially
doing the same thing as setting
it up with a standalone server,
but for each member
in a replica set.
Let's go ahead and do this.
Hopefully by now
you're starting to get
the feel of setting
up your replica
sets in different modes.
Here we're requiring SSL,
because the whole point
of this exercise
is to enable SSL
in between the members
of our replica set.
And then of course,
we're going to have
to pass in our
servers certificate,
our ca certificate so that
we can identify and verify
that everyone is who
they say they are,
we'll give our
replica set a name,
in this case myEncryptedReplSet,
specify the db path, the log
path, the port, and
we'll fork this process.
Awesome.
Now we just need to do this two
more times for the other two
members in our replica set.
And as we've done
many times before,
the only thing I changed here
is the db path, log path,
and port number, leaving all
the other parameters the same.
And here we go.
Here is the last command, only
changing the db path, log path,
and port number again.
Awesome.
Now all four of our
MongoDBs are up and running.
Now that we have each of
the members of our replica
set up and running,
we can go ahead
and connect to the first
server, initialize the ReplSet,
and add the other members.
So here we're going
to need to use
--ssl option saying that we're
going to connect via SSL.
And of course, we'll then
need to provide our client SSL
certificate and our
ca's certificate
so that we know the server
is who they say they are.
We're now connected
and we can go ahead
and initialized the ReplSet
and add the other members
of our replica set.
We can go ahead now and
initiate our ReplSet.
Here I'm passing in the
configuration for our ReplSet
specifying the
name of the replica
set, the version, and an
array of all the members.
Each member is an object that
has its ID and respective host
name.
And it's as simple as that.
Now there's something I
want to point out here.
I used localhost instead
of the actual hostname
on my machine,
which is something
that I don't normally do.
And the reason I did that
is because my certificate,
my server certificate,
if we look in here
we have this
server.pem key file.
If we go ahead and look at the
contents of this key file using
the open SSL command,
specifying x509
since this is an
x509 certificate,
and then provide it as an end
in parameter, and just go ahead
and get out the text.
We have the public
key in here and stuff,
but there's a really
important field,
which is the subject
alternative name.
And here, I have two alternative
names, one is localhost
and the other is 127.0.0.1 which
is also localhost obviously.
And I have to use one
of these two names.
Whatever names are under
the alternative name,
those are the
hostnames that you have
to use to initialize the
members of your replica set.
If I try to use education
dash iMac, which
is the name of this machine, and
passed in the port of 27 0 17
I would actually get a
SSL handshake failure.
So that's just one little common
gotcha I wanted to make clear.
If you run into this
you want to make sure
that you check the alternate
names in your actual server key
files.