In this video I'd like to
examine the different actions
that are supported in MongoDB.
We already know that there
are two parts to a privilege--
an action and a resource.
Actions describe the operations
that a given user may perform
on a resource in the database.
You can think of
actions as verbs.
While resources are the
subjects of these verbs.
Within MongoDB, we have several
different types of actions.
Let's go through each of
these categories one by one.
Let's start with query
and write actions.
All of the actions in this
category are related to CRUD.
You can see that we have things
like find, insert, remove,
update, and bypass
document validation.
Pretty straightforward.
After query and write actions,
we have database management
actions.
Most of these actions
are DDL operations.
These are structural
to the database.
Things like creating an
index, creating a collection,
dropping a user, killing
cursors, unlocking
the database.
One thing I want to
point out is that there's
a difference between
changing your own password
and changing a password.
The changeOwnPassword
role allows you
to change your own password.
Whereas the changePassword
role grants you the privilege
to change anyone's password.
After database
management actions,
we can move on to deployment
management actions.
Deployment Management
Actions are also
pretty straightforward.
They allow you to
manage your deployment.
The one thing I like
to point out here
is that all of these
operations-- all
of these actions--
are only applied
to the cluster resource.
After deployment
management actions,
we have replication actions.
As you'd expect,
all these actions
involve getting and setting
different replications
settings.
We also have the
ability to append
an oplog note, do a resync.
All these actions
are also applied
to the cluster resource.
After replication we
can talk about sharding.
All of these sharding actions,
well, pertain to sharding.
Things like adding a
shard, enabling sharding,
listing the shards,
moving a chunk,
and removing a shard, et cetera.
Next we can take a look at
server administration actions.
All of these actions
relate to administering
the actual database--
things like running compact,
getting the host info,
getting a server parameter,
shutting the
database itself down.
All these are directly
related to the server
and administrating it.
Next we have diagnostic actions.
These are the actions often
required to diagnose or monitor
your database.
Generally, these are the
actions that will have access
to statistics and
metrics collected
by profiling or
similar resources--
things like connection pool
stats, db stats, index stats,
server status, et cetera.
And finally, we can talk
about internal actions.
These actions are the most
sensitive set of actions
that we can grant to a role.
Be very careful when
granting these actions.
They should only be granted
in exceptional circumstances,
as they are internal
to the database.
And those are all the
different actions that
are supported with MongoDB.