In This video, we're going
to talk about resources.
We already know that
resources are the other half
of privileges in MongoDB.
They're the subjects
of our actions.
Resources will eventually have
their state or behavior changed
in some form by an action.
MongoDB has four resources,
collections, databases,
clusters, and the special
any resource resource.
All of these resources will be
defined by a resource document.
Let's look at how to define
each of these with a resource
document.
First, we'll check out
collections and databases.
So here's the
generic template that
is used to define a
collection or a database.
Through this document,
we can actually
describe a few
different scenarios.
First, we can specify
a specific database.
In this case, the
products database.
It's important to note
that we always have both
the db and the collection keys.
If we want to specify
a specific database,
we must use an empty string as
a value for the collection key.
This resource document
would allow anyone
to perform the associated
action for this resource
on any collection within
the products database.
Conversely, if we want to
grant someone the ability
to perform an action on
a specific collection
across any database,
then we use this syntax,
here specifying the empty
string for the db field
and then specifying
an actual collection
name for a collection.
And of course, we can
specify a specific collection
for a specific database for
any action to be performed on.
Finally, if we'd like to give
someone access to perform
their action on any non-system
collection on all databases,
then we can just
pass an empty string
to both the db field and
the collection field.
As far as the cluster
resource is concerned,
there's really just one document
and it looks just like this.
We just specify
the cluster field
to be true, simple as that.
And finally, we have the
any resource document,
which of course
allows an action to be
performed on any
resource in the database.
This is what it looks like.
We just pass in any
resource key, a true value,
and this is the resource
document for any resource.
Again, this resource is
for internal usage only.
Avoid its use at all cost.
And those are the different
resources in MongoDB.