Now that we know what roles
are, let's talk about some
of the built in roles that
come prepackaged with MongoDB.
MongoDB comes with a set of
general purpose built in roles.
Roles that we know
from experience
are generally required
by different individuals
and therefore different
responsibilities
within an organization.
These roles can be divided
into the following categories.
First we have
database user roles.
There are only
two roles in here,
but these are two of the
most commonly used roles.
First we have the read role,
which grants the following
privileges.
And these privileges make sense
based on the name of the role.
We would expect that if we were
granted the read role that we'd
be able to run find, dbHash,
listIndexes, listCollections,
et cetera.
Next we have the readWrite role.
This role grants us all the
privileges of the read role,
in addition to the
following privileges.
Now this demonstrates
a powerful feature
of the role based access
control authorization
system that MongoDB brings.
Role inheritance.
We have the ability to inherit
the privileges of other roles
for a given role.
We'll talk more
about this later,
but I wanted to bring
it to your attention
while we discuss all these
different built-in roles.
After database user
roles we can next
talk about database admin roles.
The first role I'm
going to talk about
is the dbAdmin role, a role
that grants us these following
privileges.
And again, this makes sense.
Imagine if we had a
database administrator,
they'd need to be able to create
collections for developers,
create indexes for
developers, maybe go
through old parts
of the database
by dropping some
old collections,
or dropping that
old test database
that the developers were using.
All of these
privileges make sense
for a database administrator.
The userAdmin role is
exactly what it sounds like,
is the ability to administrate
users within our database.
Things like changing a user's
password, creating a new user,
creating a new role,
granting a role to a user,
dropping a role, viewing
a user, et cetera.
Anything that involves
user management or user
administration is going
to be the userAdmin role.
And finally, we have
the dbOwner role,
which inherits the privileges
of readWrite, dbAdmin,
and the userAdmin roles.
After the database
administration roles,
we can now talk about
the all database roles.
Now, these roles are
going to sound familiar,
and that's because they're the
same roles that we just talked
about, but with privileges
on different resources.
In this case, any database.
So for example, the
readAnyDatabase role
inherits the privileges
of the read role,
but for any database.
Similarly, the read
write, user admin, and db
admin roles all have the same
privileges as their first part
of their name, except
these roles now get
privileges for any database.
After the all
database category we
can move on to the
cluster admin category.
Now here, we expect
to find roles
that allow us to perform actions
across an entire cluster.
And by cluster I mean a replica
set or a sharded cluster.
And that's exactly what we find.
First we have the clusterManager
role, which gives us
the following privileges.
A Cluster Manager, it
would make sense for them
to be able to add shards,
cleanup orphans, list shards,
remove shards, set up replica
sets, or resync a member.
Next, we have the clusterMonitor
role, which gives us
the following privileges.
Here we're going to
see a lot of stat
reading privileges like
connection pool stats,
getting server parameters,
getting host info,
getting server
status, et cetera.
Now, the hostManager
role is very
similar to the
clusterManager role,
except you'll see that
we now have privileges
like the ability to
do things specifically
on a host like running
the CPU profiler,
or ordering a forced
sync, or killing
an operation on a member,
or resyncing a member,
or shutting down a member.
It's somewhat similar to
the clusterManager role
but with regards to
an individual host
or an individual member
within our cluster.
And finally, we have
the clusterAdmin role,
which inherits the privileges
of all three of the other roles.
After clusterAdmin roles,
we can talk about the backup
and restore roles.
This group is pretty
straightforward.
First, we have the backup
role, which as you would expect
allows us to do everything
that we need in order
to back up our database.
And similarly, we
have the restore role,
which allows us to do
everything we need to restore
our database from a backup.
Moving on, we can talk about
two special categories.
First, we're going to talk
about the superuser category.
Now these first
three roles, you've
already seen these before.
But we're bringing them up again
because we consider these roles
to be superuser rules.
And that's because
these roles allow
a user to assign themselves
any role that they want.
So for example, when
the dbOwner role
is assigned to the
admin database,
a user can then assign
themselves any role
they want on any database.
Similarly, the userAdmin
role allows us to do this.
Actually, the dbOwner
role can do this
because it inherits
the userAdmin role.
And then similarly, the
userAdminAnyDatabase role
would include the userAdmin role
on the admin database, which
would then allow us
to assign ourselves
a role on any database.
And finally, we can
talk about root role.
And now, you've seen me use this
role before in other videos.
And while I might use it
a lot for convenience,
please be very careful
when assigning this role
to an individual.
And that's because
the root role inherits
all of these privileges,
the readWriteAnyDatabase,
dbAdminAnyDatabase,
userAdminAnyDatabase,
the clusterAdmin role,
and the restore role.
All of these roles and all
the privileges associated
with all these roles are
all inherited by this one
role, the root role.
So needless to
say, the root role
can pretty much do
anything it wants.
So the super user
category was the first
of two special categories.
The second being the
internal category.
And the internal category
only has one role,
and that is the underscore
underscore system role.
And the underscore
underscores system
allows you to take any
action on any resource.
So this is a very,
very internal role
that is only used
by the server itself
for very special
internal operations.
And because of this,
you should never
ever grant this role to a user.
You might see this in like logs
or somewhere in the database,
and so I wanted to bring it up
so you know what was going on,
but I also wanted to
give you this warning
and tell you that you
should not use this role
or assign this role
to any of your users
unless you really,
really, really have to.
And those are the built-in
roles that come with MongoDB.