Now that we've covered
transfer encryption,
we can talk about encryption
at rest, also known
as data at rest.
Encryption at rest concerns
encrypting the data
that we store on disk.
Like I've said before, there
are two broad approaches
to encrypting data
at rest with MongoDB.
There's storage level
encryption and application level
encryption.
Let's first talk about
application level encryption,
because it's not an
actual feature of MongoDB.
By application level
encryption, I'm
referring to encryption on a
per field or per document basis
within the application layer.
To encrypt a document
or field within our data
we can write a custom
encryption and decryption
routine for our
application, or of course we
can use a commercial
solution for encryption
within our application.
A great example of
application level encryption
is the storage of extremely
sensitive information
like health records.
A developer can add logic
to the application, where
before any information is
inserted into a collection it
first passes through an
encryption algorithm converting
the plain text--
like here I have
a health record that says you
know Kirby has appendicitis.
We can, before we ever
pass that to the driver
to insert it into MongoDB,
inside of out application
we can go ahead and encrypt
that information using
some kind of
encryption algorithm.
And then, we can then
pass that to the driver
and then insert that
information in MongoDB.
So MongoDB never saw that
information in plain text,
it always saw the
encrypted ciphertext.
And then of course, we then
would write decryption routines
so that when we pull
out the encrypted text
we would then convert
the encrypted text
into a decrypted text within
our application layer.
As of MongoDB
Enterprise 3.2, we've
introduced a native encryption
option for the WiredTiger
storage engine.
This feature allows MongoDB
to encrypt data files such
that only parties with
the decryption key
can decode and read the data.
Again, I like to emphasize
that this feature is
only available for Enterprise
versions of MongoDB 3.2,
and only exist for the
WiredTiger storage engine.
But basically, what
you can see here
is that our data lives in
RAM as unencrypted text.
And then whenever
MongoDB decides
to write that
information to disk
it will then encrypt
the information in RAM
and then store that encrypted
information in disk.
Storage engine encryption with
MongoDB is a four step process.
All the steps are
abstracted away from you
as a database
administrator, but are
important to
understand to deliver
a secure implementation.
First, a master
key is generated.
This key will be used to encrypt
each individual database key.
The second step, like I
mentioned in the last step,
is to generate a key
for each database.
After a key has been generated
for a particular database,
that key can be used to
encrypt that actual database.
After all databases
have been encrypted
with their respective
keys, each key
is then encrypted
with the master key
that we got from step 1.
It's important to note that
each database key is actually
stored within MongoDB, which
is why the master key exists
outside of MongoDB.
Only the master key is
external to the server
and requires
external management.
To manage the master key,
MongoDB's encrypted storage
engine supports two
key management options.
The first and recommend
option is an integration
with a third party key
management appliance
via the Key Management
Interoperability Protocol,
commonly referred to as KMIP.
Your other option is to
use local key management
via a key file.
We do not recommend local
key file management.
enabling the encrypted
storage engine
is relatively
straightforward in practice.
For the sake of
simplicity, we're
going to start with
the not recommended
option of using local key
management via a key file.
We'll first need to
generate a master key
and place it in a key file.
Here I'm using open SSL
passing in Rand base64
giving it a length
of 32 and then
redirecting that output to a
file called MongoDB-keyfile.
This will generate
a random assortment
of base 64 characters
to act as our key file.
Now that that key file has
been created, let's go ahead
and put the correct
permissions on the file
so that MongoDB
can read from it.
Here I'm saying chmod
600 and our file,
and we now have good
permissions for MongoDB
to read our key file.
And from here it's
as easy as starting
mongod with our storage
engine encryption enabled.
After creating our key file and
putting the correct permissions
on it, starting a mongod
instance with storage engine
encryption enabled is as
easy as passing the dash dash
encryption option and
a dash dash encryption
key file option with a
MongoDB key file argument.
And it really is that simple.
Now our server is waiting for
connections on port 27 0 17.