Sometimes we're in
a situation where
we'll need to run a
mix of TLS connections
and non-TLS connections.
A great example of this
is migrating a replica
set from one that uses
no encryption to one that
uses TLS exclusively.
While we'd love to force all of
our clients to connect via TLS,
sometimes this isn't
easy because we
might need to update
drivers or issue
new certificates to
each individual client
of our database.
In this scenario, we really
want to have all of the members
in between our ReplSet use TLS.
But we would really
like for our clients
to choose between
using TLS and using
an unencrypted connection.
In order to do this, instead of
using our regular old require
SSL mode, we can use
the prefer SSL mode.
And what prefer SSL does is
exactly what I just said.
It will allow us to require
SSL between all the members
of our replica set,
but it will allow
clients to choose to use SSL
or to just connect unencrypted.
Of course, over time
as we eventually
issue these new
certificates to our clients
and as they update their drivers
or their application logic
as necessary, we can then
switch from using prefer
TLS to using require SSL.
So that all connections to our
server, whether it be a member
or whether it be a
client, will require
TLS for all connections.
Let's go ahead and do this.
So this process should be
pretty straightforward.
We're essentially
using the same command
as we did last time, except now
we're using preferSSL instead
of requireSSL.
We've now started the first
member of our replica set.
Here's the command to start the
second member of our replica
set.
The only thing I changed is the
db path, log path, and port.
And finally, here's the third
member of our replica set.
Of course just changing the db
path, log path, and port again.
And unlike before,
now that we're
preferring SSL instead
of requiring it,
I can just run Mongo
instead of running
Mongo with the SSL options
and providing the client
certificate.
And you can see that I've
now successfully connected
to the replica set.
But the replica set
hasn't been initiated.
So let's go ahead and
initiate the ReplSet
with the correct configuration.
And here's the
same configuration
we did as last time.
I'm still using my
encrypted ReplSet
and passing in all the
members specifying localhost
as the host and their
respective ports.
And we get an OK.
So now you can see
members are all using SSL
and clients can choose between
using SSL or not using SSL.
Let's go and verify
that I can still use
SSL to connect to the server.
Server is still
running, and now I
can go ahead and try and
connect actually using SSL.
And now we've
successfully connected.