So let's assume that our intern
has proven to be very capable.
And we now want to give him
a bit more responsibility.
To do that, Alice,
our security officer,
will be able to create
a new user-defined role,
and then can change
the intern's role
to reflect this new
set of privileges.
In this particular case,
we want to allow our intern
to perform updates on
the meteorite collection
within the NASA database.
Here we have the
db.createRole command.
I'm creating a new
role called internRole.
And here's the list of
our privileged documents.
We just have one
privileged document,
which is the privileged
document that
allows us to update the
collection meteorites
on the NASA database.
So here's our resource document.
Here's our list of
actions, in this case, just
the update action.
And then we still
want this intern role
to be able to
inherit the ability
to read the NASA database, just
like the intern was before.
So here is the read role
on the NASA database.
And here are all
the inherited roles.
Now when we click Enter,
we can see that the role
has been successfully created.
To complete this
configuration, we just
need to update the intern user
and grant them the intern role.
Here we go.
I'm now going to update the user
intern with a list of roles.
So this will override any
roles they currently have.
And the only role that
we're going to give them
is the intern role on
the admin database.
Here I'm going to go ahead
and get the NASA database,
because that's the database
that the intern was created on.
And now I can go ahead
and issue updateUser
on the NASA database,
specifying that I
want to update the
intern user, and replace
all their current
roles with this list
of roles, which in this case
is just our new role-- intern
role.
Let's go ahead and
authenticate as the intern,
and see if we can
update our meteorites.
Here we go.
I'm going to go ahead
and authenticate
as the intern on
the NASA database.
And now I can go ahead
and find a meteorite.
And here's a nice meteorite.
Now let's go ahead and try
and update this meteorite.
Now I'm going to
attempt to run update
on the meteorites collection.
I'm going to get the
same document right here
by using ID equals 2.
And then I'm going to
set a new field called
newfield with the string,
"the update worked!"
Awesome.
And as you can see,
here is our result.
And there's our
updated document.
Great.
Now we can assign the
task of correcting
all the data to the intern.