Let's get started with
this real world example.
We'll start by connecting
to our cluster.
And by using the
localhost exception
we can create our first user.
Now this first user should be
a user who has the capability
to create other users.
This means we're going to start
by creating a user for Alice,
and that's because she's
our security officer.
This means it's
her responsibility
to create users that will
interact with our database.
It also means that
she's going to need
to be able to create and
drop users in our database,
grant and revoke roles,
and also be able to create,
update, and delete roles.
However, this means
she does not need
to see any collection data,
query or drop any database
or collection, or perform backup
or restoration operations.
I've already set up a
replica set on this machine
with authorization enabled.
We can take a quick peek at
the commands I used to do this,
but you should already
be familiar with how
to do this because we've
covered it in a previous video.
As you can see, we have a pretty
standard 3 node replica set,
where I'm running the same
command again and again
for each member, with
slight variations for the db
path, log path, and port.
I'm using a key file
for authentication
between the members
of our replica set.
Let's go ahead and
connect to our replica set
and create a user for Alice.
Now that I'm connected I
can go ahead and switch
to the admin database.
And from here I
can run Create User
and create a user for Alice.
And as you can see, we
created a user name alice
with the password
sharppencil and she
has a role of
userAdminAnyDatabase
on the admin database.
Now we already know that the
userAdminAnyDatabase role will
allow us to administer our
users on well any database,
but we can go ahead
and use db dot get role
to look a little
bit more closely
at how this world works.
In order to do this, we're going
to need to first authenticate
against the database.
Let's go ahead and log in
with Alice's credentials.
We're now logged in and
we can run get role.
Here I'm saying I want to
find out more information
about the user
admin database role,
and I'm saying I want to
show all the privileges.
Let's go ahead and
assign this to a variable
to make it a little
bit more readable.
Now as you can see, here is
the role, it's quite long.
But let's go into the top here
and look at the main stuff.
So here's what we would expect.
Let's go ahead and take
a little bit closer look
at the privileges.
And this is why we
made it a variable.
So we have eight privileges.
Let's go through
these one by one.
And this first privilege
makes a lot of sense.
We have a resource
that would allow
us to perform an action on any
collection on any database.
And here are the
actions that can
be performed on any collection.
The ability to change
someone's custom data,
change their password, create a
role, create a user, et cetera.
All the things a
user admin, or in
this case a security
officer, would need to do.
Let's look at the
next privilege.
Here's our second privilege,
and this makes sense.
These are cluster
wide user roles.
The ability to list databases,
invalidate the user cache,
authSchemsUpgrade, these are
all pretty user related roles.
Here's the next one.
Again, we can see
that we're interacting
with the special
system dot users
collection, which
makes sense since Alice
is going to have to be able
to do user related task.
Here's system dot users
on the admin database.
Again, basically the ability
to do basic interactions
with system dot users.
Again roles, also makes
sense for a user admin.
System dot version
also makes sense.
More user admin stuff,
and more user admin stuff.
All this looks nice and dandy.
And now that we've looked
at all of Alice's privileges
for her
userAdminAnyDatabase role,
we now know that she can
do these three things
and she can't do any
of these three things.
So we have confidence that
Alice has all the actions
and privileges needed
to do her job correctly.