- So our intern
has gone too far,
and started to change
data that was logged long
before his time.
To solve this, we need
to go back and revoke
the privilege that allows
the update on the internlog
collection.
- To do this, we just need
to authenticate and run
the db.revokePrivelegesFromRole
command.
Here's the command that we use.
On the intern role, we want
to revoke this right here,
the ability to update
on the internlog
collection on any database.
- It Looks like it
ran successfully.
Let's go ahead and
check out our roll.
And here again,
we're going to use
db.getRole to show all the
privileges on the intern role.
- And now if we scroll up,
we can see on the internlog
collection, the user
is still able to insert
but is no longer allowed to
update on the internet log
collection on any database.