By now you should have a pretty
good understanding of user
authorization with MongoDB.
We're now ready to
take our new knowledge
and apply it with a
real world example.
For this demonstration,
we're going
to imagine that we
have a technology
organization with four
users of our database.
Each of these users will
have different rules
according to the
different responsibilities
that they have.
So here's our
imaginary organization.
First, we have Alice.
She's a security officer.
Next, we have Ben.
He's the sysadmin.
Then we have Carol.
She's our DBA.
And finally, we have Dan.
Dan's an intern, and he does
most of the work on the team,
but he can only touch
one specific database.
We don't want him messing up
the configuration of the system
or anything.
So for all these
users, we should
be able to get by only using
the available built-in rules
with MongoDB.
Let's go ahead and start
by booting up a cluster
with authorization enabled.