Let's talk about how transparent
encryption works with MongoDB.
Like we said before,
transport encryption
refers to encrypting the network
traffic between the Mongo
client and the Mongo server.
More explicitly, we're
referring to the use of TLS/SSL
to encrypt all the information
between the client and server.
TLS and SSL are often
used interchangeably.
But TLS is actually
the successor to SSL,
and it's considered
much more secure.
Often though, you'll
see the usage of SSL
when people are actually
referring to TLS.
For the sake of
clarity, I'm just
gonna use TLS for the
remainder of this video.
I don't want to get into the
nitty-gritty details of how
TLS works, because it isn't
directly useful for you
to deploy a secure
MongoDB deployment.
I will, however,
mention that TLS
is underpinned by the
public/private key encryption
algorithm through the
utilization of SSL
certificates.
This allows the
client and server
to verify that each other
is who they say they are.
And it also provides
us with the ability
to encrypt messages without
ever sending the shared
key across the wire.
Because of this, MongoDB
uses open SSL libraries
to implement TLS.
MongoDB's SSL encryption
only allows the use
of strong SSL decipherers.
And in our case,
that means a minimum
of 128-bit length
for all connections.