The next user we need
to create is Ben.
He's our sysAdmin.
It's Ben's job to manage
clusters and machines.
This means he's going to need
to be able to do maintenance
operations-- things like
adding and removing members
of a replica set or
adding and removing
shards in a sharded cluster.
Ben should not,
however, be allowed
to see any collection
data, create or drop
any database or
collection, or even list
any collections or databases.
So now it's up to Alice, our
recently created security
officer, to actually
create such a user.
We'll first need to log in
with Alice's credentials.
We created Alice's account
on the admin database.
So we need to switch
that database first.
Now we can log in with
Alice's credentials.
And now we're
successfully logged in.
Before creating this user
and granting it a role,
let's go ahead and
check which roles
we think Ben will allow him
to do everything he needs.
I haven't mentioned this yet.
But it's important that you use
the online documentation that
docs.MongoDB.com to look at
all available built-in roles.
It very clearly
outlines here everything
that all the different
roles can do.
And since we want Ben to
be able to add and remove
shards or different
members of a replica set,
it probably makes sense to
use the Cluster Manager role.
This means he'll be able to
add shards, remove shards, be
able to do regular
replica set operations.
But he won't be able to
look at any collection data,
or even list any
databases or collections.
Great.
Let's go ahead and
create this user for Ben.
Here I'm going to give
Ben the username ben.
His password, of course,
is going to be cables.
And we're gonna give
him the Cluster Manager
role on the admin database.
Let's go ahead and
see if we can log in.
Great.
Now Ben should be able to
configure our replica sets
and perform cluster maintenance.