When using TLS there are
several connection modes
that can be passed to MongoD.
Here's an example command
to start a MongoDB server.
We've seen commands like
this before when setting up
x.509 authentication.
Here we're saying MongoDB
passing in the dash dash SSL
mode option, which takes
the argument of what
kind of connection mode
we're going to have.
In this case-- and as
we've seen before-- we're
using requireSSL.
And then of course, since
we're requiring SSL,
we need to pass in the KeyFile
for this SSL connection.
There actually exists
four different SSL modes
when using SSL with MongoDB.
There is disabled, where the
server does not use TLS at all.
And this is the
default mode when you
don't pass an option to MongoD.
There's allowSSL, which
means that connections
between the server do
not have to use TLS.
But if there is an incoming
connection that uses TLS,
the server will then accept it.
There is preferredSSL,
which means connections
in between members
of a replica set
or sharded cluster will use TLS.
But for incoming
connections, the server
will accept both TLS connections
and non-TLS connections.
And then there's
requireSSL, which
means that all
connections to the server,
whether between members of a
replica set or sharded cluster,
or between the
server and client,
all connections will
be required to use SSL.