In this video we're going to
talk about what privileges
look like in MongoDB.
We've already talked
about the set of actions
that a user can perform.
And we've also talked
about the resources
that those actions
can operate on.
We're finally in
a place where we
can look at what privileges
look like in MongoDB.
Privileges are defined by
using a privileged document.
In this document,
we define a resource
and the actions that are able
to operate on that resource.
The easiest way to understand
how privileged documents can
be used is to see how they are
used to define a built-in role.
Right now I'm in
the Mongo shell.
And I'm connected to a MongoD.
From here we can
go ahead and look
at how built-in
roles are defined
by privileged documents.
Let's take a look at the
simplest of all roles--
the read role.
Here I'm getting ready to
run the db.getRole command.
And I'm passing in
read as a string,
because I want to look at
the built-in role read.
As you can see, I can now
see how this role is defined.
I see the name of the
role, the database that
uniquely associates
itself to this role,
and the array of all
the inherited roles.
But I would expect to also
see all of the privileges that
make up this role.
Well, since a role is often
made up by a lot of privileges,
by default, getRole
won't show you
all of the privileges
that make up a role.
If we want to do that,
we run this command.
db.getRole.
But now we're
passing in a document
saying showPrivileges true.
I'll go ahead and
scroll up a bit
so we can see the command
we ran and see the output.
Here's the command we ran.
And here is the output
that we saw before.
And now we have a new additional
field called privileges,
which has an array on it.
To make things easier to
read, let's assign this object
to a variable so we can look
at each privilege one by one.
Now I can simply do
readRole.privileges
to see all the privileges.
And I can see how
many there are.
So now I know there
are four privileges.
So now I can choose
array notation
to look at each individual one.
Let's take a look at the
first privileged document
that makes up the read role.
As you can see, anyone
with the read role
is allowed to run
collection of stats,
dbHash, find, et cetera on
any collection within the test
database.
Cool.
This makes sense.
But I wonder what the other
privileged documents are for.
Let's check them out.
Here is the second document.
Here is the third document.
And here's the fourth
and final document.
As you can see, all these
other privileged documents
look exactly the same,
except for the collection
that they're talking about.
Each of them talking about a
different system collection.
This is because these
internal system collections
need to be explicitly defined in
a privileged document in order
for a user to access them.
In the case of the read
role, all these collections
make sense.
Let's look at them a
little bit more closely.
Here we're talking
about system.indexes.
It probably makes
sense for us to be
able to look at all of
the indexes on a database.
Here we have system.js.
This holds special
JavaScript code
for use in server
side JavaScript.
This also makes sense for our
users to be able to read from.
And finally, we have
system.namespaces.
And this also makes sense,
because it makes sense
to allow our users to be able
to list all the collections
within a database.
I hope this example illustrates
how actions, resources,
and privileges work together
to define roles in MongoDB.