To correct this
situation, we need
to change Carol's role from
dbAdmin to dbAdminAnyDatabase.
Alice, our security
officer, should
be able to update Carol's
role by using the update user
command.
Here, I'm ging to run the
db.updateUser command.
We're going to
update it for Carol,
and we're going to change her
roles from wherever they were
before, which we
know is dbAdmin,
to just being dbAdminAnyDatabase
on the admin database.
We can now confirm this
by running db.getUser.
And now can easily confirm
that Carol does indeed
have the dbAdminDatabase role.
Now when we
authenticate with Carol,
we should be able run show dbs.
And we can.
Awesome.
Carol can now do her job.