We can now discuss why MongoDB
uses role based access control.
The best way to describe why
MongoDB uses role based access
control is to say
that it gives us
a high level of
responsibility isolation
for operational tasks.
And what I mean by this is
that across our organization
there are going to be a
myriad of different people
who are going to need
access to our database.
But each of these individuals
have very different needs.
We might have a DBA.
They're going to need the
ability to create users.
We might have a developer.
They're obviously going to
need to be able to insert data
into our database.
But they're probably
not going to need
to be able to create users.
We might have a data scientist.
They're going to need
to be able to read
a bunch of data out of MongoDB.
But they're not
likely going to need
to be able to create users or
insert data into our database.
What we're basically saying here
is that within our organization
there are a bunch
of different roles.
And we can tightly define and
tailor our roles in MongoDB
to match the needs of our users.