In this video,
we're going to talk
about the authorization model
that is used with MongoDB.
MongoDB actually follows a
very straightforward and common
authorization model,
and that model
is role based access control.
Role based access control,
as the name implies,
is a model where
for any given user
we're going to go ahead and
assign a role to that user.
And that role is going to be
assigned over a given name
space.
And in the context of MongoDB,
a namespace is just a database.
So for example, here we
have a user named Kirby,
and Kirby has the
readWrite roll,
which has been granted to him
for the products database.
And this makes a lot of sense
given the command that we've
been using to create users.
As you can see
here, this is really
just a one to one relationship.
We have a user named Kirby, a
roll called the readWrite role,
and the readWrite role is
for the products database.
Now that we have a general
idea of what role based
access control is, let's
go ahead and break down
what a role is.
The formal definition
of a role with regards
to role based access
control is the following.
Roles are groups of privileges,
actions over resources,
that are granted to users
over a given namespace,
commonly referred
to as a database.
So we know what users
are and we obviously
know what databases are, but
what are privileges, actions,
and resources?
Well, let's go ahead and take
a closer look at these three
things and how they relate
together to define roles.
Let's first talk about actions.
All operations and commands that
a user can perform in MongoDB
are called actions.
And actions are performed
on the resources.
Resources are any objects that
hold state in our database.
So for example, a
collection, a database,
or a database cluster.
And when a user performs an
action on a given resource
that constitutes a privilege.
And if we then go
ahead and group
a bunch of these
privileges together,
we can go ahead and rename
that group of privileges
just a role.
This sentence should make
a lot more sense now.
I'm going to go ahead
and say it again.
Roles are groups or privileges,
actions over resources,
that are granted to users
over a given database.
We've now looked at all of the
different parts that make up
this definition of a role.
And so you should have a
much better understanding
of what roles are in
the context of MongoDB.