In this lesson, we're going
to cover the list of things
that you'll need to know
prior to taking this course.
If any of the items in this
lesson are unfamiliar to you,
feel free to pause
this video and fill
in those gaps in knowledge
before proceeding.
First and foremost,
we're looking
for database fundamentals.
Terms like table, collection,
database, relationship, schema,
entity, and database
transaction should already
be part of your vocabulary.
If you're comfortable
in using and explaining
these and other related terms,
then you're in good shape.
You can refresh your
memory on most of these
by following the reference
links in the lecture notes.
Another good thing to know
about is the entity relationship
diagram and the appropriate
notation that comes with that.
Does the image in
the right make sense?
What is the relationship between
the student and course tables?
If you can answer these
questions comfortably,
then you're prepared
to take this course.
Otherwise, check
out the references
in the lecture notes.
There is, of course, a softer
requirement for this course,
as well.
Using Compass, you'll need to
be able to connect to the M320
MongoDB Atlas cluster
that was created
for the purposes of this course.
We will walk you
through this process
in one of the following
lectures in the meantime, if you
want to read up on Atlas,
feel free to check out
the link that's
attached to this lesson.