In this lesson, we will dig
into how much you should model--
in other words, how
many steps should
be done in the three
phases of our methodology.
The main trade
that you will face
is simplicity
versus performance,
prioritizing one over the
other or trying to find
a balance between the two.
Modeling for simplicity means we
will avoid any complexity that
could slow down the development
of the system by our engineers.
The most typical case would
be developing an application
quickly with one or
few software engineers.
Frequently, for those
kind of projects,
there are limited expectations
and small requirements in term
of CPU, disk, I/O, memory.
Things are generally
small and simple.
You should start by identifying
the most important operations
for the system.
And you will need to
establish the relationships
between the entities and fields.
To keep the model simple,
you are likely to group
a lot of those pieces
inside a few collection
using sub-documents
or arrays to represent
the one-to-one, one-to-many,
too many-to-many
many relationships.
By keeping the modeling
steps to the minimum,
we can remain very
agile, with the ability
to quickly iterate on our
application, reflecting
these changes back into
the model if needed.
If you model for
simplicity, as a result,
you will likely see fewer
collection in your design
where each document contains
more information and maps very
well to the object you have
in your application code--
the objects being represented
in your favorite language
as hashes, maps, dictionary,
or nested objects.
Finally, as a result of
having larger documents
with embedded documents
in them, the application
is likely to do
less disk accesses
to retrieve the information.
These three collection
embedded into one,
a single read will be sufficient
to retrieve the information
instead of four.
At other end of our axis, we
have the performance criteria.
In this scenario,
resources are likely to be
used to the maximum
I like to compare
this situation to an engine
running at the red line.
Project that makes
use of sharding
to scatter horizontally
are likely to fall
into this category, because
you often shard your database
because there is
not enough resources
available with a
simple replica set.
The system may require very
fast read or writes operation,
or it may have to support
a ton of operations.
Although situations
are demanding
a model for performance.
More complex projects are
often done by larger teams.
And those larger teams
will require a little bit
more modeling upfront.
When you model for performance
or have more complexity
to handle, you want to
go over all the steps
of the methodology.
Again, you start by identifying
the important operations,
but also quantify those
in terms of metrics
like operation per
second, required latency,
and pinning some
quality attributes
on those queries such as--
can the application
work with data
that's a little stale,
are those operations parts
of the large analytic query?
If you model for performance you
will often see more collection
in your design.
You will also need to apply
a series of schema design
patterns to ensure the
best usage of resources
like CPU, disk, bandwidth.
And in between, well,
you have project
that have more of a balance
or trade between those two
criteria.
For example, you may
have a project that
needs to be developed
quickly, but you will also
need to apply some
transformations
and optimization to meet
performance requirements.
Here you will need to
identify what seems
important for this project.
Positioning your project on this
axis is a little bit of an art.
My advice is it is easier
to find optimization
later on than to remove
complexity from an application.
So prior to rise simplicity
over performance.
Let's look again at the steps
you may do for each phase based
on your requirements.
Regardless of your
project, you will
need to start by
identifying your workload.
It can go from a simple
identification of the most
important operations to
an exhaustive and complete
description of the read
and write operations.
Then, you need to choose
between embedding or linking
the model, the relationship.
Simplicity will favor embedding.
In the final phase, the more
performance requirements
you have, the more likely
patterns will be applied.
Let's recap what we've
learned this lesson.
MongoDB makes the development
of applications much faster
than traditional
relational databases.
And we don't want
the methodology
to slow things down either.
Doing the right thing
first and having a way
to share information
between the team members
is important for having
a successful project.
First of all,
recognize the trade off
between modeling for
simplicity and performance.
Secondly, use the methodology
in a flexible fashion.
Select the step
within a phase that
makes sense for your project.
Finally, regardless of
how much you will model,
you need to start by describing
the workload of your project.
Identifying the important
operations correctly
will get you started
on the right path.