In this lesson, we will
go over a methodology
to help you through
the old process of data
modeling for MongoDB.
The methodology we use is
composed of three phases.
The first phase is to
describe the workload.
In other terms,
it means gathering
everything there is
to know about how
you would be using your data.
The second phase is to
identify the relationships
between the different
entities you
need to handle and choose how
to model those relationships.
And the third phase is
to apply design patterns
or transformation
to the current model
to address performance
requirements.
Let's describe each
phase a little bit more.
As for the details, example, and
actions required in each phase,
those will be part
of the following
lessons in this course.
Let's start at the beginning.
Your goal is to create a data
model, what is often referred
to as your MongoDB schema.
A few things may be
available to you.
For example, you may have
a requirements document
listing the scenarios the
system needs to support.
Alternatively, or
in complement, you
may have an expert on the
domain, who can advise
on what needs to be done.
You may be migrating from
a relational database,
or you are evolving an
existing MongoDB database.
In both cases, logs,
stats, et cetera,
give you additional information
about the current state
of the system.
If they exist, you
want to use them.
Finally, someone needs to
assemble this information
together in the schema.
This is done by the
data modeling expert.
This will be you by
the end of this course.
So the first phase is
to look at the documents
that you have in your input
and create some artifacts out
of them.
You should be able to
size the amount of data
your system will have
initially, in few months,
and in few years.
Obviously, you will
get those number wrong.
Don't worry.
Practice makes perfect.
So give it your best try.
The action of
recording those numbers
will permit you to observe any
major deviations in your system
once it's in operation.
Those differences will
be a good indicator
that you may have to iterate
again over your schema.
The same applies to the
operations, the reads
and the writes.
You should be able to tell how
many are run per unit of time
and if each query has
additional requirements in terms
of execution time, the latency
from the application, tolerance
to staleness, et cetera.
For each of these
operation requirements,
record your thoughts
and assumptions.
They will also be
a good indicator
to see whether you need to
reevaluate the model again
later.
In our second phase, we start
with a piece of information
that were identified.
Each piece has a relationship
with another one.
The ones that have a
one-to-one relationship
tend to be grouped together in
the same table or collection.
In modeling for a
relational database,
you would probably have come
up with those three entities--
actors, movies, and reviews.
And place the piece
of information
inside the appropriate entity.
For example, a movie title
has a one-to-many relationship
to the reviews for the
movie, while the money earned
by the movie has a one-to-one
relationship with the movie
title.
So the movie title
and its revenues
are in the same
entity or collection,
while the reviews are in
a separate collection.
With MongoDB, you
follow the same process
of identifying the
relationships between the pieces
of information.
However, you need to decide
if you embed information
or keep it separate.
How do you decide?
This is where you start
using the knowledge you
will acquire in this class.
At the end of this
process, you will
have a list of entities
with their fields, some
of them grouped together
inside the common collection.
Our last phase is to apply
schema design patterns.
This is where you
will get to make
your model more performant
or more clear by applying
some transformations.
We will cover this phase of the
methodology in a future chapter
by giving you a
number of recipes
you can apply to your model.
You may need to iteratively
improve your solution,
and this is fine.
If any of the input information
on the left changes,
you need to assess the impact
on the decision you've made
in their corresponding phase.
For example, if you discover
another reported query,
get more data about the
size of your problem,
or run benchmarks on your
current solution, all that
known information, with feedback
as the input to the model.
Any successful application
will undergo modifications
at some point in
its lifetime, so
be ready to get new
inputs at some point.
If you track why you
made some decision
and what were the
assumptions in the past,
it will be much easier to
apply the needed changes.
Let's recap what we have
learned in this lesson.
There are three phases
in our methodology.
The first addresses
the workload.
You want to identify
the size of your data,
the important reads and
writes of the system,
and possibly quantify and
qualify those operations.
The second phase regards
the identification
of the relationships.
Coming out of that
step, you should
have a list of collection with
the decision of whether you
embed or link the
relationships between them.
Finally, the third step is to
apply schema design patterns
to your model to
address the performance
requirements by applying
the needed optimizations.