In this lesson, we will
discuss why constraints
drive the need to model.
Did you ever plan on how
you will get your oxygen
for a day of your life?
For most of us,
we don't have to.
There is plenty of
oxygen. And it's available
as quickly as
needed by our lungs.
However, if you were an
astronaut like my friend David,
here, your life will depend
on the careful planning
of the supply, the
estimation of its usage,
and securing the oxygen
from any danger or accident.
My point being that if the
resource is abundant and can
be transferred
without delay, there
is not much planning or modeling
to do about the resource.
Unfortunately,
with computers, we
deal with limited
resources, which
are crippled by restrictions
of size, speed, and cost.
For that reason,
you need to model
to make the best of
the resources available
and work around the
restrictions that you have.
Let's start with the hardware.
RAM is the fastest
location where
you can put data, besides
the processor caches.
Unfortunately, it
becomes very expensive
if you need a
humongous amount of it.
For that reason, you are likely
to offload some of the data
to disk, which are cheaper
and have larger capacities.
Solid State Drives,
or SSDs, would
be the preferred type of disk.
However, the cost of
high-capacity SSDs
may be more than
you're ready to spend.
For this situation, you may
consider traditional hard disk
drives.
Those three types of
hardware that handle data--
RAM, SSDs, and HDDs--
have a strong correlation
between their price
and their speed.
The next type of restriction
is related to your data.
The data you want to keep or
have might just be impractical.
Keeping petabytes
of data that go back
to the beginning of time may
just not work for your budget.
Often you will see
projects that discriminate
between recent
data that is often
used by [? the ?]
system versus data
mostly used by analytic queries.
A way to deal with
this situation
is to allocate faster
resources, like SSDs
for the frequently accessed
data, and HDDs for the data
that has fewer
latency requirements.
Other aspects to consider
are data retention policies
and data sovereignty
regulations that
may impact the way you define
your data model in order
to be compliant.
And obviously, security has to
be on your mind when modeling.
Giving access to some pieces
of data and not others
will influence how
you group that data
in your documents
and collections.
To cover these concerns, MongoDB
offers a set of access controls
and security checks that we'll
briefly discuss in this course
but are better covered in
our MongoDB security courses.
Your application would
like to return the data
as quickly as possible.
However, there are physical
limits on the network's speed.
We can make bigger
and faster drives.
But it may take us a while to
improve on the speed of light.
Modeling for applications
that are globally distributed
and accessed by clients
in different locations
may require a bit more
thinking about how
we can make data accessible
without compromising service
quality.
And the last group
I want to highlight
is the limits of
the database server.
In the case of
MongoDB, a document
can't be larger than 16 meg.
And with the current
WiredTiger engine,
reading information
from a document
requires the full document
to be loaded in RAM.
Both of those constraints
may drive your design
to split frequently
accessed data
from the rest of the data
less frequently accessed.
As for writes, if you need
to write too many documents,
well, you will use a transaction
with the traditional tabular
databases, which are
frequently referred
as relational databases.
However, you can
simplify your application
and avoid using transactions
by storing all the information
that needs to be updated
in a single document,
as a write to a document
is ACID compliant.
In other words,
transactions are a must-have
in tabular databases.
However, in a document
database like MongoDB,
you can do well without them.
But just to be clear, MongoDB
does support transactions.
We mentioned frequently accessed
data a few times already.
Let's clarify this expression.
As you know or may
have guessed, if you
can keep the old
database in RAM,
it will give you very
good performance.
However, it is
often not practical
or may just be a waste of money.
What you want to
aim for is keeping
the data that is
frequently accessed
and needs to be
returned quickly in RAM.
We refer to this data
as the working set.
A definition for the working set
would be the total body of data
that the application uses in
the course of normal operations.
In this picture, the
chunk of data in red
are the ones we want to keep
in memory, while we still
have some RAM left to swap
information that is used less
often in and out from the disk.
In summary, the frequently
accessed documents and indexes
is their working set, which is
a set of pages read from this
that contain the documents and
indexes that the system handles
pretty often.
Before we go, let's just
spell out some guidelines.
Keep the frequently
used documents
and indexes in memory.
They are what we just
described as a working set.
Prefer solid state drives
to hard disk drives.
However, if you have a ton
of historical data, data
you don't use very
often, hard disk drives
are cheaper and may just work
as well for this type of data.
Let's recap what we have
learned in this lesson.
The nature of your data set
and hardware define the need
to model your data.
It is important to identify
those exact constraints
and their impact to
create a better model.
As your software and the
technological landscape change,
your model should be
re-evaluated and updated
accordingly.