In this lesson,
we will learn how
to identify the workload
for a given application.
To help us in this
quest, we are going
to use an Internet
of Things use case.
The organization has 100
million water sensors
deployed around the world.
The requirement is
to collect this data
and make it available to a
team of 10 data scientists.
Going back to our methodology,
we start with the first phase,
identifying, quantifying,
and qualifying the workload.
Here's the information
we have to begin with.
We don't have production
logs and stats.
However, we do have a prototype.
We can't rely on the
business domain expert.
However, there is only a
handful of things to understand.
So I think we'll be able
to do it by ourselves.
As for the data
modeling expert, we
have a MongoDB certified
developer in our team.
As noted earlier,
our previous team
has written a
prototype that captures
the data we see
under the collection
data in the database,
sample_weatherdata.
You can explore this data
set on Atlas with Compass.
A unique string identifies
each device using the device
position in the field.
Additional fields store metrics
like air temperature, dew
point, pressure, wind,
for a given measure.
A numeric value and the relative
quality on the scale of 1 to 9
describe these metrics.
Note that a metric
like the wind may
be represented by sub-metrics.
The prototype was
useful to see which
queries our meteorologists
wanted to run.
Now it is our job to
scale up the prototype
to collecting data from a few
million devices in the field.
So far, we know the following.
10 million devices
are collecting data.
Data can be collected every
minute and sent every minute.
Any trend calculated with
the granularity of one hour
is nearly as precise
as the ones calculated
with data for each
minute, except for periods
of special events like
tornadoes and hurricanes.
We need to keep the data
for at least 10 years.
This period may be extended for
irregularity or expanded use
cases.
However, the
changing requirements
may have a massive
impact on your design,
so ensure you take the
appropriate time and effort
to validate them if needed.
The ops team needs to
be able to identify
faulty and
non-transmitting devices.
We also need to run some
script to aggregate data,
to make the data
simpler to analyze.
Our goal for data
scientists is to analyze
the data to find trends.
Maybe some queries are fixed,
while the other ones are
exploratory ones, meaning
they are difficult to predict
in advance.
Translating what we just
said in these statements,
these are the scenarios we
want to capture and support
with our application.
Now that we know for how
long we need to hold data,
what's the frequency
by which data
is transmitted to the system
and the number of devices that
are going to be sending data?
Let's make a list of the
CRUD operations, specifically
the read and write operations,
the system needs to handle.
Each actor produces
one or more operations,
which translates to
entities and field,
and we need to
identify each operation
as a read or a write operation.
In a more complex model,
you could have more queries,
and you would expand on the
type and the fields that
are used by the operations.
We have attached
the lecture notes
for this lesson as a spreadsheet
that helps with this workload
calculation.
In the context of
this calculation,
we need to identify the
most critical operation.
Most of the time, there is
only one query that stands out.
In this case, writing the
data sent by the device
dwarfs the other operation.
So this suggests that the system
should be sized and optimized
for incoming writes
from our data sensors.
Let's look closer
at this operation.
The workload comes
from the sensors,
sending weather
data to our system.
They are mostly write
operations of new documents.
The operation carries a
device ID, a time stamp,
and a device matrix.
The data is sent every minute
by 100 million devices,
or translate to 1.6
million writes per second.
Each write is about 1,000 bytes.
So this is the size we
observe for the document
in a prototype.
It is a requirement to keep
each piece of data for 10 years.
In the case of these
write operations,
we don't need to wait
for a majority of nodes
to acknowledge the
write operation.
What do we mean by this?
Each sensor reading
sent to the system
gets replicated to other hosts.
However, we are not going
to wait for the replication
process to complete.
It is sufficient
for an application
to know that the primary
has received the data.
Each single minute reading
is not a crucial piece
of information,
mainly because we
aggregate the data over time.
In the event of issues with
the network or the host,
because we did not wait for
a majority of nodes writing
the data, it could result
in a piece of data missing
on the newly elected primary.
Typically for IoT projects,
entering a single write
as on the primary
node is sufficient.
Lowering data
durability requirements
is in contrast to writing a
crucial piece of information,
like an operation involving
money, updates to user account,
or anything that you
don't want to lose.
For this type of data,
you want to confirm
that it is written to
a majority of nodes
before the cluster acknowledges
your write operation back
to the application.
On the other hand, some
data aggregated or refreshed
frequently may not
need the same care
in terms of data durability.
Understanding your
data and being
able to make this
compromise early
has a considerable impact on
the performance of your system.
Did we say 1.6 million
operations per second?
Hosts with many cores
in [? fastest ?]
can sustain around
100,000 writes per second.
To satisfy this
order of operation,
you could estimate a cluster
with a data-partition
in 10 to 20 shards to handle
this kind of workload.
Now that you know
what's the estimated
workload and requirements,
you can start
budgeting your hardware needs.
Alternatively to
provisioning a cluster
to support all
this data, you may
want to ask if you absolutely
need to record all the data.
Understanding what data
drop rate is acceptable
is an important
strategy that needs
to be used by systems that
collect data from many devices.
You should ask yourself these
interesting questions as
early as possible.
In this use case, the
system presents a workload
where writes correspond to 99%
of all database operations.
Optimizing for writes has a
lot to do with the hardware.
However, on the
data modeling side,
we want to look into
patterns or techniques that
allow for reducing the
number of individual writes
or grouping information in
individual data structures.
Reads are also
essentials, perhaps not
based on the quantity
of these operations,
but on the user experience
that they represent.
Let's look at the
most crucial read
operation, which are performed
by our data scientists.
The data scientists run
this read operation.
It is a read operation on
the metrics of the device.
Working with the data scientist
and asking more questions,
let us understand that
most of the queries
are on temperature data.
Each data scientist runs
about 10 queries per hour.
So we do get 100 of
these analytic queries
run every hour.
The surface area
of these queries
tend to span the whole data set.
That said, the
analytic queries do not
have to run on
the data collected
in the last few minutes.
Any data newer
than the last hour
is good enough
for those queries.
There is a bunch of
interesting information here.
Collection scan on data
that is one hour old,
for these type of queries,
using nodes dedicated to data
analytics this is
a viable solution.
Our primary node is likely to
be very busy processing writes.
So we may want to dedicate
a node to process the reads
and isolate all the
collection scans they
may require from other nodes.
Collection scans are
usually pretty bad news
for the primary.
We could also consider
other strategies,
such as providing the data
scientist with a staging
environment so they can
prepare the analytic queries
on the smaller data set.
Or we could also consider
pre-aggregating the data.
We talk more about this
kind of optimization
in the chapter on patterns.
Putting everything together
results in the following.
Use the attached
handout for full review.
Note the section assumption.
When you make one assumption to
the analysis of a requirement,
ensure you capture it.
Changing assumptions or
even invalidating them
may have a considerable
impact on your design.
To summarize the findings we
have on this project so far,
the workload is mostly
composed of writes,
so we need to
optimize for writes,
first by ensuring proper
write distribution,
but also by applying techniques
and patterns that can reduce
the number of write operations.
As for the read operation, even
if we execute them less often
than the write
operations, they may still
require a considerable
amount of data.
So we need to map out
the most common queries
to shape the
documents accordingly.
We cover more on this
optimization when we discuss,
again, schema design patterns.
In summary, give a try
at estimating the numbers
for your system.
Try to quantify and quantify
the queries as much as you can.
Once you collect
the real metrics
on your operational
system, contrast these
with your initial assumption.
These differences you
observe are needed
to adapt the schema design.
Moreover, it is likely
that a few CRUD operations
will drive your design.