Hi.
I'm Daniel, one of your
instructors for this course.
Did you ever wonder what is the
single most important aspect
of using MongoDB to
ensure good performance,
maximize the productivity
of your developers,
and minimize the overall
cost of your solution?
Yes-- a good data model.
Welcome to M320, the data
modeling course for MongoDB.
In this course, we're going
to discuss all aspects of data
modeling for MongoDB.
You'll learn how to gather the
requirements to create the data
model, learn those requirements
into a basic model,
apply powerful transformation
patterns to optimize your data
model, and finally, understand
how to evolve your data
model over time.
Armed with that
knowledge, you'll
be able to design schema to
make the best use of MongoDB.
This course is
five chapters long.
With each chapter, there
is a set of lesson videos.
After most of these
lessons, there
is a quiz and labs to assess
your learning of the material.
Let's go over a few
logistics for the course.
What's the target audience?
It's an advanced course.
It is geared more toward
architects and developers, then
DevOp people.
However, everyone
can benefit from it.
If you're used to tabular
or relational databases,
we try to make the
parallel between MongoDB
and these databases.
This course has another
course as a prerequisite,
M001, Introduction to MongoDB.
If you have not
done this course,
you should be familiar
with the following--
using a cluster
deploy in Atlas, using
Compass to access the cluster,
and you should also be familiar
with database concepts
and vocabulary,
reading an entity relationship
diagram using the Crow's Foot
notation.
If you're not, we recommend
you take our beginners course,
M001, and go through the
additional external resources
we reference in the first
lesson of this course.
How does grading work?
There are quizzes,
labs, and a final exam.
Quizzes are ungraded and
exist to make sure that you
understand the content.
Your grade in the
class will be based
on how well you do on the
labs and the final exam,
each of these being
worth 50% of your grade.
To receive a certificate
of course completion,
you need a passing
grade of 65% or higher.
Finally, we will highly
encourage you to participate
in the discussion forum.
We have knowledgeable MongoDB
employees who are there
to help answer your questions.
You also have your
classmates, who can also
contribute to
answering your question
and are often beneficial and
very knowledgeable resources.
We've observed that students
who perform best in the courses
are those who are the most
active in the discussion forum.
By the end of this
course, you should
be ready to design schema
for your applications.
With all that said,
we're excited to have you
as a student in this class.