When dealing with database
schema and data modeling,
we sometimes find
ourselves doing things
because we saw something
on the internet
or got some friendly
advice on how
to do things, which might
not be the most correct way
and based on some
misconceptions.
One of the most
common misconceptions
about data modeling in MongoDB
is that modeling is schemaless,
meaning that it
doesn't really matter
which field documents have or
how different the documents can
be from one another, or even
how many collections you
might have per database.
Although that can be a
flattering way of positioning
in the flexibility
of MongoDB, this
is not practical in reality.
What MongoDB unquestionably has
is a very flexible data model.
There are no default rules
on what documents should
be looking like apart
from having correctly
been defined in BSON and
containing a primary key.
But most importantly, all
data as some sort of structure
and therefore, a schema.
MongoDB he just happens
to make it easier
for you to deal with that
later rather than sooner.
Before you jump into
an ERD or UML tooling,
in order to determine the full
scope of your data structures,
it tends to be preferable to
start building your application
and finding out from that
particular experience
what the data structure
should look like.
However, if you do
know your usage pattern
how your data is
accessed, which queries
are critical to
your application,
and ratios between
reads and writes,
you will be able to extract
a very good model, even
before rewriting
the full application
to make it scale with MongoDB.
Being flexible means that
your application changes.
And it's not
unreasonable to think
that that will not be the case.
You will be able to
accommodate those changes
without experiencing
a painful migration
process, like in traditional
relational databases.
When you start having a pretty
good idea of how documents
should be looking like
and should be shaped out
and which data types
those fields you have,
you'll be able to enforce
those rules in MongoDB
by using document validation.
Another misconception
is that all information,
regardless of how data
should be manipulated,
can be stored in
one single document.
There are some use cases where
this approach is actually
correct.
But the reality is that this
is not the way applications
in general use data.
Think about your user profile,
where we have a profile data.
And that gives us the
current state of the user.
But when thinking about
all the different changes
that that given user might
incur over a period of time,
like for example, all the
variations in musical tastes,
profile messages, new
friendships, new likes,
new reviews, new
romantic partnerships,
you might get a
good understanding
that that profile will grow.
If you tried to store
all that information,
99% of the time all you do
is get the latest version
of that profile.
You might not be helping your
application all that much
by storing all these sorts of
information of that user in one
big document.
As a user interacts more
with your application,
more data will be accumulated,
and your performance
will be dropping considerably.
Keeping the amount
of information stored
per individual documents to the
data that your application uses
and having different
models to deal
with historical data or other
types of data that are not
always accessed is
something that we'll
be looking into in
this course, as well.
And there is also
this perception
that there is no way to perform
a join between documents
in MongoDB.
While MongoDB does not
call dollar look up a join,
for many good
reasons, you can still
perform all sorts
of joins in MongoDB.
But it can certainly do these
types of relational operations
in MongoDB.
We will be showing you models
where you can make the most
out of them on top of Mongo.
Sometimes, finding
a schema design
that suits your application
or application needs
is not an easy job to do.
Data, at times, may be
very, very unstructured
or with quite a high
degree of variation.
This course will teach
you how to look harder
with the tools and procedures
to identify such a schema.
That said, MongoDB
will most definitely
shine on these
three main aspects.
You can run MongoDB anywhere.
You can use MongoDB
for any type of data.
And you can put your
data everywhere.
We will be looking
into ways of showing
how to design for
scalability, flexibility,
and performance, showing
how MongoDB allows you
to deal with change, scale,
and make your applications more
dynamic and flexible.