In this lesson, we're going
to cover the MongoDB document
model.
Data in MongoDB stored in
a hierarchical structure
where the database
are at the top level
where each MongoDB deployment
can have many databases.
Then there are one or more
collections in the database.
And finally, there are
documents which are
kept at the collection level.
In MongoDB, data is stored
as BSON documents that
are composed of field
value pairs, where
BSON is a binary representation
of JSON documents.
Since BSON is not
human-readable,
we will stick with
JSON in our examples
throughout this course.
So how does a document
like that look?
Keeping with the
standard JSON notation,
we have an open curly bracket
indicating the beginning
of a document, followed
by several field value
pairs separated by commas.
Each value can be of any BSON
data type, which in this case
are a string, an integer,
another string, and an array.
With MongoDB, a
document is a collection
of attributes for an object.
If you're coming
from SQL, a document
is like a row in
the table that has
been joined with other relevant
rows from other tables.
You have a field and
its assigned value,
just like each column
in a row has a value.
In this example, we're looking
at a variety of field types
which are all
supported by MongoDB.
Here we have a string, an
integer, an array, a document,
and an array of documents,
which make up a single document.
This is a powerful
feature of MongoDB.
Instead of having to query
multiple tables of related data
and assembling it
all together, you
can keep your related
data in a single document
and pull it all down
using a single query.
If you're familiar with
computer programming languages,
then you could consider
a MongoDB document
as being similar to
a dictionary or a map
or an associative array--
an object that has a
number of key value pairs.
Since MongoDB documents
support a flexible structure,
you can use a document to
represent an entire object
rather than having
to break up the data
across multiple records
as you would have to do
with the relational database.
The exact structure of a
document-- all the fields,
values, and embedded documents--
represent the schema
of a document.
You've probably heard the term
flexible schema thrown around
in relation to MongoDB.
Well, let's just
clarify this term.
MongoDB documents
have a flexible schema
in that you're not required
to make complicated changes
to a collection's
metadata to add or remove
the fields in a documents.
Documents in the
same collection don't
need to have the exact
same list of fields.
Furthermore, the data
type in any given field
can vary across documents.
You do not have to make
changes at the cluster level
to support this.
Another way to view
this is that you
can have multiple
versions of your schema
as your application develops
over time and all the schema
versions can coexist
in the same collection.
Compare this to
database solutions
where adding of removing
columns or fields
or changing the data type
of that column or field
can be a complicated process.
That said, chances are that the
documents in a given collection
will have a common
structure between them.
MongoDB supports
enforcing the schema shape
from no rules, rules
in a few fields,
to rules on all the
fields of the documents.
Let's recap.
MongoDB stores
data as documents.
Document fields can be values,
embedded documents, or arrays
of values and documents.
MongoDB is a flexible
schema database.