The same kind of
ordering will be
applied to the index structure.
So internally how we
built our big tree
is that we will be
going to be grouping
the documents, or
the document keys,
based on the data
type representation.
That way, if we are
traversing the tree looking
for a specific data
type we can go directly
to that first branch of the
tree and get the results
in a much streamlined fashion.
So we'll start by
grouping and creating
a tree for numerical
value types,
including any floating point
values, numerical decimal,
or even integer 64.
And then we'll
create the structure
for all of our
strings and symbols,
grouping them into the
different data types
that they are represented by.
Although this is the correct way
of dealing with this scenario,
it might not be exactly what the
application actually expects.
In a situation where
these two documents, which
are represented by a string
value as their base field,
they are not exactly following
their numeric representation.
We are just ordering them
according with their data type
and using a string
comparison between them,
which is totally correct.
But probably not the expected
numeric ordering sorting.
We can solve this situation
by creating an index
or even applying a
collation on a query that
applies the numeric ordering
of that string representation.
If we run the query--
exactly the same query--
but instead of just
sorting the value,
if we apply a collation with
numeric ordering in place,
and still sorting
by the same value,
we will get the expected
string numerical
ordering representation
while we are doing our sort.
We are still going to be
doing the ordering by groups.
First numerical data types,
integer 64, numerical decimal,
number decimal,
and then strings.
But within strings,
we will order them
according with their
numeric representation.
There is also the
obvious implications
to your application logic.
If you populate documents
where a given field has seven
different data types,
the application
will need to be prepared
to handle those scenarios.
While these scenarios might
be extremely inconvenient
in terms of data
migrations or even
while using a
dynamic language, it
will create some
client side logic
that will need to be prepared
to deal with different data
types, which in turn will result
in a much more complex code
base, or expected to be complex.
And more important than that,
a more complex test base.
The number of variations of
tests that you need to create
will be in the order of
the different data types
that you might have in your
collection for the same field.
Again, while these might
be very, very useful,
we advise to use them with care.
As a recap, there are
several different data type
implications that you
should be aware of
and you need to deal
with those once you
are using a flexible scheme.
You should be aware,
and your application
should be aware, that it needs
to avoid data consistency
issues.
If one client writes
one data type,
the other clients should also
write exactly the same data
type.
Otherwise it might be
confusing for different clients
to deal with
different data types.
We will be ensuring that
the correctness on queries
and sorting in terms of
data types by default.
But if you want to add
that extra edge of being
able to capture the numerical
representation of a string
print, for example, you'll need
to apply collations in place.
There are implications
for your code base.
The more streamlined
your fields are
in terms of more normalized
with using always the same data
type, the more simple your
code base of your application
will be.
And you can enforce
certain rules,
like document
validation that can
be defined at the
collection level
to give you that extra control
of which kind of documents
are being inserted
into your collection.
And these are the different
data type implications
that we needed to cover.