In this lesson, we're going
to talk about how we can
optimize our CRUD operations.
By now we already understand
the important rule
that indexes play with
regards to performance.
In this lesson, we're going
to discuss index selectivity,
which concerns minimizing
the number of index keys
that we examine;
the equality, sort,
range rule, which is useful
when building indexes;
and finally, we'll discuss the
trade-offs between these two.
Let's go ahead and
jump into the shell
and look at some examples.
And for this lesson, we're
going to continue using
the new restaurant data set.
Here I'm creating an explainable
object, and here's our query.
We're going to search
for restaurants whose zip
code is over 50,000,
whose cuisine is sushi,
and we're going to sort
by stars descending.
Now, this collection doesn't
have any indexes on it.
So we would assume this
would not be very performant,
and this is exactly
what we want.
This is our baseline.
And when we look at
the explain output,
we can see that we're doing
a collection scan, followed
by an in-memory sort.
And when we look
at execution stats,
we can see that we
returned 11,000 documents,
and it took 386 milliseconds.
But we had to examine one
million documents to do so.
This is pretty terrible,
but it's what we expected.
Looking back at our
query, we might go ahead
and naively create
an index on zip code,
cuisine, and stars,
which is what we're
querying on and sorting on.
And now when we
rerun the same query,
we'd expect some better
results, and we do.
We can see that we're no longer
examining a million documents.
We're only examining the 11,000
that we return, is the same
that we're examining.
And instead of doing
a collection scan,
we're now doing an index scan.
But you can see that we're still
doing an in-memory sort which
isn't very cool.
And we're also
looking at a bunch
of unnecessary index keys,
which also isn't very cool.
But in general, our
execution time is down.
And we're examining an
extra 80,000 index keys
because the first key in
our index is zip code.
And in our query here,
zip code is a range query,
which isn't very selective.
If zip code was an
equality condition,
then our index key
would be very selective,
because there's only
a hundred thousand
possible different zip codes
and we have a million documents.
So if we were doing
something like this
where we were doing an
equality condition on zip code,
we expect there to only be
about 10 documents, which
is exactly how many there are.
However, our query isn't
doing an equality condition
on zip code.
It's doing a range query.
We're saying that we want all
zip codes greater than 50,000.
So since 50,000 is about half
of the hundred thousand possible
zip codes, we expect about
half a million documents,
which is pretty much
exactly what we see.
So zip code as a range query
isn't a very selective index
because we're returning
half of our million.
On the other hand, cuisine
has an equality condition,
and so we'd expect this to be
pretty selective, and it is.
We're only seeing 23,000
documents, which is about 2%
of our million
document collection.
So this is much more
selective than the 50%
that we'd get with zip code.
Knowing the selective
parts of our query,
we can reorder our index
to take advantage of this.
Let's go ahead and this
time create an index
on cuisine first instead
of zip code first.
So we're effectively just
swapping these two fields.
And now we can rerun
the same query.
And when we look at
the output, you'll
see that our execution
stats are way better.
We're now not examining
any unnecessary index keys.
Our execution time is way down.
This is almost a third of what
it took the last time to run.
But when we look up
at the winning plan,
you'll see that we're still
doing an in-memory sort.
So we know we can actually
probably do better.
And you might be
surprised that we're
doing an in-memory sort because
our index includes the stars
key.
Well, if you remember
correctly, we
can only use an index for
both filtering and sorting
if the keys in our
query predicate
are equality conditions.
And since zip code
is a range query,
we're not able to use
that index for sorting.
So we can swap
stars and zip code,
and this will
allow us to prevent
doing an in-memory sort.
And so when we look
at our explain output,
we can see that our winning
plan is just do an index scan
followed by a fetch.
No more in-memory sort.
And when we scroll down
to execution stats,
you'll see that our execution
time is way down, only
43 milliseconds.
You might also notice that we're
looking at a few more index
keys, but that's OK because by
doing this sort with the index,
we've actually saved on
the execution time overall.
And this is a nice segue
into equality, sort, range.
Here's our query,
and here's the index
that we just used to get
our most perform execution.
And so we can use
this phrase equality,
sort, range when building our
indexes to determine the best
way to service our queries.
At the beginning
of our index, we
should match on
equality conditions
in the query predicate, followed
by sort conditions, and finally
range conditions;
equality, sort, range.
And while this cool
trick won't always
give us the most
performant results,
it's a really
great rule of thumb
and it works most of the time.
And as you can see, if
we don't use indexes,
our queries are
going to be slow.
And we can build indexes
so that we're not
examining unnecessary documents
that we're not returning.
We can continue to
increase performance
by thinking about
selectivity when
we build our indexes so
that we're not looking
at superfluous index keys.
But that being said, sometimes
it makes sense for us
to make a trade-off between
examining index keys
and doing an in-memory sort.
As we can see, the
rule of equality, sort,
range when used as a rule of
thumb for building our indexes
can be very effective.
Let's recap what we've learned.
So we talked about
index selectivity.
And when we choose
our indexes, we
want to make sure that the most
selective fields are first.
We also talked about
equality, sort,
range, which is a really great
rule for determining how we
should order our index fields.
And finally, we talked about
performance trade-offs.
Sometimes it makes sense to be
a little bit less selective,
to prevent an in-memory
sort because in the end
our execution time
will be the lowest.