In this lesson, we're going
to discuss regular expression
performance in MongoDB.
Specifically, we're going to
discuss how we can utilize
indexes on regex conditions.
In the lesson on
text indexes, we
learned that we can create
indexes on string fields
to support queries using the
$text and $search operators.
But sometimes we don't want
to add the overhead of text
indexes to our deployment.
In these cases, we can fall
back on using vanilla indexes
and using regular expressions.
Unfortunately,
regex's don't always
have the best performance.
In this example, if there
isn't an index on username,
then we need to do
a collection scan.
We'd have to touch every single
document in our collection
and apply that regular
expression against each
of these documents.
Like with traditionally
quality conditions,
we can improve the
performance of this query
by creating an index
on the queried field.
Now we only need to apply
our regular expression
against every index key instead
of against the whole document.
While this will increase the
performance of the query,
we still need to look at
every index key of our index.
This somewhat defeats
the purpose of indexes.
Indexes are stored as b-trees
because of their ability
to reduce the search
space to an ordered subset
of the entire index.
We can take advantage of
this feature of indexes
by adding a carrot at the
beginning of our regex
condition.
The carrot means that we
only want to return documents
where the following
characters start
at the beginning of the string.
In this case, I want to find
documents where the user
name begins with Kirby.
By doing this, we're
effectively ignoring
all the branches of the b-tree
that don't begin with Kirby.
And so we're able to
dramatically reduce
the number of index
keys that need
to be examined and therefore
increase our overall query
performance.
This might be
obvious, but I want
to point out that this
optimization will only
work if you're matching at
the beginning of a string.
For example, with
this wildcard regex,
we need to check
every single index
key because we can't limit
ourselves to just where it
starts with Kirby.
There could be an index key
that is a-i-r-b-y, or k-i-r-b-y,
or r-r-i-b-y, or s-i-r-b-y.
We have to look at
all these index keys.
Let's recap what we've learned.
We've talked about
how to utilize indexes
using regular expression
conditions in MongoDB.