In this lesson, we're going
to talk about covered queries.
In here, we're going
to talk about what
covered queries
are, how they work,
and we'll also spend
some time discussing
some important caveats
associated with them.
Covered queries are a
highly performant way
to service the queries
to our database.
The reason that covered
queries are so fast
is because they're completely
satisfied by our index keys.
This means that the
server doesn't actually
have to touch any
of the documents.
Querying only the index
can be much faster
than querying documents
outside of the index
because the index keys
are typically smaller
than the documents they catalog
and index keys are typically
available in RAM.
Let's discuss how this works.
Imagine we have a
query where we're
trying to find all the
restaurants that start with l,
serve sushi, and have
four or more stars.
And we also have an index
on those same fields.
Now, if we were to add a
projection to this query
so that we're only including
the fields that we're indexing
on omitting the underscore
ID field, in this case,
then all the information that
we expect to get back already
exists in the keys of our index.
Because this index contains
all the fields required
by the results of
our query, MongoDB
can both match the
query conditions
and return the results
only using the index.
Let's see how this
works in practice.
I'm going to go ahead and
connect to the m201 database,
create an explainable
object, and then create
the index we were
just talking about.
Now, when I run the FIND
query from our example,
and you'll see that our results
have all the same fields
as our keys in our index.
All these values exist directly
on the index we just created.
And we can easily
confirm that this
is a covered query by looking
at the explain output.
You'll notice that
under execution stats
we didn't actually have to
examine any documents to return
our results.
It was also a super fast query.
It only took 10 milliseconds to
return almost 3,000 documents.
This is further illustrated
by the winning plan.
You can see that we're
immediately doing an index scan
followed by a projection.
We completely skipped
the fetch stage
that we would normally
see when we turn
the record IDs into documents.
I do want to point out
an important caveat.
Let's see what happens here
when we run this example.
We see the same output
as our earlier query
when we explicitly said that
we wanted name, cuisine,
and stars.
Here, we're doing
the same thing,
except we're just omitting
underscore ID and address.
And so we'd expect the
same explain output.
Right?
Wrong.
When we go and scroll up
to the execution stats,
you can see that we're
now examining documents.
And this actually makes sense.
When we explicitly omit
fields, the query planner
has no way of telling what
other fields might be present.
We might only have the
fields that are index queues,
but there also might
be documents that
have other additional fields.
Because of this, an
index covers a query only
when both all fields in the
query are a part of the index
and all the fields are
turned in the result
are in the same index.
This generally
means that we need
to filter out underscore ID.
Before we finish
this lesson, I want
to point out a few
other caveats associated
with covered queries.
We can't cover a query
if our index fields are
arrays or embedded documents.
We also can't cover a
query against a Mongos
if the index does not
contain the shard key.
Let's recap what we've learned.
We talked about what
covered queries are.
We spent some time
looking at how they work.
And we also pointed out
some important caveats
associated with them.