In this lesson, we're
going to be talking
about data type implications,
[INAUDIBLE] different data
types across same fields,
across the documents of a given
collection.
We will look into
the implications
of data types for flexible
schema trade-offs, the data
consistency implications,
and the query
correctness that you
should be aware of once
dealing with MongoDB.
One of the advantages of
working with documents
rather than browsing
a relational system
is the ability to have a
very natural representation
to work with data.
The other obvious
one is the ability
to have a very flexible model
for our data representation.
So let's say that we have
this collection, shapes,
where we insert this document,
which has a type, single length
type, base, and height.
We can insert that
document no problem.
But if we want to use a slightly
different document-- let's say
that we still have
our type and it still
has a string as a
value, we're still
going to have a
side_length_type, which
is great.
But now our base field,
instead of integer 64,
is going to be a NumberDecimal.
And we are not going
to have an i-th,
but we are going to have
a side_length field.
If we insert this, no problem.
MongoDB kind of likes it.
And our variations can continue,
to have more simplified
documents with more
or less variations.
Now, while it is
possible to have
same field with
different data types,
there are implications
for the application
that you should consider, like
for example on query matching.
Now let's say that I'm going
to be looking for a document
where base equals 2.8,
84, 42, 71, and so forth.
A filter matching a field with
an integer or floating point
value is not the
same as a filter
matching a value
that is represented
by a string or decimal type.
If we try to look for
this floating value,
we cannot find it.
There's no such thing as a
document where base equals
this floating point value.
On the other hand, if we try
to find a shapes document where
the base equals a string value
of the same floating point,
obviously it still
doesn't find it.
But if we do express our query
with the correct NumberDecimal
type, where there is
a document for it,
we will most definitely find it.
So the fact that we have
different data types
and for correctness
does not mean that
by expressing a
different data type,
even though the representation
is pretty simple for you
to find the correct
document, you
have to provide a
query where the data
type matches the documents on
the collection with exact data
type.
Sorting will also be affected
by different documents having
for the same field
different data types.
In this example, we are using
numerical data types, int64
and decimal data types.
So this ordering of the
results becomes very, very easy
to perform.
If I'm looking for all documents
and just projecting base
and not even
underscore ID, and I'm
sorting based on
base ascending, we
will get the correct
comparison order
by all of the different
data types that currently
have in our shapes collection.
It's going to have int64.
Then we're going to have
a NumberDecimal and then
another int64 and another int64.
However, what if we
set the field base
with non-numerical data type?
What happens then?
I'm going to go ahead and insert
these two different documents.
These two documents have
very similar shapes,
where the base value is
represented by a string,
in this case 3.
And in the second
document, we just
changed the base from
string 3 to string 14,
so very similar documents.
If we apply the same sorting
into this collection,
we will have first all
numerical values represented,
and then string values
represented as well.
This means that in
these cases, MongoDB
will be grouping documents and
comparing their fields based
on the different BSON types
using a specific comparison
order.
We will start by MinKey, then
null or non-existent field
documents, numerical, symbol
or string, object, array,
and all the way down to MaxKey,
so that basically that means
that we will group documents
that are represented
by MinKey or null or numbers,
like ints, longs, doubles
decimals.
Then we will group and
compare between them
symbols and strings, then
objects, and so forth.