In this lesson we're going to
talk about insert performance
from MongoDB.
By the end of this
lesson, you should
be familiar with the
following concepts
with regards to
insert performance.
First, we're going to
talk about how indexes
affect our write performance.
And we're also going to talk
about how write concerns can
affect our write performance.
We already know that
when we use indexes,
we seriously increase the read
performance of our application.
This is because
indexes store mappings
between field values
and the references
to documents that have
those field values.
And these indexes can
be searched very quickly
for these references.
But we don't get this read
performance enhancement
for free.
The downside is that we need to
keep these indexes up to date.
So as documents are
inserted, updated or deleted,
we may need to
update our indexes.
And this means that for
every index that we add,
we'll be decreasing the overall
insert, update and delete
performance of our application.
Before we look at some practical
examples of the overhead
that indexes can incur, let's
talk about our other topic
for this lesson, write concern.
When we make writes
to MongoDB we
can specify our write concern.
This write concern describes
the level of acknowledgment
requested from MongoDB
for write operations.
A write concern has three
parameters, w, k, and wtimeout.
w describes how many of the
members of our replica set
we're going to
wait for the write
to be propagated to before
we consider it truly written.
This can be a number,
like one if we just
want to wait for
the primary, or two
if we want to wait
for two members
to acknowledge the
write and so forth.
We can also use the
string "majority"
where we want to wait for
a majority of the members
to acknowledge the write.
j is a Boolean value
specifying whether or not
we want to wait for
the on disk journal.
When writes come
into the database,
they're primarily
written to memory.
But periodically
that information
is flushed to an
on disk journal.
And finally we have wtimeout.
This specifies how long we
want to wait in milliseconds
for the write to be
acknowledged before we time out.
So here's an example
write concern,
where we say we want to wait
for one member, the primary,
to acknowledge the
write, and we don't
want to wait for the on disk
journal to be written to,
and we want a timeout
after five seconds.
I do want to point out that
just because we time out doesn't
mean the write was aborted.
We can time out and the
write can still occur.
Here's another example
of a write concern.
Here we're saying
that we will wait
for a majority of the members
to acknowledge the write.
And we also want to wait until
that write has been journaled.
It's somewhat
intuitive to see how
this write concern on the bottom
will generally take longer
to be acknowledged than
the one on the top.
With the top write
concern, we only
need to wait for one server
to acknowledge the write,
and we're not waiting
on the on disk journal.
On the bottom one
here, however, we
have to wait for a
majority of the members,
and we have to wait for
the on disk journal.
Let's go ahead
and run some tests
and see how these two factors
affect write performance.
For this exercise, I'm
going to use the POC
driver that we talked about
in our benchmarking lesson.
And this is MongoDB
Atlas, our hosted MongoDB
as a service offering.
Here I've gone ahead and spun
up a three member replica set,
and this will effectively
act as our testbed.
Now let's jump into the
terminal and run some tests.
Here I've gone
ahead and connected
to my Atlas cluster
via the Mongo shell,
where I can go ahead and
keep this connection open so
that we can drop our test
collection in between tests,
and we can also create
indexes on the fly.
Let's head over
to another shell.
Here have gone ahead and
followed the instructions
in the readme, and I've
compiled our .jar file.
Now when we run this .jar
file with the -p option,
it'll print out an
example document.
And this is the kind
of document that we're
going to be inserting into
the database for our test.
And so now I can go ahead and
use my .jar file with the -c
option specified in the
connection string to my MongoDB
Atlas cluster.
And now this POC driver is
going to insert documents
as fast as it can
into my Atlas cluster.
And as you can see,
we're inserting documents
at about 16,000 per second.
And so this our baseline.
We have no indexes
and we're using
the default write concern.
Let's go ahead and go
back to our Mongo shell
and create our first index.
You'll see that we now
have this POC database.
I'm going to switch to it
and drop our collection
and create an index.
And now let's rerun our test.
So the only thing
that's changed here
is now I've added
an index, and so we
would expect to have
a little bit of loss
of write performance.
And as you can see,
we're now only inserting
documents at about
15,000 documents
per second, a little bit slower
than our 16,000 we had before.
We can now go ahead and
drop our collection again.
And this time we'll create
indexes on five fields.
Now that those five indexes have
been created, let's go ahead
and run our test again.
And so now we're
inserting documents
at about 10,000 or 11,000
documents per second.
While it's not a huge
decrease in performance,
it's still noticeable.
Now let's go ahead
and run some tests
to see how write concern
affects our write performance.
I've gone ahead and created some
different .jar files for each
of the different write concerns.
Unfortunately, this
POC driver doesn't
support different write
concerns from the command line.
So what I did was edit
the source code directly.
If you're interested,
I went ahead
and imported in
these two classes.
And then all I did was
add these lines of code.
And what I did was is for each
of the different .jar files,
I just commented out whichever
line had the write concern I
wanted to test.
And that's how I generated
these different .jar files.
So now we just need to rerun our
same tests with these different
.jar files.
But first we should go ahead
and drop our collection.
Here I'm running with w set
to one and j set to false.
These are the default settings.
So we should expect
to see similar numbers
to our first test.
And as you can see, we're
now inserting about 27,000
documents per second.
This is a little bit
faster than our first test,
but network latency.
Let's go ahead and drop
our collection again.
And now I'm going to run the
test with w still equal to one,
but now journaling is
going to be set to true.
And as you can see,
we're inserting documents
at about 19,000 per second.
You should now have an
idea of how this works.
We can go ahead and skip
to the table of results.
And here you can see how the
different indexes affected
our inserts per second.
When we had no indexes, we
were inserting about 16,000
per second.
When we added one, we
are talking about 15,000
per second.
And when we had five, we were
inserting only about 10,500
per second.
And you can see here
I've also added a percent
loss from the baseline.
And we can also see how
different write concerns
affect our performance.
Interestingly enough, it doesn't
seem like journaling matters
that much when we're dealing
with a majority write concern.
But it does seem to
matter when we're
dealing with just the primary.
And this kind of makes sense.
Here we're waiting
for multiple members
and we have network
latency going on.
And here there is
no network latency.
We're just waiting for the on
disk journal to be written to.
These are my own numbers running
on my own machine on my iMac
talking to an Atlas cluster.
So this isn't a
best case scenario.
I really should be running
these tests inside AWS instance,
because AWS is where
Atlas is hosted on.
And we probably want
to minimize the amount
of network latency
between my Atlas cluster
and my application server.
But that being said, this still
gives us a good high level idea
of what we're dealing with.
Now I don't want you to forget
about the significant read
performance gains that
we saw by adding indexes
to our collection.
With each additional
index, we lost about 6%
of our write performance.
But often we would see a more
than 10x read performance
increase when we use the
best index for a query.
And so this should give
you a good overview
of insert performance.
Let's recap what we've learned.
We've talked about
index overhead
and how as we add more
indexes, our insert performance
is going to degrade.
And we also talked
about write concern,
where we discussed different
levels of acknowledgement
affecting our write performance.